<book num="Josh">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">After the death of Moses the servant of Yahweh, Yahweh said to Joshua son of Nun, the assistant<note>Or "servant"</note> of Moses, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"My servant Moses <transChange type="added">is</transChange> dead. Get up and cross the Jordan, you and all this people, into the land that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> giving to them, to the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Every place that the soles of your feet will tread, I have given it to you, as I promised<note>Or "spoke"</note> to Moses.</verse>
    <verse num="4">From the wilderness {and the Lebanon},<note>Literally "this Lebanon"; "Lebanon" in Hebrew means "white mountain"</note> up to the great river, the river Euphrates, all of the land of the Hittites, and up to {the great sea in the west},<note>Literally "the great sea of the setting sun"</note> will be your territory.</verse>
    <verse num="5">No one will stand before you<note>Or "in your presence"</note> all the days of your life. <transChange type="added">Just</transChange> as I was with Moses, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> will I be with you; I will not fail you, and I will not forsake you.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Be strong and courageous, for you will give the people this land as an inheritance that I swore to their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> to give them.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Only be strong and very courageous {to observe diligently the whole law}<note>Literally "to keep <transChange type="added">and</transChange> to act according to the whole law"</note> that Moses my servant commanded you. Do not turn aside from it, <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the right or left, so that you may succeed {wherever you go}.<note>Literally "in all that you go"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">The scroll of this law will not depart from your mouth; you will meditate on it day and night so that {you may observe diligently all that is written}<note>Literally "to keep <transChange type="added">and</transChange> to act according to all that is written"</note> in it. For then you will succeed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> your ways and prosper.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Did I not command you? Be strong and courageous! Do not fear or be dismayed, for Yahweh your God is with you {wherever you go}."<note>Literally "in all that you go"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="11">"Pass through the midst of the camp and command the people: 'Prepare your provisions;<note>Hebrew "provision"</note> {in}<note>Literally "for in still"</note> three days you <transChange type="added">are to</transChange> cross the Jordan to go possess the land that Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> giving you to possess.'" </verse>
    <verse num="12">To the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh Joshua said,</verse>
    <verse num="13">"Remember the word that Moses Yahweh's servant commanded you, saying, 'Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> giving rest to you, and he is giving<note>Hebrew "he gave"</note> you this land.'</verse>
    <verse num="14">Your wives, your little children, and your livestock, they will remain in the land that Moses gave to you beyond the Jordan. {All of the best fighting men}<note>Literally "All the mighty warriors of the troop"</note> will cross armed in front of your families; they will help you</verse>
    <verse num="15">until Yahweh gives rest to your families as well as to you. They will take possession of the land that Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> giving to them. Then you will return to your own land and take possession of it, <transChange type="added">the land</transChange> that Moses the servant of Yahweh gave you beyond the Jordan {to the east}."<note>Literally "to the sunrise"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">And they answered Joshua, saying, "All that you have commanded us we will do, and wherever you will send us we will go.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Just as we obeyed Moses, so will we obey you. Only may Yahweh your God be with you, as he was with Moses.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Whoever {rebels against your orders}<note>Literally "defiles against your mouth"</note> and does not obey your words according to what you commanded us will be put to death. Only be strong and courageous." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Then Joshua son of Nun secretly sent two men from Acacia Grove<note>Hebrew "Shittim"</note> <transChange type="added">as</transChange> spies, saying, "Go, view the land, especially Jericho." So they went, and entered the house of a prostitute whose name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Rahab, and {spent the night}<note>Literally "lay down"</note> there.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The king of Jericho was told, "Look, <transChange type="added">some</transChange> men from the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> have come here tonight to search out the land."</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the king of Jericho sent <transChange type="added">for</transChange> Rahab, saying, "Bring out the men who came to you, the ones who have entered your house, for they have come to search out the whole land."</verse>
    <verse num="4">But the woman took the two men and hid them. And she said, "Yes, the men came to me, but I did not know where they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> from.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And when <transChange type="added">it was time</transChange> to shut the gate {for the night},<note>Literally "in the darkness" or "at dark"</note> the men left, and I do not know where they went. Chase after them quickly, for you may catch up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> them."</verse>
    <verse num="6">(But she had taken them to the roof and had hidden them {in the stalks of flax}<note>Literally "in the flaxes of the plant stalk"</note> that she {had spread out}<note>Literally "had been arranged"</note> on the roof.)</verse>
    <verse num="7">So the men chased after them on {the way to the Jordan}<note>Literally "the road of the Jordan"</note> at the fords; and they shut the gate behind the pursuers that had gone out after them. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Before {they went to sleep},<note>Literally "they lay down"</note> she came up to them on the roof</verse>
    <verse num="9">and said to the men, "I know that Yahweh has given you the land, and that dread of you has fallen on us, and that all the inhabitants of the land melt away <transChange type="added">in fear</transChange> because of your presence.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For we have heard how Yahweh dried up the waters of the {Red Sea}<note>Literally "sea of reeds"</note> before you when you went out from Egypt, and what you did to the two kings of the Amorites that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> beyond the Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom you utterly destroyed.</verse>
    <verse num="11">We heard <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, and our hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> melted, and {no courage was left in anyone}<note>Literally "a spirit no longer stood in anyone"</note> because of your presence. For Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God in the heavens above and on the earth below.</verse>
    <verse num="12">So then please swear to me by Yahweh, because {I have shown loyalty to you},<note>Literally "I have done with you a loyal love"</note> and {you will also show loyalty}<note>Literally "you will do ... loyal love"</note> {to my family}.<note>Literally "with the house of my father"</note> You must give me a sign of good faith,<note>Or "faithfulness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">and you will spare my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all that belongs to them; you will deliver our lives from death."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And the men said to her, "{Our lives for yours}.<note>Literally "Our lives in place of yours to die"</note> If you do not report this business of ours, {we will show you loyalty and faithfulness}<note>Literally "we will do with you loyal love and faithfulness"</note> when Yahweh gives us the land." </verse>
    <verse num="15">Then she lowered them with a rope through the window, as her house <transChange type="added">was</transChange> on the outer side of the wall, and she <transChange type="added">was</transChange> residing in the wall.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And she said to them, "Go to the mountain, so that the pursuers will not find you, and hide yourselves there three days until the pursuers return, and afterward you may go {on your way}."<note>Literally "to your way"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">The men said to her, "We <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> released from this oath of yours that you made us swear.</verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">When</transChange> we come to the land, you must tie this scarlet cord in the window through which you let us down, and you must gather your father and mother, and your brothers, and your whole family to your house.</verse>
    <verse num="19">If anyone goes outside the doors of your house, {they will be responsible for their own death},<note>Literally "his blood <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> on his head"</note> and we <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> innocent. Anyone who will be with you in the house, {we will be responsible for their death}<note>Literally "his blood <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> on our head"</note> {if a hand is laid on them}.<note>Literally "if a hand will be against him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">But if you report this business of ours, we will be released from your oath that you made us swear."</verse>
    <verse num="21">And she said, "According to your word it <transChange type="added">will be</transChange>." Then she sent them away, and they went, and she tied the scarlet cord in the window. </verse>
    <verse num="22">They departed and came to the mountain, and they stayed there three days until the pursuers returned. The pursuers searched {all along the way}<note>Literally "on all of the road"</note> but did not find <transChange type="added">them</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The two men returned and went down from the mountain, and they crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> and came to Joshua son of Nun, and they told him everything that happened to them.</verse>
    <verse num="24">They said to Joshua, "Surely Yahweh has given all the land into our hand; also, all the inhabitants of the land melt away <transChange type="added">in fear</transChange> because of our presence." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Joshua rose early in the morning, and they set out from Acacia Grove.<note>Hebrew "Shittim"</note> And they came up to the Jordan, he and all the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and they spent the night there before they crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="2">At the end of the three days the officers passed through the midst of the camp,</verse>
    <verse num="3">and they commanded the people: "When you see the Levitical priests carrying the ark of the covenant of Yahweh your God you must set out from your place and go after it.</verse>
    <verse num="4"><transChange type="added">But</transChange> there will be a distance between you and it of about two thousand cubits in measurement.<note>That is, about 1 km</note> Do not come near it, so that you may know the way that you must go, for you have not passed on <transChange type="added">this</transChange> way {before}."<note>Literally "from yesterday three days before"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And Joshua said to the people, "Sanctify yourselves, because tomorrow Yahweh will do wonders in your midst."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And Joshua said to the priests, "Take up the ark of the covenant and cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> {ahead of the people}."<note>Literally "before the presence of the people"</note> And they took up the ark of the covenant and went {ahead of the people}.<note>Literally "before the presence of the people"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="7">Then Yahweh said to Joshua, "This day I will begin exalting you {in the sight}<note>Literally "in the eyes"</note> of all Israel, that they may know that I was with Moses, and I will be with you.</verse>
    <verse num="8">You will command the priests carrying the ark of the covenant, saying, 'At the moment that you come to the edge of the waters of the Jordan, you will stand <transChange type="added">still</transChange> in the Jordan.'"</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Joshua said to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> "Come here, and hear the words of Yahweh your God."</verse>
    <verse num="10">Joshua said, "By this you will know that <transChange type="added">the</transChange> living God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in your midst, and he will certainly drive out the Canaanites {from before you},<note>Or "from your presence"</note> and the Hittites, Hivites, the Perizzites, the Girgashites, the Amorites, and the Jebusites.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Look! The ark of the covenant of the Lord of all the earth<note>Or "world"</note> <transChange type="added">is about to</transChange> cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> ahead of you into the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="12">So then, take twelve men from the tribes of Israel, {one from each tribe}.<note>Literally "one man for the tribe"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">When the soles of the feet of the priests carrying the ark of Yahweh, Lord of all the earth,<note>Or "world"</note> rest in the waters of the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan will be cut off {upstream},<note>Literally "going down from above"</note> and they will stand <transChange type="added">still in</transChange> one heap. </verse>
    <verse num="14">And it happened, when the people set out from their tents to cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> the Jordan, the priests carrying the ark of the covenant were {ahead of the people}.<note>Literally "before the presence of the people"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">When those carrying the ark came up to the Jordan, and the priests carrying the ark dipped their feet in the edge of the water (the Jordan was flowing over its banks during all the days of harvest),</verse>
    <verse num="16">the waters flowing down from above stood <transChange type="added">still</transChange>; they stood up <transChange type="added">in</transChange> one heap very far from Adam, the city that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> beside Zarethan, while <transChange type="added">the waters</transChange> flowing down to the sea of the Arabah, the Salt Sea,<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> {were completely cut off};<note>Literally "they were completed they were cut off"</note> and the people crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> opposite Jericho.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the priests carrying the ark of the covenant of Yahweh stood firmly on the dry land in the middle of the Jordan while all Israel crossed on dry ground, until all the nation finished crossing the Jordan. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">After all the nation finished crossing the Jordan, Yahweh said to Joshua,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"Take twelve men from the people, {one man from each tribe},<note>Literally "man one man one from tribe"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">and command them, saying, 'Take for yourselves twelve stones from the middle of the Jordan where the priests' feet stood firmly, and bring them over with you, and set them up in {the place where you will camp tonight}.'"<note>Literally "the lodging place where you will lodge tonight"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">So Joshua summoned the twelve men whom he had appointed from the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> one from each tribe.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Joshua said to them, "Cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> before<note>Or "the presence"</note> the ark of Yahweh your God to the middle of the Jordan, and each one of you lift up a stone on your<note>Hebrew "his"</note> shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">so that this may be a reminder<note>Or "sign"</note> among you. When your children ask in the future, saying, '{What do these stones mean to you}?'<note>Literally "What are these stones for you?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">you will say to them that the waters of the Jordan were cut off {from before}<note>Or "the presence of"</note> the ark of the covenant of Yahweh. When it crossed the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan were cut off. These stones will be as a memorial for the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> for eternity." </verse>
    <verse num="8">Thus the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did as Joshua commanded. They took twelve stones from the middle of the Jordan as Yahweh told Joshua, according to the number of the tribes of the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and they carried them over with them to {the camp},<note>Literally "the place of overnight lodging"</note> and they put them there.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Then Joshua set up twelve stones in the middle of the Jordan, in the place where the feet of the priests carrying the ark of the covenant <transChange type="added">stood</transChange>, and they are there to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The priests carrying the ark remained standing in the middle of the Jordan until everything that Yahweh commanded Joshua to tell the people was finished, according to all that Moses commanded Joshua. And the people hastily crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="11">And it happened, when all the people had finished crossing, the ark of Yahweh and the priests crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> in front of<note>Or "before the presence"</note> the people.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The children of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> armed before the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> as Moses told them.</verse>
    <verse num="13">About forty thousand armed for fighting crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> before the presence of Yahweh to the plains of Jericho for battle.</verse>
    <verse num="14">On that day Yahweh exalted Joshua {in the sight}<note>Literally "in the eyes"</note> of all Israel, and they respected him<note>Or "feared him"</note> as they respected<note>Or "feared"</note> Moses all the days of his life. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Then Yahweh said to Joshua, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="16">"Command the priests carrying the ark of the testimony<note>That is, the ark of the covenant</note> {to come up}<note>Literally "and let them come up"</note> from the Jordan."</verse>
    <verse num="17">So Joshua commanded the priests, saying, "Come up from the Jordan."</verse>
    <verse num="18">And it happened that when the priests carrying the ark came up from the middle of the Jordan, and the soles of the priests' feet {touched dry land},<note>Literally "were raised from the ground to dry land"</note> the waters of the Jordan returned to their place and flowed over all its banks as before. </verse>
    <verse num="19">And the people came up from the Jordan on the tenth <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the first month, and they camped in Gilgal on the eastern edge<note>That is, border</note> of Jericho.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And those twelve stones that they took from the Jordan, Joshua set up in Gilgal.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And he said to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> "When your children ask in the future {their parents},<note>Literally "their fathers"</note> '{What is the meaning of these stones}?'<note>Literally "What <transChange type="added">are</transChange> these stones?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">you will let your children know <transChange type="added">by</transChange> saying, 'Israel crossed this Jordan on dry ground.'</verse>
    <verse num="23">For Yahweh your God dried up the waters of the Jordan before you, until you had crossed, just as Yahweh your God did to the {Red Sea},<note>Literally "sea of reeds"</note> which he dried up before us until we had crossed over,</verse>
    <verse num="24">so that all the peoples of the earth may know that the hand of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> strong, so that you may fear Yahweh your God {forever}."<note>Literally "all the days"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">And it happened, when all the kings of the Amorites who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> beyond the Jordan to the west, and all the kings of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> by the sea heard that Yahweh dried up the waters of the Jordan in front of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> until they crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange>, their hearts melted, and {there was no courage left in them}<note>Literally "a spirit was no longer in them"</note> because of the presence of the {Israelites}. <note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="2">At that time Yahweh said to Joshua, "Make for yourself knives of flint, and circumcise the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> a second time."</verse>
    <verse num="3">So Joshua made knives of flint, and he circumcised the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> at the hill of the foreskins.<note>Hebrew "Gibeath-haaraloth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the reason why Joshua circumcised all the people: all the males who went out from Egypt, all the warriors, died in the wilderness as they went out from Egypt {on the journey}.<note>Literally "on the road"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">For all the people who left were circumcised, but all the people born in the wilderness {on the journey}<note>Literally "on the road"</note> <transChange type="added">after</transChange> they left from Egypt were not circumcised.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For forty years the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> traveled in the wilderness until all the nation, the warriors that left Egypt, perished, because they did not listen to the voice of Yahweh. To them Yahweh swore that they would not see the land that he<note>Hebrew "Yahweh"</note> swore to their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> to give to us, a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And it was their children <transChange type="added">whom</transChange> he raised in their place that Joshua circumcised, for they were uncircumcised, because they had not been circumcised {on the journey}.<note>Literally "on the road"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="8">And it happened, when all the nation had finished circumcising, they remained where they were in the camp until they recovered.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Today I have rolled away the disgrace of Egypt from you." Therefore, the name of that place is called Gilgal<note>Hebrew "rolling"</note> to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> camped at Gilgal, and they kept the Passover on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, on the plains of Jericho.</verse>
    <verse num="11">On the next day after the Passover, on that<note>Literally "this"</note> very day, they ate from the produce of the land, unleavened cakes and roasted corn.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And the manna ceased the day after, when they <transChange type="added">started</transChange> eating the produce of the land, and there was no longer manna for the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> They ate from the crop of the land of Canaan in that year. </verse>
    <verse num="13">And it happened, when Joshua was by Jericho, {he looked up},<note>Literally "he lifted up his eyes"</note> and he saw a man standing {opposite him}<note>Literally "against him"</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> his sword drawn in his hand. And Joshua went to him and said, "Are you with us, or with our adversaries?"</verse>
    <verse num="14">And he said, "Neither. I have come now <transChange type="added">as</transChange> the commander of Yahweh's army." And Joshua fell on his face to the earth, and {he bowed down}<note>Or "he worshiped"</note> and said to him, "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my lord commanding his servant?"</verse>
    <verse num="15">The commander of Yahweh's army said to Joshua, "Take off your sandals<note>Hebrew "sandal"</note> from your feet,<note>Hebrew "foot"</note> for the place where you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> standing <transChange type="added">is</transChange> holy." And Joshua did so. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Now Jericho <transChange type="added">was</transChange> shut up inside and out because of the presence of the {Israelites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> no one was going out or coming in.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Look, I am giving Jericho into your hand, its king and the soldiers of the army.</verse>
    <verse num="3">You will march around the city, all the warriors circling the city once; you will do so for six days.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And seven priests will bear seven trumpets of rams' horns before the ark. On the seventh day you will march around the city seven times, and the priests will blow on the trumpets.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And when they blow long on the horn of the ram, when you hear the sound of the trumpet, all the people will shout <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a great war cry, and the wall of the city will fall flat,<note>Or "in its place"</note> and {the people will charge, each one straight ahead}."<note>Literally "the people will go up, each before him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">So Joshua son of Nun summoned the priests and said to them, "Take up the ark of the covenant, and let seven priests carry the trumpets of the rams' horns before the ark of Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="7">And he said<note>Hebrew "they said"</note> to the people, "Go forward and march around the city, and let the armed <transChange type="added">men</transChange> pass before the ark of Yahweh. </verse>
    <verse num="8">{And when Joshua spoke}<note>Literally "And it happened the moment of the saying of Joshua"</note> to the people, the seven priests carrying the seven trumpets of rams' horns before the presence of Yahweh went forward and they blew the trumpets; and the ark of the covenant of Yahweh followed behind them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the armed <transChange type="added">men</transChange> went before the priests who blew the trumpets, and the rear guard came after the ark, while they were blowing the trumpets.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But Joshua commanded the people, saying, "You will not shout, and you will not let your voice be heard; a word will not go out from your mouth until the day I say to you 'Shout!' Then you will shout."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And the ark of Yahweh went around the city, {circling once},<note>Literally "circling one occurrence"</note> and they came <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the camp and spent the night in the camp.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Then Joshua got up early in the morning, and the priests took up the ark of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The seven priests carrying the seven trumpets of the rams' horns before the ark of Yahweh went on continually, and they blew on the trumpets. And the armed <transChange type="added">men</transChange> went before them, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rear guard came after the ark of Yahweh, while the trumpets blew continually.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And they marched around the city once on the second day, and they returned <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the camp. They did <transChange type="added">this</transChange> for six days. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Then on the seventh day they rose early at dawn, and they marched around the city in this manner seven times. <transChange type="added">It was</transChange> only on that day that they marched around the city seven times.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And at the seventh time the priests blew on the trumpets, and Joshua said to the people, "Shout! For Yahweh has given you the city.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The city and all that is in it will be devoted to Yahweh; only Rahab the prostitute and all who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with her in the house will live, because she hid the messengers whom we sent.</verse>
    <verse num="18">As for you, keep <transChange type="added">away</transChange> from the things<note>Hebrew "thing"</note> devoted to destruction so that you do not take them and bring about your own destruction, making the camp of Israel an object for destruction, bringing trouble upon it.</verse>
    <verse num="19">But all of the silver and gold, and the items of bronze and iron, <transChange type="added">are</transChange> holy to Yahweh, and they must go to Yahweh's treasury."</verse>
    <verse num="20">So the people shouted, and they<note>That is, the priests</note> blew on the trumpets. And when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, they raised a great shout, and the wall fell flat. {The people charged, each one straight ahead into the city},<note>Literally "The people went up, each before him"</note> and they captured it.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And they utterly destroyed {by the edge of the sword}<note>Literally "by the mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> all who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the city, both men and women, young and old, ox, sheep, and donkey. </verse>
    <verse num="22">Then Joshua said to the two men who spied on the land, "Go <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the prostitute's house and bring out from there the woman and all who belong to her, just as you swore to her."</verse>
    <verse num="23">So the young men who were spies went and brought Rahab and her father and mother, her brothers, and all who were with her. And they brought all her family out and set them outside the camp of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And they burned the city and all that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in it with fire; they put only the silver and gold, and the items of copper and iron, <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the treasury of the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="25">But Joshua spared Rahab the prostitute {and her family}<note>Literally "and the house of her father"</note> and all who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with her, and she has lived in the midst of Israel until this day, because she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho. </verse>
    <verse num="26">And Joshua swore at that time, saying, "Cursed <transChange type="added">is</transChange> anyone before Yahweh who gets up and builds Jericho, this city. At the cost of his firstborn he will lay its foundation, and at the cost of his youngest he will set up its gates."</verse>
    <verse num="27">So Yahweh was with Joshua, and his fame was in all the land. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">But the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> broke faith concerning the devoted things.<note>Or "consecrated possession<transChange type="added">s</transChange>"</note> Achan son of Carmi son of Zabdi son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took from the devoted things;<note>Hebrew "thing" or "consecrated possession"</note> and {Yahweh's anger was kindled}<note>Literally "the nose of Yahweh became hot"</note> against the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="2">Now Joshua sent men from Jericho <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Ai, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near Beth Aven, east of Bethel, and he said to them, "Go up and spy out Ai." And the men went up and spied out Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And they returned to Joshua and said to him, "Do not let all the people go up and attack Ai; <transChange type="added">only</transChange> two or three thousand men should go up because they<note>That is, the people of Ai</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> few. Do not make all the people weary <transChange type="added">up</transChange> there."</verse>
    <verse num="4">So about three thousand from the people went up there, and they fled before the men of Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The men of Ai killed about thirty-six of them, and they chased them from the gate up to Shebarim and killed them on the slope. And the hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> of the people melted and became like water. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And Joshua tore his clothes and fell to the ground on his face before the ark of Yahweh until the evening, he and the elders of Israel; and they put dust on their heads.<note>Hebrew "head"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">And Joshua said, "Ah, my Lord! Why did you bring this people across the Jordan to give us into the hand of the Amorites to destroy us? If only we had been content and stayed beyond the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Please, my Lord! What can I say after {Israel has fled from its enemies}?<note>Literally "Israel has turned its neck before its enemies"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">The Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear <transChange type="added">of this</transChange>, and they will surround us and cut off our name from the land. What will you do, for your great name?" </verse>
    <verse num="10">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Stand up! {Why}<note>Literally "For what this"</note> <transChange type="added">have</transChange> you fallen on your face?</verse>
    <verse num="11">Israel has sinned and {transgressed my covenant}<note>Literally "crossed my covenant"</note> that I commanded them. They have taken from the devoted things;<note>Hebrew "thing" or "from the consecrated possession"</note> they have stolen and acted deceitfully, and they have put <transChange type="added">them</transChange> among their belongings.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> were unable to stand before their enemies; {they fled from their enemies}<note>Literally "they turned <transChange type="added">their</transChange> neck before their enemies"</note> because they have become a thing devoted<note>Or "consecrated"</note> for destruction. {I will be with you no more}<note>Literally "I will not do again to be with you"</note> unless you destroy the devoted things<note>Hebrew "thing" or "consecrated possession"</note> from among you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Get up, sanctify the people, and say, 'Sanctify yourselves for tomorrow. Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel: "<transChange type="added">There are</transChange> devoted things<note>Hebrew "thing" or "consecrated possession"</note> in your midst, O Israel. You will be unable to stand before you enemies until you remove the devoted things<note>Hebrew "thing" or "consecrated possession"</note> from your midst."</verse>
    <verse num="14">In the morning you will come forward, {tribe by tribe},<note>Literally "according to your tribes"</note> and the tribe that Yahweh will select by lot will come forward by clans, and the clan that Yahweh selects by lot will come forward by families, and the family that Yahweh selects by lot will come forward one by one.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The one caught with the devoted things<note>Hebrew "thing" or "consecrated possession"</note> will be burned with fire, he and all that belongs to him, because {he transgressed the covenant}<note>Literally "he crossed the covenant"</note> of Yahweh, and because he did a disgraceful thing in Israel." '" </verse>
    <verse num="16">So<note>Or "And"</note> Joshua rose early in the morning and brought forward Israel, {tribe by tribe},<note>Literally "according to its tribes"</note> and the tribe of Judah was selected by lot.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And he brought forward the clans of Judah and selected the clan of the Zerahites<note>Hebrew "Zerahite"</note> by lot. Then he brought forward the clan of the Zerahites,<note>Hebrew "Zerahite"</note> one by one, and Zabdi was selected by lot.</verse>
    <verse num="18">He brought forward his family, one by one, and Achan son of Carmi son of Zabdi son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was selected by lot.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Joshua said to Achan, "My son, please, give glory to Yahweh the God of Israel, and give him a doxology in court.<note>Some interpret "make a confession"</note> Tell me, please, what you have done; do not hide <transChange type="added">it</transChange> from me."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Achan answered Joshua and said, "It is true. I have sinned against Yahweh the God of Israel, and this is what I did:</verse>
    <verse num="21">I saw among the spoil a beautiful robe from Shinar,<note>"Shinar" refers to Babylonia</note> two hundred shekels of silver, and one bar of gold <transChange type="added">that</transChange> weighed fifty shekels; I coveted them and took them. They <transChange type="added">are</transChange> hidden in the ground inside my tent, and the silver <transChange type="added">is</transChange> under it." </verse>
    <verse num="22">Joshua sent messengers, and they ran to the tent; and there <transChange type="added">they were</transChange>, hidden in his tent, and the silver <transChange type="added">was</transChange> under it.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And they took them from the tent and brought them to Joshua and all the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> And they spread them out before the presence of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Then Joshua, and all Israel with him, took Achan son of Zerah, the silver, the robe, the bar of gold, his sons and daughters, his cattle and donkeys, his sheep, his tent, and everything that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his, and they brought them <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the valley of Achor.<note>Hebrew "trouble"; a valley in the Jericho region</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">And Joshua said, "Why did you bring us trouble? Yahweh will bring you trouble on this day." And all Israel stoned them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> stones;<note>Hebrew "stone"</note> and they burned them with fire <transChange type="added">after</transChange> they stoned them with stones.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then {they placed}<note>Literally "they raised up"</note> on top of him a great pile of stones <transChange type="added">that remains</transChange> to this day. And Yahweh {turned from his burning anger},<note>Literally "turned from his burning nose"</note> and thus the name of that place to this day is called the valley of Achor.<note>Hebrew "trouble"; a valley in the Jericho region</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">Then Yahweh said to Joshua, "Do not fear or be dismayed. Take {all the fighting men}<note>Literally "all the people of war"</note> with you {and go up immediately to Ai}.<note>Literally "get up and go up to Ai"</note> Look, I am giving into your hand the king of Ai, his city, and his land.</verse>
    <verse num="2">You will do to Ai and its king that which you did to Jericho and its king; you may take only its spoils<note>Hebrew "spoil"</note> and livestock as booty for yourself. Set for yourself an ambush against the city <transChange type="added">from</transChange> behind <transChange type="added">it</transChange>." </verse>
    <verse num="3">So Joshua and {all the fighting men}<note>Literally "all the people of war"</note> went up immediately to Ai. Joshua chose thirty thousand of the best fighting men and sent them <transChange type="added">by</transChange> night.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And he commanded them, saying, "Look, you are to lay an ambush against the city from behind. Do not go very far from the city and be ready.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then I and all of the people who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with me will approach the city. And when they go out to meet us {as before},<note>Literally "as that at the first <transChange type="added">occasion</transChange>"</note> we will flee from them.<note>Or "before their presence"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">They will come out after us until we draw them away from the city, because they will think, '<transChange type="added">They are</transChange> fleeing from us<note>Or "before our presence"</note> {as before}.'<note>Literally "as that at the first <transChange type="added">occasion</transChange>"</note> So we will flee from them.<note>Or "before their presence"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Then you will rise up from the ambush and take possession of the city, for Yahweh your God will give it into your hand.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And when you capture the city you will set it on fire as Yahweh commanded. Look, I have commanded you."</verse>
    <verse num="9">So Joshua sent them out, and they went to the <transChange type="added">place of the</transChange> ambush, and they sat between Bethel and Ai, to the west of Ai; but Joshua spent the night {with the people}.<note>Literally "in the middle of the people"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="10">Joshua rose early in the morning and mustered the people, and he went up <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the elders of Israel before the people of Ai.<note>Or "before the presence of the people of Ai"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">{All the fighting men}<note>Literally "All the people of war"</note> who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him {went up and drew near before the city}<note>Literally "went up, drew near, and came before the city"</note> and camped north of Ai; <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> a valley between him and Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And he took about five thousand men and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, to the west of the city.</verse>
    <verse num="13">So they stationed the forces; all the army <transChange type="added">was</transChange> north of the city while {the rear guard was west}.<note>Literally "while its rear guard <transChange type="added">was</transChange> west of the city"</note> But Joshua went that night to the middle of the valley.</verse>
    <verse num="14">When the king of Ai saw <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, the men of the city hurried and rose early and went out to meet Israel for battle--he<note>That is, the king</note> and all his army--to the meeting place before the Arabah.<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> He did not know that <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> an ambush for him behind the city.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Then Joshua and all Israel acted like they were beaten before them, and they fled {in the direction of the wilderness}.<note>Literally "the way of the wilderness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">All of the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the city were called to pursue after them. As they pursued after Joshua, they were drawn away from the city.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Not a man remained in Ai or Bethel who had not gone out after Israel; they left the city open and pursued after Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="18">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Stretch out the sword<note>Or "spear"</note> that is in your hand to Ai, because I will give it into your hand." And Joshua stretched out the sword that was in his hand to the city.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The moment he stretched out his hand, those in the ambush stood up quickly from their place and ran. And they went <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the city and captured it, quickly setting the city ablaze with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Then the men of Ai looked behind them, and they saw smoke from the city rising to the sky; {they had no power to flee this way or that},<note>Literally "it was not in their hands to flee here and here"</note> and the people fleeing the wilderness turned around to the pursuers.<note>Hebrew "pursuer"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">And Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had captured the city and that the smoke of the city was rising; they returned and struck down the men of Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Then the others from the city came out to meet them, {and they found themselves surrounded by Israel},<note>Literally "they were in the middle of Israel"</note> {some on one side, and others on the other side}.<note>Literally "these from these, and these from this"</note> And they<note>That is, Israel</note> struck them down until no survivor or fugitive <transChange type="added">was</transChange> left.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But they captured the king of Ai alive, and they brought him to Joshua. </verse>
    <verse num="24">When Israel finished slaughtering all the inhabitants of Ai in the open field, in the wilderness where they pursued them, and when all of them had fallen by {the edge of the sword}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> until they all had perished, all Israel returned <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Ai and attacked it with {the edge of the sword}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">All the people that fell on that day, both men and women, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> twelve thousand--all the inhabitants of Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For Joshua did not draw back his hand that was stretched out with the sword until he had utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Only the livestock and the spoil of that city Israel took as booty for themselves, according to the word of Yahweh that Joshua commanded.</verse>
    <verse num="28">So Joshua burned Ai and made it an everlasting heap of rubbish, a desolate place until this day.</verse>
    <verse num="29">The king of Ai he hanged on a tree until the time of evening, and as the sun went down Joshua commanded <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, and they brought down his dead body from the tree. Then they threw it at the entrance of the gate of the city, and they raised over it a great heap of stones <transChange type="added">that remains</transChange> to this day. </verse>
    <verse num="30">Then Joshua built an altar on Mount Ebal for Yahweh the God of Israel,</verse>
    <verse num="31">as Moses Yahweh's servant commanded the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> as <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> written in the scroll of the law of Moses: "an altar of unhewn<note>Or "whole"</note> stones <transChange type="added">on</transChange> which no one has {wielded}<note>Literally "waved over them"</note> an iron implement."<note>See Exod 20:25</note> And they offered burnt offerings on it and sacrificed fellowship offerings.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And there Joshua wrote on the stones <transChange type="added">a</transChange> copy of the law of Moses, which he<note>That is, Moses</note> had written, in the presence of the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="33">Then all Israel, {foreigner as well as native},<note>Literally "as the alien as the native"</note> with the elders, officials, and judges stood {on either side}<note>Literally "from this and from this"</note> of the ark before the priests and the Levites, who carried the ark of the covenant of Yahweh. Half of them <transChange type="added">stood</transChange> in front of Mount Gerizim, and the other half in front of Mount Ebal, as Moses Yahweh's servant had commanded before to bless the people of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="34">And afterward he read all the words of the law, the blessings<note>Hebrew "blessing"</note> and the curses,<note>Hebrew "curse"</note> according to all that was written in the scroll of the law.</verse>
    <verse num="35">There was not a word from all that Moses commanded that Joshua did not read before the assembly of all Israel, and the women, the little children, and the traveling foreigners<note>Hebrew "foreigner"</note> among them. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">Now<note>Or "And it happened"</note> when all the kings who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> beyond the Jordan in the hill country and in the Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> and on all the coast of the great sea toward Lebanon<note>Literally "white mountain"</note>--the Hittites,<note>Hebrew "Hittite"</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> and the Jebusites<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note>--heard of <transChange type="added">this</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="2">they gathered themselves together to fight with one accord against<note>Hebrew "with"</note> Joshua and Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="3">But the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Joshua did to Jericho and Ai,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and they acted on their part with cunning: they went and prepared provisions,<note>The Hebrew is difficult here. Some ancient manuscripts read, "they sent out a delegation/an envoy"</note> and took worn-out sacks<note>Or "sackcloths"</note> for their donkeys and old wineskins <transChange type="added">that were</transChange> torn and mended.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The sandals on their feet <transChange type="added">were</transChange> patched and old, their clothes <transChange type="added">were</transChange> old, and their food was dry and crumbled.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And they went to Joshua at the camp <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Gilgal and said to him and to the men of Israel, "We have come from a far land; so then {make a covenant with us}."<note>Literally "cut for us a covenant"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">And the men of Israel said to the Hivites,<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> "Perhaps you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> living among us; how can we {make a covenant}<note>Literally "cut a covenant"</note> with you?"</verse>
    <verse num="8">They said to Joshua, "We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> your servants." And Joshua said to them, "Who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you, and from where do you come?"</verse>
    <verse num="9">And they said to him, "Your servants have come from a very far land because of the name of Yahweh your God; we have heard of his reputation, of all that he did in Egypt,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and of all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> beyond the Jordan--to Sihon king of Heshbon and to Og king of Bashan, who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Ashtaroth.</verse>
    <verse num="11">So our elders said to us and all the inhabitants of our land, 'Take in your hand provisions for the journey, and go to meet them, and say to them, "We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> your servants; so then {make a covenant with us}." '<note>Literally "cut for us a covenant"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> our bread; <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> hot <transChange type="added">when</transChange> we took it from our houses as provisions on the day we set out to come to you. But now, look, it is dry and crumbled.</verse>
    <verse num="13">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the wineskins that we filled new, but look, they have burst; and these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> our clothes and sandals that have worn out from the very long journey."</verse>
    <verse num="14">So the leaders<note>Or "men"</note> took from their provisions, but {they did not ask direction from Yahweh}.<note>Literally "the mouth of Yahweh they did not ask"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua made peace with them, and {he made a covenant with them}<note>Literally "he cut a covenant with them"</note> to allow them to live happily, and the leaders of the congregation swore <transChange type="added">an oath</transChange> to them. </verse>
    <verse num="16">And it happened that at the end of three days, after they made a covenant with them, they heard that {they were their neighbors}<note>Literally "they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> near them"</note> and living among them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> set out and went to their cities on the third day (their cities <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Gibeon, Kephirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath Jearim).</verse>
    <verse num="18">But the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did not attack them, because the leaders of the congregation had sworn to them by Yahweh the God of Israel. And all the congregation murmured {against their leaders}.<note>Literally "against the leaders of the congregation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">But all the leaders of the congregation said, "We have sworn to them by Yahweh the God of Israel, and so we cannot touch them.</verse>
    <verse num="20">This we will do to them: <transChange type="added">we will</transChange> let them live so that wrath will not be on us because of the oath we swore to them."</verse>
    <verse num="21">And the leaders<note>Or "men"</note> said to them, "Let them live." So they became woodcutters and water carriers for all the congregation, just as the leaders had said to them. </verse>
    <verse num="22">And Joshua summoned them and said, "Why have you deceived us saying, 'We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> very far from you' when you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> living among us?</verse>
    <verse num="23">Therefore you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> cursed; some of you will always be slaves as woodcutters and water carriers for the house of my God."</verse>
    <verse num="24">And they answered Joshua and said, "Because it was told with certainty to your servants that Yahweh your God commanded Moses his servant to give to you all the land and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land before you, so we were very afraid for our lives because of you, and so we did this thing.</verse>
    <verse num="25">So then, look, we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in your hand; do with us whatever seems good and right in your eyes."</verse>
    <verse num="26">So he did this to them: he saved them from the hand of the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and they did not kill them.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And that day Joshua made them woodcutters and water carriers for the congregation and for the altar of Yahweh, to this day, in the place that he should choose. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">And it happened that when Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem heard that Joshua captured Ai and had utterly destroyed it (just as he had done to Jericho and its king, so he did to Ai and its king) and that the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel and were among them,</verse>
    <verse num="2">he<note>Hebrew "they"</note> became very afraid because Gibeon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a very large city, {like one of the royal cities},<note>Literally "like one of the cities of the kingship"</note> and because it <transChange type="added">was</transChange> larger than Ai, and all its men <transChange type="added">were</transChange> mighty warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="3">So Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem sent <transChange type="added">word</transChange> to Hohman king of Hebron, to Piram king of Jarmuth, to Japhia king of Lachish, and to Debir king of Eglon, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="4">"Come up and help me, and let us attack Gibeon, because it has made peace with Joshua and the {Israelites}."<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And the five kings of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon, gathered <transChange type="added">together</transChange> and went up, they and all their forces, and {they laid siege to Gibeon}<note>Literally "they camped against Gibeon"; see Josh 10:31</note> and made war against it. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And the men of Gibeon sent <transChange type="added">word</transChange> to Joshua at the camp at Gilgal, saying, "{Do not abandon}<note>Literally "do not release your hands from"</note> your servant. Come up to us quickly and save us! Help us, for all the kings of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> who dwell in the hill country have gathered against us."</verse>
    <verse num="7">So Joshua went up from Gilgal, he and {all the fighting men}<note>Literally "all the people of the war"</note> with him, {all the best warriors}.<note>Literally "all the mighty warriors of the army"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Do not be afraid of them, for I have given them into your hand; {no one will withstand you}.<note>Literally "not a man of them will stand in your presence"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Joshua came upon them suddenly {by marching up}<note>Literally "he went up"</note> all night from Gilgal.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Yahweh threw them into panic before Israel, who<note>Hebrew "he"</note> struck them <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a great blow at Gibeon and pursued them by the way of the ascent of Beth-horon and struck them as far as Azekah and Makkedah.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And as they were fleeing from Israel, <transChange type="added">they were</transChange> on the slope of Beth-horon, and Yahweh threw huge stones from the heavens on them as far as Azekah; and more died by the hail stones than those whom the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> killed by the sword. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Then Joshua spoke to Yahweh, on the day Yahweh gave the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> over to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and he said in the sight of Israel, </verse>
    <verse num="13">And the sun stood still, and the moon stopped, until <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nation took vengeance <transChange type="added">on</transChange> its enemies.</verse>
    <verse num="14">There has not been a day like this before it or after, that Yahweh listened to the voice of <transChange type="added">a</transChange> man; for Yahweh fought for Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua returned and all Israel with him to the camp at Gilgal. </verse>
    <verse num="16">But these five kings fled and hid themselves in the cave at Makkedah.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And it was told to Joshua, saying, "The five kings were found hidden in the cave at Makkedah."</verse>
    <verse num="18">And Joshua said, "Roll large stones against the mouth of the cave, and set men in front of it to guard them.</verse>
    <verse num="19">But do not stay <transChange type="added">there</transChange>; pursue after your enemies and attack them from the rear. Do not allow them to go into their cities, for Yahweh your God has given them into your hand."</verse>
    <verse num="20">When Joshua and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> had finished striking them <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a very great blow, until they perished, {those of them who survived}<note>Literally "the survivors <transChange type="added">who</transChange> survived"</note> went into the fortified cities,</verse>
    <verse num="21">and all the people returned to the camp safely<note>Or "in peace"</note> to Joshua <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Makkedah. {No one spoke}<note>Literally "No one moved his tongue"</note> against the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="22">And Joshua said, "Open the mouth of the cave, and bring to me those five kings from the cave."</verse>
    <verse num="23">And they did so, and brought him these five kings from the cave, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And when they brought these kings to Joshua, Joshua called all the men of Israel and said to the commanders of {the fighting men}<note>Literally "the men of war"</note> who had gone with him, "Come near, put your feet on the necks of these kings." So they came near and put their feet on their necks.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And Joshua said to them, "Do not be afraid or dismayed! Be strong and bold, for thus Yahweh will do to all your enemies whom you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> about to fight.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And after this Joshua struck them down and killed them, and he hanged them on five trees. And they were hanging on the trees until the evening.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And it happened {at the time of sunset},<note>Literally "at the time of the going of the sun"</note> Joshua commanded, and they took them down from the trees and threw them into the cave where they had hidden themselves, and they put large stones against the mouth of the cave, <transChange type="added">which are there</transChange> to this very day. </verse>
    <verse num="28">Joshua captured Makkedah on that day, and he struck it and its king with {the edge of the sword};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> he utterly destroyed it and everyone that was in it. He did not leave behind a survivor. So he did to the king of Makkedah just as he did to the king of Jericho. </verse>
    <verse num="29">And Joshua passed on, and all of Israel with him, from Makkedah <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Libnah, and he fought against Libnah.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And Yahweh also gave it into the hand of Israel, and its king and all the people in it he struck with {the edge of the sword}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> He left in it no survivor. He did to its king just as he did to the king of Jericho. </verse>
    <verse num="31">And Joshua passed on, and all of Israel with him, from Libnah to Lachish, and {he laid siege to it}<note>Literally "he camped opposite it"</note> and fought against it.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And Yahweh gave Lachish into the hand of Israel, and he captured it on the second day. He struck it with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and everyone in it, just as he did to Libnah. </verse>
    <verse num="33">Then Horam king of Gezer came up to help Lachish, and Joshua struck him and his people until he left no survivor behind. </verse>
    <verse num="34">And Joshua passed on, and all of Israel with him, from Lachish to Eglon, and {they laid siege to it}<note>Literally "they camped opposite it"</note> and fought against it.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And they captured it on that day, and he struck it with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and all the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it on that day he utterly destroyed as he had done to Lachish. </verse>
    <verse num="36">And Joshua went up, and all Israel with him, from Eglon to Hebron, and they fought against it</verse>
    <verse num="37">and captured it, and they struck it with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> its king and all its cities, and all the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it; he left behind no survivor, as he had done to Eglon, and he utterly destroyed it and all the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it.</verse>
    <verse num="38">Then Joshua returned to Debir, and all of Israel with him, and they fought against it,</verse>
    <verse num="39">and he captured it and its king and all its cities, and they struck them with {the the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and they utterly destroyed all the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it; he left behind no survivor, just as he had done to Hebron. Thus he did to Debir and its king what he had done to Libnah and its king. </verse>
    <verse num="40">So Joshua struck all the land--the hill country, the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> the Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> and the slopes<note>The slopes of the hills of the western Jordan to the Dead Sea region</note>--and all their kings; he left behind no survivor, and {all that breathed}<note>Literally "all of the breath"</note> he utterly destroyed as Yahweh the God of Israel commanded.</verse>
    <verse num="41">Joshua struck them from Kadesh Barnea to Gaza, and all the land of Goshen up to Gibeon;</verse>
    <verse num="42">all of these kings and their land Joshua captured at one time, because Yahweh the God of Israel fought for Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="43">And Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">And it happened, when Jabin king of Hazor heard <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, he sent to Jobab king of Madon, to the king of Shimron, to the king of Acshaph,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and to the kings who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the north in the hill country, in the Arabah<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan valley</note> south of Kinnereth,<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> in the Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> and in Naphoth Dor<note>Or "the heights of Dor"</note> in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> west,</verse>
    <verse num="3">to the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east and <transChange type="added">west</transChange>, the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the Hittites,<note>Hebrew "Hittite"</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> and the Jebusites<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> in the hill country, and the Hivites<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> {at the foot of}<note>Literally "under"</note> Hermon in the land of Mizpah.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They came out, they and all their armies with them, <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a great army like the sand on the seashore, with very many horses and chariots.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And all these kings joined forces, and they came and camped together by the waters of Merom to fight with Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And Yahweh said to Joshua, "Do not be afraid because of their presence, for tomorrow at this time I <transChange type="added">will</transChange> hand them over slain to Israel; you will hamstring their horses and burn their chariots with fire."</verse>
    <verse num="7">So Joshua, and {all the fighting men}<note>Literally "all the people of war"</note> with him, came against them suddenly at the waters of Merom, and {they attacked them}.<note>Literally "they fell upon them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">And Yahweh gave them into the hand of Israel, and they struck them and pursued them up to Great Sidon and Misrephoth Maim, and eastward up to the valley of Mizpeh. And they struck them until they left behind no survivor.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Joshua did to them as Yahweh commanded him; he hamstrung their horses and burned their chariots with fire. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Then Joshua turned back at that time, and he captured Hazor and struck its king with the sword, because Hazor formerly <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the head of all these kingdoms.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He struck all the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> utterly destroying them. {There was no one left who breathed},<note>Literally "No one was left over of any breath"</note> and he burned Hazor with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Joshua captured all the cities of these kings, and all their kings, and he utterly destroyed them with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> as Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Israel did not burn the cities standing on their mounds,<note>Hebrew "mound"</note> except Hazor alone, <transChange type="added">which</transChange> Joshua burned.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And all the spoil and livestock of these cities the {Israelites} took as booty; they struck the people with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> until they had destroyed them--they left behind no one who breathed.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Just as Yahweh commanded Moses his servant, so Moses commanded Joshua, and Joshua did; he left nothing undone that Yahweh had commanded Moses. </verse>
    <verse num="16">So Joshua took all this land: the hill country, all the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> all the land of Goshen,<note>A southern region; the name means "on the mountains"</note> the Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> the Arabah,<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan valley</note> and the hill country of Israel and its Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">from Mount Halak <transChange type="added">that</transChange> rises to Seir and to Baal Gad in the valley of Lebanon<note>Or "white mountain"</note> {at the foot of}<note>Literally "under"</note> Mount Hermon; he captured all their kings, struck them, and killed them.</verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">For</transChange> many days Joshua made war with all these kings.</verse>
    <verse num="19">There was not a city that made peace with the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> besides the Hivites<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> and the inhabitants of Gibeon--{all were taken in battle}.<note>Literally "the all they took in the battle"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">For it was Yahweh that {hardened their hearts},<note>Literally "made their heart<transChange type="added">s</transChange> strong"</note> to meet Israel in war in order to utterly destroy them without mercy, that they would destroy them just as Yahweh commanded Moses. </verse>
    <verse num="21">At that time Joshua came and exterminated the Anakites from the hill country, from Hebron, Debir, Anab, and from all the hill country of Judah, and from all the hill country of Israel; Joshua utterly destroyed them with their cities.</verse>
    <verse num="22">None of the Anakites were left in the land of the {Israelites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> some remained only in Gaza, Gath, and Ashdod.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Joshua took all the land according to all that Yahweh had spoken to Moses; and Joshua gave it as an inheritance to Israel, according to their tribal divisions, and the land rested from war. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the kings of the land whom the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> defeated, and of whose land they took possession beyond the Jordon {to the east},<note>Literally "to the rising of the sun"</note> from the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon up to Mount Hermon, and all the Arabah<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> to the east:</verse>
    <verse num="2">Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived in Heshbon, and ruled from Aroer, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon, <transChange type="added">from</transChange> the middle of the valley and half of Gilead, up to the {Jabbok River},<note>Literally "Jabbok the wadi"</note> <transChange type="added">which marks</transChange> the border of the {Ammonites};<note>Literally "sons of Ammon" or "children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">and the Arabah<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> up to the Kinnereth Sea<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> to the east, and as far as the sea of Arabah, the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> to the east, {in the direction of}<note>Literally "the way of"</note> Beth Jeshimoth, and to <transChange type="added">the area</transChange> southward, {at the foot of}<note>Literally "under"</note> the slopes of Pisgah;<note>Or Ashdoth Pisgah</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">the territory of Og king of Bashan, one of the last of the Rephaites, who lived at Ashtaroth and Edrei</verse>
    <verse num="5">and ruled over Mount Hermon and Salecah and over all Bashan up to the border of the Geshurites<note>Hebrew "Geshurite"</note> and the Maacathites,<note>Hebrew "Maacathite"</note> and half of Gilead, as far as the border of Sihon king of Heshbon.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Moses Yahweh's servant and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> defeated them; and Moses Yahweh's servant gave it <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a possession to the Reubenites,<note>Hebrew "Reubenite"</note> the Gadites,<note>Hebrew "Gadite"</note> and the half-tribe of Manasseh. </verse>
    <verse num="7">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the kings of the land whom Joshua and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> defeated beyond to the Jordan to the west, from Baal Gad in the valley of Lebanon,<note>Or "white mountain"</note> and up to Mount Halak, <transChange type="added">which</transChange> rises to Seir. And Joshua gave it <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a possession to the tribes of Israel according to their allotments,</verse>
    <verse num="8">in the hill country, the Shephelah,<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> the Arabah,<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> on the slopes, in the wilderness, and in the Negev;<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> the Hittites,<note>Hebrew "Hittite"</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> and the Jebusites:<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="9">the king of Jericho, one; the king of Ai, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> beside Bethel, one; </verse>
    <verse num="10">the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Hebron, one; </verse>
    <verse num="11">the king of Jarmuth, one; the king of Lachish, one; </verse>
    <verse num="12">the king of Eglon, one; the king of Gezer, one; </verse>
    <verse num="13">the king of Debir, one; the king of Geder, one; </verse>
    <verse num="14">the king of Hormah, one; the king of Arad, one; </verse>
    <verse num="15">the king of Libnah, one; the king of Adullam, one; </verse>
    <verse num="16">the king of Makkedah, one; the king of Bethel, one; </verse>
    <verse num="17">the king of Tappuah, one; the king of Hepher, one; </verse>
    <verse num="18">the king of Aphek, one; the king of Lasharon, one; </verse>
    <verse num="19">the king of Madon, one; the king of Hazor, one; </verse>
    <verse num="20">the king of Shimron-meron, one; the king of Acshaph, one; </verse>
    <verse num="21">the king of Taanach, one; the king of Megiddo, one; </verse>
    <verse num="22">the king of Kedesh, one; the king of Jokneam in Carmel, one; </verse>
    <verse num="23">the king of Dor in Naphath Dor, one; the king of Goiim for Gilgal, one; </verse>
    <verse num="24">the king of Tirzah, one; all the kings, thirty-one. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">Now Joshua was old <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {advanced in years},<note>Literally "he went in the days"</note> and Yahweh said to him, "You are old <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {advanced in years},<note>Literally "you went in the days"</note> and very much of the land remains to be possessed.</verse>
    <verse num="2">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the remaining land: all the regions of the Philistines, and all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the Geshurites,<note>Hebrew "Geshurite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">from the Shihor, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {east of Egypt},<note>Literally "on the face of Egypt"</note> up to the border of Ekron to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north, which is reckoned as Canaanite; <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> five Philistine rulers: the Gazites,<note>Hebrew "Gazite"</note> Ashdodites,<note>Hebrew "Ashdodite"</note> Ashkelonites,<note>Hebrew "Ashkelonite"</note> Gittites,<note>Hebrew "Gittite"</note> Ekronites,<note>Hebrew "Ekronite"</note> and the Avvim.</verse>
    <verse num="4">In <transChange type="added">the</transChange> south; all the land of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> and Mearah, which <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to the Sidonians up to Aphek, to the border of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">and the land of the Gebalites, and all the Lebanon,<note>Or "white mountain"</note> {toward the east},<note>Literally "the rise of the sun"</note> from Baal Gad {at the foot of}<note>Or "below" or "under"</note> Mount Hermon up to Lebo-Hamath;</verse>
    <verse num="6">all the inhabitants of the hill country, from the Lebanon<note>Or "white mountain"</note> up to Misrephoth Maim, and all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sidonians. I will drive them out from before the {Israelites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> only allocate it to Israel as an inheritance just as I have commanded you.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Therefore, divide this land as an inheritance to the nine tribes and the half-tribe of Manasseh." </verse>
    <verse num="8">With it<note>That is, the other half-tribe of Manasseh</note> the Reubenites,<note>Hebrew "Reubenite"</note> and the Gadites<note>Hebrew "Gadite"</note> received their inheritance, which Moses gave them beyond the Jordan to the east, just as Moses Yahweh's servant gave to them:</verse>
    <verse num="9">from Aroer, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon, and the city which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the middle of the wadi, and all the plateau <transChange type="added">from</transChange> Medeba up to Dibon;</verse>
    <verse num="10">and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> who reigned in Heshbon up to the border of the {Ammonites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurite<note>Hebrew "Geshurite"</note> and the Maacathites,<note>Hebrew "Maacathite"</note> all of {Mount Hermon},<note>Or "the hill country of Hermon"</note> and Bashan up to Salecah;</verse>
    <verse num="12">all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and Edrei--he was left over from the survivors<note>Hebrew "survivor"</note> of the Rephaim; these Moses had defeated and driven out.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did not drive out the Geshurites<note>Hebrew "Geshurite"</note> or the Maacathites;<note>Hebrew "Maacathite"</note> Geshur and Maacah live among Israel to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Only the tribe of Levites<note>Hebrew "Levite"</note> Moses did not give an inheritance; the offerings made by fire to Yahweh the God of Israel <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> inheritance, just as he promised to them.<note>Hebrew "he said to him"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="15">Moses gave <transChange type="added">an inheritance</transChange> to the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Their territory was from Aroer, which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> on the edge of the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Arnon, and the city that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the middle of the valley, and all the plateau by Medeba;</verse>
    <verse num="17">Heshbon and its cities that <transChange type="added">are</transChange> on the plateau; Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon,</verse>
    <verse num="18">Jahaz, Kedemoth, Mephaath,</verse>
    <verse num="19">Kiriathaim, Sibmah, and Zereth Shahar on the hill of the valley;</verse>
    <verse num="20">Beth Peor, the slopes of Pisgah, and Beth Jeshimoth;</verse>
    <verse num="21">all of the cities of the plateau, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> who reigned in Heshbon and whom Moses defeated with the leaders of Midian, Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba, the princes of Sihon who dwelled in the land.</verse>
    <verse num="22"><transChange type="added">In addition</transChange> to their slain, the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> killed with the sword Balaam son of Beor, who practiced divination.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And the border of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the Jordan and <transChange type="added">its</transChange> banks.<note>Hebrew "bank"</note> This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben according to their families, the cities, and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="24">Moses gave <transChange type="added">an inheritance</transChange> to the tribe of Gad, to the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gad, according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Their territory was Jazer and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> up to Aroer, {which is east of Rabbah};<note>Literally "which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> before Rabbah"</note></verse>
    <verse num="26">and from Heshbon up to Ramah-Mizpeh and Betonim, and from Mahanaim up to the territory to Debir;</verse>
    <verse num="27">in the valley of Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, Succoth, Zaphon, and the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, the Jordan and <transChange type="added">its</transChange> banks,<note>Hebrew "bank"</note> up to the <transChange type="added">lower</transChange> end of the Kinnereth Sea<note>That is, the Sea of Galilee</note> beyond the Jordan to the east.</verse>
    <verse num="28">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the {Gadites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Gad"</note> according to their families, the cities, and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="29">Moses gave <transChange type="added">an inheritance</transChange> to the half-tribe of Manasseh; it was for the half-tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Their territory was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the settlements<note>Or "tent villages"</note> of Jair, which <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in Bashan, sixty cities,</verse>
    <verse num="31">and half of Gilead, with Ashtaroth, Edrei, and the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan; <transChange type="added">these were allotted</transChange> to the children of Makir son of Manasseh, for half of the children of Makir according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="32">These <transChange type="added">are the territories</transChange> that Moses gave as an inheritance on the desert-plateau of Moab, beyond the Jordan, east of Jericho.</verse>
    <verse num="33">But to the tribe of Levi Moses did not give an inheritance; Yahweh the God of Israel, he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their inheritance, just as {he promised them}.<note>Literally "he said to them"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">These <transChange type="added">are the territories</transChange> that the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> inherited in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the families of the tribes of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gave as an inheritance to them.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Their inheritance <transChange type="added">was</transChange> by lot, just as Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses, for the nine tribes and the half-tribe.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For Moses had given <transChange type="added">an</transChange> inheritance of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> two tribes and the half-tribe beyond the Jordan, but to the Levites he gave no inheritance among them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim, and they did not give a plot of ground to the Levites in the land, only cities to live <transChange type="added">in</transChange>, with their pastureland for their flocks and for their goods.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Just as Yahweh commanded Moses, so the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did; and they allotted the land. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Then the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah came to Joshua at Gilgal; and Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite said to him, "You know the word that Yahweh said to Moses the man of God at Kadesh Barnea concerning you and me.</verse>
    <verse num="7">{I was forty years old}<note>Literally "I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a son of forty year<transChange type="added">s</transChange>"</note> when Moses Yahweh's servant sent me from Kadesh Barnea to spy out the land, and I returned {with an honest report}.<note>Literally "with a word just as <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with my heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">My companions who went up with me made the hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> of the people melt, but I remained true to Yahweh my God.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Moses swore on that day, saying, 'Surely the land that your foot has trodden on will be an inheritance to you and your sons forever, because you remained true to Yahweh my God.'</verse>
    <verse num="10">So then, look, Yahweh has kept me alive just as he promised these forty-five years,<note>Hebrew "year"</note> from the time that Yahweh spoke this word to Moses while Israel {wandered}<note>Literally "went"</note> in the wilderness. Now look, today {I am eighty-five years old}.<note>Literally "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a son of eighty-five year<transChange type="added">s</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Today I am still strong, just as on the day that Moses sent me; as my strength <transChange type="added">was</transChange> then, so now also <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my strength for war {and for daily activities}.<note>Literally "for going out and for coming <transChange type="added">in</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">So now give me this hill country that Yahweh spoke <transChange type="added">of</transChange> on that day, for you heard on that day that the Anakites <transChange type="added">were</transChange> there, with great and fortified cities. Perhaps Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with me, and I will drive them out just as Yahweh promised."<note>Or "said"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="13">And Joshua blessed him and gave Hebron to Caleb son of Jephunneh as an inheritance.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Thus Hebron became the inheritance of Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite to this day, because he remained true to Yahweh the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the name of Hebron formerly <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Kiriath Arba;<note>Or "the city of Arba"</note> <transChange type="added">Arba was</transChange> the greatest person among the Anakites. And the land rested from war. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">The allotment for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah according to their families reached to the border of Edom, to the wilderness of Zin, {to the far south}.<note>Literally "to the south at the end of south"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Their southern border was from the end of the Salt Sea,<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> from the bay facing southward;</verse>
    <verse num="3">it continues<note>Hebrew "goes out"</note> to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> south to the ascent of Akrabbim, passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> to Zin, it goes up south of Kadesh Barnea, passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> Hezron, goes up to Addar, and makes a turn to Karka;</verse>
    <verse num="4">{it passes on}<note>Literally "it was to"</note> to Azmon, continues<note>Hebrew "goes out"</note> by the wadi of Egypt, and {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of the border were"</note> at the sea. This will be your southern border.</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> eastern border <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> up to the mouth<note>Or "end"</note> of the Jordan. <transChange type="added">The</transChange> border on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> northern side <transChange type="added">runs</transChange> from the bay of the sea at the mouth<note>Or "end"</note> of the Jordan;</verse>
    <verse num="6">the border goes up to Beth-hoglah and passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> north of Beth Arabah; and the border goes up the stone of Bohan son of Reuben;</verse>
    <verse num="7">and the border goes up to Debir from the valley of Achor, and to the north, turning to Gilgal, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> opposite the ascent of Adummim, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> south of the wadi;<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> and the border passes on to the waters of En Shemesh, and it ends at En Rogel.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Then the border goes up <transChange type="added">by</transChange> the Valley of Ben Hinnom<note>Or "valley of the son of Hinnom"</note> to the slope of the Jebusites<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> south (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Jerusalem); and the border goes up to the top of the mountain that <transChange type="added">lies</transChange> opposite the valley of Hinnom to the west, which is at the end of the valley of Rephaim to the north;</verse>
    <verse num="9">then the border turns from the top of the mountain to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah, and continues<note>Hebrew "goes out"</note> from there to the cities of Mount Ephron; the border <transChange type="added">then</transChange> turns <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Baalah (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Kiriath Jearim);</verse>
    <verse num="10">and the border goes around from Baalah to the west, to Mount Seir, and passes on to the slope of Mount Jearim from the north (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Kesalon), and goes down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Beth Shemesh, and passes <transChange type="added">along by</transChange> Timnah.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The border continues<note>"Hebrew "goes out"</note> to the slope of Ekron to the north, <transChange type="added">then</transChange> bends around to Shikkeron, it passes <transChange type="added">on</transChange> to Mount Baalah and continues <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Jabneel; and {the border ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of the border were"</note> at the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And <transChange type="added">the</transChange> western border <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> and its coast. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the border surrounding the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah according to their families. </verse>
    <verse num="13">{According to the commandment of Yahweh to Joshua},<note>Literally "according to the mouth of Yahweh to Joshua"</note> he gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh a plot of ground among the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah, Kiriath Arba,<note>Or "the city of Arba"</note> which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Hebron (<transChange type="added">Arba</transChange> was Anak's father).</verse>
    <verse num="14">Caleb drove out from there three of Anak's sons, Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai, the descendants<note>Or "children"</note> of Anak.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And from there he went up against the inhabitants of Debir (the former name of Debir <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Kiriath Sepher).</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Caleb said, "Whoever attacks Kiriath Sepher and captures it, I will give to him my daughter Acsah as a wife."</verse>
    <verse num="17">Othniel son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, captured it, and he gave to him Acsah his daughter as a wife.</verse>
    <verse num="18">When she came <transChange type="added">to him</transChange> she urged him to ask her father for a field. So she dismounted from the donkey, and Caleb said to her, "{What do you want}?"<note>Literally "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for you?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And she said to him, "Give to me a gift;<note>Or "blessing"</note> you have given me the land of the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> and you must give to me a spring of water." And he gave to her the upper and lower spring.<note>Joshua 15:13-19 is almost identical to Judges 1:11-15</note> </verse>
    <verse num="20">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah according to their families:</verse>
    <verse num="21">the cities belonging to the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah to the far south, to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> border of Edom to the south, were Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur,</verse>
    <verse num="22">Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah,</verse>
    <verse num="23">Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan,</verse>
    <verse num="24">Ziph, Telem, Bealoth,</verse>
    <verse num="25">Hazor Hadattah, Kerioth Hezron (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Hazor),</verse>
    <verse num="26">Amam, Shema, Moladah,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet,</verse>
    <verse num="28">Hazar Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah,</verse>
    <verse num="29">Baalah, Iim, Ezem,</verse>
    <verse num="30">Eltolad, Kesil, Hormah,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah,</verse>
    <verse num="32">Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and Rimmon; <transChange type="added">in</transChange> all, twenty-nine cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="33">In the Shephelah:<note>Or "lowlands"; a geographical region on the western edge of the hills of Judea</note> Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah,</verse>
    <verse num="34">Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam,</verse>
    <verse num="35">Jarmuth, Adullam, Socoh, Azekah,</verse>
    <verse num="36">Shaaraim, Adithaim, Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="37">Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad,</verse>
    <verse num="38">Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel,</verse>
    <verse num="39">Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon,</verse>
    <verse num="40">Cabbon, Lahma, Kitlish,</verse>
    <verse num="41">Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="42">Libnah, Ether, Ashan,</verse>
    <verse num="43">Jephthah, Ashnah, Nezib,</verse>
    <verse num="44">Keilah, Aczib, and Mareshah; nine cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="45">Ekron, its towns and villages;</verse>
    <verse num="46">from Ekron to the sea, and all that {were near}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">were</transChange> on the hand of"</note> Ashdod and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="47">Ashdod, its towns and villages; Gaza, its towns and villages, up to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Egypt and the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> and its coast.<note>Literally "border"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="48">And in the hill country: Shamir, Jattir, Socoh,</verse>
    <verse num="49">Dannah, Kiriath Sanna (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Debir),</verse>
    <verse num="50">Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim,</verse>
    <verse num="51">Goshen, Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="52">Arab, Dumah, Eshan,</verse>
    <verse num="53">Janim, Beth-tappuah, Aphekah,</verse>
    <verse num="54">Humtah, Kiriath Arba<note>Or "the city of Arba"</note> (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Hebron), and Zior; nine cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="55">Moan, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah,</verse>
    <verse num="56">Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah,</verse>
    <verse num="57">Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="58">Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor,</verse>
    <verse num="59">Maarath, Beth Anoth, and Eltekon; six cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="60">Kiriath Baal (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Kiriath Jearim) and Rabbah; two cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="61">In the wilderness: Beth Arabah, Middin, Secacah,</verse>
    <verse num="62">Nibshan, the city of Salt, and En Gedi; six cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="63">But the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah were unable to drive out the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so the Jebusites live with the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah in Jerusalem to this day. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">The allotment of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph went from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Jordan by Jericho, at the waters of Jericho to the east, <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the wilderness, going up from Jericho into the hill country <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Bethel;</verse>
    <verse num="2">it continues from Bethel to Luz, and it passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> to the territory of the Arkites<note>Hebrew "Arkite"</note> at Ataroth.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then it goes down, to the west, to the territory of the Japhletites,<note>Hebrew "Japhletite"</note> up to the territory of Lower Beth-horon, then to Gezer, and {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the sea. </verse>
    <verse num="4">And the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, received their inheritance.</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">This</transChange> was the border of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ephraim according to their families: the border of their inheritance to the east <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ataroth Addar, up to Upper Beth-horon.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The border continues to the sea; from Micmethath to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north, the border turns to the east to Taanath Shiloh, and it passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> it from the east to Janoah.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then it goes down from Janoah to Ataroth and to Naarah; it touches Jericho and ends <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the Jordan;</verse>
    <verse num="8">from Tappuah the border goes to the west, <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kanah, and {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the sea. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ephraim according to their families,</verse>
    <verse num="9">with the cities that were set apart for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ephraim in the midst of the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh, all the cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But they did not drive out the Canananites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> who were dwelling in Gezer, and so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> live in the midst of Ephraim to this day, but they became forced laborers. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">Then the allotment was made for the tribe of Manasseh, because he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the firstborn of Joseph. To Makir, the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, {were allotted}<note>Literally "and there was to him"</note> Gilead and Bashan, because he was a warrior.<note>Literally "a man of war"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">An allotment</transChange> was <transChange type="added">made</transChange> for the remaining descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh, according to their families: For the children of Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher, and Shemida--these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the male descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh son of Joseph according to their families. </verse>
    <verse num="3">But Zelophehad son of Hepher, son of Gilead, son of Makir, son of Manasseh, had no sons, only daughters. These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They came before Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the leaders, saying, "Yahweh commanded Moses to give an inheritance to us among our kinsmen."<note>Or "among our brothers"</note> Therefore, according to the {command of Yahweh}<note>Literally "mouth of Yahweh"</note> he gave them an inheritance among the kinsmen<note>Or "brothers"</note> of their father.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Thus ten shares fell to Manasseh, besides the land of Gilead and Bashan, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> beyond the Jordan,</verse>
    <verse num="6">because the daughters of Manasseh received an inheritance among his sons. And the land of Gilead was <transChange type="added">allotted</transChange> to the remaining descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The border of Manasseh was from Asher <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Micmethath, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> opposite Shechem;<note>Or "which faces Shechem"</note> then the border goes to the south, to the inhabitants of En Tappuah.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The land of Tappuah {belonged to Manasseh},<note>Literally "was to Manasseh"</note> but Tuppuah on the border of Manasseh {belonged to the descendants of Ephraim}.<note>Literally "was to the children of Ephraim"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Then the border goes down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kanah to the south of the wadi. These cities <transChange type="added">belong</transChange> to Ephraim among the cities of Manasseh. The border of Manasseh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> north of the wadi, and {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The south <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Ephraim's, and the north <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Manasseh's; the sea is their<note>Hebrew "its"</note> border; Asher touches <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north and on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east Issachar.</verse>
    <verse num="11">In Issachar and Asher, Manasseh had Beth-shean and its villages, Ibleam and its villages, the inhabitants of Dor and its villages, the inhabitants of En-dor and its villages, the inhabitants of Taanach and its villages, the inhabitants of Megiddo and its villages; the third is Napheth.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Manasseh were not able to take possession of these towns; the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> were determined to live in this land.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And it happened, when the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> grew strong, they put the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> to forced labor but never drove them out completely. </verse>
    <verse num="14">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph spoke with Joshua, saying, "Why have you given us<note>Hebrew "to me"</note> one allotment and one share <transChange type="added">as</transChange> an inheritance? We are many people, which Yahweh has blessed."</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua said to them, "If you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> many people, go up to the forest and clear <transChange type="added">a place</transChange> there for yourselves in the land of the Perizzites<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> and Rephaim, since the hill country of Ephraim is <transChange type="added">too</transChange> narrow for you."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph said, "The hill country is not enough for us, and all of the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> living in the land of the valley <transChange type="added">have</transChange> chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> of iron, those in Beth-shean and its villages, and those in the Jezreel Valley."</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Joshua said to the house of Joseph, to Ephraim and Manasseh, "You are many people and have great power; you will not have one allotment <transChange type="added">only</transChange>;</verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">the</transChange> hill country will be yours. Even though it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a forest, you will clear it, and it will be yours <transChange type="added">to</transChange> its farthest borders. You will drive out the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> even though they have iron chariots and <transChange type="added">are</transChange> strong." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">The entire congregation of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> assembled <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Shiloh, and they set up there the tent of meeting, and the land was subdued before them.<note>Or "in their presence"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">And seven tribes remained among the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> who had not been apportioned their inheritance.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And Joshua said to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> "{How long}<note>Literally "Until when"</note> <transChange type="added">will</transChange> you be slack about going to take possession of the land that Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> has given you?</verse>
    <verse num="4">Provide three men {from each tribe},<note>Literally "according to each tribe"</note> and I will send them so that they may begin to go through the land and write <transChange type="added">a description of</transChange> it {according to their inheritance},<note>Literally "according to the mouth of their inheritance"</note> and let them come to me.</verse>
    <verse num="5">They will divide it among themselves into seven portions; {Judah will maintain its border}<note>Literally "Judah will stand on its border"</note> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> south, and {the house of Joseph will maintain its border}<note>Literally "the house of Joseph will stand on its border"</note> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Describe the land <transChange type="added">in</transChange> seven divisions, and bring <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to me here; I will cast lots for you here before Yahweh our God.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The Levites among you have no portion, for their inheritance <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the priesthood of Yahweh; Gad, Reuben, and the half-tribe of Manasseh received their inheritance beyond the Jordan to the east, which Moses Yahweh's servant gave to them." </verse>
    <verse num="8">And {the men went immediately},<note>Literally "the men got up and went"</note> and Joshua commanded the ones going to describe the land, saying, "Go and walk about through the land, write <transChange type="added">a description</transChange>, and return to me, and here I will cast a lot for you before<note>Or "in the presence of"</note> Yahweh at Shiloh."</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the men went and passed through the land, and they {described}<note>Literally "wrote it"</note> the cities in seven divisions in a book; and they came to Joshua to the camp <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Shiloh,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and Joshua cast a lot for them at Shiloh before<note>Or "in the presence of"</note> Yahweh, and there he divided the land for the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> {to each a portion}.<note>Literally "according to their allotment"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="11">And the allotment of the tribe of Benjamin came up according to their families, and the border of their allotment fell<note>Literally "went out"</note> between the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Their northern border began at the Jordan and went up to the slope of Jericho on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north and continued into the hill country to the west; {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the wilderness of Beth Aven.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The border passes <transChange type="added">on</transChange> from there to Luz, to the slope of Luz to the south (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Bethel); then the border goes down to Ataroth Addar to the mountain that is south of Lower Beth-Horon.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Then the border changes direction and turns to the western side southward, from the mountain that {is opposite}<note>Literally "against the face of"</note> Beth-Horon to the south. {It ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at Kiriath Baal (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Kiriath Jearim), a town belonging to the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah. This <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> western side.</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> southern side <transChange type="added">begins</transChange> on the outskirts of Kiriath Jearim, and the border continues to the west to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah;</verse>
    <verse num="16">the border goes down to the foot<note>Or "to the edge"</note> of the mountain, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> opposite the Valley of Ben Hinnom,<note>Or "valley of the son of-Hinnom"</note> which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the valley of Rephaim to the north; then it does down the valley of Hinnom to the slope of the Jebusites<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> to the south, and then it goes down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> En Rogel.</verse>
    <verse num="17">It changes direction from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north, and it continues <transChange type="added">to</transChange> En Shemesh; it goes out to Geliloth, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> opposite the ascent of Adummim, and it goes down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the stone of Bohan, son of Reuben.</verse>
    <verse num="18">It passes <transChange type="added">on</transChange> to the slope opposite the Arabah<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note> to the north, and it goes down to the Arabah.<note>A dry region that runs south of the Sea of Galilee along the Jordan Valley</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">The border passes <transChange type="added">on</transChange> to the slope of Beth-hoglah to the north and {ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the north bay of the Salt Sea<note>That is, the Dead Sea</note> at the south end of the Jordan. This is the southern border.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The Jordan forms its border on the eastern side. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of Benjamin, its borders that surrounds <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, according to their families. </verse>
    <verse num="21">Now the towns of the tribes of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Benjamin, according to their families, were Jericho, Beth-hoglah, Emek Keziz,</verse>
    <verse num="22">Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel,</verse>
    <verse num="23">Avvim, Parah, Ophrah,</verse>
    <verse num="24">Kephar Ammoni, Ophni, and Geba; twelve cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="25">Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth,</verse>
    <verse num="26">Mizpeh, Kephirah, Mozah,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah,</verse>
    <verse num="28">Zela, Haeleph, Jebus (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Jerusalem), Gibeah, and Kiriath; fourteen cities and their villages. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Benjamin according to their families. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">The second allotment {fell}<note>Literally "went out"</note> for Simeon, for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Simeon, according to their families. And their inheritance was in the midst of the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And they had as their inheritance Beersheba, Sheba, Moladah,</verse>
    <verse num="3">Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem,</verse>
    <verse num="4">Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah,</verse>
    <verse num="5">Ziklag, Beth Marcaboth, Hazar Susah,</verse>
    <verse num="6">Beth Lebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan; four cities and their villages,</verse>
    <verse num="8">and all the villages that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> around these towns up to Baalat-Beor, Ramath of the Negev.<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Simeon according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Part of the portion <transChange type="added">allotted to</transChange> the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah <transChange type="added">became</transChange> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Simeon because the portion for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Judah was {too large for them},<note>Literally "large from them"</note> so the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Simeon inherited <transChange type="added">from</transChange> their inheritance. </verse>
    <verse num="10">The third allotment came up for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Zebulun according to their families. The border of their inheritance went up to Sarid.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Their border goes up to the west, to Maralah; it touches<note>Or "reaches to"</note> Dabbesheth, then the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> opposite Jokneam.</verse>
    <verse num="12">It turns from Sarid to the east to the sunrise, to the border of Kislot-Tabor; it continues to Daberath and goes up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Japhia.</verse>
    <verse num="13">From there it passes <transChange type="added">along</transChange> to the east toward the sunrise, to Gath Hepher and to Eth Kazin, and continuing <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Rimmon, it turns <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Neah;</verse>
    <verse num="14">it changes direction from the north of Hannathon, and {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were" </note> at the valley of Yiptah-El;</verse>
    <verse num="15">Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem; twelve cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="16">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Zebulun according to their families, these cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="17">The fourth allotment {fell}<note>Literally "came out"</note> for Issachar, for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Issachar, according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Their border went to Jezreel, Chesulloth, Shunem,</verse>
    <verse num="19">Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath,</verse>
    <verse num="20">Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez,</verse>
    <verse num="21">Remeth, En Gannim, En Haddah, and Beth Pazzez;</verse>
    <verse num="22">and the border touches Tabor, Shahazumah, and Beth Shemesh. {Its border ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of their border were"</note> at the Jordan; sixteen cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="23">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Issachar according to their families, the cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="24">The fifth allotment {fell}<note>Literally "came out" </note> for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Asher according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Their border was Helkath, Hali, Beten, Acshaph,</verse>
    <verse num="26">Allamelech, Amad, and Mishal; it touches Carmel to the west, and Shihor-Libnat.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Then it turns {eastward}<note>Literally "to the rising of the sun"</note> to Beth-dagon and touches Zebulun and the valley of Yiptah-El to the north<note>Literally "left hand/side" </note> to Beth Emeck and Neiel; it continues to Cabul from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north,</verse>
    <verse num="28">and Ebron, Rehob, Hammon, and Kanah up to Great Sidon;</verse>
    <verse num="29">then the border turns <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Ramah, and up to the fortified city of Tyre, <transChange type="added">where</transChange> the border turns <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Hosah; {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the sea, from Hebel to Aczib.</verse>
    <verse num="30"><transChange type="added">Included were</transChange> Ummah, Aphek, and Rehob; twenty-two cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="31">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Asher according to their families, these cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="32">The sixth allotment {fell}<note>Literally "came out"</note> for the children of Naphtali, for the children of Naphtali according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Their border was from Heleph, from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> oak in Zaanannim, Adami Nekeb, Jabneel, up to Lakkum; {it ends}<note>Literally "the goings out of it were"</note> at the Jordan;</verse>
    <verse num="34">then the border turns to the west, to Aznoth Tabor, and continues from there to Hukok, and it touches<note>Or "reaches to"</note> Zebulun on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> south, Asher on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> west, and Judah on {the east}<note>Literally "the rising of the sun"</note> <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="35">{The fortified cities}<note>Literally "the cities of fortification"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Kinnereth,</verse>
    <verse num="36">Adamah, Ramah, Hazor,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor,</verse>
    <verse num="38">Yiron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth-anath, Beth Shemesh; nineteen cities and their villages.</verse>
    <verse num="39">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="40">The seventh lot {fell}<note>Literally "came out"</note> for the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Dan according to their families.</verse>
    <verse num="41"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> border of their inheritance was Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir Shemesh,</verse>
    <verse num="42">Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah,</verse>
    <verse num="43">Elon, Timnah, Ekron,</verse>
    <verse num="44">Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath,</verse>
    <verse num="45">Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon,</verse>
    <verse num="46">Me Jarkon, Rakkon, with the border opposite Joppa.</verse>
    <verse num="47">The border of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Dan continued {beyond them},<note>Literally "from them"</note> because the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Dan went up and fought with Lesham, and they captured and struck it with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and they took possession of it and settled in it; and they called Leshem Dan, after the name of Dan their ancestor.<note>Or "father"</note></verse>
    <verse num="48">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the inheritance of the tribe of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Dan according to their families, these cities and their villages. </verse>
    <verse num="49">They finished assigning the land according to its borders, and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gave an inheritance <transChange type="added">from</transChange> among them to Joshua son of Nun.</verse>
    <verse num="50">{According to the commandment of Yahweh},<note>Literally "On the mouth of Yahweh"</note> they gave him the city that he requested, Timnath Serah, in the hill country of Ephraim, and he rebuilt the city and settled<note>Or "dwelt"</note> in it.</verse>
    <verse num="51">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the inheritances that Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the families of the tribes, distributed by allotment <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> at Shiloh {before Yahweh}<note>Or "in the presence of Yahweh"</note> <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the tent of meeting. And they finished dividing the land. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">And Yahweh spoke to Joshua, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"Speak to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> saying, 'Appoint for yourselves cities of refuge, of which I spoke to you through the hand of Moses.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Anyone who kills a person by accident or unintentionally<note>Or "by not knowing"</note> may flee there; they will be for yourselves a refuge from the avenger of blood.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The killer will flee to one of these cities, stand <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the gate of the city, and {state his case to the elders of that city};<note>Literally "he will speak his words in the ears of the elders of that city"</note> and they will take him<note>Or "they will gather him"</note> into the city and give him a place, and he will dwell among them.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And if the avenger of blood pursues after him, they will not hand over the killer into his hand, because he killed his neighbor unintentionally, and {he did not hate him previously}.<note>Literally "he did not hate him since yesterday and the day before that"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">The killer will stay in that city until he stands before the congregation for the trial, until the death of the one who is the high priest in those days. Then {the killer will return}<note>Literally "the killer will return and go"</note> to his city and to his house, to the city from which he fled.'" </verse>
    <verse num="7">So {they set apart}<note>Or "consecrated"</note> Kedesh in Galilee in the hill country of Naphtali, Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim, and Kiriath Arba<note>Or "the city of Arba"</note> (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Hebron) in the hill country of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Beyond the Jordan east of Jericho, they appointed Bezer in the wilderness on the plateau, from the tribe of Reuben, Ramoth in Gilead, from the tribe of Gad, and Golan in the Bashan, from the tribe of Manasseh.</verse>
    <verse num="9">These were the cities designated for all the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and for the foreigners<note>Hebrew "foreigner"</note> dwelling among them, for anyone that kills a person unintentionally to flee there, and not die by the hand of the avenger of blood, {until there is a trial}<note>Literally "until he stands"</note> before the congregation. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">Then the heads of the families of the Levites came to Eleazar the priest, to Joshua son of Nun, and to the heads of the families of the tribes of the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">And they spoke to them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, "Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses to give us cities to live <transChange type="added">in</transChange>, with their pasturelands for our livestock."</verse>
    <verse num="3">So, {by command of Yahweh},<note>Literally "by the mouth of Yahweh"</note> the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gave the Levites these cities and their pasturelands from their inheritance. </verse>
    <verse num="4">The allotment {fell}<note>Literally "came out"</note> for the families of the Kohathites.<note>Hebrew "Kohathite"</note> The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Aaron the priest, who were of the Levites, {received}<note>Literally "they had"</note> by lot thirteen towns from the tribes of Judah, Simeon, and Benjamin. </verse>
    <verse num="5">The remaining descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Kohath <transChange type="added">received</transChange> by lot ten cities from the families of the tribes of Ephraim, Dan, and the half-tribe of Manasseh. </verse>
    <verse num="6">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gershon <transChange type="added">received</transChange> by lot thirteen cities from the families of the tribes of Issachar, Asher, and Naphtali and from the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan. </verse>
    <verse num="7">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of the Merarites<note>Hebrew "Merarite"</note> according to their families <transChange type="added">received</transChange> twelve cities from the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and Zebulun. </verse>
    <verse num="8">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gave to the Levites these cities and their pastureland by lot, just as Yahweh commanded through the hand of Moses. </verse>
    <verse num="9">They gave these cities, which are <transChange type="added">here</transChange> mentioned by name, from the tribe of the families of Judah and from the tribe of the families of Simeon;</verse>
    <verse num="10">and they were for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Aaron, from the families of the Kohathites,<note>Hebrew "Kohathite"</note> from the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Levi, because the first lot was theirs.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And they gave to them Kiriath Arba,<note>Or "the city of Arba"</note> <transChange type="added">Arba being</transChange> the father of Anak (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Hebron), in the hill country of Judah and the pasturelands surrounding it.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But the field of the city and its villages they gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh as his property. </verse>
    <verse num="13">To the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron, the city of refuge <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the killer, and its pasturelands, Libnah and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="14">Jattir and its pasturelands, Eshtemoa and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="15">Holon and its pasturelands, Debir and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="16">Ain and its pasturelands, Juttah and its pasturelands, and Beth Shemesh and its pasturelands; nine cities from these two tribes.</verse>
    <verse num="17">From the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon and its pasturelands, Geba and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="18">Anathoth and its pasturelands, Almon and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="19">All the cities of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Aaron the priests, thirteen cities and their pasturelands. </verse>
    <verse num="20">For the families of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Kohath, the remaining Levites of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Kohath, they <transChange type="added">received</transChange> the cities of their lot from the tribe of Ephraim.</verse>
    <verse num="21">They gave them Shechem, the city of refuge <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the killer, and its pasturelands in the hill country of Ephraim, Gezer and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="22">Kibzaim and its pasturelands, and Beth-horon and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="23">From the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh and its pasturelands, Gibbethon and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="24">Aijalon and its pasturelands, and Gath Rimmon and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="25">From the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach and its pasturelands and Gath Rimmon with its pasturelands; two cities.</verse>
    <verse num="26">All the cities and their pasturelands for the remaining families of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Kohath <transChange type="added">were</transChange> ten. </verse>
    <verse num="27">To the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gershon, one of the families of the Levites, from the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan, a city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, and Eshtarah and its pasturelands; two cities.</verse>
    <verse num="28">From the tribe of Issachar, Kishion and its pasturelands, Daberath and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="29">Jarmuth and its pasturelands, En Gannim and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="30">From the tribe of Asher, Mishal and its pasturelands, Abdon and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Helkath and its pasturelands, Rehob and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="32">From the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee, the city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, Hammoth Dor and its pasturelands, and Kartan and its pasturelands; three cities.</verse>
    <verse num="33">All the cities of the Gershonites<note>Hebrew "Gershonite"</note> according to their families <transChange type="added">were</transChange> thirteen cities and their pasturelands. </verse>
    <verse num="34">To the families of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Merarite, the remaining Levites, from the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam and its pasturelands, Kartah and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="35">Dimnah and its pasturelands, and Nahalal and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="36">From the tribe of Reuben, Bezer and its pasturelands, Jahaz and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Kedemoth and its pasturelands, and Mephaath and its pasturelands; four cities.</verse>
    <verse num="38">From the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead, the city of refuge for the killer, and its pasturelands, Mahanaim and its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="39">Heshbon and its pasturelands, and Jazer and its pasturelands; four cities <transChange type="added">in</transChange> all.</verse>
    <verse num="40">All <transChange type="added">these were</transChange> the cities of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Merarite according to their families, the remaining families of the Levites; their allotment was twelve cities. </verse>
    <verse num="41">All the cities of the Levites among the property of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> forty-eight cities and their pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="42">Each of these cities had pasturelands surrounding them; so <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> for all of these cities.</verse>
    <verse num="43">And Yahweh gave to Israel all the land that he swore to give to their ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> and they took possession of it and {settled in it}.<note>Or "dwelled in it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="44">Yahweh gave them rest on every side, according to all that he had sworn to their ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> and nobody from all their enemies withstood them, for Yahweh had given all their enemies into their hand.</verse>
    <verse num="45">And {nothing failed from}<note>Literally "Not a thing fell"</note> all the good things<note>Hebrew "thing"</note> that Yahweh promised to the house of Israel; {everything came to pass}.<note>Literally "everything it came"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">Then Joshua summoned the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and he said to them, "You have observed all that Moses Yahweh's servant commanded you, and you have listened<note>Or "you have obeyed"</note> to my voice in all that I have commanded you;</verse>
    <verse num="3">you have not forsaken your kinsmen<note>Or "brothers"</note> these many days, up to this day, and you have observed the obligation of the command of Yahweh your God.</verse>
    <verse num="4">So then, Yahweh your God has given rest to your kinsmen,<note>Or "brothers"</note> just as he promised them; so then, turn and go to your tents to the land of your possession, which Moses Yahweh's servant gave to you beyond the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Only be very careful to observe the commandment and law that Moses Yahweh's servant commanded you, to love Yahweh your God, to walk in all his ways, to keep his commandments, to hold fast to him, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul."<note>Or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">And Joshua blessed them and sent them away, and they went to their tents.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And to the half-tribe of Manasseh Moses had given <transChange type="added">a possession</transChange> in Bashan, but to the other half Joshua had given <transChange type="added">a possession</transChange> with their kinsmen<note>Or "brothers"</note> beyond the Jordan to the west; and when Joshua sent them to their tents and blessed them,</verse>
    <verse num="8">he said to them, "Return to your tents with much wealth, and with very much livestock, with silver, gold, copper, iron, and with very much clothing; divide the war-booty of your enemies with your kinsmen."<note>Or "brothers"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">So the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh returned <transChange type="added">home</transChange> and departed with the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> at Shiloh, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the land of Canaan, to go to the land of Gilead to the land of their possession, which they had acquired {according to the command of Yahweh}<note>Literally "on the mouth of Yahweh"</note> through the hand of Moses. </verse>
    <verse num="10">And they came to the region of the Jordan that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the land of Canaan, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh built there an altar on the Jordan, {a large and imposing altar}.<note>Literally "a large altar to appearance"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange> said that the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh had built an altar next to the land of Canaan, in the region of the Jordan, on the side <transChange type="added">belonging to</transChange> the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">When the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> heard <transChange type="added">of it</transChange>, the whole congregation of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gathered <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Shiloh to go up against them for battle.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> sent to the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, Phinehas the priest son of Eleazar,</verse>
    <verse num="14">and ten leaders with him, {one leader for each}<note>Literally "one leader, one leader"</note> {family}<note>Literally "of the house of father"</note> from each of the tribes of Israel; and each one <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the head of {his family}<note>Literally "house of their fathers"</note> among the clans of Israel.<note>Or "thousands of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">They came to the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, and they spoke with them, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="16">"Thus says all the congregation of Yahweh: 'What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this treachery that you have committed against the God of Israel by turning away today from following Yahweh, by building for yourselves an altar to rebel today against Yahweh?</verse>
    <verse num="17"><transChange type="added">Is</transChange> not the sin of Peor {enough for us},<note>Literally "too little for us"</note> from which we have not cleansed ourselves today, and for which a plague came to the congregation of Yahweh,</verse>
    <verse num="18">that you must turn today from following Yahweh? <transChange type="added">If</transChange> you rebel today against Yahweh, tomorrow he will be angry with all of the congregation of Israel;</verse>
    <verse num="19">if, however, the land of your property <transChange type="added">is</transChange> unclean, cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> to the land of Yahweh's property, where Yahweh's tabernacle resides,<note>Or "stands"</note> and take possession among us. But you must not rebel against Yahweh or against us by building for yourselves an altar other than the altar of Yahweh our God.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Did not Achan son of Zerah commit treachery with devoted things,<note>Or "consecrated possession"</note> and wrath fell on all the congregation of Israel? {And he alone}<note>Literally "And he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one man that"</note> did not perish because of his iniquity.'" </verse>
    <verse num="21">And the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh spoke with the heads of the clans<note>Or "thousands"</note> of Israel,</verse>
    <verse num="22">"Yahweh, God of gods! Yahweh, God of gods knows. And let Israel itself know, if <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> in rebellion or treachery against Yahweh, do not spare us this day</verse>
    <verse num="23">for building for ourselves an altar to turn away from Yahweh, or if <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> to offer burnt offerings,<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> grain offerings,<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> or fellowship offerings on it, may Yahweh himself take vengeance.</verse>
    <verse num="24">But in fact, we have done this because of anxiety, because of a reason, saying, 'In the future your children may say to our children, '{What is the relationship between you and Yahweh the God of Israel}?<note>Literally "What is to you and to Yahweh the God of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">Yahweh has made the Jordan a border between us and you, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben and Gad; you have no portion in Yahweh.' So your children may put an end to our children worshiping<note>Or "seeing"</note> Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="26">So we said, 'Let us build immediately for ourselves an altar, not for burnt offerings<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> or for sacrifices;<note>Hebrew "sacrifice"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">instead, it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us for performing the serving of Yahweh in his presence with our burnt offerings, sacrifices, and fellowship offerings; so that your children may not say in the future to our children, "You have no portion in Yahweh." '</verse>
    <verse num="28">And we thought, if they say to us and to our children in the future, we can say, 'Look at this replica of the altar of Yahweh, which our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> made, not for burnt offerings<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> or sacrifices;<note>Hebrew "sacrifice"</note> rather, it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a witness between us and you.'</verse>
    <verse num="29">Far be it from us to rebel against Yahweh, to turn today from following Yahweh, to build an altar for burnt offerings,<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> grain offerings,<note>Hebrew "offering"</note> or sacrifices,<note>Hebrew "sacrifice"</note> instead of the altar of Yahweh our God that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> before his tabernacle." </verse>
    <verse num="30">Phinehas the priest, the leaders of the congregation, and the heads of the clans<note>Or "thousands"</note> of Israel who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him heard the words that the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and Manasseh spoke, and {they were satisfied}.<note>Literally "it was good in their eyes"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">Phinehas the priest, son of Eleazar, said to the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben, Gad, and Manasseh, "Today we know that Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> among us, because you have not committed this treachery against Yahweh. Therefore you have rescued the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> from the hand of Yahweh." </verse>
    <verse num="32">And Phinehas the priest, son of Eleazar, and the leaders returned from the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben and Gad, from the land of Gilead, to the land of Canaan to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and {they gave them their report}.<note>Literally "they brought back a word to them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="33">{The report satisfied the Israelites};<note>Literally "The report was good in the eyes of the children of Israel"</note> they blessed God, and they did not speak of going up for battle against them to destroy the land in which the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben and Gad were living.<note>Or "dwelling"</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reuben and Gad called the altar Witness, "Because," <transChange type="added">they said</transChange>, "it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a witness between us that Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">And it happened, after {a long time},<note>Literally "many days"</note> after Yahweh had given rest to Israel from all their surrounding enemies, and <transChange type="added">after</transChange> Joshua was old and {well-advanced in years},<note>Literally "he went into the days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Joshua summoned all Israel, their elders, heads, judges, and officials, and he said to them, "I am old and {well-advanced in years},<note>Literally "I went into the days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">and you have seen all that Yahweh your God has done to all these nations {for your sake},<note>Literally "because of your presence"</note> for Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fighting for you.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Look! I have allotted to you these remaining nations as an inheritance for your tribes, from the Jordan, <transChange type="added">with</transChange> all the nations that I have cut off, to the Great Sea<note>That is, the Mediterranean</note> {in the west}.<note>Literally "to the setting of the sun"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And Yahweh your God will push them {back before you}<note>Literally "from your presence"</note> and drive them {out of your sight},<note>Literally "from your face"</note> and you will possess their land, just as Yahweh your God promised to you.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Be very strong to observe carefully all that is written in the scroll of the law of Moses so as not to turn aside from it, <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the right or left,</verse>
    <verse num="7">so as not to go among these remaining nations with you; {do not profess}<note>Literally "do not mention"</note> the name of their gods, and do not swear by them, serve them, or {bow down to them}.<note>Literally "bow yourselves down to them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">But hold fast to Yahweh your God, just as you have done up to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Yahweh has driven out before you great and strong nations; and as for you, {nobody has withstood}<note>Literally "a man has not stood in your presence"</note> you to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="10">One of your men put to flight a thousand, for Yahweh your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fighting for you, just as he promised you.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Take utmost care for <transChange type="added">the sake of</transChange> your life to love Yahweh your God,</verse>
    <verse num="12">for if indeed you turn back and join these remaining nations {among you},<note>Literally "with you"</note> and you intermarry with them, {marrying their women and they yours},<note>Literally "you go into them and they into you"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">know for certain that Yahweh your God {will not continue to drive out}<note>Literally "will not drive out again"</note> these nations from before you; they will be for you a snare and a trap, a whip on your sides and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from this good land that Yahweh your God has given to you. </verse>
    <verse num="14">Look! {I am about to die},<note>Literally "I am going today on the way of all the earth"</note> and you know in all your hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> and souls<note>Hebrew "soul"; or "inner self"</note> that not one thing {failed}<note>Literally "fell"</note> from all the good things that Yahweh your God promised concerning you; everything {has been fulfilled};<note>Literally "has come <transChange type="added">out</transChange>"</note> {not one thing failed}.<note>Literally "not one thing fell from it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">But just as all the good things<note>Hebrew "thing"</note> came to you that Yahweh your God promised, so will Yahweh bring to you all the bad things<note>Hebrew "things"</note> until he has destroyed you from this good land that Yahweh your God has given to you.</verse>
    <verse num="16">If you transgress the covenant of Yahweh your God, which he commanded <transChange type="added">to</transChange> you, and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, {Yahweh's anger will be kindled}<note>Literally "Yahweh's nose will become hot"</note> against you, and you will perish quickly from the good land that he has given to you." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">And Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem; he summoned the elders of Israel, their heads, their judges, and their officials, and they presented themselves before God.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Joshua said to all the people, "Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel: '{Long ago}<note>Literally "from ancient"</note> your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note>--Terah the father of Abraham and the father of Nahor--lived beyond the river,<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> and they served other gods.</verse>
    <verse num="3">I took your ancestor<note>Or "father"</note> Abraham from beyond the river<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> and led him through all the land of Canaan, and I increased his offspring; I gave him Isaac,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and to Isaac I gave Jacob and Esau. To Esau I gave the hill country of Seir to possess, but Jacob and his children went down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Egypt.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And I sent Moses and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt with what I did in its midst; and afterward I brought you out.</verse>
    <verse num="6">When I brought out your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> from Egypt, you came to the sea, and the Egyptians pursued after your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> with chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> and horsemen to the {Red Sea}.<note>Literally "sea of reed"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">They cried out to Yahweh, and he put darkness between you and the Egyptians, and he brought the sea over them<note>That is, the Egyptians</note> and covered them; your own eyes saw what I did in Egypt. Then you lived in the wilderness for many days.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And I brought you to the land of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> who lived beyond the Jordan; they fought you, and I gave them into your hand; you took possession of their land, and I destroyed them {before you}.<note>Literally "in your presence"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Then Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab, set out and fought against Israel, and he sent and summoned Balaam son of Beor to curse you,</verse>
    <verse num="10">but I was not willing to listen to Balaam, and he richly blessed you. So I rescued you from his hand,</verse>
    <verse num="11">and you crossed the Jordan and came to Jericho. And the citizens of Jericho, the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the Hittites,<note>Hebrew "Hittite"</note> the Girgashites,<note>Hebrew "Girgashite"</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> and the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> fought against you, and I gave them into your hand.</verse>
    <verse num="12">I sent before you <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hornet and they drove out before you two kings of the Amorites;<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> <transChange type="added">but</transChange> not by your sword or bow.</verse>
    <verse num="13">I gave to you a land that you have not labored on, and cities that you have not built, and you live<note>Or "dwell"</note> in them; you eat <transChange type="added">from</transChange> vineyards and olive groves that you have not planted.' </verse>
    <verse num="14">"So now, revere Yahweh and serve him in sincerity and faithfulness; remove the gods that your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> served beyond the river<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> and in Egypt, and serve Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="15">But if it is bad in your eyes to serve Yahweh, choose for yourselves today whom you want to serve, whether it is the gods that your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> served beyond the river,<note>That is, the Euphrates</note> or the gods of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> in whose land you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> living; but as for me and my household, we will serve Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And the people answered and said, "Far be it from us that we would forsake Yahweh to serve other gods,</verse>
    <verse num="17">for Yahweh our God brought us and our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> from the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery, and did these great signs before our eyes. He protected us along the entire way that we went, and among all the peoples through whose midst we passed.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And Yahweh drove out all the people before us, the Amorites<note>"Hebrew "Amorite"</note> who live<note>Or "dwell"</note> <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the land. We will serve Yahweh, for he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> our God." </verse>
    <verse num="19">But Joshua said to the people, "You cannot serve Yahweh, for he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a holy and jealous God; he will not forgive your transgressions or your sins.</verse>
    <verse num="20">If you forsake Yahweh and serve foreign gods, he will turn and bring disaster to you; he will destroy you after he has done good to you."</verse>
    <verse num="21">And the people said to Joshua, "No, we will serve Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Joshua said to the people, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> witnesses against yourselves that you have chosen for yourselves to serve Yahweh." And they said, "<transChange type="added">We are</transChange> witnesses."</verse>
    <verse num="23">He said, "Remove the foreign gods that <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in your midst, and incline your hearts to Yahweh the God of Israel."</verse>
    <verse num="24">And the people said to Joshua, "We will serve Yahweh our God, and we will listen to his voice."</verse>
    <verse num="25">So Joshua {made a covenant}<note>Literally "cut a covenant"</note> with the people on that day, and he established for them a statute and a judgment at Shechem.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then Joshua wrote these words in a scroll of the law of God, and he took a large stone and set it up there under a large tree, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> at the shrine of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And Joshua said to all the people, "Look, this stone will be a witness against us, for it has heard all the words of Yahweh that he spoke with us. It will be as a witness against you, so that you do not deny your God."</verse>
    <verse num="28">Then Joshua sent the people away to their inheritance. </verse>
    <verse num="29">After these things Joshua son of Nun servant of Yahweh died; {he was one hundred and ten years old}.<note>Literally "a son of one hundred and ten years"</note></verse>
    <verse num="30">They buried him in the territory of his inheritance, at Timnath-Serah, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the hill country of Ephraim, north of Mount Gaash.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Israel served Yahweh all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who lived long after Joshua, and who had known all the work that Yahweh did for Israel.<note>Joshua 24:28-31 is repeated in Judges 2:6-10</note></verse>
    <verse num="32">The bones of Jacob, which the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> had brought out from Egypt, they buried at Shechem, in a piece of land that Jacob had bought from the children of Hamor, the father of Shechem, for one hundred pieces of money;<note>Hebrew kesitah</note> it became <transChange type="added">an</transChange> inheritance for the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joseph.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And Eleazar son of Aaron died; and they buried him in Gibeah in the hill country of Ephraim, which had been given to his son Phinehas. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>