<book num="Phil">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul and Timothy, slaves of Christ Jesus, to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, together with the overseers and deacons.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="3">I give thanks to my God upon my every remembrance of you,<note>Or "upon your every remembrance <transChange type="added">of me</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">always in my every prayer for all of you, making the prayer with joy,</verse>
    <verse num="5">because of your participation in the gospel from the first day until now,</verse>
    <verse num="6">convinced of this same <transChange type="added">thing</transChange>, that the one who began a good work in you will finish <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> until the day of Christ Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="7">just as it is right for me to think this about all of you, because I have you in my heart, <transChange type="added">since</transChange><note>*Here "since" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as causal</note> both in my imprisonment and in the defense and confirmation of the gospel all of you are sharers of grace with me.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my witness, that I long for all of you with the affection of Christ Jesus. </verse>
    <verse num="9">And this I pray: that your love may abound still more and more in knowledge and all discernment,</verse>
    <verse num="10">so that you may approve what is superior, in order that you may be sincere and blameless in<note>Or "for," or "until"</note> the day of Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="11">having been filled <transChange type="added">with the</transChange> fruit of righteousness which <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> through Jesus Christ to the glory and praise of God. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Now I want you to know, brothers, that {my circumstances}<note>Literally "the things with me"</note> have happened instead for the progress of the gospel,</verse>
    <verse num="13">so that my imprisonment in Christ has become known in the whole praetorium<note>Or "praetorian guard," or "imperial guard"</note> and to all the rest,</verse>
    <verse num="14">and most of the brothers, trusting in the Lord because of my imprisonment, dare <transChange type="added">even</transChange> more to speak the word without fear.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Some even because of envy and strife preach Christ, but some also because of good will.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The latter <transChange type="added">do so</transChange> from love, knowing that I am appointed for the defense of the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The former proclaim Christ from selfish ambition, not sincerely, thinking to raise up affliction in my imprisonment.</verse>
    <verse num="18">{What is the result?}<note>Literally "for what"</note> Only that in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is proclaimed, and in this I rejoice. But also I will rejoice,</verse>
    <verse num="19">for I know that this will turn out to me for deliverance through your prayer and the support of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="20">according to my eager expectation and hope, that I will be put to shame in nothing, but with all boldness, even now as always Christ will be exalted in my body, whether through life or through death.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For to me to live <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Christ and to die <transChange type="added">is</transChange> gain.</verse>
    <verse num="22">But if <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> to live in the flesh, this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fruitful work for me, and which I will prefer <transChange type="added">I do</transChange> not know.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But I am hard pressed {between the two options}<note>Literally "by the two"</note>, having the desire to depart and to be with Christ, {for this is very much better}<note>Literally "for <transChange type="added">this is</transChange> more better by much"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="24">But to stay on in the flesh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> more necessary for your sake.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And because I am<note>*Here "because" is supplied as a component of the participle ("convinced") which is understood as causal</note> convinced of this, I know that I will remain and continue with all of you for your progress and joy in the faith,</verse>
    <verse num="26">so that <transChange type="added">what</transChange> you can be proud of may increase in Christ Jesus because of me through my return again to you. </verse>
    <verse num="27">Only lead your lives in a manner worthy of the gospel of Christ, so that whether I come and see you or am absent I hear {your circumstances}<note>Literally "the things concerning you"</note>, that you are standing firm in one spirit, with one soul contending side by side for the faith of the gospel,</verse>
    <verse num="28">and not letting yourselves be intimidated in anything by your opponents, which is a sign of destruction to them, but of your salvation, and this from God,</verse>
    <verse num="29">because to you has been graciously granted on behalf of Christ not only to believe in him, but also to suffer on behalf of him,</verse>
    <verse num="30">having the same struggle which you saw in me and now hear about in me. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, if <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any affection and compassion,</verse>
    <verse num="2">complete my joy, so that {you are in agreement}<note>Literally "you think the same <transChange type="added">thing</transChange></note>, having the same love, united in spirit, {having one purpose}<note>Literally "thinking the one <transChange type="added">thing</transChange>"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="3"><transChange type="added">Do</transChange> nothing according to selfish ambition or according to empty conceit, but in humility considering one another better than yourselves,</verse>
    <verse num="4">each of you<note>Some manuscripts have "each one of you"</note> not looking out for {your own interests}<note>Literally "the things of yourselves"</note>, but also each of you <transChange type="added">for</transChange> {the interests}<note>Literally "the things"</note> of others. </verse>
    <verse num="5">Think this in<note>Or "among"</note> yourselves which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> also in Christ Jesus, </verse>
    <verse num="6">who, existing in the form of God, did not consider being equal with God something to be grasped,</verse>
    <verse num="7">but emptied himself <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "by" is supplied as a component of the participle ("taking") which is understood as means</note> taking the form of a slave, <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "by" is supplied as a component of the participle ("becoming") which is understood as means</note> becoming in the likeness of people. And being found in appearance like a man,</verse>
    <verse num="8">he humbled himself <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "by" is supplied as a component of the participle ("becoming") which is understood as means</note> becoming obedient to the point of death, that is, death on a cross.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Therefore also God exalted him and graciously granted him the name above every name,</verse>
    <verse num="10">so that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of <transChange type="added">those</transChange> in heaven and of <transChange type="added">those</transChange> on earth and of <transChange type="added">those</transChange> under the earth,</verse>
    <verse num="11">and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore my dear friends, just as you have always obeyed, not as in my presence only but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling.</verse>
    <verse num="13">For the one at work in you, both to will and to work for his good pleasure, is God.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Do all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> without grumbling and disputing,</verse>
    <verse num="15">in order that you may become blameless and innocent, children of God without fault<note>Or "blameless"</note> in the midst of a crooked and perverted generation, among whom you shine as stars in the world,<note>Or possibly "in the universe"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">holding fast to the word of life, for a source of pride<note>Or "for a cause of boasting"</note> to me in the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain or labor in vain.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But even if I am being poured out as a drink offering on the sacrifice and service of your faith, I rejoice and rejoice with all of you.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the same <transChange type="added">way</transChange> also you rejoice and rejoice with me. </verse>
    <verse num="19">But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, so that I also may be encouraged <transChange type="added">when I</transChange><note>*Here "when" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as temporal</note> know {your circumstances}<note>Literally "the things concerning you"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For I have no one like-minded who <transChange type="added">will</transChange> sincerely be concerned about {your circumstances}<note>Literally "the things concerning you"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For they all seek {their own interests}<note>Literally "the things of themselves"</note>, not those of Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="22">But you know his proven character, that like a child with a father he served with me for the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Therefore I hope to send him at once, as soon as I see {my circumstances}<note>Literally "the things concerning me"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And I am convinced in the Lord that I myself will arrive shortly also. </verse>
    <verse num="25">But I considered <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow worker and fellow soldier, but your messenger and servant of my need,</verse>
    <verse num="26">because he was longing for all of you and was distressed because you had heard that he was sick.</verse>
    <verse num="27">For indeed he was sick, coming near to death, but God had mercy on him and not <transChange type="added">on</transChange> him only, but also <transChange type="added">on</transChange> me, so that I would not have grief upon grief.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Therefore I am sending him with special urgency, in order that <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "when" is supplied as a component of the participle ("see") which is understood as temporal</note> you see him again you may rejoice, and I may be less anxious.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Therefore welcome him in the Lord with all joy, and consider such <transChange type="added">people</transChange> highly honored,</verse>
    <verse num="30">because on account of the work of Christ he came near to the point of death, risking his life in order that {he might make up for your inability to serve me}<note>Literally "he might fill up your lack of service to me"</note>. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Finally, my brothers, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not troublesome to me, but <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a safeguard for you.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Beware of the dogs, beware of the evil workers, beware of the mutilation.<note>This term is a wordplay on the Greek word "circumcision"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">For we are the circumcision, the ones who worship<note>Or "who serve"</note> by the Spirit<note>Or "in the Spirit"</note> of God and boast in Christ Jesus and do not <transChange type="added">put</transChange> confidence in the flesh,</verse>
    <verse num="4">although I <transChange type="added">could</transChange> have confidence even in the flesh. </verse>
    <verse num="5">{circumcised on the eighth day}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">with respect to</transChange> circumcision <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> on the eighth day"</note>, from the nation of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew <transChange type="added">born</transChange> from Hebrews, according to the law a Pharisee,</verse>
    <verse num="6">according to zeal persecuting the church, according to the righteousness in the law being blameless.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But whatever <transChange type="added">things</transChange> were gain to me, these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> I have considered loss because of Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="8">{More than that}<note>Literally "but on the contrary"</note>, <transChange type="added">I</transChange> even consider all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to be loss because of the surpassing greatness of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for the sake of whom I have suffered the loss of all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and consider <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> dung, in order that I may gain Christ</verse>
    <verse num="9">and may be found in him, not having my righteousness <transChange type="added">which is</transChange> from the law, but <transChange type="added">which is</transChange> through faith in Christ,<note>Or "through Christ's faithfulness"</note> the righteousness from God on the basis of faith,<note>Or "on the basis of <transChange type="added">his</transChange> faithfulness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">so that I may know him and the power of his resurrection and the fellowship of his sufferings, being conformed to his death,</verse>
    <verse num="11">if somehow I may attain to the resurrection from the dead.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Not that I have already received <transChange type="added">this</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> or <transChange type="added">have</transChange> already been made perfect, but I press on if indeed I may lay hold of <transChange type="added">that</transChange> for which also I was laid hold of by Christ.<note>Some manuscripts have "Christ Jesus"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">Brothers, I do not consider myself to have laid hold of <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> But <transChange type="added">I do</transChange> one <transChange type="added">thing</transChange>, forgetting the things behind and straining toward the things ahead,</verse>
    <verse num="14">I press on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God in Christ Jesus. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Therefore as many as <transChange type="added">are</transChange> perfect, {let us hold this opinion}<note>Literally "let us think this"</note>, and if you think anything differently, God will reveal this also to you.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Only to what we have attained, to the same hold on.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Become fellow imitators of me, brothers, and observe those who walk in this way, just as you have us <transChange type="added">as</transChange> an example.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For many live, of whom I spoke about to you many times, but now speak about even weeping, <transChange type="added">as</transChange> the enemies of the cross of Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="19">whose end <transChange type="added">is</transChange> destruction, whose God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the stomach, and <transChange type="added">whose</transChange> glory <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in their shame, the ones who think on earthly things.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For our commonwealth exists in heaven, from which also we eagerly await a savior, the Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="21">who will transform our humble body <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> conformed to his glorious body, in accordance with the power that enables him even to subject all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to himself. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">So then, my beloved and greatly desired brothers, my joy and crown, thus stand firm in the Lord, dear friends.</verse>
    <verse num="2">I appeal to Euodia and I appeal to Syntyche {to be in agreement}<note>Literally "to think the same <transChange type="added">thing</transChange>"</note> in the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Yes, I ask also you, true yokefellow, help them, who struggled along with me in the gospel with both Clement and the rest of my fellow workers whose names <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the book of life. </verse>
    <verse num="4">Rejoice in the Lord always; again I say, rejoice.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Let your gentleness be made known to all people. The Lord <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Be anxious for nothing, but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known to God.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your minds<note>Or "thoughts"</note> in Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Finally, brothers, whatever <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are true, whatever <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> honorable, whatever <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> right, whatever <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> pure, whatever <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> pleasing, whatever <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> commendable, if <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> any excellence of character and if anything praiseworthy, think about these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which you have learned and received and heard about and seen in me, practice these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and the God of peace will be with you. </verse>
    <verse num="10">But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly that now at last {you have renewed your concern for me}<note>Literally "you have revived to think on behalf of me"</note>, for whom also you were thinking, but you had no opportunity <transChange type="added">to express it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Not that I speak from need, for I have learned to be content in whatever <transChange type="added">circumstances</transChange> I am.</verse>
    <verse num="12">I know <transChange type="added">how</transChange> both {to make do with little}<note>Literally "to be humbled"</note> and I know <transChange type="added">how</transChange> {to have an abundance}<note>Literally "to abound"</note>. In everything and in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> I have learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both {to have an abundance}<note>Literally "to abound"</note> and to go without.</verse>
    <verse num="13">I am able <transChange type="added">to do</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> by the one who strengthens me.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Nevertheless you have done well by sharing<note>*Here "by" is supplied as a component of the participle ("sharing") which is understood as means</note> with me in my affliction.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Now you also know, Philippians, that at the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving except you alone,</verse>
    <verse num="16">because even in Thessalonica {on more than one occasion}<note>Literally "both once and twice"</note> you sent for my need.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Not that I seek the gift, but I seek for the profit that increases to your account.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But I have received everything <transChange type="added">in full</transChange> and have an abundance; {I am well supplied}<note>Literally "I have been made full"</note> <transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "because" is supplied as a component of the participle ("received") which is understood as causal</note> I received from Epaphroditus {what you had sent}<note>Literally "the things from you"</note>, a fragrant offering, an acceptable sacrifice, well-pleasing to God.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And my God will fulfill your every need according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Now to our God and Father <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the glory {forever and ever}<note>Literally "to the ages of the ages"</note>. Amen. </verse>
    <verse num="21">Greet every saint in Christ Jesus. The brothers with me greet you.</verse>
    <verse num="22">All the saints greet you, and especially those of Caesar's household.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with your spirit. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>