<book num="Lam">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">How desolate the city sits <transChange type="added">that</transChange> was full of people! She has become like a widow, <transChange type="added">once</transChange> great among the nations! Like a woman of nobility in the provinces, she has become a forced laborer.</verse>
    <verse num="2">She weeps bitterly in the night, her tears <transChange type="added">are</transChange> on her cheeks; she has no comforter among all her lovers. All her friends have been unfaithful to her; they have become her enemies.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Judah has gone into exile with misery and under hard servitude; she lives among the nations, she has not found a resting place; all her pursuers have overtaken her amidst <transChange type="added">her</transChange> distress.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The roads of Zion <transChange type="added">are</transChange> mourning because no one comes to the festival. All her gates <transChange type="added">are</transChange> desolate, her priests groan; her young women <transChange type="added">are</transChange> worried, and she herself suffers bitterly.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Her foes have become <transChange type="added">her</transChange> {master},<note>Literally "head"</note> her enemies are at ease; Yahweh has made her suffer because of the greatness of her transgressions. Her children have gone away, captive before the foe.</verse>
    <verse num="6">All her majesty has gone away from the daughter of Zion; her princes have become like young stags that have not found pasture; they have gone away without strength, before the pursuer.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Jerusalem remembers the days of her misery and wanderings, all her treasures that were from the days of long ago. When her people fell into <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hand of the enemy, there was no one helping her; the enemies saw her, they mocked at her destruction.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Jerusalem sinned grievously, thus she became an objection of derision; all those who honored her despise her because they have seen her nakedness. She herself groans and turns away.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Her uncleanness <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in her skirts; she did not remember her future, she has descended beyond understanding, there is no comforter for her. See, O Yahweh, my persecution! <transChange type="added">My</transChange> enemy has been made great!</verse>
    <verse num="10">The enemy has stretched out his hand over all her treasures; for she has seen the nations, they entered her sanctuary, those whom you commanded not to enter in your assembly.</verse>
    <verse num="11">All her people groan, they are searching for bread. They give their treasures for food, to bring back life. See, O Yahweh, and look, <transChange type="added">how</transChange> I am despised.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Is it nothing to you, {all who pass by}?<note>Literally "all who cross a road"</note> Look and see if there is sorrow like my sorrow,<note>Or "pain like my pain"</note> which was dealt to me, which Yahweh inflicted on the {day of his wrath}.<note>Literally "on the day of the blaze of his nose"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">From heaven he sent fire, into my bones he let it descend. He spread out a net for my feet; he turned me back, he gave me devastation, fainting all day.</verse>
    <verse num="14">My rebellion was bound <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a yoke, with his hand it was fastened together; it was put on my neck <transChange type="added">and</transChange> caused my strength to fail. The Lord gave me into the hands <transChange type="added">of those whom</transChange> I cannot withstand.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The Lord has rejected all my mighty ones in my midst. He called an assembly against me, to crush my young men; <transChange type="added">like in</transChange> a wine press, the Lord has trodden <transChange type="added">on</transChange> the virgin daughter of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, I am weeping, {my eyes flow with tears};<note>Literally "my eye my eye is going down <transChange type="added">with</transChange> water"</note> because a comforter is far from me, one to restore my life. My sons are desolate because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> enemy has prevailed.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Zion stretches out her hands; there is no one to comfort her. Yahweh has commanded against Jacob, <transChange type="added">that</transChange> those surrounding him<note>NRSV translates "his neighbors"</note> <transChange type="added">should be</transChange> his enemies; Jerusalem has become a defilement among them.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Yahweh is righteous; I have rebelled <transChange type="added">against</transChange> {his word}.<note>Literally "his mouth"</note> Please hear, all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nations, And see my pain; My young women<note>Or "virgins"</note> and young men went into captivity.</verse>
    <verse num="19">I have called to my lovers, they themselves deceived me; my priests and elders perished in the city when they sought food for themselves to revive their life.<note>Or "their soul"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">See, O Yahweh, that {I am in distress};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">there is</transChange> distress for me"</note> {my stomach}<note>Literally "inner parts"</note> is in torment, my heart has turned inside me because I have certainly rebelled. From outside a sword brings bereavement, inside the house <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> like death.</verse>
    <verse num="21">They hear that I was groaning; <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> no comforter for me. All my enemies have heard my misery, they are pleased that you have done it. Bring <transChange type="added">that</transChange> day that you have proclaimed,<note>Or "you have called"</note> And let them be like me.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Let all their evil come before you; and deal with them just as you have dealt with me because of all my crimes; for my groaning is much and my heart <transChange type="added">is</transChange> faint.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">How, {in his anger},<note>Literally "in his nose"</note> the Lord has covered the daughter of Zion in a cloud! He has thrown down from heavens <transChange type="added">to</transChange> earth the splendor of Israel, and he has not remembered his footstool in the day of {his anger}.<note>Literally "his nose"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">The Lord has devoured; he has not shown mercy to all the dwellings of Jacob; he has broken down in his wrath the fortifications of the daughter of Judah; he has leveled to the ground, he has dishonored the kingdom and its commanders.<note>Or "her commanders"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">He has cut down {in fierce anger}<note>Literally "in a fierce nose"</note> all the might of Israel; he has withdrawn his right hand from the faces of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> enemy, and he has burned in Jacob like a flaming fire, it has consumed all around.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He has bent his bow like an enemy; he has set his right hand like a foe, and he has slain all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> treasures of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> eye;<note>NRSV translates "all in whom we took pride"</note> in the tent of the daughter of Zion, he has poured out his anger like fire.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The Lord has become like an enemy; he has destroyed Israel; he has destroyed all its citadel fortresses;<note>Or "her citadel fortresses"</note> he has ruined all its fortifications and multiplied lamentation and mourning in the daughter of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="6">He has broken down {his dwelling}<note>Literally "his booth"; or "his tabernacle"</note> place like the garden; he has ruined his appointed feasts; Yahweh has made <transChange type="added">them</transChange> forget in Zion {festival}<note>Literally "appointed time"</note> and Sabbath, and he has despised in his anger king and priest.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The Lord has rejected his altar; he has rejected his sanctuary; he has delivered into the hands of the enemy the walls of its citadel fortresses.<note>Or "her citadel fortress"</note> They have cried out in the house of Yahweh like a day of an appointed feast.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Yahweh has planned to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion. He measured <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a line; he has not restrained his hand from destroying; he caused rampart and wall to mourn; together they have languished away.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Her gates have sunk into the earth; he has ruined and broken her bars, her kings and its princes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> among the nations; there is no more law.<note>Hebrew torah</note> Also, her prophets have not found a revelation from Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="10">They sit on the ground, the elders of the daughter of Zion are silent. They cast dust on their head, they have put on sackcloth; the young women of Jerusalem have bowed their head down to the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="11">My eyes have {spent all their tears};<note>Literally "finished with the weeping"</note> {my stomach}<note>Literally "my inward parts"</note> is in torment, {my heart}<note>Literally "my liver"</note> is poured out on the earth because of the destruction of the daughter of my people, because child and babe faint in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> public squares of a city.</verse>
    <verse num="12">To their mothers they say, "Where is the bread and wine?" as they faint like the wounded in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> public squares of a city, as their life is being poured out onto the bosom of their mothers.</verse>
    <verse num="13">What can I say for you? What can I compare to you, O daughter of Jerusalem? To what can I liken you so that I can comfort you, O virgin daughter of Zion? For your destruction <transChange type="added">is</transChange> as vast as the sea; who can heal you?</verse>
    <verse num="14">Your prophets had a vision for you, false and worthless; they have not exposed your sin, to restore your fortune; they have seen oracles for you, false and misleading.</verse>
    <verse num="15">They clap hands over you, all who pass along the way; they hiss and they shake their head, at the daughter of Jerusalem. Is this the city of which it is said, "A perfection of beauty, a joy for all the earth?"</verse>
    <verse num="16">They have opened their mouths against you, all your enemies. They hiss and gnash a tooth, and they say, "We have destroyed <transChange type="added">her</transChange>! Surely this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the day we have hoped for; we have found <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, we have seen <transChange type="added">it</transChange>!"</verse>
    <verse num="17">Yahweh has done what he has planned; he has fulfilled his promise that he ordained from the days of old; he has demolished and not shown mercy; he has made an enemy rejoice over you, he has exalted the {might}<note>Literally "horn"</note> of your foes.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Their heart cried to the Lord, "O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears stream down like a river; day and night, do not give yourself relief, do not give your eyes rest.</verse>
    <verse num="19">"Arise, cry out in the night, at the beginning of the night watches; pour out your heart like water, before the face of the Lord. Lift to him your hands, for the life of your children, who faint in starvation, at the head of all streets."</verse>
    <verse num="20">See, Yahweh, and take note! With whom have you dealt thus? Should women eat their young children of tender care? Should priest and prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?</verse>
    <verse num="21">They lie in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> soil of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> streets, young and old; my young women<note>Or "my virgins"</note> and young men, they have fallen by the sword; you have slain on the day of {your anger},<note>Literally "your nose"</note> you have slaughtered and not shown mercy.</verse>
    <verse num="22">You have summoned my horror from all around, as if for a feast day; no one on the day of Yahweh's anger <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fugitive and a survivor; whoever I have cared for and reared, my enemy has destroyed.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">I am a man who has seen misery, under the rod of his wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="2">He has driven me along, he brought darkness and not light.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Surely he has turned his hand against me, all day long.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He has worn out my flesh and skin, he has broken my bones.</verse>
    <verse num="5">{He has besieged}<note>Literally "he has built against"</note> and engulfed me with bitterness and hardship.</verse>
    <verse num="6">In darkness he has let me dwell like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> dead of long ago.</verse>
    <verse num="7">He has built a wall around me, I cannot go out; he has made my bronze fetters heavy.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Though I cry out for help, he shuts out my prayers.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He has blocked my ways with dressed stones; he has made my paths crooked.</verse>
    <verse num="10">To me he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a bear lying in wait, a lion in hiding.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He has forsaken my way and torn me to pieces; he has caused me desolation.</verse>
    <verse num="12">He has bent his bow and set me as the target for the arrow.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He shot {the arrows of his quiver}<note>Literally "the offspring of his arrow quiver"</note> into my kidneys.</verse>
    <verse num="14">I have become a laughingstock for all the people, their mocking song all day long.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He has filled me with bitterness, he has drenched me <transChange type="added">with</transChange> wormwood.</verse>
    <verse num="16">He has broken my teeth on grit, he has trampled me down in ash.</verse>
    <verse num="17">My life has been removed from peace, I have forgotten goodness.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And I have said, "My glory is ruined, my expectation from Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="19">Remember my misery and bitterness, the wormwood<note>Or "the bitter substance"</note> and venom!</verse>
    <verse num="20">Surely my soul remembers and bows down within me.</verse>
    <verse num="21">This {I have reminded myself},<note>Literally "I have brought back to my heart"</note> therefore I will hope.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The loyal love of Yahweh does not cease; his compassions do not come to an end.</verse>
    <verse num="23"><transChange type="added">They</transChange> are new in the morning, great is your faithfulness.</verse>
    <verse num="24">"Yahweh is my portion," says my soul, "Thus I will hope on him."</verse>
    <verse num="25">Yahweh is good to those who wait on him, to the person that seeks him.</verse>
    <verse num="26"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> good to wait in silence for the salvation of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="27"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> good for a man who carries the yoke of his childhood.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Let him sit alone and be silent when he<note>Yahweh</note> has laid it on him.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Let {him put}<note>Literally "him give"</note> his mouth in the dust; perhaps there is hope.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Let him give a cheek to his smiter, let him be filled with disgrace.</verse>
    <verse num="31">For the Lord will not reject forever.</verse>
    <verse num="32">For even though he causes grief he has compassion according to the greatness of his royal love.</verse>
    <verse num="33">He does not {afflict willingly},<note>Literally "afflict from the heart"</note> or grieve {anyone}.<note>Literally "the sons of men"</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">To crush under his feet all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prisoners of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth;</verse>
    <verse num="35">{to deprive one of justice}<note>Literally "to turn aside the judgment of a man"</note> before the face of the Most High;</verse>
    <verse num="36">to subvert a person in a legal dispute --the Lord has not found delight <transChange type="added">in these things</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="37">{Who can speak}<note>Literally "Who is this that speaks"</note> and it will happen <transChange type="added">if</transChange> the Lord has not commanded <transChange type="added">it</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="38"><transChange type="added">Is</transChange> it not from the mouth of the Most High <transChange type="added">that</transChange> disaster and good will come?</verse>
    <verse num="39">Why should any living person complain about his sin?</verse>
    <verse num="40">Let us test and examine our ways; let us return to Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="41">Let us lift up our hearts with our hands to God in the heavens.</verse>
    <verse num="42">We ourselves have transgressed and rebelled, you have not forgiven.</verse>
    <verse num="43">You have covered <transChange type="added">yourself</transChange> {in anger}<note>Literally "in the nose"</note> and pursued us, you have slain and not shown mercy.</verse>
    <verse num="44">You have covered yourself in a cloud {so that prayer cannot pass through}.<note>Literally "from a passing prayer"</note></verse>
    <verse num="45">You have made us scum and refuse in the midst of the nations.</verse>
    <verse num="46">All our enemies have opened their mouth against us.</verse>
    <verse num="47">Fear and a pit have come upon us, desolation and destruction.</verse>
    <verse num="48">Channels of water run down my eyes because of the destruction of the daughter of my people.</verse>
    <verse num="49">My eyes have poured down unceasingly without respite,</verse>
    <verse num="50">until Yahweh looks down and sees from heaven.</verse>
    <verse num="51">My eyes inflict my soul because of all the daughters of my city.</verse>
    <verse num="52">My enemies hunt me without cause, like a bird.</verse>
    <verse num="53">{They have silenced me in a pit},<note>Literally "they have put to silence my life in a pit"</note> they have thrown a stone at me.</verse>
    <verse num="54">Water has flown over my head, I said, "I am cut off."</verse>
    <verse num="55">I have called your name, O Yahweh, from the depths of the pit.</verse>
    <verse num="56">You have heard my cry, "Do not shut your ear to my cry for help, for my relief!"</verse>
    <verse num="57">You came near on a day <transChange type="added">when</transChange> I called you, you said, "Do not fear!"</verse>
    <verse num="58">O Lord, you have pleaded for {my cause},<note>Literally "the legal disputes of my soul"</note> you have redeemed my life.</verse>
    <verse num="59">You have seen my injustice, O Yahweh; judge my case.</verse>
    <verse num="60">You have seen all their vengeance, all there plans against me.</verse>
    <verse num="61">You have heard their disgrace, O Yahweh, all their plans against me.</verse>
    <verse num="62">The lips and meditation of my assailants <transChange type="added">are</transChange> against me all day long.</verse>
    <verse num="63">Look at their sitting and their standing, I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> their mocking song.</verse>
    <verse num="64">Return to them what is deserved, O Yahweh, according to the work of their hands.</verse>
    <verse num="65">Give them a stubborn heart; curse them!</verse>
    <verse num="66">Pursue them {in anger}<note>Literally "in nose"</note> and destroy them from under the heavens of Yahweh.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">How <transChange type="added">the</transChange> gold has grown dim, the pure gold has changed. The stones of holiness are scattered at the head of every street.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The precious sons of Zion weighed against fine gold, how they are thought of as earthen vessels of clay, the work of the potter's hands.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Even the jackal bears the beast and nurses their cubs; <transChange type="added">but</transChange> the daughter of my people has become ruthless, like ostriches in the wilderness.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The tongue of the nursling cleaves to its palate in thirst. Children beg <transChange type="added">for</transChange> food, {no one lays it out before them}.<note>Literally "nothing spreads to them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">The ones who eat delicacies, they are ruined in the streets; the ones nurtured in purple lie <transChange type="added">on</transChange> piles of trash.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the sin of Sodom; it was overthrown in a moment and no hands were laid on her.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Her princes were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk; <transChange type="added">their</transChange> bodies were more ruddy than rubies, sapphire their appearance.</verse>
    <verse num="8"><transChange type="added">Now</transChange> their appearance is blacker than soot, they are not recognized in the streets; their skin has shriveled on their bones, it has become dry like wood.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Happier were <transChange type="added">the</transChange> victims of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword than the victims of famine; they have pined away, very hungry for the crops of my field.</verse>
    <verse num="10"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> hands of compassionate women, have cooked their children; they became as something to eat in the destruction of the daughter of my people.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Yahweh has completed his anger, he has poured out {his fierce anger};<note>Literally "the fierce anger of his nose"</note> he has kindled a fire in Zion, it consumed her<note>Or "its"</note> foundations.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> kings of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth did not believe, and all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> inhabitants of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> world, that a foe and an enemy could enter into the gates of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Because of the sins of her prophets, the guilt of her priests, who shed blood in her midst, of righteous people.</verse>
    <verse num="14">They wander blindly in the streets; they were defiled with the blood, their clothes could not be touched.</verse>
    <verse num="15">"Go away! Defiled!" they shout to them. "Go away! Go away! Do not touch!" so they left, they left; it was said among the nations, "{They will no longer dwell with us}."<note>Literally "They will no longer be <transChange type="added">here</transChange> as aliens"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">The presence of Yahweh has scattered them, he will no longer watch over them; {they did not honor the priests},<note>Literally "they did not lift up the faces of the priests"</note> they did not show mercy <transChange type="added">to</transChange> elders.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Still our eyes failed, <transChange type="added">looking for</transChange> our help in vain; in our watchtower, we kept watch for a nation that could not save.</verse>
    <verse num="18">They hunted our steps, from walking in our streets; our end has come near, {our days are finished},<note>Literally "our days are filled"</note> our end has come.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Our pursuers were swifter than <transChange type="added">the</transChange> eagles of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> heavens; they chased us on the mountains, they have set an ambush for us in the desert.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The breath of our nostrils, the anointed one of Yahweh, was captured in their pits; of whom we said, "In his shadow we will live among the nations."</verse>
    <verse num="21">Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, you who dwell in the land of Uz; but to you also the cup will pass, you will become drunk and strip yourself bare.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The <transChange type="added">punishment</transChange> of your iniquity is completed, O daughter of Zion, your exile will not continue; <transChange type="added">but</transChange> he will punish your iniquity, O daughter of Edom, he will reveal your sins.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">Remember, O Yahweh, what has become of us; take note, and see our disgrace!</verse>
    <verse num="2">Our inheritance has been turned over to strangers, our houses, to foreigners.</verse>
    <verse num="3">We have become orphans, fatherless, our mothers are like widows.</verse>
    <verse num="4">{We pay for water with money},<note>Literally "we drink our water by money"</note> our wood comes <transChange type="added">to us</transChange> at a price.</verse>
    <verse num="5">We are driven on our necks; we are weary, there is no rest for us.</verse>
    <verse num="6">We have made a deal with Egypt <transChange type="added">and</transChange> Assyria to be satisfied <transChange type="added">with</transChange> food.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Our fathers have sinned, they are no more; we bear their iniquity.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Slaves rule over us; there is no one to deliver us from their hand.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{We risk our life for food}<note>Literally "We take our food at our life"</note> because of the sword of the desert.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Our skin is hot like an oven because of the scorching famine.</verse>
    <verse num="11">They raped women in Zion, young women<note>Or "virgins"</note> in the cities of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="12">They hang princes by their hand; they do not show respect before elders.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Young men must carry a hand-mill and boys stumble under the wood.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Elders are no longer at the gate, young men no longer play stringed instruments.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The joy of our hearts has stopped; our circle-dancing has changed to a mourning ceremony.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The crown has fallen from our head; woe to us, for we have sinned!</verse>
    <verse num="17">Because of this, our heart has become faint, because of these, our eyes have become dim.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Because of Mount Zion, which lies desolate, {foxes tread on it}.<note>Literally "foxes go on it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">You, O Yahweh, will sit forever <transChange type="added">on</transChange> your throne for generation to generation.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Why have you forgotten us forever? Why have you forsaken us {for so long}?<note>Literally "for long days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">Restore us to you, O Yahweh, that we will be restored; renew our days as of old.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Unless you have utterly rejected us, unless you are angry with us beyond measure.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>