<book num="Dan">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">In <transChange type="added">the</transChange> third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And the Lord gave Jehoiakim the king of Judah into his hand and {some of}<note>Literally "from the end/extremity/limits"</note> of the utensils of the temple of God,<note>Hebrew "the God"</note> and he brought them <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the land of Shinar <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the temple of his gods, and he brought the utensils to {the treasury}<note>Literally "the house of the treasury"</note> of his gods. </verse>
    <verse num="3">And the king {ordered}<note>Literally "said to"</note> Ashpenaz, the commander of his court officials, to bring {some of the Israelites}<note>Literally "from the sons/children of Israel"</note> from {the royal family}<note>Literally "from the seed of the kingship"</note> and from the lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">youths who {have no physical defect},<note>Literally "there is not in them any physical defect"</note> and <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> {handsome},<note>Literally "good/pleasing of appearance"</note> and <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> prudent<note>Or "insightful"</note> in all wisdom and {endowed with knowledge},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">who have</transChange> knowledge of knowledge"</note> and <transChange type="added">who</transChange> understand insight, and who <transChange type="added">have</transChange> the {ability}<note>Literally "strength"</note> in them to serve in the palace of the king. <transChange type="added">And the king ordered him</transChange> to teach them the literature and the language of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Chaldeans.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the king assigned to them {his daily portion}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> portion of the day on its day"</note> from the fine food of the king, and from {the wine that he drank},<note>Literally "the wine of his drink"</note> and <transChange type="added">instructed that</transChange> {they were to be educated for three years}.<note>Literally "and to be educated them years three"</note> And at the end <transChange type="added">of</transChange> their <transChange type="added">training</transChange>, {they were to be stationed}<note>Literally "they would stand"</note> {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the king.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Now there was among them {from the Judeans},<note>Literally "from the children of Judah"</note> Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And the commander of the court officials gave them names, and he called Daniel, Belteshazzar; and Hananiah, Shadrach; and Mishael, Meshach; and Azariah, Abednego. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Now {Daniel resolved}<note>Literally "Daniel placed upon his heart"</note> that he would not defile himself with the fine food of the king, and with {the wine that he drank},<note>Literally "the wine of his drink"</note> and <transChange type="added">so</transChange> he requested from the commander of the court officials <transChange type="added">permission so</transChange> that he would not defile himself.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And God<note>Hebrew "the God"</note> gave Daniel favor and compassion {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the commander of the court officials,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and the commander of the court officials said to Daniel, "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> afraid <transChange type="added">of</transChange> my lord, the king, who has determined your food and your drink, for {why should}<note>Literally "to what would"</note> he see your face having a worse appearance than the young men who {are your age}?<note>Literally "like your age"; "your" is plural</note> Then you will endanger my head with the king."</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then<note>Hebrew "And"</note> Daniel asked the guard<note>Or "overseer"</note> whom the commander of the court officials <transChange type="added">had</transChange> appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,</verse>
    <verse num="12">"Please test your servants <transChange type="added">for</transChange> ten days, and let them give us {some of the vegetables},<note>Literally "from the vegetables"</note> and let us eat and let us drink water.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then<note>Hebrew "And"</note> let our appearances and the appearance of the young men who are eating the fine food of the king be compared {before you},<note>Literally "in your presence"</note> and <transChange type="added">then</transChange> deal with your servants {according to what you see}."<note>Literally "and according to/that you see"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">So he agreed to this proposal with them, and he tested them <transChange type="added">for</transChange> ten days.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And at the end of ten days their appearances appeared better and <transChange type="added">they were</transChange> healthier of body than all the young men who were eating the fine food of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="16">{So}<note>Literally "And it happened"</note> the guard {continued to withhold}<note>Literally "he was ... withdrawing"</note> their fine food and the wine of their drink, and he gave them<note>Hebrew "to them"</note> vegetables. </verse>
    <verse num="17">{And as for these four young men},<note>Literally "And these young men, four of them"</note> God<note>Hebrew "the God"</note> gave to them knowledge and insight into all literature and wisdom, and Daniel had insight into all visions<note>Hebrew "vision"</note> and dreams.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And at the end of the time the king had set to bring them, the commander of the court officials brought them in {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> Nebuchadnezzar.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And the king spoke with them, {and among all of them no one was found like}<note>Literally "and he was not found from all of them like"</note> Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah; then they stood {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the king.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And in every matter of wisdom <transChange type="added">and</transChange> understanding <transChange type="added">about</transChange> which the king inquired from them, he found them ten times better <transChange type="added">than</transChange> all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the magicians<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> conjurers<note>Or "enchanters"</note> that {were in his entire kingdom}.<note>Literally "in the whole of his kingdom"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">And Daniel was <transChange type="added">there</transChange> until the first year of Cyrus the king. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Now<note>Hebrew "And"</note> in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams; and his spirit was troubled and his sleep left him.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So the king said to call the magicians<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> and the conjurers<note>Or "enchanters"</note> and the sorcerers and the {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> to tell to the king his dreams. And they came in and they stood {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the king.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the king said to them, "{I have had a dream}<note>Literally "A dream I have dreamed"</note> and my spirit is anxious to know the dream." </verse>
    <verse num="4">And the {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> said to the king <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Aramaic,<note>The text of Daniel is in Aramaic from this point on through Daniel chapter 7. Then the text resumes in Hebrew to the end of the book</note> "O king, live forever! Tell the dream to your servants and we will reveal the explanation."</verse>
    <verse num="5">The king answered and said to the {astrologers},<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> "The command from me is firm: if you <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not make known to me the dream and its explanation,<note>Or "interpretation"</note> <transChange type="added">then</transChange> you will be broken into pieces and your houses will be laid in ruins.</verse>
    <verse num="6">But if you tell me the dream and its explanation, you will receive gifts and rewards<note>Aramaic "reward"</note> and great honor from me. Therefore, tell me the dream and its explanation."<note>Or "interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">They answered once more and said, "Let the king tell the dream to his servants and we will make the explanation known."</verse>
    <verse num="8">The king answered and said, "{Certainly}<note>Literally "From <transChange type="added">a</transChange> certainty"</note> I know that {you are trying to gain time}<note>Literally "the time you are gaining"</note> {because}<note>Literally "all because of that"</note> you have seen {that this matter is firmly decreed by me},<note>Literally "that firm from me <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the decree"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">for if you <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not make the dream known to me, {your verdict is fixed},<note>Literally "one is your verdict"</note> and you have conspired to say <transChange type="added">a</transChange> lying and deceitful word to me until the {circumstances}<note>Literally "time"</note> will change. Therefore, tell me the dream, and I will know that you can tell me its explanation."</verse>
    <verse num="10">The {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> answered the king and said, "There is not a man on earth that is able to reveal the word of the king; {in fact},<note>Literally "all because that"</note> no great and powerful king has <transChange type="added">ever</transChange> asked a thing like this of any magician<note>Or "soothsayer-priest"</note> or conjurer<note>Or "enchanter"</note> or {astrologer}.<note>Literally "Chaldean"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And the thing that the king is asking <transChange type="added">is too</transChange> difficult and {there is no one who}<note>Literally "there is not another"</note> can reveal it to the king except <transChange type="added">the</transChange> gods {whose dwelling is not with mortals}."<note>Literally "concerning their dwelling is not with flesh"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="12">Because of this the king became angry, and he became very much enraged, and he said <transChange type="added">that</transChange> all the wise men of Babylon <transChange type="added">are</transChange> to be destroyed.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the decree was issued, and the wise men {were on the verge of being executed},<note>Literally "were in the process of being killed"</note> and they searched for Daniel and his companions to be executed.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Then Daniel responded prudently and discretely to Arioch, the commander of the imperial guard of the king, who had gone out to execute the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
    <verse num="15">{He asked}<note>Literally "he answered"</note> and said to Arioch, the royal official of the king, "{Why}<note>Literally "Over what"</note> is the decree from the king <transChange type="added">so</transChange> severe?" Then Arioch explained the matter<note>Or "situation"</note> to Daniel.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Daniel went in and requested from the king that he would give him time, and {he would tell the king}<note>Literally "to tell/reveal to the king"</note> the explanation.<note>Or "interpretation"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="17">Then Daniel went to his home, and he made the matter known to Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah, his companions,</verse>
    <verse num="18">and <transChange type="added">told them</transChange> to seek mercy {from the God of heaven}<note>Literally "from before the God of the heaven"</note> concerning this mystery, so that Daniel and his companions, along with the remainder of the wise men of Babylon, would not be killed. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Then in a vision of the night the mystery was revealed to Daniel; then Daniel blessed the God of heaven. </verse>
    <verse num="20">Daniel {said}:<note>Literally "answered and he said"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="21">And he changes the times and the seasons, and he deposes kings and he sets up kings; he gives wisdom<note>Aramaic "the wisdom"</note> to wise men and knowledge to <transChange type="added">men who</transChange> know understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="22">He reveals the deep and the hidden things; he knows what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the darkness, and the light dwells with him.</verse>
    <verse num="23">To you, O God of my ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> I give thanks and I give praises, for the wisdom and the power you gave to me, and now you have made known to me what we have asked from you, for you have made known to us the matter of the king."</verse>
    <verse num="24">{Therefore}<note>Literally "Now because this"</note> Daniel went to Arioch, whom the king had appointed<note>Aramaic "has appointed"</note> to destroy the wise men of Babylon; he went and thus he said to him: "You must not destroy the wise men of Babylon; take me in before the king and I will give the explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> to the king." </verse>
    <verse num="25">Then Arioch {quickly}<note>Literally "in haste"</note> brought Daniel in before the king and thus he said to him: "I have found a man among {the exiles}<note>Literally "the children of exiles"</note> of Judah<note>Aramaic "Jehud"</note> who {can relate}<note>Literally "he will make known"</note> the explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> to the king.</verse>
    <verse num="26">{The king then asked}<note>Literally "The king answered"</note> and said to Daniel, whose name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Belteshazzar, "Are you able to make known to me the dream that I have seen and its explanation?"<note>Or "interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">Daniel answered the king and said, "The mystery that the king asks, no wise men, conjurers,<note>Or "enchanters"</note> magicians,<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> <transChange type="added">or</transChange> diviners are able to make known to the king.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But there is a God in heaven <transChange type="added">who</transChange> reveals mysteries, and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar what <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> that will be at the end of days. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your dream and the visions of your head on your bed. </verse>
    <verse num="29">"<transChange type="added">As for you</transChange>, king,<note>Aramaic "the king"</note> your thoughts on your bed {turned to}<note>Literally "they went up"</note> what <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> that would be {in the future},<note>Literally "after this"</note> and the revealer of mysteries has made known to you what that would be.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And as for me, <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> not because of wisdom that is in me more than {any other living person}<note>Literally "all of living beings"</note> <transChange type="added">that</transChange> this mystery is revealed to me, but {in order that}<note>Literally "concerning the matter of"</note> the explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> may be made known to the king and you will {understand}<note>Literally "know"</note> the thoughts of your {mind}.<note>Literally "heart"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="31">"You, O king, were looking and, look, there was one great statue. This statue <transChange type="added">was</transChange> huge and its brilliance extraordinary, standing <transChange type="added">there</transChange> before you, and its appearance <transChange type="added">was</transChange> frightening.<note>Or "dreadful"</note></verse>
    <verse num="32">The head of this statue <transChange type="added">was</transChange> of fine gold, its chest and its arms of silver, its belly and its thighs of bronze,</verse>
    <verse num="33">its legs of iron, its feet, part of them of iron and part of them of clay.</verse>
    <verse num="34">You were looking on {until}<note>Literally "until that"</note> a stone was chiseled out<note>Or "became loose"</note>--that not by hands--and it struck the statue on its feet of iron and clay, and it broke them in pieces.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Then the iron, the clay, the bronze, the silver and the gold {all at once}<note>Literally "like one"</note> broke into pieces<note>Or "were crushed"</note> and they became like chaff from the summer threshing floor, and the wind carried them away and any trace of them could not be found. But the stone that struck the statue became a great mountain and it filled the whole earth. </verse>
    <verse num="36">"This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the dream, and <transChange type="added">now</transChange> we will tell its interpretation to the king.</verse>
    <verse num="37">You, O king, the king of kings, to whom the God of heaven has given the kingdom, the power and the might and the glory,</verse>
    <verse num="38">and <transChange type="added">also</transChange> {human beings wherever they dwell},<note>Literally "and into all that dwell sons of humankind"</note> the animals of the field and the birds<note>Aramaic "bird"</note> of heaven<note>Or "the sky"</note>--he has given into your hand and made you ruler over all of them--you are the head of gold.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And after you another kingdom inferior to yours will arise, and another third <transChange type="added">kingdom</transChange> of bronze that will rule over the whole earth.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And <transChange type="added">a</transChange> fourth kingdom will be strong as iron, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {just as}<note>Literally "all of because"</note> iron crushes and smashes {everything},<note>Literally "the whole thing"</note> and as iron shatters all of these <transChange type="added">other metals</transChange>, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> it will crush and it will shatter <transChange type="added">these nations</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="41">{And just as}<note>Literally "And that"</note> you saw the feet and the toes, {partly potter's clay}<note>Literally "from them clay of the potter"</note> and {partly iron},<note>Literally "from them iron"</note> it will be a divided kingdom; and {some hardness}<note>Literally "from the hardness"</note> of the iron will be <transChange type="added">in it</transChange>, {just as}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> you have seen the iron mixed with the wet clay.</verse>
    <verse num="42">And <transChange type="added">as</transChange> the toes of the feet <transChange type="added">were</transChange> partly iron and partly clay, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> part of the kingdom will be strong {and partly brittle}.<note>Literally "and from it, it will be brittle"</note></verse>
    <verse num="43">And <transChange type="added">in</transChange> that you saw the iron was mixed with wet clay, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> {they will mix in marriage}<note>Literally "mixing they will in the seed of man"</note> and they will not cling {to one another},<note>Literally "this one with that one"</note> just as iron <transChange type="added">does</transChange> not mix with clay.</verse>
    <verse num="44">And {in the day of those kings},<note>Literally "in their days of those kings"</note> the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will {never}<note>Literally "to forever not"</note> be destroyed, and the kingdom will not be left for another nation,<note>Or "people"</note> and it will bring an end to all these kingdoms, but it will stand {forever}.<note>Literally "to eternity"</note></verse>
    <verse num="45">{Inasmuch as}<note>Literally "All of because that"</note> you saw that a stone from the mountain was chiseled out<note>Or "became loose"</note> <transChange type="added">but</transChange> not by hands, and <transChange type="added">that</transChange> it crushed the iron, the bronze, the clay, the silver and the gold, <transChange type="added">thereby</transChange> the great God made known to the king what will be {in the future},<note>Literally "after this"</note> and the dream is certain and its explanation trustworthy." </verse>
    <verse num="46">Then the king, Nebuchadnezzar, fell on his face and he paid homage to Daniel; and he commanded <transChange type="added">them</transChange> to offer <transChange type="added">a</transChange> grain offering and incense offering to him.</verse>
    <verse num="47">The king answered Daniel and said, "{Truly}<note>Literally "From truth that"</note> your God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the God of gods and the Lord of kings, and he reveals mysteries, for you are able to reveal this mystery."</verse>
    <verse num="48">Then the king promoted Daniel and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon and the chief prefect over all the wise men of Babylon.</verse>
    <verse num="49">And Daniel made a request from the king, and he appointed Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego over the affairs of the province of Babylon, while Daniel <transChange type="added">remained</transChange> in the court of the king. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Nebuchadnezzar the king made a statue of gold. Its height <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sixty cubits <transChange type="added">and</transChange> its width <transChange type="added">was</transChange> six cubits; he set it up in the valley of Dura in the province of Babylon.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent <transChange type="added">directions</transChange> to assemble the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the magistrates and all of the officials of the provinces to come to the dedication of the statue that Nebuchadnezzar the king <transChange type="added">had</transChange> set up.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then the satraps, the prefects, the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the magistrates, and all the officials of the province <transChange type="added">were</transChange> assembled for the dedication of the statue that Nebuchadnezzar the king <transChange type="added">had</transChange> set up, and <transChange type="added">were</transChange> standing {before}<note>Literally "to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> front"</note> the statue that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then the herald proclaimed {aloud},<note>Literally "with power"</note> "To you {it is commanded},<note>Literally "they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> saying"</note> O peoples, {nations and people of all languages},<note>Literally "the nations and the languages"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">that</transChange> at the time that you hear the sound of the horn, the flute, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lyre, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trigon, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harp, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> drum and all kinds of music, you must fall down and you must worship the statue of gold<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note> that Nebuchadnezzar the king <transChange type="added">has</transChange> set up.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And {whoever}<note>Literally "who that"</note> does not fall down and worship will be thrown {immediately}<note>Literally "the time"</note> into the midst of the furnace of blazing fire."</verse>
    <verse num="7">{Therefore},<note>Literally "All of because this"</note> {at that time},<note>Literally "at the time"</note> {as soon as}<note>Literally "as that"</note> all the peoples heard the sound of the horn, the flute, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lyre, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trigon, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harp and all kinds of music, all the peoples, {the nations and people of all languages}<note>Literally "the nations and the languages"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> falling down <transChange type="added">and</transChange> were worshiping the statue of gold<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note> that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. </verse>
    <verse num="8">{Therefore}<note>Literally "All because of this"</note> {at this time}<note>Literally "at it the time"</note> <transChange type="added">some</transChange> {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldean men"</note> came forward and {they denounced the Jews}.<note>Literally "they ate their pieces of the Jews"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">{They responded and said}<note>Literally "they answered and <transChange type="added">were</transChange> saying"</note> to Nebuchadnezzar the king, "O king, may <transChange type="added">you</transChange> live {forever}!<note>Literally "to eternity"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">You, O king, have made a decree that {everyone}<note>Literally "all of humanity"</note> who hears the sound of the horn, the flute, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lyre, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trigon, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harp and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> drum and all kinds of music, he shall fall down and shall worship the statue of gold.<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">{And whoever}<note>Literally "And who that"</note> {does not fall down}<note>Literally "not he falls down"</note> and worship shall be thrown into the midst of the furnace of blazing fire.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">However</transChange> there are Judean men whom you have appointed<note>Aramaic "whom you have appointed them"</note> over the affairs of the province of Babylon--Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego--these men, O king, {pay you no heed}<note>Literally "not they pay heed to you"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> not serving your god, and the statue of gold<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note> that you set up they are not worshiping." </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then Nebuchadnezzar said in rage and anger to bring in Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego; then they brought in these men before the king.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Nebuchadnezzar answered and said to them, "<transChange type="added">Is it</transChange> true, Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, <transChange type="added">that</transChange> you are not serving my god, and <transChange type="added">you are</transChange> not worshiping the statue of gold<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note> that I have set up?</verse>
    <verse num="15">Now if you are ready so that {when}<note>Literally "at that time"</note> you hear the sound of the horn, the flute, the lyre, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trigon, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harp and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> drum and all kinds of music, you fall down and you worship the statue that I have made, <transChange type="added">that will be good</transChange>. But if you do not worship it, {immediately}<note>Literally "at that <transChange type="added">very</transChange> time"</note> you will be thrown into the midst of the furnace of blazing fire, and {who is the god}<note>Literally "who he god"</note> who<note>Or "that"</note> will rescue you from my hands?" </verse>
    <verse num="16">Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego answered and said to the king, Nebuchadnezzar, "We have no need on this matter {to present a defense to you}.<note>Literally "to return to you"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">{If it is so},<note>Literally "If there is"</note> our God, whom we serve, is able to rescue us from the furnace of blazing fire. And from your hand, O king, let him rescue us.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And if not, let it be known to you, O king, that {we will not serve your gods},<note>Literally "your gods not there is us serving"</note> and the statue of gold<note>Aramaic "the gold"</note> that you have set up we will not worship." </verse>
    <verse num="19">Then Nebuchadnezzar was filled with anger and the image of his face was changed {toward}<note>Literally "against"</note> Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, <transChange type="added">so he</transChange> {ordered and said}<note>Literally "answering and saying"</note> to heat up the one furnace seven times what was usual to heat <transChange type="added">it</transChange> up.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And he commanded {the strongest men of the guards}<note>Literally "to the strong men, men of strength"</note> who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego and to throw <transChange type="added">them</transChange> into the furnace of blazing fire.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then these men were bound with their garments, their trousers and their turbans and their <transChange type="added">other</transChange> clothing, and they were thrown into the midst of the furnace of blazing fire.</verse>
    <verse num="22">{Therefore}<note>Literally "because of this"</note> {because}<note>Literally "from that"</note> the word of the king was severe and the furnace was exceedingly hot, the flame of the fire killed these men who lifted up Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But these men, the three of them, Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, fell down into the midst of the furnace of blazing fire, <transChange type="added">and they</transChange> were bound. </verse>
    <verse num="24">Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonished, and he rose up in haste <transChange type="added">and</transChange> he asked, saying to his advisers, "<transChange type="added">Did</transChange> we not throw three men, bound, into the midst of the fire? They answered, saying to the king, "Certainly, O king!"</verse>
    <verse num="25">{He answered},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">was</transChange> answering"</note> saying, "Look, I see four men unbound walking in the midst of the fire and there is no damage to them, and the<note>Aramaic "its"</note> appearance of the fourth <transChange type="added">man</transChange> resembles the son of a god."</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then Nebuchadnezzar approached the door of the furnace of blazing fire, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> he called out, saying, "Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, {servants}<note>Literally "his servant"</note> of the Most High God, come out<note>Or "Go out"</note> and come here!"</verse>
    <verse num="27">And the satraps, the prefects, the governors and the advisors of the king <transChange type="added">were</transChange> assembling, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> they saw these men, that the fire had no power over their bodies, and the hair of their heads was<note>Aramaic plural</note> not singed, and their garments were not harmed, and the smell of fire did not come from them. </verse>
    <verse num="28">Nebuchadnezzar {responded},<note>Literally "answering"</note> saying, "Blessed be their God, <transChange type="added">the God</transChange> of Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, who sent his angel<note>Or "messenger"</note> and rescued his servants who trusted in him, and the command of the king they disobeyed, and they gave their bodies so that they <transChange type="added">did</transChange> not serve and <transChange type="added">did</transChange> not worship any god except their God.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And from me {is set forth}<note>Literally "setting out"</note> a decree that any people, nation, or language that <transChange type="added">may</transChange> utter criticism against their God--<transChange type="added">the God of</transChange> Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego--will be broken into pieces and their<note>Aramaic "his"</note> house will be made like ruins. {For}<note>Literally "All of because"</note> there is not another God who is able to rescue like this <transChange type="added">God</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="30">Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego in the province of Babylon. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1"><note>Daniel 4:1-4:37 in the English Bible is 3:31-4:34 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Nebuchadnezzar the king to all of the nations, the peoples and languages that live in the whole earth: "May your prosperity increase!</verse>
    <verse num="2">It is pleasing to me to recount the signs and wonders that the Most High God worked for me.</verse>
    <verse num="3">How great <transChange type="added">are</transChange> his signs and wonders, how strong <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his kingdom, {an everlasting kingdom};<note>Literally "a kingdom of eternity"</note> and his sovereignty is from generation to generation. </verse>
    <verse num="4">"I, Nebuchadnezzar, was content in my house and prospering in my palace.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And I saw a dream and a revelation on my bed and it frightened me, and the visions of my head terrified me.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And a decree was {sent out},<note>Literally "put/placed"</note> <transChange type="added">ordering that</transChange> all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wise men of Babylon <transChange type="added">were</transChange> to be brought in before me <transChange type="added">so</transChange> that they may make known to me <transChange type="added">the</transChange> explanation of the dream.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then the magicians,<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> the conjurers,<note>Or "enchanters"</note> the {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> and the diviners came in and I told them the dream, but they could not make known to me its explanation.<note>Or "interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Then {at last}<note>Literally "until another"</note> Daniel came before me {whose name was}<note>Literally "who name his"</note> Belteshazzar, {according to}<note>Literally "like"</note> the name of my god, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {in whom was the spirit of the holy gods},<note>Literally "and who <transChange type="added">the</transChange> spirit of gods holy in him"</note> {and I related the dream to him}.<note>Literally "and the dream before him I told"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="9">" '<transChange type="added">O</transChange> Belteshazzar, chief of the magicians,<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> I myself know that <transChange type="added">the</transChange> spirit<note>Or "a spirit"</note> of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy gods <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in you, and {no mystery is too difficult}<note>Literally "every mystery is not difficult"</note> for you. <transChange type="added">Now</transChange> tell <transChange type="added">me</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> visions of my dream that I saw, and its explanation.<note>Or "interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Now <transChange type="added">these were</transChange> the visions of my head <transChange type="added">as I was lying</transChange> on my bed: I was {gazing}<note>Literally "seeing"</note> and, look, a tree <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in the midst of the earth, and its height <transChange type="added">was</transChange> exalted. </verse>
    <verse num="11">The tree grew and it became strong, and its height reached to heaven,<note>Or "the sky"</note> and {it was visible to the end of the whole earth}.<note>Literally "and its appearance <transChange type="added">was</transChange> to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end of the whole earth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">Its foliage <transChange type="added">was</transChange> beautiful, and its fruit abundant, and in it <transChange type="added">was</transChange> provision for all. Under it the animals<note>Aramaic "animal"</note> of the field sought shade, and in its branches the birds of heaven<note>Or "the sky"</note> nested, and from it all the living beings were fed.</verse>
    <verse num="13">" 'I was looking in the vision of my head <transChange type="added">as I lay</transChange> on my bed, and look, a watcher,<note>Or "angelic being"</note> and <transChange type="added">a</transChange> holy <transChange type="added">one</transChange>, came down from heaven. </verse>
    <verse num="14">He cried {aloud}<note>Literally "in strength"</note> and so he said: </verse>
    <verse num="15">But the stump of its roots leave in the earth, {along with}<note>Literally "and with"</note> a band of iron and bronze; <transChange type="added">leave it</transChange> in the grass of the field. And in<note>Or "with"</note> the dew of heaven let it<note>Or "him," that is, the king</note> be watered, and with the animals<note>Aramaic "animal"</note> let his lot <transChange type="added">be</transChange> in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> grass of the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Let his mind be changed from <transChange type="added">that of a</transChange> human,<note>Or "the human"</note> and let <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mind of an animal be given to him, and let seven times pass over him.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The sentence <transChange type="added">is</transChange> by <transChange type="added">the</transChange> decree of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> watchers, and the decision <transChange type="added">by</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> command of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy <transChange type="added">ones</transChange>, {in order that}<note>Literally "until matter that"</note> the living will know that the Most High <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sovereign over <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom of humankind, and {to whomever}<note>Literally "to whom that"</note> he wills he gives it, and he <transChange type="added">even</transChange> sets <transChange type="added">the</transChange> humblest of men over it."</verse>
    <verse num="18">" 'This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the dream <transChange type="added">that</transChange> I, Nebuchadnezzar the king, saw. Now<note>Or "And"</note> you, Belteshazzar, declare its explanation, {for}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> all of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wise men of my kingdom were not able to make the explanation known to me, but you are able because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> spirit of holy gods <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in you.' </verse>
    <verse num="19">"Then Daniel, whose name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Belteshazzar, was distressed {for some time},<note>Literally "for one hour"</note> and his thoughts disturbed him. The king answered and he said, 'Belteshazzar, let the dream and its explanation not disturb you.' Belteshazzar answered and said, 'My lord, <transChange type="added">may</transChange> the dream and its explanation <transChange type="added">be</transChange> for <transChange type="added">those who</transChange> hate you and for your enemies.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The tree that you saw, which grew and became strong and its height reached to heaven<note>Or "the sky"</note> and {it was visible to the end of the whole earth},<note>Literally "its appearance to the all the earth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">and its foliage <transChange type="added">was</transChange> beautiful and its fruit abundant, and <transChange type="added">so there was</transChange> provision for all in it, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the animals<note>Aramaic "animal"</note> of the field lived under it and in its branches nest <transChange type="added">the</transChange> birds of heaven,<note>Or "the sky"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">--it is you, O king, who have grown <transChange type="added">great</transChange> and you have grown strong, and <transChange type="added">so</transChange> your greatness has increased and it has reached to heaven<note>Or "the sky"</note> and your sovereignty to the end of the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And <transChange type="added">inasmuch</transChange> that the king saw <transChange type="added">the</transChange> watcher, a holy <transChange type="added">one</transChange> coming down from heaven<note>Or "the sky"</note> and he said, "Cut down the tree and destroy it, but the stump of its root in the earth leave with a band of iron and bronze in the grass of the field, and let it be watered with the dew of heaven and <transChange type="added">let</transChange> his lot <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> animals of the field {until seven times have passed over him}."<note>Literally "until that seven times <transChange type="added">they</transChange> pass over him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the explanation, O king, and it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a decree of the Most High that has come upon my lord the king:</verse>
    <verse num="25">you will be driven away {from human society}<note>Literally "from the humankind"</note> and {you will dwell}<note>Literally "your dwelling will be"</note> with the animals<note>Aramaic "animal"</note> of the field, and you will be caused to graze grass like the oxen {yourself},<note>Literally "with respect to you"</note> and you will be watered with the dew of heaven, and seven <transChange type="added">periods of</transChange> time will pass over you until that you have acknowledged that the Most High <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind, and {to whom he wills}<note>Literally "that he wills"</note> he gives it.</verse>
    <verse num="26">{And in that}<note>Literally "And for"</note> they said to leave alone the stump of the tree's root, so your kingdom <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> restored for you {when}<note>Literally "from that"</note> you acknowledge that heaven <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sovereign.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Therefore, O king, let my advice be acceptable <transChange type="added">to you</transChange> and your sin remove<note>Or "replace"</note> with righteousness and your iniquity with having mercy on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> oppressed, {in case there might be a prolongation of your prosperity}.'"<note>Literally "if will be prolongation for your prosperity"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="28">{All this happened}<note>Literally "It came upon"</note> to Nebuchadnezzar the king.</verse>
    <verse num="29">At the end of twelve months he was walking on the <transChange type="added">roof of</transChange> {the royal palace}<note>Literally "the place of the kingdom"</note> of Babylon.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the king answered and said, "Is this not the great Babylon which I have built as a royal palace by the strength of my own power, and for the glory of my own majesty?"</verse>
    <verse num="31"><transChange type="added">While</transChange> the words <transChange type="added">were</transChange> still in the mouth of the king, a voice from heaven came, <transChange type="added">saying</transChange>, 'To you, King Nebuchadnezzar, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> is declared that the kingdom has departed from you,</verse>
    <verse num="32">and you will be driven away from {human society}<note>Literally "the humankind"</note> and your dwelling <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> with the animals<note>Aramaic "animal"</note> of the field and they will cause you to graze <transChange type="added">the</transChange> grass like oxen, and seven times will pass over you, until you acknowledge that the Most High <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind and that he gives it to whom he wills.'</verse>
    <verse num="33">{Immediately}<note>Literally "In that hour"</note> the word was fulfilled {concerning}<note>Literally "over"</note> Nebuchadnezzar, and he was expelled from {human society}<note>Literally "the humankind"</note> and he ate grass like oxen, and his body was bathed with the dew of heaven until his hair <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like <transChange type="added">the hair of</transChange> an eagle and his nails grew like <transChange type="added">a</transChange> bird's <transChange type="added">claws</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="34">"But at the end of {that period},<note>Literally "the day"</note> I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and <transChange type="added">then</transChange> my reason returned to me; and I blessed the Most High and {the one who lives forever}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the one</transChange> living forever"</note> I praised and I honored. </verse>
    <verse num="35">And all the dwellers of the earth are regarded as nothing, and he does {according to}<note>Literally "as"</note> his desire in the host of heaven and <transChange type="added">among</transChange> the dwellers of earth, and there is not <transChange type="added">one</transChange> who can hold back his hand, or {ask him},<note>Literally "or asks to him"</note> 'What are you doing?'</verse>
    <verse num="36">"{At that time}<note>Literally "In it the time"</note> my reason returned to me, and <transChange type="added">also</transChange> the glory of my kingdom and my majesty and splendor returned to me, and my advisers and my lords<note>Or "nobles"</note> searched <transChange type="added">me</transChange> out, and I was established over my kingdom and abundant greatness was added to me.</verse>
    <verse num="37">Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and exalt and honor the king of heaven, for all his works <transChange type="added">are</transChange> truth,<note>Or "true"</note> and his ways <transChange type="added">are</transChange> justice and that he is able to humble those who walk in pride." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">Belshazzar the king made a great festival for <transChange type="added">a</transChange> thousand <transChange type="added">of</transChange> his lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> and {in the presence of}<note>Literally "to over against"</note> the thousand <transChange type="added">lords</transChange> he was drinking wine.<note>Or "the wine"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">{When he tasted the wine},<note>Literally "At the taste of the wine"</note> Belshazzar commanded <transChange type="added">that they</transChange> bring <transChange type="added">the</transChange> vessels of gold and silver that Nebuchadnezzar his {predecessor}<note>Literally "father"</note> had taken from the temple that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Jerusalem, so that the king and his lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> his wives and his concubines may drink from them.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then they brought in the vessels of gold that they took from the temple, the house of God that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Jerusalem, and the king and his lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> his wives and his concubines drank from them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They drank the wine and praised the gods of gold and silver, bronze, iron, wood and stone.<note>All these metals have the definite article that does not have to be translated into English to retain the meaning</note> </verse>
    <verse num="5">{Immediately}<note>Literally "In its the hour"</note> {human fingers}<note>Literally "fingers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hand of a man"</note> appeared and they wrote {opposite}<note>Literally "to over against"</note> the lampstand on the plaster of the wall of the palace of the king, and the king was watching<note>Or "gazing at"</note> the palm of the hand that was writing.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then his face changed and his thoughts terrified him, and {his hip joints gave way}<note>Literally "the limbs of his hip became loose"</note> and {his knees knocked together}.<note>Literally "his knees this to this they knocked together"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">The king cried {aloud}<note>Literally "with strength"</note> to bring <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the conjurers,<note>Or "enchanters"</note> the {astrologers}<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> and the diviners; the king {spoke}<note>Literally "answered"</note> and said to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wise men of Babylon, "Any man that can read this writing and can tell me its explanation will be clothed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> purple and <transChange type="added">will have</transChange> <transChange type="added">a</transChange> necklace of gold <transChange type="added">hung</transChange> around his neck and he will rule <transChange type="added">as</transChange> third <transChange type="added">in authority</transChange> in the kingdom."</verse>
    <verse num="8">Then all the wise men of the king came in, but they were not able to read the writing or to make known its explanation.<note>Aramaic "the explanation/ interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Then the king, Belshazzar, became greatly terrified, and {his facial features}<note>Literally "shining of his face"</note> changed upon him, and his lords<note>Or "nobles"</note> were perplexed. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Because of the words of the king and his lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> the queen came into {the banqueting hall}<note>Literally "the house of the drinking"</note> and the queen {spoke up}<note>Literally "answered"</note> and said, "O king, live {forever},<note>Literally "to eternity"</note> and let not your thoughts terrify you and <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not let your facial expressions {grow pale}.<note>Literally "change"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">There is a man in your kingdom {who has the spirit of the holy gods in him}.<note>Literally "who <transChange type="added">the</transChange> spirit of holy gods <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in him"</note> And in the days of your {predecessor},<note>Literally "father"</note> enlightenment and insight and wisdom like the wisdom of the gods was found in him; and, O king, Nebuchadnezzar your {predecessor}<note>Literally "father"</note> appointed him <transChange type="added">as</transChange> chief of the magicians,<note>Or "soothsayer-priests"</note> the conjurers,<note>Or "enchanters"</note> the {astrologers},<note>Literally "Chaldeans"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the diviners. Your {predecessor}<note>Literally "father"</note> the king <transChange type="added">did this</transChange></verse>
    <verse num="12">{because}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was found in him <transChange type="added">an</transChange> excellent spirit and understanding and insight <transChange type="added">for</transChange> interpreting dreams and explaining riddles and solving riddles; <transChange type="added">that is</transChange>, in Daniel {whom the king named}<note>Literally "whom the king gave his name"</note> Belteshazzar. Now, let Daniel be called and he will tell the explanation."<note>Or "interpretation"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then Daniel was brought in before the king, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the king {spoke}<note>Literally "answered"</note> and said to Daniel, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> Daniel {who are one of the exiles}<note>Literally "who from sons of the exile"</note> of Judah<note>Aramaic "Jehud"</note> whom my {predecessor},<note>Literally "father"</note> the king, brought from Judah.<note>Aramaic "Jehud"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">And I have heard that a spirit of the gods <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in you and enlightenment and insight and excellent wisdom was found in you.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And now the wise men <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the conjurers<note>Or "enchanters"</note> were brought in before me <transChange type="added">so</transChange> that they could read this writing <transChange type="added">in order to</transChange> make its explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> known to me, but they were not able to disclose the explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> of the matter.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But I have heard concerning you that you are able {to produce interpretations}<note>Literally "to interpret interpretations"</note> and to solve riddles; now if you are able to read the writing and to make known its explanation<note>Or "interpretation"</note> to me, you will be clothed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> purple and <transChange type="added">a</transChange> necklace of gold <transChange type="added">will be placed</transChange> around your neck and you will rule <transChange type="added">as</transChange> third <transChange type="added">in command</transChange> in the kingdom." </verse>
    <verse num="17">Then Daniel answered and said before the king, "Let your gifts be for yourself or your rewards give to another; nevertheless, I will read the writing to the king and I will make known to him the explanation.<note>Or "interpretation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">{O king},<note>Literally "You, O king"</note> the Most High God gave the kingdom and the greatness and the glory and the majesty to Nebuchadnezzar your {predecessor}.<note>Literally "father"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And because of the greatness that he gave to him, all the peoples, the nations and languages trembled and feared before him; whomever he wanted he killed, and whomever he wanted he let live, and whomever he wanted he honored, and whomever he wanted he humbled.</verse>
    <verse num="20">But {when}<note>Literally "as that"</note> his heart became arrogant and his spirit became hard <transChange type="added">so as</transChange> to act proudly, he was deposed from the throne of his kingdom and the<note>Or "his"</note> glory {was taken away from him}.<note>Literally "they took away"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">And he was driven away {from human society}<note>Literally "from the sons of the humankind"</note> and his mind was made like the animals<note>Aramaic "with the animals"</note> and his dwelling <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with the wild asses; <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {he was given}<note>Literally "they gave him"</note> grass like oxen to eat, and with<note>Aramaic "from"</note> the dew of heaven his body was bathed, until he acknowledged that the Most High God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sovereign over the kingdom of humankind, and {whoever}<note>Literally "to from that"</note> he wants he sets over it. </verse>
    <verse num="22">"But you his {successor},<note>Literally "son"</note> Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart {even though}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> you knew all this.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And <transChange type="added">now</transChange> you have exalted yourself against the Lord of heaven, and the vessels of his temple you have brought in before you, and you and your lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> your wives and your concubines, have been drinking wine from<note>Aramaic "with"</note> them, and you have praised the gods of silver, gold, bronze, iron, wood, and stone<note>All the materials in this list have the definite article that does not have to be translated into English</note> that <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not see and <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not hear and <transChange type="added">do</transChange> not know, but the God {who holds your life in his hand}<note>Literally "who your breath <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in his hand"</note> and all of your ways {come from him},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">belong</transChange> to him"</note> you have not honored.</verse>
    <verse num="24">So then the palm of the hand was sent out from his presence and this writing was inscribed. </verse>
    <verse num="25">"Now this was the writing that was inscribed: 'Mene, Mene, Tekel and Parsin.' </verse>
    <verse num="26">"This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the explanation of the matter:<note>Or "word, message"</note> 'Mene'--God has numbered your kingdom and brought an end <transChange type="added">to</transChange> it. </verse>
    <verse num="27">" 'Tekel'--you have been weighed on scales and you have been found wanting.<note>Or "deficient"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="28">" 'Peres'--your kingdom has been divided and given to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Medes and Persians.'" </verse>
    <verse num="29">Then Belshazzar commanded, and they clothed Daniel <transChange type="added">with</transChange> purple and <transChange type="added">placed</transChange> a necklace of gold around his neck, and they made a proclamation concerning him that he would be <transChange type="added">the</transChange> third ruler <transChange type="added">in authority</transChange> in the kingdom.</verse>
    <verse num="30">{That same night}<note>Literally "In it, in the night"</note> Belshazzar, the Chaldean king, was killed.</verse>
    <verse num="31"><note>Daniel 5:31-6:28 in the English Bible is 6:1-29 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And Darius the Mede received the kingdom {when he was about sixty-two years old}.<note>Literally "when a son of sixty and two years"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">{It pleased Darius},<note>Literally "It was pleasant before Darius"</note> and he set up one hundred and twenty satraps over the kingdom, that they were {throughout the whole kingdom},<note>Literally "in all the kingdom"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">and over them <transChange type="added">were</transChange> three administrators, <transChange type="added">of</transChange> whom Daniel <transChange type="added">was</transChange> one, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> that these satraps were giving account to them, and the king would not be suffering loss.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then Daniel {began distinguishing himself}<note>Literally "was distinguishing himself"</note> above the administrators and the satraps {because}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> an exceptional spirit <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in him, and <transChange type="added">so</transChange> the king planned to appoint him over the whole kingdom.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then the <transChange type="added">other</transChange> administrators and satraps {began to seek}<note>Literally "were seeking"</note> to find <transChange type="added">a</transChange> pretext against Daniel {in connection with the kingdom},<note>Literally "from the side of the kingdom"</note> but they were not able to find any pretext and {corruption}<note>Literally "being corrupt"</note> {because}<note>Literally "all because that"</note> he was trustworthy, and no<note>Aramaic "any"</note> negligence or {corruption}<note>Literally "being corrupt"</note> {could be found in him}.<note>Literally "not could be found"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">Then these men {said},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">were</transChange> saying"</note> "We will not find any pretext<note>Or "basis for accusation"</note> against this Daniel unless we find it in connection with the law of his God." </verse>
    <verse num="6">So the administrators and the satraps conspired {with respect to}<note>Literally "on/upon"</note> the king and so they said to him, "Darius, O king, live {forever}!<note>Literally "to eternity"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">All of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> administrators of the kingdom, and the prefects, the satraps, the counselors and the governors took counsel <transChange type="added">and have</transChange> agreed to establish an edict of the king and to enforce a decree that {whoever}<note>Literally "all that"</note> will seek a prayer from any god or human except from you <transChange type="added">for</transChange> up to thirty days will be thrown into {the lion pit}.<note>Literally "pit of lions"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Now, O king, establish the edict and you must sign the document <transChange type="added">so</transChange> that <transChange type="added">it</transChange> cannot be changed, according to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> law of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Medes and Persians which cannot be revoked." </verse>
    <verse num="9">{So}<note>Literally "Like to before this"</note> the king, Darius, signed the writing and the interdict.<note>Or "the writing that is the interdict"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Now {when}<note>Literally "as that"</note> Daniel realized that the document was signed, he went to his house ({now he had windows in his upper room that were open}<note>Literally "and windows were open to him in his upper room"</note> toward Jerusalem), and three times {daily}<note>Literally "in the day"</note> he knelt on his knees and prayed and <transChange type="added">gave</transChange> praise before his God, {just as}<note>Literally "all because that"</note> he had been doing {previously}.<note>Literally "from before this"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Then these men came as a group and they found Daniel praying and pleading for mercy before his God.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Then they approached {and spoke with the king}<note>Literally "and saying before the king"</note> concerning the edict of the king, "{Did you not sign an edict}<note>Literally "Not an edict you signed?"</note> that any person who would seek <transChange type="added">anything</transChange> from any God or human within thirty days except from you, O king, would be thrown into {the lion pit}?"<note>Literally "pit of lions"</note> The king answered and said, "The matter <transChange type="added">as you have just stated</transChange> is certain according to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> law of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Medes and Persians which cannot be revoked." </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then {they responded}<note>Literally "they answered"</note> and said before the king, "Daniel, who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from {the exiles}<note>Literally "the sons of the exile"</note> of Judah,<note>Aramaic "Jehud"</note> {is not paying any attention}<note>Literally "not he sets <transChange type="added">his mind</transChange>"</note> to you, O king, or to the decree that you have signed, {and three times daily}<note>Literally "and three times on the day"</note> he says his prayer."</verse>
    <verse num="14">Then the king, when<note>Aramaic "as "</note> he heard that {report},<note>Literally "word"</note> he was extremely distressed over it; and {concerning Daniel}<note>Literally "upon Daniel"</note> {he was determined}<note>Literally "he set <transChange type="added">his</transChange> heart"</note> to rescue him. And until the setting of the sun he was making every effort to deliver him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Then these men came as <transChange type="added">a</transChange> group to the king and {said},<note>Literally "saying"</note> "Recall, O king, that <transChange type="added">with respect to</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> law of<note>Aramaic "to"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Medes and Persians that {any}<note>Literally "all/every"</note> decree or edict that the king establishes cannot be changed." </verse>
    <verse num="16">Then the king gave the command, and Daniel was brought in and they threw <transChange type="added">him</transChange> into {the lion pit}.<note>Literally "pit of lions"</note> {The king said}<note>Literally "The king answered and saying"</note> to Daniel, "Your God, whom you serve {faithfully},<note>Literally "in the loyalty"</note> may he rescue you!"</verse>
    <verse num="17">And a<note>Aramaic "one"</note> stone was brought and it was put on the entrance of the pit, and the king sealed it with his signet <transChange type="added">ring</transChange> and with the signet <transChange type="added">rings</transChange> of his lords,<note>Or "nobles"</note> so that nothing would be changed concerning Daniel.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then the king went to his palace and spent the night in fasting, and no food was brought in before him and his sleep fled from him. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Then the king got up at daybreak, at first light, and he went {in haste}<note>Literally "to hasten"</note> to {the lion pit}.<note>Literally "pit of lions"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">And {when he came near}<note>Literally "as coming near him"</note> to the pit, he cried out to Daniel with <transChange type="added">a</transChange> distressed voice, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the king {spoke}<note>Literally "answered"</note> and said to Daniel, "O Daniel, servant of the living God, your God whom you serve faithfully, was he able to rescue you from the lions?"</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then Daniel spoke to<note>Aramaic "with"</note> the king, "O king, live {forever}!<note>Literally "unto endless ages"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">My God sent his angel and he shut the mouth of the lions and they did not<note>Aramaic "would not"</note> hurt me, {because}<note>Literally "all of because that"</note> before him {I was found}<note>Literally "it was found for me"</note> blameless, and also before you, O king, I have not done <transChange type="added">any</transChange> wrong." </verse>
    <verse num="23">Then the king was exceedingly glad over it<note>That is, the situation</note> and commanded <transChange type="added">that</transChange> Daniel be lifted up from the pit; and <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was not any wound found on him, because he had trusted in his God.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The king then commanded, and these men were brought {who had accused Daniel},<note>Literally "they ate his pieces of Daniel"</note> and they threw them and their children and their wives into {the lion pit},<note>Literally "pit of lions"</note> and they had not reached the floor of the pit {before}<note>Literally "until that"</note> the lions had overpowered them and they had crushed all of their bones. </verse>
    <verse num="25">Then Darius the king wrote to all the people, the nations, and the languages living in the whole earth, "May your prosperity become great!</verse>
    <verse num="26">{I make a decree}<note>Literally "From before me is put forth a decree"</note> that in all the dominion of my kingdom <transChange type="added">people</transChange> will be trembling and fearing before the God of Daniel, for he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the living God and endures {forever}<note>Literally "to eternity/endless ages"</note> and his<note>Literally "and whose"</note> kingdom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one that will not be destroyed and his {dominion has no end}.<note>Literally "dominion his to the end"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27"><transChange type="added">He is</transChange> rescuing, delivering, and working signs and wonders in the heavens and on earth, for he <transChange type="added">has</transChange> rescued Daniel from the {power}<note>Literally "hand"</note> of the lions."</verse>
    <verse num="28">So this Daniel prospered during the kingdom of Darius and during the kingdom of Cyrus the Persian. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">In the first year of Belshazzar the king of Babylon, Daniel saw a dream and visions<note>Or "the visions"</note> of his head <transChange type="added">as he lay</transChange> on his bed; then he wrote down the dream <transChange type="added">and</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> {summary}<note>Literally "head"</note> of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> words {as follows}:<note>Literally "saying"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Daniel {explained}<note>Literally "answered"</note> and said, "I was looking in my vision in the night, and look, the four winds of heaven were stirring <transChange type="added">up</transChange> the great sea.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And four great beasts <transChange type="added">were</transChange> coming up from the sea, differing {from one another}.<note>Literally "this from this"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">The first <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like <transChange type="added">a</transChange> lion and {had}<note>Literally "for him/it"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wings of an eagle. I was watching until its wings were plucked off, and it was lifted up from the earth and it was raised on <transChange type="added">its</transChange> feet like a human, and a human heart was given to it.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And look, another beast, a second one, looking like a bear. And it was raised up on one side and three tusks<note>Or "ribs"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in its mouth between its teeth, and so {it was told},<note>Literally "they were saying"</note> "Arise, eat much flesh!"</verse>
    <verse num="6">After this I was watching and look, another <transChange type="added">beast</transChange> like a leopard; {it had four wings}<note>Literally "and <transChange type="added">there were</transChange> to it four wings"</note> of a bird on its back, and {the beast had}<note>Literally "to the beast"</note> four heads, and dominion was given to it.</verse>
    <verse num="7">After this in the visions of the night I was looking and there was a fourth beast, terrifying and frightful and exceedingly strong, and {it had}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">were</transChange> to it"</note> {great iron teeth},<note>Literally "teeth of iron for it great"</note> <transChange type="added">and it was</transChange> devouring and crushing, and it stamped the remainder<note>Or "residue"</note> with its feet; and it was different from all <transChange type="added">the other</transChange> beasts {that preceded it}<note>Literally "that preceding her/it"</note> {and it had ten horns}.<note>Literally "and ten horns for her/it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">I was considering the horns, and look, another little horn came up {among}<note>Literally "between"</note> them, and three of the earlier horns {were rooted out}<note>Literally "dehorned"</note> from before it, and there were eyes like the eyes of <transChange type="added">a</transChange> human<note>Or "humankind"</note> in this horn and <transChange type="added">also</transChange> a mouth <transChange type="added">that was</transChange> speaking boastfully. </verse>
    <verse num="9">"{I continued watching}<note>Literally "I was watching"</note> until thrones were placed and an Ancient of Days sat; his clothing <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like white snow and the hair of his head <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like pure wool and his throne <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a flame<note>Or "ablaze with"</note> of fire and its wheels<note>Aramaic "wheel"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> burning fire.</verse>
    <verse num="10">A stream of fire issued forth and flowed {from his presence};<note>Literally "from before him"</note> thousands <transChange type="added">upon</transChange> thousands served him and ten thousand <transChange type="added">upon</transChange> ten thousand stood before him. The judge sat, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> books were opened. </verse>
    <verse num="11">"{I continued watching}<note>Literally "I was watching"</note> then<note>Aramaic "in then"</note> because of the noise of the boastful words of the horn <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> speaking; {I continued watching}<note>Literally "I was watching"</note> until the beast was slain and its body was destroyed, and it was given <transChange type="added">over</transChange> to burning with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And <transChange type="added">as for</transChange> the remainder of the beasts, {their dominion was taken away},<note>Literally "they took away their dominion"</note> but a prolongation {of their life}<note>Literally "in life"</note> was given to them for a season and a time. </verse>
    <verse num="13">"{I continued watching}<note>Literally "I was watching"</note> in the visions of the night, and look, with the clouds of heaven <transChange type="added">one</transChange> like a son of man<note>Or "mortal," or "son of humankind"</note> was coming, and he came to the Ancient of Days, and {was presented}<note>Literally "they presented him"</note> before him.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And to him was given dominion and glory and kingship that<note>Aramaic "and"</note> all the peoples, the nations, and languages <transChange type="added">would</transChange> serve him; his dominion <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a dominion {without end}<note>Literally "of eternity"</note> that will not cease, and his kingdom <transChange type="added">is one</transChange> that will not be destroyed. </verse>
    <verse num="15">"{As for me, Daniel},<note>Literally "I Daniel"</note> my spirit was troubled {within me},<note>Literally "in the midst of sheath"</note> and the visions of my head terrified me.</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">So</transChange> I approached one of the attendants and I asked him<note>Aramaic "from him"</note> <transChange type="added">about</transChange> the truth concerning all this; and he told me<note>Aramaic "to me"</note> <transChange type="added">that</transChange> he would make known to me the explanation of the matter.</verse>
    <verse num="17">'These great beasts which are four <transChange type="added">in number</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> four kings <transChange type="added">who</transChange> will arise from the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But the holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> of the Most High will receive the kingdom, and they will take possession of the kingdom forever, {forever and ever}.'<note>Literally "forever and to forever"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="19">"Then I desired to make certain concerning the fourth beast that was different from {all the others}<note>Literally "all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> them"</note>--exceedingly terrifying, with its iron teeth and its claws of bronze; it devoured and crushed <transChange type="added">and</transChange> stamped the remainder with its feet--</verse>
    <verse num="20">and concerning the horns that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on its head, and <transChange type="added">concerning</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> other <transChange type="added">horn</transChange> that came up and {before which three horns fell},<note>Literally "and fell from before it three"</note> and this horn {had eyes}<note>Literally "and eyes to it"</note> and <transChange type="added">a</transChange> mouth speaking {boastfully},<note>Literally "abundantly"</note> and its appearance <transChange type="added">was</transChange> larger than its companions.</verse>
    <verse num="21">{I continued watching},<note>Literally "I was watching"</note> and this horn made war with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> and it prevailed over them,</verse>
    <verse num="22">until the Ancient of Days came and gave judgment to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Most High; and the time arrived and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> took possession of the kingdom. </verse>
    <verse num="23">"And he said, 'The fourth beast <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the fourth kingdom <transChange type="added">that</transChange> will be on the earth that will be different from all the <transChange type="added">other</transChange> kingdoms, and it will devour the whole earth and it will trample it and it will crush it.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And <transChange type="added">as for</transChange> the ten horns <transChange type="added">coming</transChange> from it, <transChange type="added">from</transChange> this kingdom<note>Or "the kingdom"</note> ten kings will arise, and another will arise after them. And he will be different from the earlier <transChange type="added">ones</transChange>, and he will subdue three kings.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And he will speak words against the Most High, and he will wear out <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> of the Most High, and he will attempt to change times and law, and they will be given into his hand for a time and two times and half a time.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then the court will sit, and his dominion will be removed,<note>Or "taken away"</note> to be eradicated and to be destroyed {totally}.<note>Literally "until the end"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">And the kingdom and the dominion and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven will be given to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nation of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones<note>Or "saints"</note> of the Most High; his kingdom {is an everlasting kingdom},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">is</transChange> a kingdom of eternity"</note> and all the dominions will serve and obey him.' </verse>
    <verse num="28">{This is the end of the account}.<note>Literally "Up to here <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the end of the account"</note> {As for me, Daniel}<note>Literally "I Daniel"</note>--my thoughts terrified me greatly and my face changed over me, but I kept the matter in my heart."<note>Or "to myself"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">In the third year <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the kingdom of Belshazzar the king, a vision appeared {to me, Daniel},<note>Literally "I Daniel"</note> after the one that appeared to me {previously}.<note>Literally "in the beginning"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">And I saw in the vision, {and when I saw},<note>Literally "and it was at my seeing"</note> I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Susa, the citadel that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in the province of Elam. And I saw in the vision, and {I myself}<note>Literally "I, I was"</note> was at the stream of Ulai.<note>Or "Ulai Canal" (NASB); "stream of the Ulai" (NEB)</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And I lifted up my eyes and I saw, and look! A ram<note>Hebrew "One ram"</note> standing {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the stream, and {it had}<note>Literally "for it"</note> two horns, and the horns <transChange type="added">were</transChange> long, but the one <transChange type="added">was</transChange> longer than the second, and the longer <transChange type="added">one</transChange> came up {after the other one}.<note>Literally "in the behind of the other"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">I saw the ram charging westward and northward and southward, and {none of the beasts stood before it},<note>Literally "all <transChange type="added">the</transChange> beasts not they withstood to the face of him"</note> and there was no rescuing from {its power},<note>Literally "its hand"</note> and it did {what it wanted}<note>Literally "according to its will"</note> and it became strong.<note>Or "it/he magnified itself/himself"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="5">And I was considering <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, and look, a he-goat coming from the west across the face of the whole earth, and <transChange type="added">it</transChange> was not touching the ground;<note>Or "earth," or "land"</note> and the he-goat <transChange type="added">had</transChange> {a conspicuous horn}<note>Literally "a horn of vision"</note> between its eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then it came toward the ram {that had the two horns}<note>Literally "the owner of the two horns"</note> that I saw standing {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> the stream, and it ran at it with<note>Or "in"</note> the rage of its power.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And I saw it approaching the ram and it was furious at it, and it struck the ram, and it broke its two horns, and {there was not strength in the ram to stand before him},<note>Literally "and not was strength in the ram to withstand to the face of him"</note> and he threw it down to the ground and trampled it, {and there was no one who could rescue the ram}<note>Literally "and not he/it was one rescuing"</note> from its power.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And the he-goat grew {exceedingly great},<note>Literally "until much"</note> and {at the height of its power}<note>Literally "and at his being powerful"</note> the great horn was broken, and four conspicuous horns<note>LXX reads "others" here for "conspicuous." The words in Hebrew can be confused for each other</note> came up in place of it toward the four winds of heaven. </verse>
    <verse num="9">{And from one of them}<note>Literally "And from the one from them"</note> came forth <transChange type="added">a</transChange> horn, {a little one},<note>Literally "one from little"</note> and it grew exceedingly<note>Or "pre-eminently"</note> toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the beautiful land.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And it grew up to the host of heaven, and it threw down to the ground some of the host and some of the stars and trampled them.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Even against the prince of the hosts it acted arrogantly and took away from him the regular burnt offering, and the place of his sanctuary was overthrown.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And on account of transgression, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> host was given over <transChange type="added">to the horn</transChange> in addition to the regular burnt offering. And it cast down truth to the ground, and it {acted},<note>Literally "did"</note> and it had success. </verse>
    <verse num="13">And I heard a certain holy one speaking, and a certain other holy one said to the specific one {who was speaking},<note>Literally "the <transChange type="added">one</transChange> speaking"</note> "{For how long}<note>Literally "Until when"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the vision <transChange type="added">concerning</transChange> the regular burnt offering, and the transgression <transChange type="added">that</transChange> makes desolate, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> giving over <transChange type="added">of the</transChange> sanctuary and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> host to trampling?"</verse>
    <verse num="14">And he said to me, "For two thousand three hundred evenings and mornings, then <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sanctuary will be restored." </verse>
    <verse num="15">{And then}<note>Literally "And it happened"</note> when I, Daniel, saw the vision, and I was seeking understanding, there was <transChange type="added">one</transChange> standing before me with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appearance of a man.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And I heard <transChange type="added">the</transChange> voice of a human at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Ulai, and he called and said, "Gabriel, <transChange type="added">make</transChange> this <transChange type="added">man</transChange> understand the vision."</verse>
    <verse num="17">And he came beside {where I was standing},<note>Literally "my standing"</note> and {when he came}<note>Literally "at his coming"</note> I became terrified and I fell prostrate on my face. And he said to me, "Understand, son of man,<note>Or "mortal," or "son of humankind"</note> that the vision <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end." </verse>
    <verse num="18">And {when he spoke}<note>Literally "at his speaking"</note> with me I fell into a trance with my face to the ground, and he touched me and made me stand on by feet.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And he said, "Look, I am making known to you what will happen in the period of wrath,<note>Or "the wrath"</note> for <transChange type="added">it refers</transChange> to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appointed time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end. </verse>
    <verse num="20">"The ram that you saw {who had two horns}<note>Literally "the owner of the two horns"</note> <transChange type="added">represents</transChange> the kings of Media and Persia. </verse>
    <verse num="21">"And the hairy he-goat <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the {kingdom}<note>Literally "king"</note> of Greece, and the great horn that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> between his eyes--he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the first king.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And the <transChange type="added">horn</transChange> <transChange type="added">that</transChange> was broken, and <transChange type="added">then</transChange> there arose four <transChange type="added">horns</transChange> in place of it--<transChange type="added">these are</transChange> four kingdoms <transChange type="added">that</transChange> will arise from <transChange type="added">his</transChange> nation, but not with his power.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And at the end of their kingdom, when the transgressions are completed, a king will arise, fierce in countenance and skilled in riddles.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And his power will grow, but not by his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> power, and he will cause fearful destruction, and he will succeed and {he will act},<note>Literally "he will do"</note> and he will destroy <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mighty and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> people of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> holy ones.<note>Or "saints"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">And by his planning<note>Or "cunning"</note> he will make a success of deceit by<note>Hebrew "in"</note> his hand, and in his {mind}<note>Literally "heart"</note> he will {boast},<note>Literally "magnify himself"</note> and in <transChange type="added">their</transChange> ease he will destroy many, and <transChange type="added">even</transChange> against <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prince of princes he will rise up, and he will be broken, <transChange type="added">but</transChange> not by human hands.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And the vision of the evening and the morning that has been {described},<note>Literally "told"</note> it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> true; and you, seal <transChange type="added">up</transChange> the vision, for {it refers to many days to come}."<note>Literally "for to days many"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="27">And I, Daniel, was overcome, and I became ill for <transChange type="added">some</transChange> days, and I {performed}<note>Literally "did"</note> the business of the king, and I was dismayed over the vision and {I did not understand it}.<note>Literally "there was not understanding"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">In <transChange type="added">the</transChange> first year <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Darius, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> son of Ahasuerus,<note>That is, Xerxes</note> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> offspring of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Medes, who became king over <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Chaldeans--</verse>
    <verse num="2">in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> first year <transChange type="added">of</transChange> his kingship I, Daniel, observed in the scrolls the number of the years that it was <transChange type="added">that were</transChange> to be fulfilled <transChange type="added">according to</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> word of Yahweh to Jeremiah the prophet for the devastation of Jerusalem--seventy years. </verse>
    <verse num="3">Then I turned my face to the Lord God to seek <transChange type="added">him</transChange> <transChange type="added">by</transChange> prayer and pleas for mercy,<note>Or "supplications"</note> in fasting and <transChange type="added">in</transChange> sackcloth and ashes.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And I prayed to Yahweh my God, and I made confession and I said, "O Lord, the great and awesome God, keeping the covenant and loyal love with <transChange type="added">those who</transChange> love him and with <transChange type="added">those who</transChange> keep his commandments,</verse>
    <verse num="5">we have sinned and we have done wrong and we acted wickedly and we rebelled and <transChange type="added">have been</transChange> turning aside from your commandments and from your ordinances.</verse>
    <verse num="6">We have not listened to your servants the prophets, who spoke in your name to our kings, our princes and our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> and to all the people of the land. </verse>
    <verse num="7">"{Righteousness belongs to you, O Lord},<note>Literally "for you Lord the righteousness"</note> and on us <transChange type="added">is</transChange> open shame, <transChange type="added">just</transChange> as <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> this day to the people of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to all Israel, {those who are near and those who are far off}<note>Literally "those near and those far"</note> in all the lands <transChange type="added">to</transChange> which you have driven them,<note>Hebrew "<transChange type="added">to</transChange> which you have driven them there"</note> because of their infidelity which they displayed against you.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Yahweh, on us <transChange type="added">is</transChange> open shame, on our kings, on our princes, and on our ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> because we have sinned against you.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{Compassion and forgiveness belong to the Lord, our God},<note>Literally "to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Lord our God the compassion and the forgiveness"</note> for we have rebelled against him,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and we have not listened to the voice of Yahweh our God, by following his law {which he placed before us}<note>Literally "which he gave to the face of us"</note> by <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hand of his servants the prophets. </verse>
    <verse num="11">"And all Israel transgressed your law and turned aside <transChange type="added">so as</transChange> not to listen to your voice, and <transChange type="added">so</transChange> the curse and the oath which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> written in the law of Moses, the servant of God, has been poured out upon us, because we have sinned against him.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And <transChange type="added">so</transChange> he <transChange type="added">has</transChange> carried out his words which he spoke against us and against our rulers who ruled us, to bring upon us <transChange type="added">a</transChange> great calamity which was not done under all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> heaven as it was done in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Just as <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> written in the law of Moses, all of this calamity has come upon us, and {we have not implored}<note>Literally "we not implored"</note> the face of Yahweh our God <transChange type="added">so as</transChange> to turn from our iniquities and to attend closely to your faithfulness.<note>Or "truth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">So Yahweh <transChange type="added">has</transChange> kept watch over the<note>Or "his"</note> calamity, and <transChange type="added">now</transChange> he <transChange type="added">has</transChange> brought it upon us. Indeed, Yahweh our God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> righteous concerning all his works<note>Or "acts"</note> that he has done, but we have not listened to his voice. </verse>
    <verse num="15">"And now, Lord our God, who have brought your people out from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> land of Egypt with a strong hand, and you <transChange type="added">have</transChange> made for yourself a name <transChange type="added">until</transChange> this day--we have sinned, we have acted wickedly.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Lord, according to all your righteousness, please let your anger and your rage turn away from your city Jerusalem, {your holy mountain},<note>Literally "the mountain of your holiness"</note> because through our sins and through the iniquities of our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> Jerusalem and your people have become an object of mockery among all of our neighbors. </verse>
    <verse num="17">"And now, listen to the prayer of your servant and to his pleas for mercy. Shine<note>Or "let shine" or "cause to shine"</note> your face upon your desolate sanctuary {for your sake, O Lord}.<note>Literally "for the sake of the Lord"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">Incline your ear, my God, and listen; open your eyes and look at our desolation and the city that is called <transChange type="added">by</transChange> your name, for we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not presenting our pleas for mercy {before you}<note>Literally "to the face of you"</note> because of our righteousness, but <transChange type="added">rather</transChange> because of your great compassion.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Lord, listen! Lord, forgive! Lord, pay heed and act! You must not delay {for your sake},<note>Literally "for the sake of you"</note> my God; because {your city and your people are called by your name}."<note>Literally "your name is called over your city and over your people"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="20">Now I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> still speaking and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my plea {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> Yahweh my God, on behalf {of the holy mountain of my God}.<note>Literally "the mountain of the holiness of my God"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">And I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> still speaking in prayer, and the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision {previously},<note>Literally "in the beginning"</note> {in my weariness touched me}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">my</transChange> being wearied, touching me"</note> at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> evening offering.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And he instructed <transChange type="added">me</transChange> and he spoke with me and he said, "Daniel I have now come out<note>Or "forth"</note> to teach you understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="23">At the beginning of your pleas for mercy, a word went out, and <transChange type="added">now</transChange> I have come to declare<note>Or "deliver"</note> <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, for you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> highly esteemed, and <transChange type="added">so</transChange> consider the word and understand the vision. </verse>
    <verse num="24">"Seventy weeks is decreed for your people and {for your holy city},<note>Literally "for <transChange type="added">the</transChange> city of your holiness"</note> to put an end to the transgression and to seal <transChange type="added">up</transChange> sin<note>Or "to make an end to sin"</note> and to make atonement for guilt and to bring <transChange type="added">in</transChange> everlasting righteousness and to seal vision and prophet and to anoint {the most holy place}.<note>Literally "the holy place of holy places"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">And you must know and you must understand<note>Or "so you are to know and discern" (NASB), or "know then and understand" (e.g. NEB)</note> <transChange type="added">that</transChange> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of the going out of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> word to restore and build Jerusalem until <transChange type="added">an</transChange> anointed<note>Or "messiah"</note> <transChange type="added">one</transChange>--<transChange type="added">a</transChange> leader--<transChange type="added">will be</transChange> {seven weeks and sixty-two weeks};<note>Literally "weeks seven and weeks sixty and two"</note> it will be restored and will be built <transChange type="added">with</transChange> streets and <transChange type="added">a</transChange> moat, but {in a time of oppression}.<note>Literally "in distress/oppression of the times/time"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="26">"And after the sixty and two weeks an anointed one<note>Or "messiah"</note> shall be cut off, and {he shall have nothing},<note>Literally "there is not for him"</note> and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> people of the coming leader will destroy the city and the sanctuary,<note>Or "holy place"</note> and its end <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> with the flood and <transChange type="added">on</transChange> to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end <transChange type="added">there shall be</transChange> war; <transChange type="added">these</transChange> desolations are determined.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And he will make a strong covenant with the many <transChange type="added">for</transChange> one week, but <transChange type="added">in</transChange> half of the week he will let cease sacrifice and offering {and in its place}<note>Literally "and on a wing of"</note> a desolating abomination <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> even until {the determined complete destruction}<note>Literally "a complete destruction and being determined"</note> is poured out on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> desolator." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">In the third year of Cyrus <transChange type="added">the</transChange> king of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Persians, a word<note>Or "matter," or "message"</note> was revealed to Daniel, who was called <transChange type="added">by</transChange> his name Belteshazzar, and the word<note>Or "matter," or "message"</note> <transChange type="added">was</transChange> reliable and <transChange type="added">it concerned</transChange> a great tribulation,<note>Or "conflict"</note> and he understood the word<note>Or "matter," or "message"</note> and {he received understanding}.<note>Literally "and understanding to him"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="2">In those days, I, Daniel, I <transChange type="added">myself</transChange><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> was <transChange type="added">in</transChange> mourning {for three whole weeks}.<note>Literally "three weeks <transChange type="added">of</transChange> days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">I had not eaten <transChange type="added">any</transChange> choice food, and meat and wine did not enter my mouth, and {I did not use any ointment}<note>Literally "I have not anointed at all"</note> {until the end of three whole weeks}.<note>Literally "until being full/complete three weeks <transChange type="added">of</transChange> days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And <transChange type="added">then</transChange> on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-fourth day of the first month, I <transChange type="added">myself</transChange><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> was on the bank of the great river; that is, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Tigris.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And I lifted up my eyes and I saw,<note>Or "looked"</note> and there was a man, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> he was dressed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> linen, and his waist was girded with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> gold of Uphaz.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Now his body <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like turquoise,<note>Or "yellow jasper" or other gold-colored stones; the exact identity of ancient precious stones is difficult</note> and his face <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appearance of lightning, and his eyes <transChange type="added">were</transChange> like torches of fire, and his arms and his legs <transChange type="added">were</transChange> like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> gleam of polished bronze, and the sound of his words <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sound of a multitude.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And I saw, I, Daniel {alone},<note>Literally "to alone me"</note> the vision; and the people who were with me {did not see}<note>Literally "not they saw"</note> the vision; nevertheless, a great trembling fell upon them and they fled <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to hide themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And I myself, Daniel, alone saw this great vision, and <transChange type="added">as a result</transChange> {no strength was left in me}<note>Literally "not was left in me strength"</note> and {my complexion grew deathly pale},<note>Literally "and complexion my changed over me to destruction"</note> and I did not retain any strength.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And I heard the sound of his words, and {when I heard}<note>Literally "at my hearing"</note> the sound of his words I myself <transChange type="added">began</transChange> falling into a trance on my face, {with my face to the ground}.<note>Literally "and my face toward the ground"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="10">And look, a hand touched me and it roused me to my knees<note>Hebrew "on my knees"</note> and the palms<note>Hebrew "palm"</note> of my hands.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And he said to me, "Daniel, <transChange type="added">a</transChange> man beloved, pay attention to the words that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> speaking to you and {stand upright where you are},<note>Literally "stand on your position"</note> for I have now been sent to you." And {while he was speaking}<note>Literally "at his speaking"</note> with me this word,<note>Or "matter," or "message"</note> I stood up trembling.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And he said to me, "You must not fear, Daniel, for from the first day that you set your heart to understand and to humble yourself {before}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> your God, your words were heard, and I <transChange type="added">myself</transChange><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> have come because of your words.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prince of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom of Persia stood {before me}<note>Literally "to front of me"</note> <transChange type="added">for</transChange> twenty-one days. And look,<note>Or "finally"</note> Michael, one of the chief princes, came to assist me, and I left <transChange type="added">him</transChange> there beside <transChange type="added">the</transChange> king of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Persians.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And I have come<note>Hebrew "I came"</note> to instruct you about what<note>Hebrew "that"</note> will happen to your people {in the future},<note>Literally "at the end of the days"</note> for <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> a further vision <transChange type="added">here</transChange> {for the future}.<note>Literally "for the days"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="15">And while he was speaking with me according to these words, I turned my face toward the ground and I was speechless.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Then look, there was {one in the form of a human};<note>Literally "as <transChange type="added">the</transChange> likeness of <transChange type="added">a</transChange> son of man"</note> he touched my lips and I opened my mouth and I spoke and I said to the <transChange type="added">one</transChange> standing {before me},<note>Literally "to opposite me"</note> "My lord, because of the vision my anxieties fell upon me and I <transChange type="added">have</transChange> not retained <transChange type="added">my</transChange> strength.</verse>
    <verse num="17">So {how am I, a servant of my lord}<note>Literally "how is <transChange type="added">he</transChange> able a servant <transChange type="added">of</transChange> my lord this"</note> to speak with {you, my lord},<note>Literally "with my lord this"</note> and I {just now}<note>Literally "from now"</note> {have no strength in me}?"<note>Literally "not it remains in me strength"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="18">And {he again touched}<note>Literally "he added to and touched"</note> me, {the one in the form of a human},<note>Literally "like vision of a man"</note> and he strengthened me.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And he said, "You must not fear, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> beloved man. {Peace be to you};<note>Literally "Peace to/for you"</note> be strong and be courageous!" And {when he spoke}<note>Literally "at his speaking"</note> with me, I was strengthened and I said, "Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me."</verse>
    <verse num="20">Then he asked, "Do you know why I have come to you? And now I return to fight against the prince of Persia and I <transChange type="added">myself</transChange><note>This is an emphatic use of the first person personal pronoun</note> <transChange type="added">am</transChange> going, and look,<note>Or "listen"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prince of Javan<note>That is, Greece</note> will come.</verse>
    <verse num="21">However, I will tell you {what is inscribed}<note>Literally "the being inscribed"</note> in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> book of truth, and there is not one <transChange type="added">who</transChange> contends with me against these <transChange type="added">beings</transChange> {except}<note>Literally "but if"</note> Michael, your prince." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">"And I, in the first year of Darius the Mede, {I stood}<note>Literally "my standing"</note> as a support and as a protection for him. </verse>
    <verse num="2">And now I will reveal <transChange type="added">the</transChange> truth to you. Look! Still three kings will arise in Persia, and the fourth will get abundance <transChange type="added">and</transChange> great wealth, <transChange type="added">even</transChange> more than all <transChange type="added">of them</transChange>, and {when he becomes strong}<note>Literally "at his strength"</note> through his wealth, <transChange type="added">then</transChange> he will stir up {everyone}<note>Literally "the all"</note> against <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom of Javan.<note>That is, Greece</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And a mighty king will arise, and he will rule <transChange type="added">with</transChange> great dominion, and he will do {as he pleases}.<note>Literally "as his pleasure"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">But {as he rises in power},<note>Literally "as his rising/to rise"</note> his kingdom will be divided toward the four winds of heaven, but not to his posterity, and not according to his dominion <transChange type="added">by</transChange> which he ruled, for his kingdom will be uprooted and <transChange type="added">be given</transChange> {to others besides them}.<note>Literally "to others from to alone these"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="5">"Then the king of the south will grow strong and <transChange type="added">also</transChange> {one of his officials},<note>Literally "from among his officials"</note> and he will grow stronger {than him}<note>Literally "over him"</note> and he will rule {a dominion greater than his dominion}.<note>Literally "a dominion great dominion his"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">And at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end of <transChange type="added">some</transChange> years they will make an alliance, and the daughter of the king of the south will come to the king of the north to make a peace treaty, but {she will not retain her position of power},<note>Literally "she will not retain the power of her arm"</note> and his offspring<note>Or "power"</note> will not endure, and she will be given up, she and her attendants and her child supporting her, in those times.<note>Hebrew "in the times"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">And a branch from her roots<note>That is, a member of her family</note> will rise up <transChange type="added">in</transChange> his place, and he will come against the army and he will enter the stronghold of the king of the north and he will take action against them and he will prevail.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And also their gods with their idols <transChange type="added">and</transChange> with the {precious vessels},<note>Literally "vessels of their desire"</note> silver and gold he will take to Egypt into captivity, and <transChange type="added">for</transChange> years {he will leave the king of the north alone}.<note>Literally "he will stand back from the king of the north"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">And <transChange type="added">then</transChange> he<note>That is, the king of the north</note> will come into the kingdom of the king of the south, but he will return to his land. </verse>
    <verse num="10">"But his sons will wage war and they will gather a multitude of great forces and {he will advance with great force},<note>Literally "he will come, to come"</note> and he will overflow <transChange type="added">like a flood</transChange> and he will pass through and he will return, and they will wage war up to his fortress.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And the king of the south will become furious, and he will go and he will battle against him, against the king of the north; and he will muster a great multitude, and the multitude will be given into his hand.</verse>
    <verse num="12">When the multitude is carried off, his heart will be exalted and he will overthrow {tens of thousands},<note>Literally "myriads"</note> but he will not prevail.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the king of the north will again raise a multitude, greater than the former, and {at the end of some years}<note>Literally "to the end of the times years"</note> he will surely come with <transChange type="added">a</transChange> great army and with great supplies.<note>Or "resources"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="14">"And in these times many will rise <transChange type="added">up</transChange> against the king of the south, and {the violent ones of your people}<note>Literally "the sons of the lawless ones of your people"</note> will lift themselves {to fulfill}<note>Literally "to cause to stand"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> vision, but they will fall.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the king of the north will come, and he will throw up siege ramps<note>Hebrew "ramp"</note> and capture a city of fortifications and the military forces of the south and {his choice troops}<note>Literally "the army of his chosen troops"</note> will not stand, for<note>Hebrew "and"</note> there is no strength <transChange type="added">left</transChange> to resist.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And the <transChange type="added">one</transChange> coming to him will act {according to}<note>Literally "as"</note> his pleasure, and there is no <transChange type="added">one who</transChange> {will stand}<note>Literally "standing"</note> {before him},<note>Literally "to the face of him"</note> and he will stand in {the beautiful land}<note>Literally "in the land of the beauty"</note> and complete destruction <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> in his power.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And he will set his face to come with the authority of his whole kingdom and will form an agreement;<note>Or "treaty," or "peace proposal"; the Hebrew is difficult</note> and he will {act},<note>Literally "do, perform"</note> and the daughter of women he will give to him to destroy it,<note>Or "her"</note> but <transChange type="added">the ploy</transChange> will not succeed {and she will not support him}.<note>Literally "and not for him will she be"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">And he will turn his face to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> coastlands, and he will capture many, but<note>Hebrew "and"</note> a commander will end his insults to him {so that instead his insults will turn back upon him}.<note>Literally "so that not his insults he will return against him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And he will turn back his face toward<note>Hebrew "to"</note> the strongholds of his land, but he will stumble and he will fall and will not be found. </verse>
    <verse num="20">"Then in his place will arise <transChange type="added">one</transChange> sending an official <transChange type="added">throughout</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> glory<note>Or "splendor"</note> of <transChange type="added">his</transChange> kingdom, and {in a few days}<note>Literally "in some days"</note> he will be broken, but not in anger and not in battle.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And in his place a despicable person will arise on whom<note>Hebrew "him"</note> they have not conferred the majesty of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom, and he will come in {without warning}<note>Literally "in ease"</note> and he will seize <transChange type="added">the</transChange> kingdom by deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And {before him}<note>Literally "to the face of him"</note> {mighty military forces}<note>Literally "military forces of the flood"</note> will be utterly swept away, and they will be broken, and also <transChange type="added">the</transChange> leader of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> covenant.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And after an alliance <transChange type="added">is made</transChange> with him, he will act deceitfully, and he will rise and he will become powerful with few people <transChange type="added">backing him</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="24">In <transChange type="added">a time of</transChange> ease and in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rich parts of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> province, he will come and he will do what {his predecessors}<note>Literally "his fathers and the father of his fathers"</note> did not do; he will distribute plunder and spoil and possessions to them, and he will devise his plans against fortifications, but <transChange type="added">only</transChange> {for a time}.<note>Literally "until time"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">And he will stir up his power and his heart against the king of the south and {with a much greater and stronger army};<note>Literally "with an army great and numerous exceedingly"</note> but he will not succeed, for they will devise plans against him.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And those who eat of his royal rations will break him and his army will be overwhelmed, and many will fall, slain.</verse>
    <verse num="27">{And two of the kings}<note>Literally "And two of them, the kings"</note> {will bend their hearts}<note>Literally "their heart"</note> to evil. And at the {same table}<note>Literally "one table"</note> they will speak lies, but <transChange type="added">what is discussed</transChange> will not succeed, for still an end <transChange type="added">is coming</transChange> at the appointed time.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Then he will return to his land with many possessions, but his heart <transChange type="added">will be set</transChange> against {the holy covenant},<note>Literally "covenant of holiness"</note> and he will take action and he will return to his land. </verse>
    <verse num="29">"At the appointed time he will return and he will come into the south, but it will not be {as it was before}.<note>Literally "as the former and as the last"</note></verse>
    <verse num="30">And <transChange type="added">the</transChange> ships of Kittim will come against him, and he will lose heart, and he will turn back, and he will be enraged {against the holy covenant},<note>Literally "against the covenant of holiness"</note> and he will take action, and he will turn back, and he will pay attention to <transChange type="added">those who</transChange> forsake {the holy covenant}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> covenant of holiness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">And military forces from him {will occupy}<note>Literally "will stand forth"</note> and will profane<note>Or "desecrate"</note> the {sanctuary stronghold},<note>Literally "the sanctuary, the stronghold"</note> and they will abolish the regular burnt offering, and they will set up the abomination that causes desolation. </verse>
    <verse num="32">"And those who violate <transChange type="added">the</transChange> covenant he will seduce with flattery, but the persons who know their God<note>Hebrew "the ones who know his God"</note> will stand firm and will take action.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And those who have insight {will instruct}<note>Literally "make understand"</note> the many, but they will fall by sword and by flame, by captivity and by plunder {for some time}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">during</transChange> days"</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">And {when they fall}<note>Literally "in/at their falling"</note> they will receive little help, and many will join with them <transChange type="added">in</transChange> hypocrisy.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And <transChange type="added">even</transChange> some of those {who have insight}<note>Literally "the <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> who produce insight"</note> will fall<note>Or "stumble"</note> <transChange type="added">in order for</transChange> them to be refined by it, and to be purified and cleansed until the time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end, for the appointed time <transChange type="added">is</transChange> still to come. </verse>
    <verse num="36">"Then the king will do {as he pleases},<note>Literally "as his pleasure"</note> and he will exalt himself and will consider himself above any god, and he will speak horrendous things {against}<note>Literally "over"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> God of gods, yet he will succeed until <transChange type="added">the period</transChange> of anger is finished, for <transChange type="added">what</transChange> is determined will be done.</verse>
    <verse num="37">He will not pay respect to the gods of his ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> or to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> darling of women, and not to any god will he pay respect, for he will consider himself great over all <transChange type="added">gods</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="38">But {instead}<note>Literally "in his place"</note> he will honor the god of fortresses, a god whom his ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> did not know. He will honor <transChange type="added">him</transChange> with gold, and with silver, and with precious stones<note>Hebrew "precious stone"</note> and with costly gifts.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And he will deal with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> {fortified strongholds}<note>Literally "the fortifications of strongholds"</note> with <transChange type="added">the help of</transChange> {a foreign god};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> god of a foreign land"</note> and he will increase wealth for whoever will acknowledge <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, and he will cause them to rule<note>Or "appoint"</note> over the many, and he will distribute land for a price. </verse>
    <verse num="40">"And at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end the king of the south will attack him, and the king of the north will storm against him with chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> and with horsemen and with many ships, and he will advance against the countries and {he will sweep through like a flood}.<note>Literally "and he will overflow <transChange type="added">them</transChange> and he will pass through"</note></verse>
    <verse num="41">And he will come {into the beautiful land}<note>Literally "into the land of the beauty"</note> and many will fall victim, but these will escape from his power: Edom and Moab and the best part<note>A difficult word to translate in this context: possibly it means "the foremost" (NASB), or it may mean "the remnant" (NEB)</note> of the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="42">And he will stretch out his hand against countries and the land of Egypt {will not escape}.<note>Literally "not it will be to escape"</note></verse>
    <verse num="43">And he will rule over the treasures of gold and the silver and over all the precious things of Egypt; and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Libyans and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Cushites <transChange type="added">will follow</transChange> in his footsteps.</verse>
    <verse num="44">But reports will terrify him from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east and from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> north, and he will go out with great fury to destroy and <transChange type="added">to</transChange> exterminate many.</verse>
    <verse num="45">And <transChange type="added">then</transChange> he will pitch the tents of his palace between <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sea <transChange type="added">and</transChange> {the beautiful holy mountain},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mountain of the beauty holiness"</note> and he will come to his end, and there is no one<note>Or "not one"</note> helping him." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">"Now at that time, Michael, the great prince, will arise, {the protector}<note>Literally "the one who stands with"</note> over the sons of your people, and it will be a time of distress that has not been since <transChange type="added">your people</transChange> {have been}<note>Literally "to be" or "being"</note> a nation until that time. And at that time your people will escape, {everyone who is found}<note>Literally "all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the being found"</note> written in the scroll.<note>Or "book"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">And many from <transChange type="added">those</transChange> sleeping {in the dusty ground}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">of the</transChange> ground of dust"</note> will awake, some to {everlasting life}<note>Literally "life of eternity"</note> and some to disgrace and {everlasting contempt}.<note>Literally "contempt <transChange type="added">of</transChange> eternity"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">But the <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> having insight will shine like the brightness of the expanse, and <transChange type="added">the ones</transChange> providing justice <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the many<note>Or "leading the many in righteousness"</note> <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> like the stars {forever and ever}.<note>Literally "to eternity and ever"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">But you, Daniel, keep the words secret and seal the scroll<note>Or "book"</note> until <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end; many will run back and forth and knowledge will increase." </verse>
    <verse num="5">Then I looked, I myself, Daniel, and look, there were two others standing: {one on this bank of the stream and one on the other}.<note>Literally "one here on the bank of the stream and one there on the bank of the stream"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Then he said to the man <transChange type="added">who</transChange> was clothed in linen who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> above<note>Hebrew "from above"</note> the water of the stream,<note>Or "river"</note> "{How long until}<note>Literally "Until when"</note> the end of the wonders?"</verse>
    <verse num="7">And I heard the man <transChange type="added">who</transChange> was clothed in linen who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> above<note>Hebrew "from above"</note> the water of the stream,<note>Or "river"</note> and he raised his right hand and his left hand to heaven and he swore {by the one who lives forever}<note>Literally "by the life of the eternity"</note> that <transChange type="added">an</transChange> appointed time, appointed times, and half <transChange type="added">an appointed time</transChange> <transChange type="added">would pass</transChange> when <transChange type="added">the</transChange> shattering of {the power of the holy people}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> power of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> people of holiness"</note> {would be completed};<note>Literally "to come to an end"</note> <transChange type="added">then</transChange> all these things will be accomplished. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Now I myself heard, but I <transChange type="added">did</transChange> not understand, and I said, "My lord, what <transChange type="added">will be the</transChange> outcome <transChange type="added">of</transChange> these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="9">And he said, "Go, Daniel, for the words <transChange type="added">are</transChange> secret and <transChange type="added">are</transChange> sealed <transChange type="added">up</transChange> until <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> end.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Many will be purified and will be cleansed and will be refined, but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wicked will act wickedly {and none of the wicked will understand},<note>Literally "and not will understand all the wicked"</note> but {those who have insight}<note>Literally "the <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> having insight"</note> will understand.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> time the regular burnt offering is removed and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> abomination that causes desolation {is set up}<note>Literally "to be set up" or "to put in place"</note> <transChange type="added">there will be</transChange> one thousand two hundred and ninety days.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Happy <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the <transChange type="added">one who is</transChange> persevering, and attains <transChange type="added">to</transChange> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> one thousand three hundred and thirty-five days.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But you, go <transChange type="added">on</transChange> to the end and rest, and you will arise for your allotted inheritance at the end of the days." </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>