<book num="Obad">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The vision of Obadiah. Thus says my Lord Yahweh concerning Edom: </verse>
    <verse num="2">"Look, I will<note>The NET Bible note for this verse points out: "The Hebrew perfect verb form used here usually describes past events. However, here and several times in the following verses it is best understood as portraying certain fulfillment of events that at the time of writing were still future. It is the perfect of certitude"</note> make you insignificant among the nations. You <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> utterly despised!</verse>
    <verse num="3">The pride of your heart has deceived you, you who live in the clefts of a rock, the heights of its dwelling, <transChange type="added">you who</transChange> say in your heart: 'Who can bring me down <transChange type="added">to the</transChange> ground?'</verse>
    <verse num="4"><transChange type="added">Even</transChange> if you soar like the eagle, <transChange type="added">even</transChange> if your nest is set among <transChange type="added">the</transChange> stars, from there I will bring you down!" {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh:</verse>
    <verse num="5">"If thieves came to you, if plunderers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> night--How you have been destroyed!--would they not steal {what they wanted}?<note>Literally "their sufficiency"</note> If grape gatherers came, would they not leave gleanings?</verse>
    <verse num="6">How Esau has been pillaged; his treasures have been ransacked!</verse>
    <verse num="7">All of your {allies}<note>Literally "men of your covenant"</note> have driven you up to the boundary; your {confederates}<note>Literally "men of your peace"</note> have deceived you and have prevailed against you. <transChange type="added">Those who eat</transChange> your bread have set an ambush for you, there is no<note>The preposition בּ plus אֵין indicates the absence of a thing within a location</note> understanding of it.<note>Or "in him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">On that day," {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh, "will I not destroy the wise men from Edom, and understanding from the mountain of Esau?</verse>
    <verse num="9">And your warriors will be shattered, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Teman, so that {everyone}<note>Literally "each"</note> from the mountain of Esau will be cut off because of the slaughter! </verse>
    <verse num="10">"Because of the violence done to your brother Jacob, shame will cover you and you will be cut off forever.</verse>
    <verse num="11">On {the day you stood nearby},<note>Literally "the day of your standing nearby"</note> {on the day strangers took}<note>Literally "the day of the taking captive by strangers"</note> his wealth, and foreigners entered his gates and cast lots over Jerusalem, you were also like one of them.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But you should not have gloated<note>The Hebrew expression "to look upon" often has the sense of "to feast the eyes upon" or "to gloat over"</note> over your brother's day, on the day of his misfortune, and you should not have rejoiced over the {people}<note>Literally "son"</note> of Judah on the day of their perishing, and you should not have opened your mouth wide on the day of distress.</verse>
    <verse num="13">You should not have entered the gate of my people on the day of their disaster. You also should not have gloated over his misery on the day of his disaster, and you should not have stretched out <transChange type="added">your hands</transChange> on the day of his disaster.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And you should not have stood at the crossroad<transChange type="added">s</transChange> to cut off his fugitives and you should not have handed over his survivors on the day of distress. </verse>
    <verse num="15">"For the day of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near against all the nations! Just as you have done, it will be done to you. Your deeds will return on your <transChange type="added">own</transChange> head.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For just as you have drunk on {my holy mountain},<note>Literally "the mountain of my holiness"</note> all the nations will drink continually. They will drink and they will slurp, and they will be as <transChange type="added">if</transChange> they had never been.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But on Mount Zion there will be an escape, and it will be holy, and the house of Jacob will take possession <transChange type="added">of</transChange> their dispossessors.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And the house of Jacob will be a fire and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau stubble; and they will set them on fire and will consume them. And there will not be a survivor for the house of Esau," for Yahweh has spoken. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Those of the Negev will take possession of the mountain of Esau, and those of the Shephelah <transChange type="added">will possess the land of</transChange> the Philistines, and they shall take possession of the territory of Ephraim and the territory of Samaria, and Benjamin <transChange type="added">will take possession of</transChange> Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And the exiles<note>Hebrew "exile"</note> of this army of the people of Israel <transChange type="added">will possess</transChange> Canaan up to Zarephath, and the exiles<note>Hebrew "exile"</note> of Jerusalem who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in Sepharad will take possession of the cities of the Negev.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And those who have been saved will go up on Mount Zion to rule the mountain of Esau. And the kingdom {will belong to}<note>Literally "will be for"</note> Yahweh. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>