<book num="Ezra">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">In the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, in order to accomplish the word of Yahweh by the mouth of Jeremiah, Yahweh stirred the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia and he sent a message to all of his kingdom and also <transChange type="added">put the message</transChange> in writing: </verse>
    <verse num="2">"Thus says Cyrus king of Persia: Yahweh, the God of the heavens, has given me all the kingdoms of the earth. And he himself has appointed me to build a house for him in Jerusalem, which is in Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Whoever among you <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> from all of his people, may his God be with him and may he go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and may he build the house of Yahweh, the God of Israel. He is the God who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And let every survivor, from wherever he {resides}<note>Literally "resides as a foreigner"</note> be assisted by the men of that place with silver and gold, with possessions and domestic animals, and with the freewill offering for the house of God which is in Jerusalem." </verse>
    <verse num="5">So the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> for Judah and Benjamin, and the priests and the Levites--to all whose spirit God had stirred--<transChange type="added">prepared</transChange> to go up and build the house of Yahweh which is in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And all of their neighbors {helped them}<note>Literally "helped with their hands"</note> with objects of silver, gold, possessions, domestic animal<transChange type="added">s</transChange>, and with valuable gifts--besides all of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> freewill offering.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And Cyrus the king brought out the objects of the house of Yahweh that Nebuchadnezzar had brought from Jerusalem and placed in the house of his gods.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Cyrus the king of Persia let them go out by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and he counted them out to Sheshbazzar the prince of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Now these were the inventories: thirty gold metal dishes, one thousand silver metal dishes, twenty-nine vessels,</verse>
    <verse num="10">thirty bowls of gold, four hundred and ten matching silver metal bowls, and one thousand other objects.</verse>
    <verse num="11">All of the objects of gold and silver metal <transChange type="added">were</transChange> five thousand four hundred. All this Sheshbazzar brought up along with the exiles from Babylonia to Jerusalem. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Now these were the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of the province who came up from the captivity of the exile whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon carried captive to Babylonia. They returned to Jerusalem and Judah, each to his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> city.</verse>
    <verse num="2">They came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, and Baanah. </verse>
    <verse num="3">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Parosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two;</verse>
    <verse num="4">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shephatiah, three hundred and seventy-two;</verse>
    <verse num="5">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Arah, seven hundred and seventy-five;</verse>
    <verse num="6">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Pahath-moab, <transChange type="added">particularly</transChange> the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="7">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
    <verse num="8">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Zattu, nine hundred and forty-five;</verse>
    <verse num="9">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty;</verse>
    <verse num="10">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bani, six hundred and forty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="11">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bebai, six hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="12">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Azgad, one thousand two hundred and twenty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="13">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty-six;</verse>
    <verse num="14">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bigvai, two thousand fifty-six;</verse>
    <verse num="15">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Adin, four hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
    <verse num="16">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ater, <transChange type="added">particularly</transChange> of Hezekiah, ninety-eight;</verse>
    <verse num="17">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bezai, three hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="18">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jorah, one hundred and twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="19">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hashum, two hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="20">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gibbar, ninety-five;</verse>
    <verse num="21">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bethlehem, one hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="22">the men of Netophah, fifty-six;</verse>
    <verse num="23">the men of Anathoth, one hundred and twenty-eight;</verse>
    <verse num="24">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Azmaveth, forty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="25">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Kiriath Αrim, Kephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="26">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ramah and Geba, six hundred and twenty-one;</verse>
    <verse num="27">the men of Micmash, one hundred and twenty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="28">the men of Bethel and Ai, two hundred and twenty-three;</verse>
    <verse num="29">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Nebo, fifty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="30">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Magbish, one hundred and fifty-six;</verse>
    <verse num="31">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred and fifty-four;</verse>
    <verse num="32">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Harim, three hundred and twenty;</verse>
    <verse num="33">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred and twenty-five;</verse>
    <verse num="34">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jericho, three hundred and forty-five;</verse>
    <verse num="35">the people<note>Or "sons"</note> of Senaah, three thousand six hundred and thirty. </verse>
    <verse num="36">The priests: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred and seventy-three;</verse>
    <verse num="37">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Immer, one thousand fifty-two;</verse>
    <verse num="38">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred and forty-seven;</verse>
    <verse num="39">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Harim, one thousand seventeen. </verse>
    <verse num="40">The Levites: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hodaviah, seventy-four. </verse>
    <verse num="41">The singers: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Asaph, one hundred and twenty-eight. </verse>
    <verse num="42">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of the gatekeepers: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shallum, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ater, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Talmon, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Akkub, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hatita, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shobai; in total one hundred and thirty-nine. </verse>
    <verse num="43">The temple servants: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ziha, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hasupha, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Tabbaoth,</verse>
    <verse num="44">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Keros, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Siaha, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Padon,</verse>
    <verse num="45">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Lebanah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hagabah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Akkub,</verse>
    <verse num="46">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hagab, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shamlai, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hanan,</verse>
    <verse num="47">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Giddel, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gahar, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Reaiah,</verse>
    <verse num="48">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Rezin, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Nekoda, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Gazzam,</verse>
    <verse num="49">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Uzza, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Paseah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Besai,</verse>
    <verse num="50">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Asnah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Meunim, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Nephisim,</verse>
    <verse num="51">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bakbuk, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hakupha, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Harhur,</verse>
    <verse num="52">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bazluth, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Mehida, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Harsha,</verse>
    <verse num="53">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Barkos, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Sisera, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Temah,</verse>
    <verse num="54">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Neziah, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hatipha. </verse>
    <verse num="55">The descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Solomon's servants: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Sotai, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hassophereth, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Peruda,</verse>
    <verse num="56">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Jaalah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Darkon, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Giddel,</verse>
    <verse num="57">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shephatiah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hattil, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Pochereth-hazzebaim, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ami. </verse>
    <verse num="58">All the temple servants and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Solomon's servants were three hundred and ninety-two. </verse>
    <verse num="59">Now these were the ones who came up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addan, and Immer, but they were not able to prove their fathers' household and their descent, if they were from Israel:</verse>
    <verse num="60">the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Delaiah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Tobiah, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Nekoda, six hundred and fifty-two.</verse>
    <verse num="61">And from the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of the priests: the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Habaiah, the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Hakkoz, and the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Barzillai (who took a wife from the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called by their name).</verse>
    <verse num="62">These sought their record in the genealogy <transChange type="added">records</transChange>, but they were not found, and {were excluded from the priesthood as unclean}.<note>Literally "they were unclean from the priesthood"</note></verse>
    <verse num="63">The governor said to them that they could not eat from the holy food of the sanctuary<note>Or "most holy things"</note> until there was present a priest for the Urim and Thummim. </verse>
    <verse num="64">The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty,</verse>
    <verse num="65">apart from their male and female servants, of whom were seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and they had two hundred male and female singers.</verse>
    <verse num="66">Their horses <transChange type="added">numbered</transChange> seven hundred and thirty-six, their mules <transChange type="added">numbered</transChange> two hundred and forty-five,</verse>
    <verse num="67">their camels <transChange type="added">numbered</transChange> four hundred and thirty-five, their donkeys <transChange type="added">numbered</transChange> six thousand seven hundred and twenty. </verse>
    <verse num="68">When <transChange type="added">some</transChange> of the heads of {families}<note>Literally "the fathers"</note> came to the house of Yahweh that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in Jerusalem, they gave freewill offerings for the house of God to erect it on its place.</verse>
    <verse num="69">According to their ability they gave to the treasury room for the work sixty-one thousand darics of gold, five thousand minas of silver, and one hundred priestly tunics. </verse>
    <verse num="70">The priests, the Levites, and some of the people lived <transChange type="added">in Jerusalem</transChange>, and the singers, the gatekeepers, and the temple servants <transChange type="added">lived</transChange> in their cities, and all Israel in their cities. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Now the seventh month drew near and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the cities, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> the people gathered as {one}<note>Literally "one man"</note> in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Jeshua son of Jehozadak and his brothers the priests stood up, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and his brothers built the altar of the God of Israel, in order to offer burnt offerings on it, as it is written in the law of Moses, the man of God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">They set up the altar on its foundations, because {they were in terror}<note>Literally "in terror before them"</note> because of the peoples of the lands. And they offered burnt offerings on it for Yahweh, burnt offerings for the morning and the evening.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And they kept the feast of booths, as it is written, and <transChange type="added">offered</transChange> burnt offerings day by day in number according to the ordinance {as described for each day}.<note>Literally "the daily word on its day"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">After <transChange type="added">this, they presented</transChange> the daily sacrifice of burnt offerings, <transChange type="added">the offerings</transChange> for the New Moon Festival, and for all of the appointed times consecrated for Yahweh and for all who gave a freewill offering to Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="6">From the first day of the seventh month they began to offer burnt offerings to Yahweh. But the temple of Yahweh was not yet founded.</verse>
    <verse num="7">So they gave money to the stone craftsmen and skilled craftsmen, and food, drink, and olive oil to the Sidonians and Tyrians, to bring cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea of Joppa, according to the authorization over them of Cyrus king of Persia. </verse>
    <verse num="8">In the second year after their coming to the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel and Jeshua son of Jehozadak began <transChange type="added">their work</transChange>, and the remainder of their brothers the priests and the Levites and all who came from the captivity to Jerusalem. They appointed the Levites {from twenty years and older}<note>Literally "a son of twenty years and above"</note> to direct the work of the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Jeshua <transChange type="added">with</transChange> his sons and brothers, and Kadmiel and his sons--the sons of Judah--together directed the workers in the house of God, <transChange type="added">along with</transChange> the sons of Henadad and their sons and brothers the Levites. </verse>
    <verse num="10">And the builders laid the foundation of the temple of Yahweh, and the priests <transChange type="added">in their</transChange> apparel with the trumpets, and the Levites, the sons of Asaph, with the cymbals, were positioned to praise Yahweh, {as described by}<note>Literally "by the hands of"</note> King David of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And they {sang responsively},<note>Literally "they answered"</note> with praising and thanksgiving to Yahweh <transChange type="added">saying</transChange>, "For he is good, for his loyal love is everlasting for Israel." </verse>
    <verse num="12">But many of the elderly priests, Levites, and heads of the families who had seen the first temple, wept with a loud voice when they saw the foundation of this house, but many {shouted aloud with joy}.<note>Literally "exalted with voice in joy with a shout"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">No person could distinguish the sound of joyful acclaim from the sound of people weeping, for the people shouted with great joyful acclaim and the sound was heard from afar. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Now the enemies of Judah and Benjamin heard that the {returned exiles}<note>Literally "the sons of the exile"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> building a temple for Yahweh the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And they approached Zerubbabel and the heads of the {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> and they said to them, "Let us build with you. Like you, we seek your God and have been sacrificing <transChange type="added">to him</transChange> from the days of Esarhaddon the king of Assyria who brought us up here.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But Zerubbabel, Jeshua, and the rest of the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of Israel said to them, "<transChange type="added">It is</transChange> not for you but for us to build a house for our God. For we ourselves alone will build <transChange type="added">it</transChange> for Yahweh the God of Israel, just as Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us." </verse>
    <verse num="4">Then the people of the land discouraged {the people of Judah}<note>Literally "the hands of the people of Judah"</note> and made them afraid to build</verse>
    <verse num="5">and bribed officials against them to frustrate their plan for all the days of Cyrus king of Persia until the reign of Darius king of Persia. </verse>
    <verse num="6">In the reign of Ahasuerus, at the beginning of his reign, they wrote an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And in the days of Artaxerxes, Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of their colleagues wrote to Artaxerxes king of Persia. The letter was written in Aramaic and translated from Aramaic.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Rehum the royal officer and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to King Artaxerxes as follows</verse>
    <verse num="9">(then Rehum the royal officer, Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their associates, the judges, the envoys, the officials, the Persians, the Erechs, the Babylonians, the Susians (that is the Elamites)</verse>
    <verse num="10">and the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Osnappar deported and settled in the cities of Samaria and the rest of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River) and now</verse>
    <verse num="11">this is the copy of the letter which they sent to him: </verse>
    <verse num="12">be it known to the king that the Jews who have come up from near you to us have gone to Jerusalem. They are building the rebellious and wicked city. They are finishing the wall and repairing the foundation.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Now be it known to the king that if this city is built and the walls are finished, they will not pay tribute and toll, and the royal revenue will be reduced.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Now since we eat the salt of the palace and the dishonor of the king is not proper for us to see, we send and make <transChange type="added">this</transChange> known to the king,</verse>
    <verse num="15">so that it may be investigated in the book of records of your ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note> You will find in the book of records and learn that this city is a rebellious city, hurtful to kings and provinces, and they have rebelled in its midst from ancient times. Because of that this city was destroyed.</verse>
    <verse num="16">We make known to the king that if this city is built and the walls are finished, you will have nothing in <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River." </verse>
    <verse num="17">The king sent a reply: "To Rehum the royal officer, Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their associates who live in Samaria and the rest <transChange type="added">of the province</transChange> Beyond the River, greetings. And now</verse>
    <verse num="18">the letter that you sent to us has been translated <transChange type="added">and</transChange> read before me.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And {I issued}<note>Literally "by my means made"</note> a decree, and they searched and found that this city from ancient days revolted against kings, and rebellion and sedition has been made in it.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Mighty kings have ruled over Jerusalem, <transChange type="added">governing</transChange> all <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River, to whom tribute, duty, and tax has been given.</verse>
    <verse num="21">So now, issue forth a decree that these men stop and this city not be built, until a decree is issued from me.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And be careful not to be negligent on this matter. Why should damage grow to hurt kings?" </verse>
    <verse num="23">Then when a copy of the letter of King Artaxerxes was read before Rehum, Shimshai the scribe, and their associates they returned in a hurry to Jerusalem against the Jews and they stopped them by force and power.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Then the work on the house of God in Jerusalem stopped, and was discontinued until the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">Now the prophets, Haggai and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied to the Jews who were in {Judah}<note>Literally "Jehud"</note> and in Jerusalem, in the name of the God of Israel who was over them.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and Jeshua the son of Jozadak set out and began to build the house of God that is in Jerusalem. And with them the prophets of God <transChange type="added">were</transChange> helping them. </verse>
    <verse num="3">At the same time Tattenai, governor of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River, and Shethar-bozenai, and their associates came to them and spoke to them thus: "Who issued you all a decree to build this house and to finish this structure?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then we<note>Hebrew is first person plural</note> asked them this: "What are the names of the men who are building this building?"</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the eye of their God was on the elders of the Jews, and they did not stop them until the report came to Darius, and then <transChange type="added">answer</transChange> was received. </verse>
    <verse num="6">The copy of the letter that Tattenai, the governor of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River, and Shethar-bozenai and his associates the envoys who were in <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River sent to Darius the king.</verse>
    <verse num="7">They sent to him the report {in which was written as follows}:<note>Literally "and like this was written in its middle"</note> "To Darius the king, all peace.</verse>
    <verse num="8">May it be known to the king that we went to the province of Judah, the house of the great God. It is being built with stone blocks and timber is being put in the walls. This work is being done with diligence and is making progress in their hands.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Then we asked those elders and said this to them, 'Who issued forth to you a decree to build this house and to finish this structure?'</verse>
    <verse num="10">We also asked them their names to make them known to you, that we might write down the {name of their leaders}.<note>Literally "name of the men at their head"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And this is the answer they returned to us: 'We are servants of the God of heaven and earth, and we are building the house that was built formerly many years ago, <transChange type="added">which</transChange> a great king of Israel had built and finished.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But because our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> angered the God of heaven, he gave them into the hand of the Chaldean King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon. He destroyed this house and carried away the people to Babylonia.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But in the first year of King Cyrus of Babylon's reign he issued forth a decree to build this house of God.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Also, the gold and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took away from the temple in Jerusalem and brought to the temple in Babylonia, King Cyrus removed them from the temple in Babylonia and they were given to Sheshbazzar, whom he appointed governor.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He said to him, 'Take these vessels. Go put them in the temple in Jerusalem and let the house of God be built on its site.'</verse>
    <verse num="16">Then this Sheshbazzar came and laid the foundation of the house of God in Jerusalem. And from that <transChange type="added">time</transChange> until now it is being built, but not yet finished.'</verse>
    <verse num="17">And now, if it seems good for the king, let it be investigated in the house of the treasury of the king in Babylonia <transChange type="added">to see</transChange> if a decree was issued forth from King Cyrus to build this house of God in Jerusalem. And let the king send to us his desire on this matter." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Then King Darius issued forth a decree, and they searched the house of the treasury of scrolls being stored in Babylonia.</verse>
    <verse num="2">But it was in Ecbatana in the province of Media, in the citadel, that a certain scroll had written on it, "A record.</verse>
    <verse num="3">In the first year of King Cyrus, he issued forth a decree concerning the house of God in Jerusalem. Let the house be built, the place where sacrifices are offered and let its foundations be raised. Its height <transChange type="added">shall be</transChange> sixty cubits and its width sixty cubits,</verse>
    <verse num="4">with three layers of great stones and a layer of timber. Let the new expenses be paid from the house of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Also, let the gold and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took from the temple in Jerusalem and brought to Babylonia, be returned and brought to the temple in Jerusalem to its place. Put them in the house of God." </verse>
    <verse num="6">"Now then, Tattenai governor of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and your associates, the envoys who are in <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River--keep far away from there.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Leave this work of the house of God alone. Let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God on its site.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And I issue forth a decree for what you should do for these elders of the Jews to build this house of God. The full expense will be paid to these men from the riches of the king from the taxes of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River, without delay.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Whatever may be needed--{young bulls},<note>Literally "the sons of young bulls"</note> young rams, sheep for burnt offerings to the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil for the priests in Jerusalem--let it be given to them day by day with no negligence,</verse>
    <verse num="10">that they may offer incense offerings to the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king and his children.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Furthermore, I issue forth a decree that if any person violates this decree, let a beam be pulled out from his house and let him be impaled on it. And let his house be made a pile of rubble on <transChange type="added">account of</transChange> this.</verse>
    <verse num="12">May the God who has set his name there overthrow any king or people who sets his hand to alter <transChange type="added">or</transChange> to destroy this house of God in Jerusalem. I, Darius, issue forth a decree. Let it be done with diligence." </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then Tattenai the governor of the <transChange type="added">province</transChange> Beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and their associates consequently did with diligence what Darius the king ordered.</verse>
    <verse num="14">So the elders of the Jews were building and prospering, through the prophecy of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah son of Iddo. They finished building by the command of the God of Israel and by the decree of Cyrus, Darius, and King Artaxerxes of Persia.</verse>
    <verse num="15">This house was completed on the third day of the month of Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of King Darius. </verse>
    <verse num="16">And the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> the priests, the Levites, and the rest of the {returned exiles}<note>Literally "sons of the exile"</note> celebrated the dedication of this house of God with joy.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And they offered during the dedication of this house of God one hundred young bulls, two hundred young rams, four hundred lambs, and twelve male goats as a sin offering for Israel <transChange type="added">according to</transChange> the number of the tribes of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then they set the priests in their divisions and the Levites in their sections for the work of God in Jerusalem, as it is written in the book of Moses. </verse>
    <verse num="19">On the fourteenth day of the first month the returned exiles observed the Passover feast.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For the priests and Levites together had consecrated themselves; all of them were clean. And they slaughtered the Passover sacrifice for all of the returned exiles, for their brothers the priests, and for themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> who returned from the exile and all those who separated themselves from the uncleanness of the nations of the earth to seek Yahweh the God of Israel, ate.</verse>
    <verse num="22">With joy they celebrated the festival of unleavened bread <transChange type="added">for</transChange> seven days, because Yahweh had made them joyful and had turned the heart of the king of Assyria toward them in order to help them with the work of their hands on the house of the God of Israel. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">After these things <transChange type="added">during</transChange> the reign of King Artaxerxes of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, son of Azariah, son of Hilkiah,</verse>
    <verse num="2">son of Shallum, son of Zadok, son of Ahitub,</verse>
    <verse num="3">son of Amariah, son of Azariah, son of Meraioth,</verse>
    <verse num="4">, son of Zerahiah, son of Uzzi, son of Bukki,</verse>
    <verse num="5">son of Abishua, son of Phinehas, son of Eleazar, son of Aaron the chief priest--</verse>
    <verse num="6">this Ezra went up from Babylonia. He was a scribe skilled in the law of Moses, which Yahweh the God of Israel gave. The king granted him all his requests, for the hand of Yahweh was upon him. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Some of the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> some priests and Levites, the singers, the gatekeepers, and the temple servants went up to Jerusalem in the seventh year of King Artaxerxes.</verse>
    <verse num="8">He came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For on the first day of the first month he began the journey from Babylonia; and on the first day of the fifth month he came to Jerusalem, for the good hand of his God <transChange type="added">was</transChange> on him.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For Ezra had set his heart to seek the law of Yahweh, to do <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, and to teach the regulations and judgments in Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="11">This is the copy of the letter that King Artaxerxes gave to Ezra the priest, the scribe of the scroll of the words of the commands of Yahweh and his statutes for Israel:</verse>
    <verse num="12">"Artaxerxes, the king of kings, to Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of the heavens. Peace. And now</verse>
    <verse num="13">I issue forth a decree that any of the people of Israel, their priests, or their Levites in my kingdom who are willing to go to Jerusalem may go with you.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For you are sent from the king and his seven counselors to enquire about Judah and Jerusalem concerning the law of your God, which is in your hand.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Also, bring the silver and gold that the king and his advisors have freely offered to the God of Israel whose dwelling is in Jerusalem,</verse>
    <verse num="16">and all of the silver and gold that you will find in the whole province of Babylonia, with the freewill offerings of the people and the priests giving willingly for the house of their God in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="17">With this money, then, with diligence you must buy young bulls, young rams, lambs, and their offerings and libations. You must offer them on the altar that is in the house of your God in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="18">You may do whatever seems best to you and your brothers to do with the remainder of the silver and gold according to the desire of your God.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And the vessels that were given to you for the service of the house of your God you shall deliver before the God of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And the remainder of the needs for the house of your God that falls to you to provide, you may provide from the house of the king's treasury." </verse>
    <verse num="21">"I, even I, King Artaxerxes, issue forth a decree to all the treasurers who are in <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River. Whatever the priest Ezra, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, may ask of you, let it be done with diligence,</verse>
    <verse num="22">up to one hundred talents of silver, one hundred measures of wheat, one hundred baths of wine, one hundred baths of oil, and {unlimited salt}.<note>Literally, "salt that is not specified"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">All that is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be done with diligence for the house of the God of heaven, otherwise wrath will come on the kingdom of the king and his sons.</verse>
    <verse num="24">You also should be aware that it is not permitted to place tax, tribute, or duty upon all of the priests, the Levites, the singers, the doorkeepers, the temple servants, and other servants of the house of God. </verse>
    <verse num="25">"You, Ezra, according to the wisdom of your God that you possess, appoint magistrates and judges who can judge all of the people <transChange type="added">in the province</transChange> Beyond the River who know the laws of your God. And you will teach those who do not know.</verse>
    <verse num="26">All who do not obey the law of your God and the law of the king, let judgment be executed on him with diligence, whether for death or for banishment or for confiscation of goods and for imprisonment." </verse>
    <verse num="27">Blessed be Yahweh the God of our ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> who put this in the heart of the king to glorify the house of Yahweh in Jerusalem</verse>
    <verse num="28">and who extended to me loyal love before the king and his counselors, and before all of the mighty officials of the king. I took courage, for the hand of Yahweh my God was upon me, and I gathered leaders from Israel to go up with me. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">These were the heads of their {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> and the register of those returnees from Babylonia who <transChange type="added">came up</transChange> with me in the reign of King Artaxerxes:</verse>
    <verse num="2">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Phinehas: Gershom. From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Ithamar: Daniel. From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of David: Hattush.</verse>
    <verse num="3">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shecaniah, from the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Parosh: Zechariah and with him one hundred and fifty registered males.</verse>
    <verse num="4">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Pahath-Moab: Eliehoenai son of Zerahiah and with him two hundred males.</verse>
    <verse num="5">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of <transChange type="added">Zattu</transChange>:<note>Commentators and translators agree that there is a name missing from the Masoretic text. Zattu has been restored from the LXX</note> Shecaniah son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred males.</verse>
    <verse num="6">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Adin: Ebed son of Jehonathan, and with him fifty males.</verse>
    <verse num="7">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Elam: Jeshaiah son of Athaliah, and with him seventy males.</verse>
    <verse num="8">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Shephatiah: Zebadiah son of Michael, and with him eighty males.</verse>
    <verse num="9">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Joab: Obadiah son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen males.</verse>
    <verse num="10">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of <transChange type="added">Bani</transChange>:<note>Commentators and translators agree that there is a name missing from the Masoretic text. Bani has been restored from the LXX</note> Shelomith son of Josiphiah, and with him one hundred and sixty males.</verse>
    <verse num="11">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bebai: Zechariah son of Bebai, and with him twenty-eight males.</verse>
    <verse num="12">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Azgad: Jehohanan son of Haqqatan, and with him one hundred and ten males.</verse>
    <verse num="13">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Adonikam, those who came last, these were their names: Eliphelet, Jeiel, Shemaiah, and with them sixty males.</verse>
    <verse num="14">From the descendants<note>Or "sons"</note> of Bigvai: Uthai son of Zabud,<note>Or "and Zabud"</note> and with him seventy males. </verse>
    <verse num="15">I gathered them by the river that goes to Ahava and we camped there for three days. And I looked at the people and the priests, I found no one there from the sons of Levi.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And I sent for Eliezer, Ariel, Shemaiah, Elnathan, Jarib, Elnathan, Nathan, Zechariah, and Meshullam, who were family heads, and for Jehoiarib and Elnathan who were wise.</verse>
    <verse num="17">I sent them to Iddo, the head of the place called Casiphia, and I placed in their mouths what words to say to Iddo and his brothers the temple servants in Casiphia, to send to us ministers for the house of our God.</verse>
    <verse num="18">With the good hand of our God before us, they brought us a man of understanding from the sons of Mahli, son of Levi, son of Israel--Sherebiah and his sons and brothers, eighteen <transChange type="added">in total</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Also Hashabiah and with him Jeshaiah, the sons of Merari, with his brothers and their sons, twenty <transChange type="added">in total</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And from the temple servants, whom David and <transChange type="added">his</transChange> officials had set up to serve the Levites, two hundred and twenty <transChange type="added">in total</transChange>. All of them were registered by name. </verse>
    <verse num="21">I proclaimed a fast there at the river Ahava to humble ourselves before our God in order to seek from him a safe journey for us, our children, and our possessions.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For I was ashamed to ask the king for troops and horses to protect us from enemies on the way because we said to the king, "the hand of our God is favorable to all who seek him, but his strength and anger are against all who forsake them."</verse>
    <verse num="23">So we fasted and sought our God for this and he responded to our prayer. </verse>
    <verse num="24">I set apart twelve of the official priests: Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brothers with them.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Then I weighed out to them silver and gold and the vessels, the offering of the house of our God that the king, his counselors, his commanders, and all of Israel who was present offered.</verse>
    <verse num="26">I weighed out into their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, one hundred vessels of silver, one hundred talents of gold,</verse>
    <verse num="27">twenty gold bowls worth one thousand darics, and two vessels of good polished bronze as precious as gold.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And I said to them, "You are holy to Yahweh and the vessels are holy. The silver and gold are a freewill offering to Yahweh, God of your ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note></verse>
    <verse num="29">Guard and look after <transChange type="added">them</transChange> until you weigh <transChange type="added">them</transChange> before the chief priests, the Levites, and the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of Israel in Jerusalem, in the chamber of the house of Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="30">So the priests and Levites took over the weighed silver, gold, and the vessels to bring to Jerusalem for the house of our God. </verse>
    <verse num="31">On the twelfth day of the first month we set out from the river of Ahava to go to Jerusalem. The hand of our God was on us and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy and from ambushing on the way.</verse>
    <verse num="32">We came to Jerusalem and remained there three days.</verse>
    <verse num="33">On the fourth day, the silver, gold, and vessels were weighed in the house of our God into the hand of priest Meremoth, the son of Uriah, and with him Eleazar son of Phinehas. With them were the Levites, Jehozabad son of Jeshua and Noadiah son of Binnui.</verse>
    <verse num="34">The amount and weight of all the weighed <transChange type="added">items</transChange> was recorded at that time. </verse>
    <verse num="35">The exiles that returned from captivity offered burnt offerings to the God of Israel; twelve bulls for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven lambs, and twelve goats as a sin offering. All was a burnt offering to Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="36">They delivered the customs of the king to the king's satraps and to the governor of <transChange type="added">the province</transChange> Beyond the River. And they supported the people of the house of God. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">After finishing these things the officials approached me saying, "The people of Israel, the priests, and the Levites have not separated from the people of the lands with their detestable things, and from the Canaanites, Hittites, Perizzites, Jebusites, Ammonites, Moabites, Egyptians, and Amorites.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For they have taken from their daughters for themselves and their sons. So the holy seed has mixed itself with the peoples of the lands, and the hand of the officials and prefects were foremost in this sin.</verse>
    <verse num="3">When I heard this I tore my garment and my robe, and I pulled the hair out from my head and beard, and I sat appalled.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then all who trembled at the words of the God of Israel because of the sin of the returned exiles were gathered around me and I sat appalled until the evening offering. </verse>
    <verse num="5">At the evening offering I got up from my mourning posture and, with my garment and robe torn, I fell down on my knees and I spread out my palms to Yahweh my God</verse>
    <verse num="6">and said, "My God, I am ashamed and embarrassed to lift my face to you, my God. For our sins have risen above our heads and our guilt has grown up to the heavens.</verse>
    <verse num="7">From the days of our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> until this day we have been in great guilt, and because of our sins we ourselves, our kings, and our priests have been handed into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, to plunder, and to utter shame, as it is this day.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But now for a brief moment mercy has been shown by Yahweh our God, who left behind for us a remnant, and given us security in his holy place--for our God to brighten our eyes and to give us brief relief in our bondage.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For we are slaves and in our bondage our God did not forsake us, and he has extended to us loyal love in the presence of the kings of Persia, to give to us deliverance<note>Or "preservation"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> to set up the house of our God, to repair its ruins, and to give us a wall in Judea and Jerusalem. </verse>
    <verse num="10">"And now our God what shall we say after this? For we have forsaken your commandments,</verse>
    <verse num="11">which you commanded by the hand of your servants the prophets saying, 'The land that you are entering to possess is a land of impurity with the impurity of the peoples of the lands, with their detestable things which they have filled from end to end with their uncleanness.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore, do not give your daughters to their sons, and do not take their daughters for your sons. Do not seek their peace and prosperity so that forever you may be strong and eat the good of the land and may give it as an inheritance to your sons.'</verse>
    <verse num="13">After all that has come upon us for our evil practices and for our great guilt--you, our God, have held back less than our guilt <transChange type="added">deserved</transChange> and you have given us a remainder such as this.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Shall we again break your commandments and intermarry with the peoples who practice these detestable things? Would you not be angry with us until you destroy us with no remnant or remainder?</verse>
    <verse num="15">Yahweh, God of Israel, you are righteous, for we have been left this day as a remnant. Here we are before you in our guilt, for none can stand before you because of this." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">While Ezra was praying and confessing, weeping and throwing himself down before the house of God, a very great assembly of men, women, and children from Israel gathered to him. And the people wept bitterly.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Shecaniah son of Jehiel, of the sons of Elam, answered and said to Ezra, "We ourselves have broken faith with our God and have married foreign women from the peoples of the land, and even now there is hope for Israel in spite of this.</verse>
    <verse num="3">So now let us make a covenant with our God to send away all of these women and their offspring, according to the advice of my lord and those who tremble at the commandment of our God. Let it be done according to the law.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Arise, for it is your task and we are with you. Be strong and do it."</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then Ezra stood up and made the chief priests, Levites, and all of Israel swear to do according to what was said. So they swore this oath. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Ezra rose from before the house of God and went to the chamber of Jehohanan son of Eliashib. He did not eat food nor drink water because he was mourning over the sin of the exiles.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And they sent a proclamation through Judah and Jerusalem to all the {returned exiles}<note>Literally "the sons of the exile"</note> to assemble in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Anyone who did not come within three days, by decision of the officials and elders, all of his possessions would be devoted to God, and he himself would be excluded from the assembly of exiles. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin assembled in Jerusalem within the three days. It was the ninth month on the twentieth day of the month. All the people sat in the public square of the house of God trembling because of this matter and from the rains.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Then Ezra the priest stood up and said to them, "You have broke faith and married foreign women, increasing the guilt of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Now make a confession to Yahweh the God of your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> and do his will. Separate yourselves from the peoples of the land and from the foreign women." </verse>
    <verse num="12">Then all the assembly answered with a great voice and said, "It is so. We must do according to your words.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But the people are many, and it is the time of rain; we are unable to stand outside. The task is not for one day or two, for we greatly rebelled in this matter.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Please let our leaders stand for the whole assembly, and let all that are in our cities who have married foreign women come at set times, and with them the elders of and judges of each city, until the fierce wrath of our God because of this matter is averted from us."</verse>
    <verse num="15">Only Jehonathan son of Asahel and Jahzeiah son of Tikvah stood against this, and the Levites Meshullam and Shabbethai supported them. </verse>
    <verse num="16">The {returned exiles}<note>Literally "the sons of the exile"</note> did so. Ezra the priest selected men, the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> according to the house of their fathers, all of them by name. They sat down to examine the matter on the first day of the tenth month.</verse>
    <verse num="17">They finished <transChange type="added">investigating</transChange> all the men who married foreign women by the first day of the first month. </verse>
    <verse num="18">There was found from the sons of the priests those who had married foreign women, from the sons of Jeshua son of Jehozadak and his brothers: Maaseiah, Eliezer, Jarib, and Gedaliah.</verse>
    <verse num="19">{They pledged themselves}<note>Literally "they gave their hand"</note> to put away their wives, and their guilt offering was a ram of the flock for their guilt.</verse>
    <verse num="20">From the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah.</verse>
    <verse num="21">From the sons of Harim: Maaseiah, Elijah, Shemaiah, Jehiel, and Uzziah.</verse>
    <verse num="22">From the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethanel, Jozabad, and Eleasah. </verse>
    <verse num="23">From the Levites: Jozabad, Shimei, Kelaiah (that is, Kelita), Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.</verse>
    <verse num="24">From the singers: Eliashib. From the gatekeepers: Shallum, Telem, and Uri. </verse>
    <verse num="25">And from Israel, the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, Izziah, Malkijah, Mijamin, Eleazar, Malkijah, and Benaiah.</verse>
    <verse num="26">From the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, Jehiel, Abdi, Jeremoth, and Elijah.</verse>
    <verse num="27">From the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, Jeremoth, Zabad, and Aziza.</verse>
    <verse num="28">From the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, and Athlai.</verse>
    <verse num="29">From the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, Adaiah, Jashub, Sheal, and Jeremoth.</verse>
    <verse num="30">From the sons of Pahath-Moab: Adna, Kelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezalel, Binnui, and Manasseh.</verse>
    <verse num="31">From the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Isshiah, Malkijah, Shemaiah, Simeon,</verse>
    <verse num="32">Benjamin, Malluch, and Shemariah.</verse>
    <verse num="33">From the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattattah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, and Shimei.</verse>
    <verse num="34">From the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, Uel,</verse>
    <verse num="35">Benaiah, Bedeiah, Keluhi,</verse>
    <verse num="36">Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Mattaniah, Mattenai, Jaasu,</verse>
    <verse num="38">Bani, Binnui, Shimei,</verse>
    <verse num="39">Shelemiah, Nathan, Adaiah,</verse>
    <verse num="40">Macnadebai, Shashai, Sharai,</verse>
    <verse num="41">Azarel, Shelemiah, Shemariah,</verse>
    <verse num="42">Shallum, Amariah, and Joseph.</verse>
    <verse num="43">From the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Iddo, Joel, and Benaiah.</verse>
    <verse num="44">All of these had married foreign wives, and some from among the wives bore children. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>