<book num="Phlm">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon, our dear friend and fellow worker,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and to Apphia our sister, and to Archippus our fellow soldier, and to the church in your house.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="4">I thank my God, always making mention of you in my prayers,</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">because I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("hear about") which is understood as causal</note> hear about your love and faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus and for all the saints.</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">I pray</transChange> that the fellowship of your faith may become effective in the knowledge <transChange type="added">of</transChange> every good <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in us for Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For I have great joy and encouragement from your love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through you, brother. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Therefore, <transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have") which is understood as concessive</note> have great confidence in Christ to order you <transChange type="added">to do what</transChange> is proper,</verse>
    <verse num="9">instead I appeal to <transChange type="added">you</transChange> because of love, <transChange type="added">since I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">since</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am") which is understood as causal</note> am such a one as Paul, now an old man and also a prisoner of Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="10">I am appealing to you concerning my child whom I became the father of during my imprisonment, Onesimus.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Once he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> useless to you, but now <transChange type="added">he is</transChange> useful to you<note>Some manuscripts have "both to you"</note> and to me,</verse>
    <verse num="12">whom I have sent back to you himself, that is, my heart,</verse>
    <verse num="13">whom I wanted to keep with me, in order that he might serve me on behalf of you during my imprisonment for the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But apart from your consent, I wanted to do nothing, in order that your good <transChange type="added">deed</transChange> might be not as according to necessity, but according to <transChange type="added">your own</transChange> free will.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For perhaps because of this, he was separated <transChange type="added">from you</transChange> for a time, in order that you might have him back forever,</verse>
    <verse num="16">no longer as a slave, but more than a slave, a beloved brother, especially to me, but how much more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord. </verse>
    <verse num="17">If therefore you consider me a partner, receive him as <transChange type="added">you would</transChange> me.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But if in anything he has caused you loss or owes <transChange type="added">you anything</transChange>, {charge this to my account}<note>Literally "this to me charge to <transChange type="added">my</transChange> account"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="19">I, Paul, write <transChange type="added">this</transChange> with my <transChange type="added">own</transChange> hand: I will pay it back, lest I mention to you that {you owe me even your very self besides}<note>Literally "even yourself to me you owe besides"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Yes, brother, I ought to have some benefit of you in the Lord; refresh my heart in Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="21">Confident of your obedience, I am writing to you <transChange type="added">because I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know that you will do even beyond what I say.</verse>
    <verse num="22">At the same time also, prepare a guest room for me, for I hope that through your prayers I will be restored to you. </verse>
    <verse num="23">Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus, greets you,</verse>
    <verse num="24"><transChange type="added">and so do</transChange> Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> Luke, my fellow workers.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with your spirit.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>