<book num="Hab">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The oracle that Habakkuk the prophet saw.</verse>
    <verse num="2">O Yahweh, how long shall I cry for help and you will not listen? <transChange type="added">How long</transChange> will I cry out to you, "Violence!" and you will not save?</verse>
    <verse num="3">Why do you cause me to see evil <transChange type="added">while</transChange> you look at trouble? Destruction and violence happen before me; contention and strife arise.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Therefore the law is paralyzed, and justice does not go forth perpetually.<note>Or "forever"</note> For the wicked surround the righteous; therefore justice goes forth perverted.</verse>
    <verse num="5">"Look among the nations and see; be astonished and astounded. For a work <transChange type="added">is about to</transChange> be done in your days that you will not believe if it is told.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For look! I am raising up the Chaldeans, the bitter and impetuous nation, the one who walks through the spacious places of earth to take possession of dwellings not belonging to it.<note>Or "him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">They<note>Hebrew "He"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> dreadful and awesome; their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> justice and their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> dignity proceed from themselves.<note>Hebrew "him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Their<note>Hebrew "His"</note> horses <transChange type="added">are</transChange> more swift than leopards; they are more menacing than wolves <transChange type="added">at</transChange> dusk. Their<note>Hebrew "His"</note> horsemen gallop; their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> horsemen come from afar; they fly like an eagle <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> swift to devour.</verse>
    <verse num="9">All of them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> come for violence, their faces pressing forward. They gather captives like the sand.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And they themselves scoff at kings and rulers <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a joke to them. They laugh at every fortification, and they heap up earth and take it.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then they sweep <transChange type="added">like the</transChange> wind and pass on; they become guilty, whose might <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> god!"</verse>
    <verse num="12">Are you not from of old, O Yahweh my God, my Holy One? You<note>Hebrew "we shall not die," considered a deliberate scribal change of the text to avoid offensive language toward Yahweh</note> shall not die. O Yahweh, you have marked them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> for judgment; O Rock, you have established them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> for reproof.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Your eyes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> too pure to see evil, and you are not able to look at wrongdoing.<note>Or "trouble"</note> Why do you look at the treacherous? <transChange type="added">Why</transChange> are you silent when the wicked swallows up <transChange type="added">someone</transChange> more righteous than him?</verse>
    <verse num="14">You make humankind like fish of the sea, like crawling creatures that have no ruler among them.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He brings up all of them with a fishhook; he drags them up with a fishnet; he gathers them in his dragnet. Therefore, he rejoices and exults.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Therefore he sacrifices to his fishnet and makes offerings to his dragnet, for by them {he makes a good living}<note>Literally "his portion is fat"</note> and his food <transChange type="added">is</transChange> rich.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Will he therefore empty his fishnet and continually kill nations without showing mercy?</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">I will stand at my post, and station myself on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rampart. And I will keep watch to see what he will say to me, and what he will answer concerning my complaint.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Then Yahweh answered me and said, "Write <transChange type="added">the</transChange> vision and make <transChange type="added">it</transChange> plain on the tablet so that {it might be read quickly}.<note>Literally "it might run reading upon it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">For <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> yet a vision for the appointed time; it will give witness to the end, and it will not lie. If it tarries, wait for it, for it will surely come and not delay.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Look! His spirit within him is puffed up; it is not upright. But the righteous shall live by his faithfulness.</verse>
    <verse num="5">{How much less}<note>Literally "And moreover because"</note> the defiant;<note>"Defiant" follows the Dead Sea Scrolls (1QpHab)</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> arrogant, treacherous man? He who broadens his throat like Sheol, and who, like death, is not satisfied, and who gathers to himself all the nations, and harvested for himself all the peoples, will not succeed.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Shall not all of these take up a taunt against him, with ridicule and riddles against him, saying, 'Woe to him who heaps up what is not his'? <transChange type="added">For</transChange> how long? And, '<transChange type="added">Woe to him</transChange> who makes himself heavy with pledges'?</verse>
    <verse num="7">Will not your creditors suddenly rise up and awaken those who make you tremble? Then you shall be as plunder for them.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Because you plundered many nations, all the remaining nations will plunder you on account of the blood of humanity and violence <transChange type="added">against the</transChange> land, <transChange type="added">and against</transChange> cities and all who live in them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Woe to <transChange type="added">him who</transChange> obtains profit <transChange type="added">from</transChange> evil gain for his house, to set his nest on high, to be saved from the hand of misfortune!</verse>
    <verse num="10">You have plotted shame for your house, cutting off many peoples and sinning against your life.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For the stone will cry out from the wall, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> plaster from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wood will answer it.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Woe to <transChange type="added">him who</transChange> builds a city by bloodguilt, and <transChange type="added">who</transChange> founds a city by wickedness!</verse>
    <verse num="13">Look! <transChange type="added">Is it</transChange> not from Yahweh of hosts that people labor for mere fire, and nations exhaust themselves for mere vanity?</verse>
    <verse num="14">For the earth will be filled with the knowledge of the glory of Yahweh, like the waters covering the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Woe to <transChange type="added">him who</transChange> gives a drink to his neighbors, pouring out your wrath and also making <transChange type="added">them</transChange> drunk in order to see their nakedness!</verse>
    <verse num="16">You will be sated with shame rather than glory. Drink also yourself, and expose yourself! The cup of the right hand of Yahweh will come around upon you and disgrace upon your glory.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For <transChange type="added">the</transChange> violence of Lebanon will cover you, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> destruction of wild animals will shatter them on account of the blood of humanity, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> violence <transChange type="added">against the</transChange> land, <transChange type="added">against</transChange> a city and all the inhabitants in it.</verse>
    <verse num="18">What value <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an idol when its carver has fashioned it, a molten idol, a teacher of lies? For <transChange type="added">he who</transChange> fashioned his creation trusts in it, <transChange type="added">though</transChange> making mute idols!</verse>
    <verse num="19">Woe to <transChange type="added">him who</transChange> says to the wood, 'Wake up!' <transChange type="added">And</transChange> to a lifeless stone, 'Arise!' Can he teach? Look, it is covered <transChange type="added">with</transChange> gold and silver, and there is no breath within it.</verse>
    <verse num="20">But Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in his holy temple. Let all the earth be silent before him."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">A prayer of Habakkuk the prophet, according to Shigionoth.</verse>
    <verse num="2">O Yahweh, I have heard the report of you; O Yahweh, I stand in awe of your works. In the midst of the years, revive it! In the midst of the years, make <transChange type="added">it</transChange> known! In wrath, may you remember to show compassion.</verse>
    <verse num="3">God came from Teman; the Holy One from Mount Paran. Selah His splendor covers the heavens, and his praise fills the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And his brightness was like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> light; flashing rays <transChange type="added">came</transChange> from his hand for him; And there <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the covering of his strength.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Before him went Disease,<note>The Hebrew term is also the name of a Canaanite deity</note> and Pestilence<note>The Hebrew term is also the name of a Canaanite deity</note> went out at his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="6">He stood and measured the earth; he looked and made the nations tremble. Then the mountains of old were shattered; the hills of old collapsed. The ways of old belong to him.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Under affliction I saw the tents of Cushan; the tent curtains of the land of Midian trembled.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Was the anger of Yahweh against the rivers? Was your wrath against the rivers, or your fury against the sea, when you mounted upon your horses, upon your victory chariot?</verse>
    <verse num="9">You laid bare the nakedness of your bow, swearing oaths <transChange type="added">with the</transChange> arrows of <transChange type="added">your</transChange> word. You split the earth <transChange type="added">with</transChange> rivers.</verse>
    <verse num="10"><transChange type="added">When the</transChange> mountains saw you they writhed; a torrent of waters swept by; the deep gave its voice; it raised its hands on high.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Sun <transChange type="added">and</transChange> moon stood still in <transChange type="added">their</transChange> place; at the light of your arrows they moved about; at the gleam of the flashing of your spear.</verse>
    <verse num="12">In fury you marched through <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth; in anger you trampled the nations.</verse>
    <verse num="13">You went forth for the salvation of your people, for the salvation of your anointed. You crushed the head of the house of wickedness, laying bare <transChange type="added">from the</transChange> foundation to the top.<note>Or "to the neck"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">You pierced the head of his warriors with his own arrows; they came like a whirlwind to scatter me, their exultation like <transChange type="added">one who</transChange> devours the afflicted in ambush.</verse>
    <verse num="15">You trampled upon the sea <transChange type="added">with</transChange> your horses, the churning of many waters.</verse>
    <verse num="16">I hear and my stomach shakes; my lips quiver at the sound; infection enters my bones; that which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> beneath me trembles; I wait quietly for the day of trouble to come upon the people attacking us.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Though the fig tree <transChange type="added">does</transChange> not blossom, nor there be fruit on the vines; the yield of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> olive tree fails, and the cultivated fields do not yield food; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> flock is cut off from the animal pen, and there is no cattle in the stalls,</verse>
    <verse num="18">Yet I will rejoice in Yahweh; I will exult in the God of my salvation.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Yahweh, my Lord, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my strength; he makes my feet like the deer; he causes me to walk on my high places. To the choirmaster with stringed instruments.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>