<book num="Hos">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The word of Yahweh that came to Hosea son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, the kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="2">{At the beginning when Yahweh spoke}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">At</transChange> the beginning of the talking of Yahweh"</note> through Hosea, Yahweh said to Hosea, "Go, take for yourself a wife and children of whoredom, because the land commits great whoredom {forsaking Yahweh}."<note>Literally "from behind Yahweh"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">So he went and took Gomer daughter of Diblaim, and she conceived and bore him a son.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Yahweh said to him, "{Name him}<note>Literally "Call his name"</note> Jezreel;<note>Jezreel means "God sows"</note> because in a little while {I will punish}<note>Literally "I will visit sin upon"</note> the house of Jehu<note>Or "the dynasty of Jehu"</note> for the blood<note>Or "bloodshed"</note> of Jezreel,<note>Jezreel means "God sows"</note> and I will put an end to the kingdom of the house of Israel.<note>Or "the dynasty of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">{On that day}<note>Literally "And it will happen on that day"</note> I will break the bow of Israel in the Valley of Jezreel."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And she conceived again and bore a daughter, and he<note>Yahweh</note> said to him, </verse>
    <verse num="7">But I will have pity <transChange type="added">on</transChange> the house of Judah and I will save them by Yahweh their God, and will not deliver them by bow, sword, war, horses, or horsemen.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And when she had weaned Lo-ruhamah,<note>Lo-ruhamah means "Not pitied"</note> she conceived and bore a son.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And he<note>Yahweh</note> said, "{Name him}<note>Literally "Call his name"</note> Lo-ammi,<note>Lo-ammi means "not my people"</note> for you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not my people and I am not your <transChange type="added">God</transChange>.<note>Hebrew "not yours"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10"><note>Hosea 1:10-2:23 in the English Bible is 2:1-25 in the Hebrew Bible</note> The number of the children of Israel will be like the sand of the sea that cannot be measured or counted; and in the place where it is said to them, "You are not my people," it will be said to them, "Children of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> living God."</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then the children of Judah and Israel will be gathered together, and they will appoint for themselves one head; and {they will take possession of}<note>Literally "they will go up from"</note> the land, for great <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the day of Jezreel.<note>Jezreel means "God sows"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Say to your brother,<note>Hebrew "brothers"</note> "Ammi,"<note>Ammi means "My people"</note> and to your sister,<note>Hebrew "sisters"</note> "Ruhamah."<note>Ruhamah means "Pitied"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Plead with your mother, plead-- because she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not my wife, and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> not her husband. Let her put away her whoring {from before her},<note>Literally "from her face"</note> and her adultery from between her breasts.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Lest I strip her naked and expose her like the day when she was born; I will make her like the desert and turn her into parched land; I will kill her with thirst.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And I will not have pity on her children, because <transChange type="added">they are</transChange> children of whoredom.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Because their mother was unfaithful;<note>Or "their mother played the whore"</note> she who conceived them has acted shamefully, for she said: "I will go after my lovers, the ones who give <transChange type="added">me</transChange> my bread, my water, my wool, and my flax, my oil, and my drink."</verse>
    <verse num="6">Therefore, Look! I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> going to hedge her path<note>Hebrew "your path"</note> {with thorns},<note>Literally "with the thorns"</note> and I will build a stone wall, a stone wall <transChange type="added">against</transChange> her, and she will not find her paths.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then she will pursue {her lovers},<note>Literally "the ones who love her"</note> but she will not overtake them; she will seek them and not find <transChange type="added">them</transChange>; and she will say, "I will go and return to my first husband because <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> better for me then than now."</verse>
    <verse num="8">But she did not know that <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> I who gave her grain, new wine, and oil, and who gave her silver in abundance, and gold which they made into a Baal.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Therefore I will take again my grain in its time, and my wine in its season; and I will take away my wool and my flax, <transChange type="added">which were</transChange> to cover her nakedness.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And now I will uncover her nakedness before the eyes of her lovers, and no one will rescue her from my hand.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And I will put an end to all her mirth, her festivals,<note>Hebrew "festival"</note> her new moons,<note>Hebrew "new moon"</note> and her Sabbaths,<note>Hebrew "Sabbath"</note> and all her appointed festivals;<note>Hebrew "festival"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">and I will lay waste to her vines<note>Hebrew "vine"</note> and her fig trees,<note>Hebrew "fig tree"</note> of which she said, "They <transChange type="added">are</transChange> my payment for prostitution, which my lovers gave to me." I will make them a forest, and the wild animals<note>Hebrew "animal"</note> of the field will devour them.</verse>
    <verse num="13">{I will punish her}<note>Literally "To visit sins upon her;" see 1:4</note> <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the days of the Baals, to whom she burns incense, and she decked herself <transChange type="added">with</transChange> her ornamental ring and jewelry, and she went after her lovers, and forgot me --a declaration of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Therefore, Look! I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> going to allure her and bring her <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the desert, and {I will speak tenderly to her}.<note>Literally "I will speak to her heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">From there I will give her her vineyards, and the Valley of Achor as a doorway of hope. And there she will respond, as <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the days of her youth, just as <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the day of her coming out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
    <verse num="16">{And on that day}--<note>Literally, "And it will happen on that day"</note> a declaration of Yahweh-- you will call me, "My husband;"<note>Hebrew "Ishi"</note> you will no longer call me, "My Baal."<note>Hebrew "Baali"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">I will remove the names of the Baals from her mouth, and they will no longer be mentioned by their name.</verse>
    <verse num="18">I will make a covenant for them on that day, with the animals<note>Hebrew "animal"</note> of the field, with the birds<note>Hebrew "bird"</note> of the heaven, and <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the creeping things<note>Hebrew "creeping thing"</note> of the ground; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> bow, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> war I will abolish from the land, and I will let them lie down in safety.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And I will take you as my wife forever; I will take you as a wife for myself in righteousness and in justice, in steadfast love and in mercy.</verse>
    <verse num="20">{I will take you as my wife}<note>Literally "I will take you as a wife to me"</note> in faithfulness, and you will know Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="21">On that day I will answer, {declares Yahweh},<note>Literally "a declaration of Yahweh</note> I will answer the heavens, and they will answer the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And the earth will answer the grain, the wine, and the oil, and they will answer Jezreel.<note>Jezreel means "God sows"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">I will sow her for myself in the land; I will have pity on Lo-ruhama;<note>Lo-ruhama means "Not pitied"</note> I will say to Lo-ammi,<note>Lo-ammi means "Not my people"</note> "You are my people," and he himself will say, "<transChange type="added">you are</transChange> my God."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">And Yahweh said to me again, "Go, love a woman {who has a lover}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">who is</transChange> beloved of a friend"</note> and <transChange type="added">is</transChange> committing adultery, just like the love of Yahweh <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the children of Israel, but they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> turning to other gods and love raisin cakes."</verse>
    <verse num="2">So I bought her for fifteen shekels of silver and a homer of barely and a measure of wine.<note>Hebrew "a measure of barley"; the LXX has "a nebel of wine," although some modern translations, e.g. NASB, have "a homer and a half of barley"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And I said to her, "{You must remain as mine}<note>Literally "You must sit <transChange type="added">at home</transChange> for me"</note> for many days, and you will not play the whore; {you will not belong}<note>Literally "you will not be"</note> to a man, and I <transChange type="added">will</transChange> belong to you."</verse>
    <verse num="4">The children of Israel will remain for many days without a king and prince, without sacrifice and stone pillar, ephod and teraphim.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Afterward the children of Israel will return and seek Yahweh their God and David their king. They will come in fear to Yahweh and to his goodness at the end of days.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Hear the word of Yahweh, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> children of Israel, for Yahweh has an indictment against the inhabitants of the land. There is no faithfulness or loyalty, there is no knowledge of God in the land.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Swearing and lying, murdering and stealing, and adultery break out,<note>The LXX adds "and adultery breaks out in the land"</note> and bloodshed follows bloodshed.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Therefore the land mourns, and all <transChange type="added">those</transChange> living in it languish with the animals of the field, and the birds of the heaven, and even the fish of the sea are being swept away.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Yet, let no one contend, and let no one accuse, for with you, O priest, <transChange type="added">is my</transChange> contention.<note>The Hebrew is unclear; the NASB translates "For your people are like those who contend with the priest"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">You will stumble <transChange type="added">by</transChange> day, and the priest also will stumble with you at night. And I will destroy your mother;</verse>
    <verse num="6">My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge; because you have rejected knowledge, I reject you from acting as a priest for me.<note>Or "to me"</note> And since you have forgotten the law of your God, I will also forget your children.<note>Hebrew "sons"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">When they became many, their sin increased against me; they changed<note>Hebrew uncertain; MT "I will exchange"</note> their glory into shame.</verse>
    <verse num="8">{They feed on the sin of my people},<note>Literally "They eat the sins of my people"</note> {they are greedy}<note>Literally "they lift up their throat"</note> for their iniquity.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And it will be like people, like priest; I will punish them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> <transChange type="added">for</transChange> their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> ways, and I will requite them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> for their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> deeds.</verse>
    <verse num="10">They will eat and not be satisfied; they will play the whore and not multiply, because they have forsaken Yahweh {to devote themselves to</verse>
    <verse num="11">whoredom}.<note>Literally "to watch over whoredom"</note> Wine and new wine {take away the understanding}.<note>Literally "take away heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">My people, consult {their wooden idols},<note>Literally "their wood"</note> and their divining rod gives them oracles; because a spirit of whoredom led <transChange type="added">them</transChange> astray, and they played the whore from under their God.<note>That is, "they played the whore forsaking their God"; See Ezek 23:5</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">On the tops of the mountains they sacrifice, and on the hills they make offerings, under oak, poplar, and terebinth, because their<note>Hebrew "its"</note> shade is good. Therefore your daughters play the whore, and all your daughters-in-law<note>Or "brides"</note> commit adultery.</verse>
    <verse num="14">{I will not punish your daughters}<note>Literally "I will not visit sins upon your daughters"</note> when they play the whore, or your daughters-in-law<note>Or "brides"</note> when they commit adultery; because they go aside with whores, and they sacrifice with temple prostitutes, a people that does not understand comes to ruin.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Even though you, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel, <transChange type="added">are</transChange> playing the whore, do not let Judah become guilty; do not enter Gilgal, or go up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Beth-aven; and do not swear, "{As Yahweh lives}!"<note>Literally "the life of Yahweh"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">Indeed, like a stubborn heifer, Israel is stubborn; Now Yahweh will feed them, like a lamb in broad pasture.<note>Or "Can Yahweh feed them, like a lamb in broad pasture?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">Ephraim is joined to idols; let him alone.</verse>
    <verse num="18">When their drinking has ended, they surely indulge in sexual orgies. They love lewdness more than their<note>Hebrew "her"</note> glory.</verse>
    <verse num="19">A wind has wrapped them<note>Hebrew "her"</note> in its wings, and they will be ashamed because of their altars.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">Hear this, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> priests! Give heed, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> house of Israel! Listen, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> house of the king! Because the judgment <transChange type="added">applies</transChange> to you; because you have been a snare for Mizpah, and a net spread out on Tabor;</verse>
    <verse num="2">they dug a deep pit<note>Hebrew uncertain</note> <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Shittim, but I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a punishment for all of them.</verse>
    <verse num="3">I myself know Ephraim, and Israel is not hidden from me; because now you have played the whore, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Ephraim-- Israel is defiled.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Their deeds do not permit them to return them to God. Because a spirit of whoredom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in their midst, they do not know Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The pride of Israel testifies {against him},<note>Literally "against his face;" see 7:10</note> and Israel and Ephraim stumble in their guilt, and Judah stumbles with them.</verse>
    <verse num="6">With their flocks<note>Hebrew "flock"</note> and herds<note>Hebrew "herd"</note> they will go to seek Yahweh, but they will not find him; he has withdrawn from them.</verse>
    <verse num="7">They have dealt faithlessly with Yahweh because they have borne illegitimate children. Now <transChange type="added">the</transChange> new moon will devour them with their fields.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Blow the {horn}<note>Hebrew "shofar"</note> in Gibeah, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trumpet in Ramah. Sound the alarm <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Beth-aven; <transChange type="added">look</transChange> behind you, Benjamin.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Ephraim will be a desolation in the day of punishment; among the tribes of Israel I will reveal what is true.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The princes of Judah have become like those who remove a landmark; on them I will pour out my wrath like water.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Ephraim is oppressed, crushed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> judgment, because he was determined to go after filth.<note>Hebrew uncertain; another possible translation is "that he follows human commands"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">But I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> like a maggot to Ephraim and like rottenness to the house of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And <transChange type="added">when</transChange> Ephraim saw his illness, and Judah his wound, Ephraim went to Assyria, he sent to the great king.<note>Some translate literally "King Jareb" (see the NASB, NKJV)</note> But he was unable to cure you and heal your wound.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Because I <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> like a lion to Ephraim and like a fierce strong lion to the house of Judah. I myself will tear and I will go; I will carry off, and there is no one who delivers.</verse>
    <verse num="15">{I will return again}<note>Literally "I will go, I will return"</note> to my place until they acknowledge <transChange type="added">their</transChange> guilt and seek my face; in their distress they will search<note>Or "they will beg favor of"</note> me.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Come, let us return to Yahweh; because <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> he who has torn, and he will heal us; he has struck us down and will bind us up.</verse>
    <verse num="2">He will revive us after two days; on the third day he will raise us up, that we may live in his presence.<note>Or "before his face"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Let us know, let us press on to know Yahweh; his rising <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sure like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> dawn. He will come like the showers to us, like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> spring rain that waters <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth.</verse>
    <verse num="4">What will I do with you, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Ephraim? What will I do with you, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Judah? Your love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a morning cloud, like the dew that goes away early in the morning.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Therefore, I have hewn <transChange type="added">them</transChange> by <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prophets; I have killed them by the words of my mouth, and my judgment<note>Hebrew "your judgments"</note> goes forth like the light.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Because I desire steadfast love and not sacrifice, and knowledge of God rather than burnt offerings.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But like Adam, they transgressed <transChange type="added">the</transChange> covenant; there they dealt faithlessly with me.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Gilead <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a city of evil, a cunning <transChange type="added">city</transChange> because of blood.<note>The Hebrew is difficult; NRSV translates "tracked with blood"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Like bandits lying in wait, <transChange type="added">so is</transChange> a band of priests; they murder <transChange type="added">on the</transChange> road to Shechem; indeed, they commit a monstrous crime.</verse>
    <verse num="10">In the house of Israel I have seen something horrible; Ephraim's unfaithfulness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> there. Israel is defiled.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For you also, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Judah, a harvest is appointed, when I restore the fortunes of my people,</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">when I would heal Israel, and the corruption of Ephraim is revealed, and the wicked deeds of Samaria; because they deal <transChange type="added">in</transChange> falsehood, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> thief breaks in,<note>Or "comes in"</note> <transChange type="added">and the</transChange> bandit raids the outside.</verse>
    <verse num="2">{But they did not consider}<note>Literally "But they did not say to their heart"</note> that I remember all their wickedness. Now their deeds surround them; they are before my face.</verse>
    <verse num="3">By their wickedness they make <transChange type="added">the</transChange> king glad, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> officials by their treacheries.</verse>
    <verse num="4">All of them commit adultery, like a burning oven whose baker has stopped from stirring the fire, and from kneading <transChange type="added">the</transChange> dough until it is leavened.</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">On</transChange> the day of our king, the princes became sick <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the heat of wine;<note>This phrase refers to the effects of wine on the body</note> he stretched out his hand with mockers.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Because they are kindled<note>Hebrew "they drew near;" other ancient translations read "they are kindled"</note> like an oven, their heart burns within them; all night their anger {smolders},<note>Literally "sleeps"</note> <transChange type="added">in the</transChange> morning it blazes like a flaming fire.</verse>
    <verse num="7">All of them are hot as an oven, and they devour<note>Or "they eat"</note> their rulers. All their kings have fallen; there is none who calls to me amongst them.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Ephraim mixes himself with the nations; Ephraim is a bread cake not turned over.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Foreigners devour<note>Or "Foreigners eat"</note> his strength, and he does not know <transChange type="added">it</transChange>; {mold}<note>Literally "grey hair," but in this case the word refers to the "hairs of mold" on food</note> is also sprinkled upon him, and he does not know <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The pride of Israel {testifies against him}<note>Literally "answers against his face"</note>-- they do not return to Yahweh their God; they do not seek him for all of this.<note>Or "in all of this"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Ephraim was like a dove, silly, {without sense};<note>Literally "without heart"</note> they call <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Egypt, they go <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Assyria.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Just as they go, I will cast my net over them; I will bring them down like the birds<note>Hebrew "bird"</note> of the heavens;<note>Or "sky"</note> I will discipline them according to a report to their assembly.<note>Hebrew uncertain</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">Woe to them, because they have strayed from me! Destruction to them, because they have rebelled against me! I myself would redeem them, but they speak lies against me.</verse>
    <verse num="14">They do not cry out to me from their heart, but they wail on their beds; because of grain and new wine they lacerate<note>Or "gash"</note> themselves; they depart from me.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And I myself trained and strengthened their arms; but they plan evil against me.</verse>
    <verse num="16">They turn, not to the Most High,<note>Hebrew uncertain; the NRSV translates "to that which does not profit"; the NASB translates "but not upward"</note> like a slack bow; their officials will fall by the sword because of the anger of their tongue. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their scorn<note>The NRSV translates "So much for their babbling"</note> in the land of Egypt.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1"><transChange type="added">Put</transChange> to your lips <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trumpet like a vulture over the house of Yahweh, because they have {broken my covenant}<note>Literally "transgressed my covenant"</note> and rebelled against my law.</verse>
    <verse num="2">They cry out to me, "My God! We, Israel, know you!"</verse>
    <verse num="3">Israel has spurned <transChange type="added">the</transChange> good; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> enemy will pursue him.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They appointed kings, but not through me; they made officials, but without my knowledge. <transChange type="added">With</transChange> their silver and gold they made idols for themselves for their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> own {destruction}.<note>Literally "cut off"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">Your calf is rejected,<note>Hebrew "he rejects" or "has rejected you"</note> <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Samaria; my anger burns against them. How long<note>Hebrew "Until when"</note> will they be incapable of innocence?</verse>
    <verse num="6">Because <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> from Israel, an artisan made it, it <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not a god; for the calf of Samaria will be broken <transChange type="added">to</transChange> pieces.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Because they sow the wind, they will reap the whirlwind. <transChange type="added">The</transChange> standing grain does not have heads;<note>Hebrew "head"</note> it will not yield flour. <transChange type="added">And</transChange> if it would yield, strangers would devour it.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Israel is swallowed up; now they are among the nations, like an object that no one desires.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For they have gone up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Assyria, a wild donkey alone to itself; Ephraim has sold itself <transChange type="added">for</transChange> lovers.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Even though they have sold themselves to the nations, now I will gather them. They will soon writhe from the burden of kings<note>Hebrew "king"</note> and princes.</verse>
    <verse num="11">When Ephraim multiplied altars to expiate sins, they became to him altars to sin <transChange type="added">on</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="12">I write for him myriads of my instruction;<note>Or "my law"</note> they are regarded as a strange thing.</verse>
    <verse num="13">They offer sacrifices of my choice<note>Hebrew uncertain; or "loved ones"</note> and they eat flesh; Yahweh does not accept them. Now he will remember their iniquity and punish their sins; they will return <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Egypt.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Israel has forgotten his maker and built palaces, and Judah has multiplied fortified cities; but I will send fire on his cities and it will devour her strongholds.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">Do not rejoice, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel, do not exult like the nations! For you played the whore, departing from your God; you loved a harlot's wage on all the threshing floors of grain.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Threshing floor and wine vat will not feed them, and new wine will fail her.<note>That is, Israel</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">They will not remain in the land of Yahweh. But Ephraim will return <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Egypt, and in Assyria they will eat unclean food.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They will not pour <transChange type="added">drink offerings of</transChange> wine to Yahweh, and their sacrifices will not please him. <transChange type="added">They are</transChange> like mourners' bread for them; all those who eat it will be defiled. For their bread will be {for their hunger};<note>Literally "for their soul"</note> it will not come <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="5">What will you do on the day of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appointed time, and on the day of the festival of Yahweh?</verse>
    <verse num="6">For look! <transChange type="added">If</transChange> they flee from the destruction, Egypt will gather them; Memphis<note>Hebrew "Noph"</note> will bury them. Nettles will possess their precious things of silver; thorns <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> in their tents.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The days of punishment have come; the days of retribution have come; Israel knows! The prophet <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fool, the man of the spirit <transChange type="added">is</transChange> acting like a madman. Because of the greatness of your sin, <transChange type="added">your</transChange> hostility <transChange type="added">is</transChange> great.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The prophet keeps watch <transChange type="added">over</transChange> Ephraim for my God; the snare of a fowler <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on all his ways, and hostility in the house of his God.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{They deeply corrupted themselves}<note>Literally "They made deep, they corrupted themselves"</note> as <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the days of Gibeah; he will remember their sin, he will punish their sins.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Like the grapes in the wilderness, I found Israel. Like early ripened fruit on the fig tree in the first season,<note>Or "in the beginning"</note> I saw your ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note> They themselves came <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Baal Peor, and they consecrated themselves to shame. And they became detestable things, like {the thing they love}.<note>Literally "like loving things"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Ephraim's glory <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a bird; it will fly away-- no birth, no pregnancy, and no conception.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Even though they bring up their children, I will bereave them before maturity.<note>Or "until no one is left"</note> Woe to them indeed, when I depart from them!</verse>
    <verse num="13">Ephraim, as I see <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a palm in a meadow; but Ephraim must bring out his children to the slayer.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Give them, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Yahweh-- what will you give <transChange type="added">them</transChange>? Give them a miscarrying womb and dry breasts.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Every evil of theirs <transChange type="added">began</transChange> at Gilgal, so I <transChange type="added">began</transChange> to hate them there; because of the evil of their deeds I will drive them out from my house. I will love them no more; all their officials <transChange type="added">are</transChange> rebels.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Ephraim is stricken, their root is dried up, they shall not bear fruit. Even if they give birth, I will kill the cherished offspring of their womb.</verse>
    <verse num="17">My God will reject them because they did not listen to him, and they will be wanderers among the nations.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">Israel <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a luxuriant vine;<note>Or "ravaged vine"</note> he yields fruit for himself. The more his fruit increased, <transChange type="added">the more</transChange> he made numerous altars. The more his land prospered, <transChange type="added">the more</transChange> he<note>Hebrew "they"</note> improved<note>Or "made beautiful"</note> <transChange type="added">his</transChange> stone pillars.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Their heart is false; now they must bear <transChange type="added">their</transChange> guilt. He himself<note>That is, "Yahweh himself"</note> will break down their altars; he will destroy their stone pillars.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For now they will say, "We have no king; indeed, we did not fear Yahweh, and what can a king do for us?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">They utter words of vain oaths <transChange type="added">when</transChange> {making covenants},<note>Literally "cutting covenant"</note> and judgment blossoms like a poisonous plant on the furrows of the field.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The inhabitants<note>Hebrew "inhabitant"</note> of Samaria tremble for the calf<note>Hebrew "calves"</note> of Beth-aven. Indeed, his people will mourn for it, and his idolatrous priests will wail<note>Or "rejoice"</note> over it-- over its glory because it has departed from it.</verse>
    <verse num="6">It will also be brought to Assyria, <transChange type="added">as</transChange> tribute to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> great king.<note>See 5:13; some translate literally "King Jareb"</note> Ephraim will obtain disgrace and Israel will be ashamed from his advice.<note>Or "counsel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Samaria will be destroyed; her king <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a chip on the surface of the water.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The high places of Aven, the sin of Israel, will be destroyed. Thorn and thistle will grow on their altars. They will say to the mountains, "Cover us," and to the hills, "Fall on us."</verse>
    <verse num="9">From the days of Gibeah you have sinned, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel; there {they have remained}.<note>Literally "they stood"</note> Will not war in Gibeah overtake them against the children of evil?</verse>
    <verse num="10">In my desire<note>The LXX translates "I will come"</note> I will punish them; nations will be gathered against them when they are punished for {their double iniquities}.<note>So Qere; Masoretic Hebrew text (Kethib) "their two eyes"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Ephraim <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a trained heifer, that loved to thresh <transChange type="added">grain</transChange>, and I myself {spared}<note>Literally "passed over"</note> the fairness of her neck; I will make Ephraim break the ground, Judah will plow, Jacob must till for himself.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Sow for yourselves righteousness; {reap loyal love}.<note>Literally "reap according to loyal love"</note> Break up for yourself fallow ground; <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> time to seek Yahweh so he will come and rain righteousness upon you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">You have plowed wickedness, you have reaped injustice, you have eaten the fruit of lies,<note>Hebrew "lie"</note> because you have trusted in your strength, in the multitude of your warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The tumult of war will rise up against your people, and all your fortresses will be destroyed, as Shalman destroyed Beth-arbel; on the day of war mothers were dashed to pieces with <transChange type="added">their</transChange> children.<note>Or "upon <transChange type="added">their</transChange> children"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">So it will be done to you, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Bethel, because of the evil of your wickedness; at dawn, the king of Israel will be utterly destroyed.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">When Israel was a child, I loved him, and out of Egypt I called my son.</verse>
    <verse num="2">When I called<note>Hebrew "When they called"; the LXX and modern translations read "When I called"</note> them, they went from my face.<note>Hebrew "their face"</note> They sacrificed to the Baals, and they sacrificed to idols.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And I myself taught Ephraim to walk; I took them<note>Hebrew uncertain</note> in my<note>Hebrew "his"</note> arms, but they did not know that I healed them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">I drew them {with human ties},<note>Literally "ropes of a human"</note> with the bands of love. I was to them like one who lifted up<note>Or "like one who imposed"</note> a yoke on their jaws,<note>Or "infants to their cheeks"</note> <transChange type="added">though</transChange> I bent down to them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> let them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> eat.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He will return<note>Or "They will not return"</note> to the land of Egypt, and Assyria will be his king,<note>That is "Israel's king"</note> because they refused to return.</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> sword rages in his cities; it consumes his false prophets and devours because of their plans.</verse>
    <verse num="7">My people are bent on backsliding from me. To the Most High they call, he does not raise them at all.</verse>
    <verse num="8">How can I give you up, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Ephraim? <transChange type="added">How</transChange> can I hand you over, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel? How can I make you like Admah? <transChange type="added">How</transChange> can I treat you like Zeboiim? My heart is disturbed<note>Or "My heart is overturned"</note> within me; {all}<note>Literally "together"</note> my compassions are aroused.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{I will not execute}<note>Literally "I will not do"</note> {my fierce anger},<note>Literally "the anger of my nose"</note> I will not again destroy Ephraim; because I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> God and not a mortal,<note>Or "human"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Holy <transChange type="added">One</transChange> in your midst; and I will not come in wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="10">They will go after Yahweh; he roars like a lion. When he roars, his children will come trembling from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sea.<note>That is, "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> West"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">They will tremble like birds<note>Hebrew "bird"</note> from Egypt, and like doves<note>Hebrew "dove"</note> from the land of Assyria; and I will let them return<note>Hebrew "I will cause them to live"</note> to their homes-- a declaration of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><note>Hosea 11:12-12:14 in the English Bible is 12:1-15 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Ephraim has surrounded me with lies,<note>Hebrew "lie"</note> and the house of Israel with deceit; and Judah is still wandering with God and <transChange type="added">is</transChange> faithful to the Holy One.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">Ephraim herds <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wind<note>Or "Ephraim befriends <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wind"</note> and <transChange type="added">is</transChange> pursuing <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east wind all day long; he multiplies deception and violence and he<note>Hebrew "they"</note> {makes a treaty with Assyria},<note>Literally "cuts a covenant with Assyria"</note> and oil is brought to Egypt.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Yahweh has a quarrel<note>This word in Hebrew conveys a legal setting</note> with Judah and will punish Jacob according to his ways and repay him according to his deeds.</verse>
    <verse num="3">In the womb he deceived his brother, and in his manhood he struggled with God.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He struggled with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> angel and prevailed; he pleaded for his mercy. He met him at Bethel, and there he spoke with him.<note>Hebrew "us"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">Yahweh the God of hosts, Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his renowned name!</verse>
    <verse num="6">But you, you must return to your God; keep love and justice, and wait continually for your God.</verse>
    <verse num="7"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> trader, in his hand <transChange type="added">are</transChange> scales of deceit;<note>Or "false balances"</note> he loves to oppress.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And Ephraim said, "Surely, I am rich, I gained<note>Or "I found"</note> wealth for myself; in all my toil they have not found guilt in me that is <transChange type="added">sin</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">But I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> Yahweh your God since<note>Or "from"</note> the land of Egypt; I will make you live in tents again, like the days of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appointed festival.</verse>
    <verse num="10">I spoke to the prophets; I myself multiplied revelations<note>Hebrew "revelation"</note> and through the hand of the prophets I will destroy.</verse>
    <verse num="11">If <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Gilead <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> evil, surely they will come to nothing. In Gilgal they sacrifice bulls, also their altars will be like stone heaps on furrows of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> field.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Jacob fled <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the open field of Aram,<note>Or "the land of Aram"</note> and Israel served for a wife, and for a wife he watched over <transChange type="added">sheep</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And by a prophet Yahweh brought Israel up from Egypt, and by a prophet he<note>Israel</note> was watched over.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Ephraim has caused bitter provocation, and his Lord will {hold him responsible for his crimes}<note>Literally "will bring down on him his blood"</note> and pay back to him his insults.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">When Ephraim spoke,<note>Hebrew "speaks"</note> <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> terror; he was exalted in Israel, but he incurred guilt through Baal and died.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And now they sin again, and they make for themselves a molten idol, idols from their silver metal according to their understanding, all of them the work of skilled craftsmen. To these they say, "Sacrifice!" People are kissing bull calves.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Therefore, they will be like the morning cloud, and like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> dew of early morning going <transChange type="added">away</transChange>, like chaff swirling from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> threshing floor, or like smoke from a window.</verse>
    <verse num="4">I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> Yahweh your God since<note>Or "from"</note> the land of Egypt; you know no god except me, and no one saves besides me.</verse>
    <verse num="5">I fed you<note>So LXX; Hebrew "I knew you"</note> in the desert, in the land of drought.</verse>
    <verse num="6">When I fed them,<note>Hebrew "According to their pasture"</note> they were satisfied; they were satisfied and their heart was lifted up; therefore they forgot me.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And I will be like a lion to them; I lie in wait beside <transChange type="added">the</transChange> way, like a leopard.</verse>
    <verse num="8">I will attack them like a bear robbed of her offspring, and I will tear open the covering of their heart; there I will devour them like a lion, like an animal of the field would mutilate them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">I will destroy you,<note>Hebrew "He destroys you"</note> <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel; who will help you?<note>Hebrew "for in me, in your help"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Where now <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your king that he may save you? <transChange type="added">Where</transChange> in all your cities <transChange type="added">are</transChange> your judges, of whom you said, "Give to me a king and rulers?"</verse>
    <verse num="11">I gave you a king in my anger, and I took <transChange type="added">him</transChange> in my wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The sin of Ephraim <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wrapped up; his sin <transChange type="added">is</transChange> concealed.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The labor pains of childbirth come for him; he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an unwise son because <transChange type="added">at the</transChange> proper time, he does not present himself {at the mouth of the womb}.<note>Literally "the place where the sons burst forth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">Should I redeem them from {the power}<note>Literally "the hand"</note> of Sheol? <note>"Sheol" is a Hebrew term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the underworld</note> Should I deliver them from death? Where <transChange type="added">are</transChange> your plagues, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Death? Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your destruction, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Sheol?<note>"Sheol" is a Hebrew term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the underworld</note> Compassion is hidden from my eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Although he may flourish among reeds,<note>Hebrew "brothers"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east wind will come, a wind of Yahweh rising from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> desert; his fountain will dry up, his spring will be parched. It will plunder his treasury,<note>Or "its treasury"</note> every object of desire.</verse>
    <verse num="16"><note>Hosea 13:16-14:9 in the English Bible is 14:1-10 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Samaria will be guilty, because she has rebelled against her God; they will fall by <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword, their children will be dashed to pieces, and their pregnant women will be ripped open.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">Return to Yahweh your God, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Israel, for you have stumbled because of your sin.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Take words with you, and return to Yahweh. Say to him, "Take away all guilt; accept good, and we will offer the fruit<note>Hebrew uncertain</note> of our lips.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Assyria will not save us; we will not ride on horses,<note>Hebrew "horse"</note> and we will say no more, "Our God," to the work of our hands because in you <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fatherless child finds mercy.</verse>
    <verse num="4">I will heal their disloyalty;<note>Or "backsliding"</note> I will love them freely because my anger has turned back from them.<note>Hebrew "him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">I will be like the dew to Israel; he will blossom like the lily plant, and he will strike his roots like the <transChange type="added">trees of</transChange> Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="6">His new plant shoots will spread out; his splendor will be like the olive tree, and his scent like the <transChange type="added">trees of</transChange> Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="7">{They will again dwell}<note>Literally "They shall return, they shall dwell"</note> in my<note>Hebrew "his"</note> shadow; they will grow grain and they will blossom like the plant vine; his fame <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> like the wine of Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="8"><transChange type="added">O</transChange> Ephraim, {what have I to do}<note>Literally "what for me"</note> with idols? I myself have answered and looked after you.<note>Hebrew "him"</note> I am like a luxuriant cypress; your fruit<note>Or "your faithfulness"</note> comes from me.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wise that he can understand these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>? Who is discerning that he knows them? The ways of Yahweh <transChange type="added">are</transChange> right, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> righteous walk in them; but transgressors stumble in them.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>