<book num="2Thess">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul and Silvanus and Timothy, to the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Grace to you and peace from God the Father<note>Some manuscripts have "God our Father"</note> and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="3">We ought to give thanks to God always concerning you, brothers, just as it is fitting, because your faith is flourishing and the love of each one of you all toward one another is increasing</verse>
    <verse num="4">so that we ourselves boast in you in the churches of God about your patient endurance and faith in all your persecutions and the afflictions that you are enduring,</verse>
    <verse num="5">a proof of the righteous judgment of God, so that you may be considered worthy of the kingdom of God, on behalf of which also you are suffering,</verse>
    <verse num="6">since <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> righteous in the sight of God to pay back those who are afflicting you with affliction,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and to you who are being afflicted, rest with us at the revelation of the Lord Jesus from heaven with his powerful angels,</verse>
    <verse num="8">with burning flame<note>Some manuscripts have "with flaming fire"</note> giving punishment to those who do not know God and who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="9">who will pay the penalty <transChange type="added">of</transChange> eternal destruction, away from the presence of the Lord and from the glory of his strength,</verse>
    <verse num="10">whenever he should come to be glorified on that day by his saints and to be marveled at by all who believe, because our testimony was believed among you,</verse>
    <verse num="11">for which <transChange type="added">purpose</transChange> we also pray always for you, that you may be considered worthy of the calling of our God, and he might fulfill every desire for goodness and work of faith with power,<note>Or "by <transChange type="added">his</transChange> power"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">in order that the name of our Lord Jesus may be glorified in you, and you in him, according to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Now we ask you, brothers, concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our assembling to him,</verse>
    <verse num="2">that you not be easily shaken from your composure, nor be troubled either by a spirit or by a message or by a letter {alleged to be from us}<note>Literally "as <transChange type="added">if</transChange> by us"</note>, to the effect that the day of the Lord has arrived.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Do not let anyone deceive you in any way, for <transChange type="added">that day will not come</transChange> unless the rebellion comes first, and the man of lawlessness is revealed, the son of destruction,</verse>
    <verse num="4">who opposes and who exalts himself over every so-called god or object of worship, so that he sits down in the temple of God, proclaiming that he himself is God. </verse>
    <verse num="5">Do you not remember that <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were") which is understood as temporal</note> we were still with you, we were saying these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you?</verse>
    <verse num="6">And you know that which restrains <transChange type="added">him</transChange> now, so that he will be revealed in his own time.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For the mystery of lawlessness is at work already; only the one who now restrains<note>Or "restrains it" (referring to the "mystery of lawlessness"; or "restrains him" (referring to the "man of lawlessness" in v. 3)</note> <transChange type="added">will do so</transChange> until he is out of the way,<note>Literally "out of the midst"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">and then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will slay with the breath of his mouth, and wipe out by the appearance of his coming,</verse>
    <verse num="9">whose coming is in accordance with the working of Satan, with all power and signs and lying wonders,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and with every unrighteous deception against those who are perishing, in place of which they did not accept the love of the truth, so that they would be saved.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And because of this, God sends them {a powerful delusion}<note>Literally "a working of deceit"</note> so that they will believe the lie,</verse>
    <verse num="12">in order that all may be condemned who did not believe the truth, but delighted in unrighteousness. </verse>
    <verse num="13">But we ought to give thanks to God always concerning you, brothers <transChange type="added">dearly</transChange> loved by the Lord, because God has chosen you <transChange type="added">as</transChange> first fruits for salvation by the sanctification of the Spirit and faith in the truth,</verse>
    <verse num="14">for which <transChange type="added">purpose</transChange> he called<note>Some manuscripts have "he also called"</note> you through our gospel for the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="15">So then, brothers, stand firm and hold fast to the traditions which you were taught, whether by <transChange type="added">spoken</transChange> word or by letter from us.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Now may our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father, who has loved us and given <transChange type="added">us</transChange> eternal encouragement and good hope by grace,</verse>
    <verse num="17">encourage your hearts and strengthen <transChange type="added">you</transChange> in every good work and word. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Finally, brothers, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may progress and be honored, just as also <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> with you,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and that we may be delivered from evil and wicked people, {for not all have the faith}<note>Literally "for not of all <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the faith"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But the Lord is faithful, who will strengthen you and guard <transChange type="added">you</transChange> from the evil one.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And we have confidence in the Lord about you, that you are both doing and you will do <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> that we are commanding.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Now may the Lord direct your hearts toward the love of God and toward the patient endurance of Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="6">But we command you, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, <transChange type="added">that</transChange> you keep away from every brother who lives irresponsibly and not according to the tradition that they received from us.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For you yourselves know how it is necessary to imitate us, that we did not behave irresponsibly among you,</verse>
    <verse num="8">nor did we eat bread from anyone without paying, but with toil and labor, <transChange type="added">we were</transChange> working night and day in order not to be a burden to any of you,</verse>
    <verse num="9">not that we do not have the right, but so that we may give ourselves <transChange type="added">as</transChange> an example to you, so that <transChange type="added">you</transChange> may imitate us.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For even when we were with you, we used to command this to you: that if anyone does not want to work, neither should he eat.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For we hear <transChange type="added">that</transChange> some among you are living irresponsibly, working <transChange type="added">at</transChange> nothing, but being busybodies.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now we command and we exhort such people in the Lord Jesus Christ that, working with quietness, they eat their own bread.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But <transChange type="added">as for</transChange> you, brothers, do not be discouraged <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("doing what is right") which is understood as temporal</note> doing what is right.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But if anyone does not obey our message through this letter, take note not to associate with him, in order that he may be put to shame.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And do not consider <transChange type="added">him</transChange> as an enemy, but admonish <transChange type="added">him</transChange> as a brother. </verse>
    <verse num="16">Now may the Lord of peace himself grant you peace through everything in every way. <transChange type="added">May</transChange> the Lord <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with all of you.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The greeting <transChange type="added">is</transChange> by my hand, Paul's, which is {a sign of genuineness}<note>Literally "a sign"</note> in every letter: {this is how I write}<note>Literally "in this way I write"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with all of you. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>