<book num="Ruth">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">And it happened in the days <transChange type="added">when</transChange> {the judges ruled},<note>Literally "the judging of the judges"</note> there was a famine in the land, and a man from Bethlehem <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Judah went {to reside}<note>Literally "to dwell as an alien"</note> in the countryside of Moab--he and his wife and his two sons.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And the name of the man <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Elimelech, and the name of his wife <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Naomi, and the name<transChange type="added">s</transChange> of his two sons <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Mahlon and Kilion. <transChange type="added">They were</transChange> Ephraimites from Bethlehem <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Judah. And they went <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the countryside of Moab and remained there. </verse>
    <verse num="3">But Elimelech the husband of Naomi died and she was left behind <transChange type="added">with</transChange> {her two sons}.<note>Literally "she and her two sons"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And {they took}<note>Literally "they lifted up"</note> for themselves Moabite wives. The name of the one <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Orpah and the name of the other <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ruth. And they lived there about ten years.</verse>
    <verse num="5">But {both}<note>Literally "the two of them"</note> Mahlon and Kilion died, and the woman was left without her two sons and without her husband. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And she got up, she and her daughters-in-law, and returned from the countryside of Moab, because she had heard in the countryside of Moab that Yahweh had {come to the aid of}<note>Literally "had considered"</note> his people to give food to them.</verse>
    <verse num="7">So she set out from the place {where she was}<note>Literally "which she was there"</note> and her two daughters-in-law with her, and they went on the way to return to the land of Judah. </verse>
    <verse num="8">But Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, "Go, each <transChange type="added">of you</transChange> return to her mother's house. May Yahweh {show kindness to you}<note>Literally "do loyal love with you"</note> <transChange type="added">just</transChange> as you did with the dead and with me.</verse>
    <verse num="9">May Yahweh {grant that you}<note>Literally "give to you"</note> find a resting place, each <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the house of her husband." And she kissed them, and they lifted up their voice<transChange type="added">s</transChange> and cried. </verse>
    <verse num="10">And they said to her, "<transChange type="added">No,</transChange> we want to return with you to your people."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Naomi said, "Return, my daughters. {Why do you still want to go with me}?<note>Literally "To what do you want to go still for me?"</note> <transChange type="added">Are there</transChange> sons {in my womb}<note>Literally "in my intestines"</note> that may be husbands for you?</verse>
    <verse num="12">Turn back, my daughters! Go, for {I am too old to have a husband}.<note>Literally "I am too old from being to a man"</note> If I should think there is hope for me, even if I should have a husband <transChange type="added">this</transChange> night, and even if I should bear sons,</verse>
    <verse num="13">would you therefore wait until they were grown? Would you therefore {refrain from marrying}?<note>Literally "Would you therefore let yourself be hindered to not belong to a man?"</note> No, my daughters, for it is far more bitter to me than <transChange type="added">to</transChange> you. For the hand of Yahweh has gone out against me."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And they lifted up their voices and cried again. And Orpah kissed her mother-in-law <transChange type="added">goodbye</transChange>, but Ruth clung to her.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And she said, "Look, your sister-in-law has returned to her people and to her gods. Return after your sister-in-law <transChange type="added">too</transChange>." </verse>
    <verse num="16">But Ruth said, "{Do not urge}<note>Literally "You shall not press me"</note> me to leave you <transChange type="added">or</transChange> to return from {following you}!<note>Literally "from behind you"</note> For where you go, I will go, and where you lodge, I will lodge. Your people <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> my people and your God <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> my God.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. So may Yahweh do to me, {and even more, unless}<note>Literally "and so may he do again, that"</note> death {separates you and me}!"<note>Literally "makes a separation between you and between me"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">When Naomi</transChange> saw that she was determined to go with her, {she said no more}.<note>Literally "she ceased to speak to her"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="19"><transChange type="added">So</transChange> the two of them went until they came to Bethlehem. {And when they came}<note>Literally "And it happened at the moment of coming"</note> to Bethlehem, all of the town was stirred because of them. And they said, "<transChange type="added">Is</transChange> this Naomi?"</verse>
    <verse num="20">And she said to them, "You should not call me Naomi; call me Mara, for Shaddai<note>Often translated "the Almighty"</note> has {caused me to be very bitter}.<note>Literally "caused very bitterness to me"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">I went <transChange type="added">away</transChange> full, but Yahweh brought me back empty-handed! Why call me Naomi {when Yahweh has testified against me}<note>Literally "and Yahweh answered against me"</note> and Shaddai<note>Often translated "the Almighty"</note> has brought calamity upon me?"</verse>
    <verse num="22">So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabite her daughter-in-law with her, returning from the countryside of Moab. And they came <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Bethlehem at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> beginning of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harvest of barley. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">{Now}<note>Literally "and for"</note> Naomi {had a relative of her husband},<note>Literally "was an acquaintance of a man of her husband"</note> {a prominent rich man}<note>Literally "a man mighty of wealth"</note> from the clan of Elimelech, <transChange type="added">whose</transChange> name was Boaz.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Ruth the Moabite said to Naomi, "Please let me go <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the field and glean among the ears of grain after <transChange type="added">someone</transChange> in whose eyes I <transChange type="added">may</transChange> find favor." And she said to her, "Go, my daughter."</verse>
    <verse num="3">So she went and came and gleaned in the field behind the reapers. And she happened <transChange type="added">by</transChange> chance <transChange type="added">upon</transChange> the tract of field {belonging to}<note>Literally "was for"</note> Boaz, who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> from the clan of Elimelech.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And look, Boaz came from Bethlehem and said to the reapers, "<transChange type="added">May</transChange> Yahweh <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with you." And they said to him, "<transChange type="added">May</transChange> Yahweh bless you."</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Boaz said to his servant {in charge of the reapers},<note>Literally "the one standing over the reapers"</note> "To whom <transChange type="added">does</transChange> this young woman <transChange type="added">belong</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="6">And {the servant in charge of the reapers}<note>Literally "the servant the one standing over the reapers"</note> said, "She <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a Moabite girl returning with Naomi from the countryside of Moab.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And she said, 'Please let me glean and let me gather among the sheaves behind the reapers.' So she came and remained from the morning up to now. {She is sitting for a little while in the house}."<note>Literally "this one she is sitting a little in the house"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="8">And Boaz said to Ruth, "{Listen carefully},<note>Literally, "You have heard"</note> my daughter, go no longer to glean in another field. Moreover, do not leave from this one, but {stay close}<note>Literally "cling"</note> with my young women.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Keep your eyes on the field that they reap and go after them. Have I not ordered the servants not to bother you? And if you get thirsty, you shall go to the containers and drink from where the servants have drawn."</verse>
    <verse num="10">And she fell on her face and bowed down to the ground and said to him, "Why have I found favor in your eyes by recognizing me--for I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a foreigner?"</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Boaz answered and said to her, "All that you have done for your mother-in-law after the death of your husband was fully told to me. <transChange type="added">How</transChange> you left your father and mother and the land of your birth, and you went to a people that you did not know {before}.<note>Literally "yesterday three days ago"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">May Yahweh reward your work and may a full reward be <transChange type="added">given to</transChange> you from Yahweh, the God of Israel, under whose wings you came to take refuge."</verse>
    <verse num="13">And she said, "May I find favor in your eyes, my lord, for you have comforted me and have spoken {kindly to your servant},<note>Literally "on the heart of your servant"</note> and I am not one of your servants." </verse>
    <verse num="14">And Boaz said to her {at mealtime},<note>Literally "at the time of the food"</note> "Come here and eat from the bread and dip your morsel in the wine vinegar." So she sat beside the gleaners, and he offered to her roasted grain. And she ate and was satisfied, and she had some left over.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And she got up to glean, and Boaz instructed his servants saying, "Let her also glean between the sheaves and do not reproach her.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And also pull out for her from your bundles and leave <transChange type="added">it</transChange> so that she may glean--and do not rebuke her." </verse>
    <verse num="17">So she gleaned in the field until the evening and she beat out what she had gleaned, and it was about an ephah <transChange type="added">of</transChange> barley.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And she picked <transChange type="added">it</transChange> up and went <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the town. Her mother-in-law saw how much she had gleaned. And she took <transChange type="added">it</transChange> out and gave to her what she had left over {after being satisfied}.<note>Literally "from her satiety"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And her mother-in-law said to her, "Where did you glean {today}<note>Literally "the day"</note> and where did you work? May he <transChange type="added">who</transChange> took notice of you be blessed." And she told her mother-in-law {with whom she had worked}<note>Literally "who she had worked with him"</note> and said, "The name of the man who I worked with today <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Boaz."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Naomi said to her daughter-in-law, "<transChange type="added">May</transChange> he be blessed by Yahweh, whose loyal love has not forsaken the living or the dead." And Naomi said to her, "The man is a close relative for us, he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one of our redeemers."</verse>
    <verse num="21">And Ruth the Moabite said, "Also, he said to me, 'You shall stay close with the servants which are mine until they have finished all of the harvest which is mine.'"</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, "<transChange type="added">It is</transChange> good, my daughter, that you go out with his maidservants so that you will not {be bothered}<note>Literally "they touch on you"</note> in another field."</verse>
    <verse num="23">So she stayed close with the maidservants <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Boaz to glean until the end of the barley harvest and wheat harvest. And she lived with her mother-in-law. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Now Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, "My daughter, should I not seek for you security that <transChange type="added">things</transChange> may be good for you?</verse>
    <verse num="2">So then, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not Boaz our kinsman whose maidservants you were with? Look, he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> winnowing the barley at the threshing floor tonight.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Wash, anoint yourself, put your clothing on, and go down to the threshing floor. Do not make yourself known to the man until he finishes eating and drinking.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And when he lies, take notice of the place where he lies. And you shall go and {uncover}<note>Literally "open"</note> his feet and lie <transChange type="added">down</transChange>, and he shall tell you what to do."</verse>
    <verse num="5">And she said to her, "I will do all that you say." </verse>
    <verse num="6">And she went down to the threshing floor and did all that her mother-in-law had instructed her.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And Boaz ate and drank <transChange type="added">until</transChange> his heart was {merry}<note>Literally "good"</note> <transChange type="added">and then</transChange> he came to lie at the end of the grain heap. And she came in quietly and {uncovered}<note>Literally "opened"</note> his feet and lay down.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And it happened in the middle of the night the man was startled and he reached out and behold, a woman <transChange type="added">was</transChange> lying at his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And he said, "Who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you?" And she said, "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> Ruth, your servant. Spread {your garment}<note>Literally "your wing"</note> over your servant because you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a redeemer."</verse>
    <verse num="10">And he said, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> blessed by Yahweh my daughter. You did better <transChange type="added">in this</transChange> last kindness than the first by not going after young men, whether poor or rich.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And so then my daughter, do not be afraid. All that you ask I will do for you, for the entire assembly of my people knows that you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a worthy woman.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now truly I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a redeemer, but there is also a redeemer <transChange type="added">of a</transChange> closer relationship than me.</verse>
    <verse num="13">{Stay tonight,}<note>Literally "Spend the night tonight"</note> and in the morning, if he wants to redeem you, good; but if he is not willing to redeem, {then as Yahweh lives,}<note>Literally "the life of Yahweh"</note> I will redeem you. Lie down until the morning." </verse>
    <verse num="14">So she lay at his feet until morning and got up before {anyone could recognize each other}.<note>Literally "a man could recognize his friend"</note> And he said, "It must not be known that {you}<note>Literally "the woman"</note> came <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the threshing floor."</verse>
    <verse num="15">And he said, "Bring the cloak that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on you and {hold it out}."<note>Literally "hold on her"</note> And she held it out and he measured six <transChange type="added">measures of</transChange> barley and put it on her <transChange type="added">cloak</transChange>. Then she went <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the city.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And she came to her mother-in-law, and she said, "{How did it go for you,}<note>Literally "who are you?"</note> my daughter?" And she told her all that the man did for her.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And she said, "These six measures of barley he gave to me, for he said, 'You shall not go empty-handed to your mother-in-law.'"</verse>
    <verse num="18">And she said, "Wait, my daughter, until you know how the matter turns out, for the man will not rest but will settle the matter today." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">And Boaz had gone up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the <transChange type="added">city</transChange> gate and sat there. And look, the redeemer of whom Boaz had spoken <transChange type="added">was</transChange> passing by. And he said, "Come over here to sit, {friend}."<note>Literally "certain someone"</note> And he came over and sat.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he took ten men from the elders of the city and said, "Sit here." And they sat.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And he said to the redeemer, "Naomi, who returned from the countryside <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Moab, is selling the tract of land which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> for our brother Elimelech.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And I thought {I would tell you}<note>Literally "I would open your ear"</note> and say, '{Buy it in the presence of}<note>Literally "Buy before"</note> those sitting and before the elders of my people,' if you want to redeem <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, redeem <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. But if you do not want to redeem, tell me so that I may know, for there is no one except you to redeem <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> after you." And he said, "I want to redeem <transChange type="added">it</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Boaz said, "On the day of your acquiring the field from the hand of Naomi, you also acquire Ruth the Moabite, the wife of the dead <transChange type="added">man</transChange>, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to raise up <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the name of the dead his inheritance."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And the redeemer said, "I am not able to redeem for myself, lest I ruin my inheritance. You redeem for yourself my kinsman-redemption, for I am not able to redeem <transChange type="added">it</transChange>." </verse>
    <verse num="7">(Now this {was the custom in former times}<note>Literally "before faces"</note> in Israel concerning the kinsman-redemption and transfer of property: to confirm the matter, a man removed his sandal and gave <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to his fellow countryman. This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the manner of attesting in Israel.)</verse>
    <verse num="8">So the redeemer said to Boaz, "Acquire <transChange type="added">it</transChange> for yourself," and he removed his sandal.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Boaz said to the elders and all of the people, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> witnesses today that I have acquired all that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> for Elimelech and that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> for Kilion and Mahlon from the hand of Naomi.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And also Ruth the Moabite, the wife of Mahlon, I have acquired as a wife, to raise up the name of the dead over his inheritance, so that the name of the dead may not be cut off from his relatives and from the gate of his <transChange type="added">birth</transChange> place. You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> witnesses today."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And all of the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> at the gate and the elders said, "<transChange type="added">We are</transChange> witnesses. May Yahweh make the woman coming into your house as Rachel and as Leah, who {together}<note>Literally "the two of them"</note> built the house of Israel. May you have strength in Ephrathah and bestow a name in Bethlehem.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And may your house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah from the offspring that Yahweh will give to you from this young woman." </verse>
    <verse num="13">So Boaz took Ruth and she became his wife. And he went <transChange type="added">in</transChange> to her, and Yahweh {enabled her to conceive},<note>Literally "gave to her conception"</note> and she bore a son.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And the women said to Naomi, "Blessed be Yahweh who today {did not leave you without a redeemer}!<note>Literally "did not allow to be missing for you a redeemer"</note> And may his name be renowned in Israel!</verse>
    <verse num="15">He shall be for you a restorer of life and a sustainer in your old age, for your daughter-in-law who loves you, who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> better for you than seven sons, has borne him."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Naomi took the child and she put him on her bosom and became his nurse.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the women of the neighborhood gave him a name, saying, "A son has been born to Naomi." And they called his name Obed. He <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Jesse, the father of David. </verse>
    <verse num="18">Now these are the descendants of Perez: Perez fathered Hezron,</verse>
    <verse num="19">and Hezron fathered Ram, and Ram fathered Amminadab,</verse>
    <verse num="20">and Amminadab fathered Nahshon, and Nahshon fathered Salmon,</verse>
    <verse num="21">and Salmon fathered Boaz, and Boaz fathered Obed,</verse>
    <verse num="22">and Obed fathered Jesse, and Jesse fathered David. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>