<book num="Judg">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">After the death of Joshua, the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> inquired of Yahweh, saying, "Who will go up first for us against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> to fight against them?"</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Yahweh said, "Judah will go up. I hereby give the land into his hand."</verse>
    <verse num="3">And Judah said to Simeon his brother, "Go up with me into my allotment, and let us fight against the Canaanites; then I too will go with you into your allotment." And Simeon went with him.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Judah went up, and Yahweh gave the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> and the Perizzites<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> into their hand, and they defeated ten thousand men at Bezek.</verse>
    <verse num="5">At Bezek they came upon Adoni-bezek, and they fought against him and defeated the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> and the Perizzites.<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">And Adoni-bezek fled, but they pursued after him; they caught him and cut off {his thumbs and big toes}.<note>Literally "the thumbs of his hands and feet"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Adoni-bezek said, "Seventy kings with {their thumbs and big toes}<note>Literally "the thumbs of their hands and feet"</note> cut off used to pick up <transChange type="added">scraps</transChange> under my table; just as I have done, so God has repaid to me. And they brought him <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Jerusalem, and he died there. </verse>
    <verse num="8">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Judah fought against Jerusalem, and they captured it, {put it to the sword},<note>Literally "they struck it with the mouth of the sword"</note> and {set the city on fire}.<note>Literally "the city they sent away with fire"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Afterward the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Judah pursued to fight against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> who were living in the hill country, the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judean hills</note> and the Shephelah.<note>A geographical region associated with an area of low country on the western edge of the Judaean hills.</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">And Judah went against the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> living in Hebron (the former name of Hebron <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Kiriath Arba). And they defeated Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai. </verse>
    <verse num="11">And from there they went to the inhabitants of Debir (the former name of Debir <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Kiriath Sepher).</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Caleb said, "Whoever attacks Kiriath Sepher and captures it, I will give to him Acsah my daughter as a wife."</verse>
    <verse num="13">Othniel son of Kenaz, the younger brother of Caleb, captured it, and he gave to him Acsah his daughter as a wife.</verse>
    <verse num="14">When she came <transChange type="added">to him</transChange>, she urged him to ask her father for a field. As she dismounted from the donkey, Caleb said to her, "{What do you want}?"<note>Literally "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for you?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">And she said to him, "Give me {a gift};<note>Literally "blessing"</note> you have given me the land of the Negev,<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> and give me also a spring of water." And Caleb gave to her the upper and lower spring.<note>Judges 1:11-15 is almost identical to Joshua 15:13-19</note> </verse>
    <verse num="16">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Hobab <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Kenite, Moses' father-in-law, went up with the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Judah from the city of palms <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the wilderness of Judah, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Negev<note>An arid region south of the Judaean hills</note> <transChange type="added">near</transChange> Arad. And they went<note>Hebrew "he went"</note> and settled with the people.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Judah went with his brother Simeon, and they defeated the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> inhabiting Zephath; they utterly destroyed it, so he called the name of the city Hormah.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Judah captured Gaza and its territory, Ashkelon and its territory, and Ekron and its territory.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Yahweh was with Judah, and he took possession of the hill country, but they could not drive out the inhabitants of the plain because they <transChange type="added">had</transChange> chariots of iron.</verse>
    <verse num="20">They gave Hebron to Caleb just as Moses said, and he drove out the three sons of Anak from there.</verse>
    <verse num="21">But the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> who lived in Jerusalem, so the Jebusites have lived among the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin in Jerusalem to this day. </verse>
    <verse num="22">Likewise, the house of Joseph went up <transChange type="added">against</transChange> Bethel, and Yahweh <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with them.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And the house of Joseph spied out Bethel (the former name of the city was Luz).</verse>
    <verse num="24">And when the spies saw a man leaving the city,<note>Or "going out from the city"</note> they said to him, "Please show us the entrance of the city, and we will deal kindly<note>Or "do a loyal love"</note> with you."</verse>
    <verse num="25">So he showed them the entrance of the city, and they struck the city with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> but they let go the man and all his family.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And the man went <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the land of the Hittites, and he built a city and named it Luz; this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> its name to this day. </verse>
    <verse num="27">Manasseh did not drive out Beth-Sean and its towns, or Taanach and its towns, or the inhabitants<note>Hebrew "inhabitant"</note> of Dor and its towns, or the inhabitants of Ibleam and its towns, or the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns; the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> determined to live in this land.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And it happened, when Israel grew strong, they put the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> to forced labor, but they never totally drove them out.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Ephraim did not drive out the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> living in Gezer, so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> lived in their midst in Gezer.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Zebulun did not drive out the inhabitants of Kitron or Nahalol, so the Canaanites<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> lived in their midst and became <transChange type="added">subjected</transChange> to forced labor.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Asher did not drive out the inhabitants of Acco, Sidon, Ahlab, Aczib, Helbah, Aphik, or Rehob,</verse>
    <verse num="32">so the Asherites<note>Hebrew "Asherite"</note> lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the inhabitants of the land, for they did not drive them out. </verse>
    <verse num="33">Naphtali did not drive out the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh or Beth-anath, but lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the inhabitants of the land; the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh and Beth-anath became forced labor for them. </verse>
    <verse num="34">The Amorites pressed<note>Or "forced"</note> the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan to the hill country, and they did not allow them to come down to the plain;</verse>
    <verse num="35">the Amorites <transChange type="added">were</transChange> determined to live in Har-heres,<note>Or "Mount Heres"</note> in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim, but the hand of the house of Joseph was heavy <transChange type="added">on them</transChange>, and they became <transChange type="added">subjected</transChange> to forced labor.</verse>
    <verse num="36">The border of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> <transChange type="added">ran</transChange> from the ascent of Akrabbim from Sela and upward. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">And the angel of Yahweh went up from Gilgal to Bokim and said, "I brought you up from Egypt, and I brought you to the land that I had promised to your ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note> I said, 'I will never break my covenant with you.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And <transChange type="added">as for</transChange> you, do not {make a covenant}<note>Literally "cut a covenant"</note> with the inhabitants of this land; break down their altars.' But you did not listen to my voice. {Why would you do such a thing}?<note>Literally "What is this thing you have done?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Now I say, I will not drive them out from before you; they will {become as thorns}<note>Or "become snares;" some ancient manuscripts read "be adversaries"</note> for you, and their gods will be a trap for you."</verse>
    <verse num="4">And as the angel of Yahweh spoke these words to all the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> the people {wept bitterly}.<note>Literally "lifted up their voices and they wept"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And they called the name of this place Bokim,<note>"Bokim" means "weepers"</note> and there they sacrificed to Yahweh. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And Joshua sent the people away, and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went each to their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> own inheritance to take possession of the land.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And the people served Yahweh all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, who saw all the great work Yahweh had done for Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And Joshua son of Nun, servant of Yahweh, died {at the age of one hundred and ten years}.<note>Literally "a son of one hundred and ten years"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">They buried him within the border of his inheritance in Timnah-heres, in the hill country of Ephraim north of Mount Gaash.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Moreover, that entire generation was gathered to their<note>Hebrew "his"</note> ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> and another generation grew up after them who did not know Yahweh or the work he had done for Israel.<note>Judges 2:6-10 is repeated in Joshua 24:28-31</note> </verse>
    <verse num="11">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and {they served}<note>Or "they worshiped"</note> the Baals.</verse>
    <verse num="12">They abandoned Yahweh the God of their ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> who brought them out from the land of Egypt. They {followed}<note>Literally "went after"</note> other gods from the gods of the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> around them; and they bowed down to them, and they provoked the anger of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="13">They abandoned Yahweh, and they served Baal and the Ashtaroth.</verse>
    <verse num="14">So {the anger of Yahweh was kindled}<note>Literally "The nose of Yahweh became hot"</note> against Israel, and he gave them into the hand of plunderers; and they plundered them, and he sold them into the hand of their enemies from all sides. They were unable to withstand their enemies any longer.</verse>
    <verse num="15">{Whenever}<note>Literally "At all that"</note> they went out, the hand of Yahweh was against them to harm <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, just as Yahweh warned, and just as Yahweh had sworn to them. And {they were very distressed}.<note>Literally "it was very cramped for them"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="16">Then Yahweh raised up leaders,<note>Or "judges"</note> and they delivered them from the hand of their plunderers.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But they did not listen to their leaders,<note>Or "judges"</note> but lusted after other gods and bowed down to them. They turned away quickly from the way that their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> went, who had obeyed the commandment of Yahweh; they did not do <transChange type="added">as their ancestors</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And when Yahweh raised leaders<note>Or "judges"</note> for them, Yahweh was with the leader,<note>Or "judge"</note> and he delivered them from the hand of their enemies all the days of the leader,<note>Or "judge"</note> for Yahweh was moved by their groaning because of their persecutors and oppressors.</verse>
    <verse num="19">But when the leader<note>Or "judge"</note> died they relapsed and acted corruptly, more than their ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> following other gods, serving them,<note>Or "worshiping them"</note> and bowing down to them. They would not give up their deeds or their stubborn ways.</verse>
    <verse num="20">{So the anger of Yahweh burned}<note>Literally "So the nose of Yahweh became hot"</note> against Israel, and he said, "Because this people transgressed my covenant that I commanded their ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> and have not obeyed my voice,</verse>
    <verse num="21">I will not again drive out anyone from before them from the nations that Joshua left when he died,</verse>
    <verse num="22">in order to test Israel whether or not they would observe the way of Yahweh, to walk in it just as their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> did."</verse>
    <verse num="23">So Yahweh left those nations; he did not drive them out at once, and he did not give them into the hand of Joshua. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the nations that Yahweh left, to test Israel by them (<transChange type="added">that is, to test</transChange> all those who {had not experienced}<note>Literally "did not know"</note> any of the wars of Canaan,</verse>
    <verse num="2">in order that the generations of Israel would know war, to teach those {who had not experienced it}<note>Literally "who had not known it"</note> before):</verse>
    <verse num="3">the five rulers of the Philistines, all the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the Sidonians,<note>Hebrew "Sidonian"</note> and the Hivites<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> living on Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal Hermon up to Lebo-Hamath.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They were <transChange type="added">left</transChange> for testing Israel, to know <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> they would keep the commands of Yahweh that he commanded their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> through the hand of Moses.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> lived in the midst of the Canaanites,<note>Hebrew "Canaanite"</note> the Hittites,<note>Hebrew "Hittite"</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> the Perizzites,<note>Hebrew "Perizzite"</note> the Hivites,<note>Hebrew "Hivite"</note> and the Jebusites.<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">And they took their daughters as wives for themselves, and they gave their daughters to their sons, and they served their gods.<note>Or "worshiped their gods"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="7">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. They forgot Yahweh their God, and they served the Baals and the Asheroth.<note>Asheroth are cultic poles set up next to an altar symbolizing the goddess Asherah</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">And {the anger of Yahweh was kindled}<note>Literally "the nose of Yahweh became hot"</note> against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cushan-Rishathaim, the king of Aram Naharaim; and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> served Cushan-Rishathaim eight years.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried out to Yahweh, and Yahweh raised up a deliverer for the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> who delivered them, Othniel son of Kenaz, Caleb's younger brother.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the spirit of Yahweh came upon him, and he judged Israel. He went out to war, and Yahweh gave Cushan-Rishathaim king of Aram into his hand, and {he prevailed over}<note>Literally "his hand was strong over"</note> Cushan-Rishathaim.</verse>
    <verse num="11">So the land rested forty years. Then Othniel son of Kenaz died. </verse>
    <verse num="12">And again the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. So Yahweh strengthened Eglon king of Moab against Israel, because they did evil in the eyes of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He gathered to himself the {Ammonites and Amalekites},<note>Literally "sons of Ammon and Amalek" or "children of Ammon and Amalek"</note> and he went and defeated Israel, and they took possession of the city of palms.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> served Eglon king of Moab eighteen years. </verse>
    <verse num="15">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried out to Yahweh, and Yahweh raised up for them a deliverer, Ehud son of Gera, a Benjaminite and {a left-handed man}.<note>Literally "a man bound by his right hand"</note> And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> sent a tribute to Eglon king of Moab {through him}.<note>Literally "in his hand"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">Ehud made for himself a short, {two-edged}<note>Literally "with two mouths"</note> sword (a cubit in length), and he fastened it under his clothes on his right thigh.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Then he presented the tribute to Eglon king of Moab. Now Eglon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a very fat man.</verse>
    <verse num="18">When Ehud<note>That is, Eglon</note> had finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who carried the tribute.</verse>
    <verse num="19">But he turned back from the sculptured stones<note>Or "Pesilim"; some translations translate the phrase as a proper name</note> that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> near Gilgal, and he said, "I have {a secret message}<note>Literally "a word of secrecy"</note> for you, O king." And he<note>Hebrew "he"</note> said, "Silence!" So all those standing in his presence went out,</verse>
    <verse num="20">and Ehud came to him <transChange type="added">while</transChange> he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sitting alone in his cool upper room. And Ehud said, "I have a {message from God}<note>Literally "word of God"</note> for you." So he got up from his seat.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then Ehud reached with his left hand for the sword on his right thigh, and he thrust it into his<note>That is, Eglon's</note> stomach.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And the handle also went <transChange type="added">in</transChange> after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade because he did not draw back the sword from his stomach; and it went protruding out the back.<note>The Hebrew is uncertain; some translations have "and the dirt/entrails came out"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">And Ehud went out the vestibule, and he closed the doors of the upper room and locked <transChange type="added">them</transChange> behind him. </verse>
    <verse num="24">After he left, his servants returned. When they saw <transChange type="added">that</transChange> the doors of the upper room <transChange type="added">were</transChange> locked, {they thought},<note>Hebrew "they said"</note> "Surely he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {relieving himself}<note>Literally "covering his feet"</note> in the cool inner room."</verse>
    <verse num="25">And they waited so long they became embarrassed because he did not open the doors of the upper room. So they took the key and opened <transChange type="added">the doors</transChange>, and there their lord was lying on the ground dead. </verse>
    <verse num="26">And Ehud escaped while they delayed. He passed by the sculptured stones<note>Or "Pesilim;" some translations to translate the phrase as a proper name</note> and escaped to Seirah.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And when he arrived he sounded the trumpet in the hill country of Ephraim, and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went down from the hill country with him leading them.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And he said to them, "Follow after me! Yahweh has given Moab your enemies into your hand." So they went down after him, and they captured the fords of the Jordan toward Moab; and they did not allow anyone to cross over.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And they struck Moab at that time, about ten thousand men, {all strong and able men};<note>Literally "all fat and men of strength"</note> no one escaped.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And Moab was subdued on that day under the hand of Israel. And the land rested eighty years.<note>Hebrew "year"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="31">And Shamgar son of Anath came after him, and he killed six hundred Philistines with the goad of an ox; he also delivered Israel. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">And again the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and Ehud died.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So Yahweh sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in Hazor. The commander of his army <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Sisera, and he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> living in Harosheth Haggoyim.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried to Yahweh, as he <transChange type="added">had</transChange> nine hundred iron chariots,<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> and he oppressed the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> {cruelly}<note>Literally "with force"</note> for twenty years.<note>Hebrew "year"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="4">Now at that time Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> judging<note>Or "leading"</note> Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And she used to sit under the palm tree of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in the hill country of Ephraim; and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went up to her for judgment.</verse>
    <verse num="6">She sent and called for Barak son of Abinoam from Kedesh Naphtali and said to him, "Has not Yahweh the God of Israel commanded you? 'Go, {march to}<note>Literally "take the lead at"</note> Mount Tabor, and take ten thousand men from the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Naphtali and Zebulun.</verse>
    <verse num="7">{I will draw out}<note>Literally "I will draw to you"</note> Sisera, the commander of Jabin's army, with his chariots and troops, to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kishon, and I will give him into your hand.'"</verse>
    <verse num="8">Barak said to her, "If you go with me, I will go; but if you do not go with me, I will not go."</verse>
    <verse num="9">She said, "Surely I will go with you; however, there will be no glory for you in {the path you are taking},<note>Or "the way you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> going"</note> for Yahweh will sell Sisera into <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hand of a woman." And Deborah stood up and went with Barak to Kedesh.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Barak summoned Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh; and {they went up behind him},<note>Literally "they went up in his feet"</note> ten thousand men, and Deborah went up with him. </verse>
    <verse num="11">And Heber the Kenite <transChange type="added">was</transChange> separated from <transChange type="added">the other</transChange> Kenites,<note>Hebrew "Kenite"</note> <transChange type="added">that is</transChange>, from the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Hobab the father-in-law of Moses. And {he was encamped}<note>Literally "he spread his tent"</note> at Elon-bezaanannim, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near Kedesh. </verse>
    <verse num="12">When they<note>The subject is not specified in Hebrew</note> reported to Sisera that Barak son of Abinoam had gone up to Mount Tabor,</verse>
    <verse num="13">Sisera summoned all his chariots--all nine hundred chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> of iron--and the entire army that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him from Harosheth Haggoyim to the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Kishon.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Deborah said to Barak, "Get up! This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the day that Yahweh has given Sisera into your hand. Has Yahweh not gone out before you?" So Barak went out from Mount Tabor with ten thousand men following him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Yahweh threw Sisera and all his chariots and army into confusion<note>Or "routed Sisera and all <transChange type="added">his</transChange> chariot<transChange type="added">s</transChange> and army"</note> before {the edge of Barak's sword};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword before Barak"</note> and Sisera dismounted from <transChange type="added">his</transChange> chariot and fled on foot.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But Barak pursued after the chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> and army as far as Harosheth Haggoyim, and all of Sisera's army fell to {the edge of the sword};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> no one was left. </verse>
    <verse num="17">Sisera fled on foot to the tent of Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, because <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> peace between Jabin king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And Jael came out to meet Sisera, and she said to him, "Turn aside, my lord; turn aside to me and do not be afraid." So he turned aside into her tent, and she covered him {with a blanket}.<note>Literally "with a covering/rug"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And he said to her, "Please, give me a drink of water, because I am thirsty." So she opened a skin vessel of milk and gave him a drink and covered him.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And he said to her, "Stand <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the doorway of the tent, and if anyone comes and asks you, and says, 'Is there anyone here?' You must answer, 'No.'"</verse>
    <verse num="21">But Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, took in her hand a tent peg and a hammer, and she went softly<note>Or "secretly"</note> to him and drove the peg into his temple, and it went through into the ground; he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> fast asleep since he was exhausted, and he died.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And behold, Barak <transChange type="added">was</transChange> pursuing Sisera, and Jael went out to meet him, and she said to him, "Come, and I will show you the man whom you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> seeking." And he came with her and saw that Sisera was lying dead with the peg in his temple.</verse>
    <verse num="23">On that day God subdued Jabin king of Canaan before the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">And the hand of the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> {pressed harder}<note>Literally "went harder"</note> and harder on Jabin king of Canaan, until they destroyed Jabin king of Canaan. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">And Deborah and Barak son of Abinoam sang on that day: </verse>
    <verse num="2">"When long hair hangs loosely in Israel, when the people willingly offer themselves, bless Yahweh!</verse>
    <verse num="3">Hear, O kings! Give ear, O princes! I will sing to Yahweh; I will sing praise to Yahweh, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Yahweh, when you went down from Seir, when you marched from the region of Edom, the earth trembled, the heavens poured down, the clouds poured down water.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The mountains trembled<note>Or "quaked"</note> before Yahweh, this Sinai, at the presence of Yahweh, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="6">"In the days of Shamgar son of Anath, in the days of Jael, the caravans had ceased, {the travelers},<note>Literally "the ones walking on the paths"</note> {they kept to the byways}.<note>Literally "they went <transChange type="added">on the</transChange> crooked roads"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">The warriors<note>Others interpret this word as referring to the "rural dwellers"</note> ceased; they failed to appear in Israel, until I,<note>Or "you"</note> Deborah, arose; I<note>Or "you"</note> arose <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a mother in Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="8">God chose new <transChange type="added">leaders</transChange>,<note>ESV, NRSV translate "when new gods were chosen"</note> then war <transChange type="added">was at the</transChange> gates; a small shield or a spear was not seen among forty thousand in Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="9">My heart <transChange type="added">goes out</transChange> to the commanders of Israel, those offering themselves willingly among the people; bless Yahweh!</verse>
    <verse num="10">The riders of white female donkeys, <transChange type="added">those</transChange> sitting on saddle blankets, and <transChange type="added">those</transChange> going on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> way, talk about it!</verse>
    <verse num="11">At the sound of <transChange type="added">those</transChange> dividing<note>Meaning uncertain; other translations have "archers" (Tanakh), "musicians" (ESV, NRSV) or "singers" (NIV, HCSB)</note> <transChange type="added">the sheep</transChange> among the watering places, there they will recount the righteous deeds of Yahweh, the righteous deeds for his warriors<note>Hebrew "warrior"</note> in Israel. Then the people of Yahweh went down to the gates.</verse>
    <verse num="12">"Wake up, wake up, Deborah! Wake up, wake up, sing a song! Get up, Barak! Take captive your captives, O son of Abinoam.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then <transChange type="added">the</transChange> remnant went down to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nobles; the people of Yahweh went down for him<note>Hebrew "me"</note> against <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mighty.</verse>
    <verse num="14">From Ephraim <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their root into Amalek, after you, Benjamin, with your family; from Makir <transChange type="added">the</transChange> commanders went down, and from Zebulun <transChange type="added">those</transChange> carrying <transChange type="added">the</transChange> scepter of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> military commander.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the chiefs<note>Hebrew "my chiefs"; ancient translations read "the chiefs"</note> in Issachar <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with Deborah; and Issachar likewise <transChange type="added">was with</transChange> Barak; into the valley {he was sent to get him from behind}.<note>Literally "he was sent at his feet"</note> Among the clans of Reuben <transChange type="added">were</transChange> great {decisions of the heart}.<note>Or "thoughts of the heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">Why do you sit among the sheepfolds, to hear <transChange type="added">the</transChange> calling sounds of the herds? For the clans of Reuben, <transChange type="added">there were</transChange> great searchings of the heart.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Gilead has remained<note>Or "stayed"</note> beyond the Jordan. Why did Dan dwell as a foreigner <transChange type="added">with</transChange> ships? Asher sat at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> coast of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> waters, and by his coves he has been settling down.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Zebulun <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a people who scorned death, and Naphtali, on the heights of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> field.</verse>
    <verse num="19">"The kings came, they fought; then the kings of Canaan fought; at Taanach by the waters of Megiddo, they got no plunder in silver.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The stars fought from heaven; from their courses they fought against Sisera.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> torrent of Kishon swept them away, the raging wadi torrent, the wadi torrent of Kishon. March on, my soul, <transChange type="added">with</transChange> strength!</verse>
    <verse num="22">"Then the hooves of the horse beat loudly, because of galloping, galloping of his stallions.</verse>
    <verse num="23">'Curse Meroz,' says the angel of Yahweh; 'curse bitterly its inhabitants, because they did not come to the help of Yahweh, to the help of Yahweh against the mighty.'</verse>
    <verse num="24">"Most blessed of women is Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite; most blessed is she of women among tent dwellers.</verse>
    <verse num="25">He asked for water, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> she gave milk; in a drinking bowl for nobles, she brought curds.</verse>
    <verse num="26">She reached out her hand to the peg, and her right hand for the workman's hammer; and she struck Sisera, crushed his head, and she shattered and pierced his temple.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Between her feet he sank, he fell, he lay. Between her feet he sank down, he fell; Where he sank down, there he fell--{dead}.<note>Literally "devastated"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28">"Through the window she looked down; the mother of Sisera cried out through the lattice, 'Why is his chariot delayed in coming? Why do the hoof beats<note>Or "steps"</note> of his chariot tarry?'</verse>
    <verse num="29">The wisest of her ladies answer her; she also answers the question herself:</verse>
    <verse num="30">'Are they not finding and dividing the plunder? {A bedmate or two bedmates for every man};<note>Literally "a womb, two wombs for <transChange type="added">head</transChange> of <transChange type="added">every</transChange> man"</note> colorful garments for Sisera, plunder of colorful garments,<note>Hebrew "garment"</note> beautifully finished colorful garments, on the neck of the plunderer?'</verse>
    <verse num="31">So may all your enemies perish, O Yahweh, but those who love him are like the rising sun at its brightest."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and Yahweh gave them into the hand of the Midianites<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> for seven years.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The hand of the Midianites<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> prevailed over Israel; because of the presence of the Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> made for themselves hiding places that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the mountains, caves, and strongholds.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And whenever Israel sowed seed, the Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> Amalekites,<note>Hebrew "Amalekite"</note> and the people of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east would come up against them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">They would camp against them and destroy the produce of the land {as far as}<note>Literally "until your coming to"</note> Gaza; they left no produce in Israel, or sheep, ox, or donkey.</verse>
    <verse num="5">For they, their livestock, and their tents would come up like a great number of locusts; they and their camels could not be counted; they came into the land and devoured it.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Israel was very poor because of the presence of the Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried out to Yahweh. </verse>
    <verse num="7">When the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried out to Yahweh on account of the Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Yahweh sent a prophet to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and he said to them, "Thus says Yahweh the God of Israel: 'I brought you up from Egypt; I brought you from the house of slavery.<note>Hebrew "slaves"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">I delivered you from the hand of Egypt and from the hand of all your oppressors, and drove them out from {before you};<note>Literally "your face/presence"</note> and I gave you their land.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And I said to you, 'I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> Yahweh your God; do not fear<note>Or "revere"</note> the gods of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> in whose land you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> living.' But you have not listened to my voice." </verse>
    <verse num="11">The angel of Yahweh came and sat under the oak<note>Or "terebinth"</note> that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> at Ophrah that belonged to Jehoash <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Abiezrite; and Gideon his son <transChange type="added">was</transChange> threshing wheat in the winepress to hide <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>Or "keep <transChange type="added">it</transChange> away"</note> from the Midianites.<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">The angel of Yahweh appeared to him and said to him, "Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with you, {you mighty warrior}."<note>Literally "strong/mighty of power"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">Gideon said to him, "Excuse me, my lord. <transChange type="added">If</transChange> Yahweh is with us, why then has all this happened to us? Where are all his wonderful deeds that our ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> recounted to us, saying, 'Did not Yahweh bring us up from Egypt?' But now Yahweh has forsaken us; he has given us into the palm of Midian."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Yahweh turned to him and said, "Go in this your strength, and you will deliver Israel from the palm of Midian. Did I not send you?"</verse>
    <verse num="15">He said to him, "Excuse me, my lord. How will I deliver Israel? Look, my clan <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the weakest in Manasseh, and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> the youngest in my father's house."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Yahweh said to him, "But I will be with you, and you will defeat Midian {as if they are one man}."<note>Literally "as one man"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">And he<note>That is, Gideon</note> said to him, "Please, if I have found favor in your eyes, {show me a sign}<note>Literally "make a sign for me"</note> that you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> speaking with me.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Please, do not depart from here until I come <transChange type="added">back</transChange> to you and bring out my gift and set it out before you."<note>Or "in your presence"</note> And he said, "I will stay until you return." </verse>
    <verse num="19">And Gideon went and prepared {a young goat}<note>Literally "a kid of goat"</note> and unleavened cakes <transChange type="added">from</transChange> an ephah of flour; he put meat in a basket, and the broth he put in a pot, and he brought <transChange type="added">them</transChange> to him under the oak<note>Or "terebinth"</note> and presented <transChange type="added">them</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The angel of God said to him, "Take the meat and the unleavened cakes and put <transChange type="added">them</transChange> on this rock; pour the broth <transChange type="added">over it</transChange>." And he did so.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then the angel of Yahweh reached out the tip of the staff that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in his hand, and he touched the meat and the unleavened cakes; and fire went up from the rock and consumed the meat and the unleavened cakes. And the angel of Yahweh went {from his sight}.<note>Literally "from his eyes"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">And Gideon realized that he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the angel of Yahweh; and Gideon said, "Oh, my lord Yahweh! For now I have seen the angel of Yahweh face to face."</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Yahweh said to him, "Peace be with you. Do not fear; you will not die."</verse>
    <verse num="24">And Gideon built there an altar to Yahweh, and he called it "Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> peace." To this day it is still in Ophrah <transChange type="added">of the</transChange> Abiezrites.<note>Hebrew "Abiezrite"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="25">Now on that same night Yahweh said to him, "Take the bull of the cattle that belongs to your father, and a second bull seven years old, and pull down the altar of Baal that belongs to your father, and cut down the Asherah<note>An Asherah is a cultic pole set up next to an altar symbolizing the goddess Asherah</note> that is beside it;</verse>
    <verse num="26">and build an altar to Yahweh your God on the top of this stronghold in the proper arrangement, and take a second bull and offer <transChange type="added">it as</transChange> a burnt offering with the wood of the Asherah<note>An Asherah is a cultic pole set up next to an altar symbolizing the goddess Asherah</note> that you will cut down.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Gideon took ten men from his servants, and he did just as Yahweh told him;<note>Or "spoke to him"</note> and because he was too afraid of his {father's family}<note>Literally "father's house"</note> and the men of the city to do <transChange type="added">it during</transChange> the day, he did <transChange type="added">it during</transChange> night. </verse>
    <verse num="28">When the men of the city got up early in the morning, look, the altar of Baal and the Asherah<note>An Asherah is a cultic pole set up next to an altar symbolizing the goddess Asherah</note> that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> beside it <transChange type="added">were</transChange> cut down, and the second bull was offered on the altar that had been built.</verse>
    <verse num="29">{And they said to one another},<note>Literally "And each man to his neighbor said"</note> "Who did this thing?" So they searched and inquired, and they said, "Gideon son of Jehoash did this thing."</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the men of the city said to Jehoash, "Bring out your son so that he may die, for he has pulled down the altar of Baal and cut down the Asherah that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> beside it."</verse>
    <verse num="31">But Jehoash said to all who stood against him,<note>Or "who arrayed against him"</note> "Will you contend for Baal? Will you rescue him? Whoever contends for him will be put to death by the morning. If he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a god, let him contend for himself because {his altar has been pulled down}."<note>Literally "because he has pulled down his altar"; the subject in Hebrew has not been specified</note></verse>
    <verse num="32">Thus, on that day he<note>That is, Gideon</note> was called Jerub-Baal, {which means},<note>Literally "saying"</note> "Let Baal contend against him," because he had pulled down his altar. </verse>
    <verse num="33">Then all the Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> Amalekites,<note>Hebrew "Amalekite"</note> and the people of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east gathered together and crossed <transChange type="added">the Jordan</transChange>; and they camped in the valley of Jezreel.</verse>
    <verse num="34">So the Spirit of Yahweh {took possession of}<note>Literally "clothed"</note> Gideon, and he blew on the trumpet, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Abiezrites<note>Hebrew "Abiezerite"</note> were called to follow him.</verse>
    <verse num="35">He sent messengers throughout all Manasseh, and they were also called to follow him; and he sent messengers throughout Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali, and they went up to meet them. </verse>
    <verse num="36">Then Gideon said to God, "In order to see that you will deliver Israel by my hand, just as you have said,</verse>
    <verse num="37">I will place a fleece of wool on the threshing floor. If there is dew on the fleece only, and all of the ground <transChange type="added">is</transChange> dry, I will know that you will deliver Israel by my hand, just as you have said."</verse>
    <verse num="38">And it was so. He arose early the next day and squeezed the fleece, and he wrung out dew from the fleece, a full drinking bowl of water.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And Gideon said to God, "{Do not let your anger burn}<note>Literally "Do not let your nose become hot"</note> against me; let me speak once more. Please let me test once more with the fleece; let the fleece be dry, and let there be dew on the ground."</verse>
    <verse num="40">And God did so that night; only the fleece was dry, and dew was on all the ground. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">Then Jerub-Baal (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange>, Gideon) rose early, and all the army that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him. They were camped beside the spring of Harod;<note>Or "En-Harod"</note> the camp of Midian was north of the hill of Moreh, in the valley.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Yahweh said to Gideon, "The troops that <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> too many for me to give Midian into their hands; Israel will boast, saying, 'My hand has delivered me.'</verse>
    <verse num="3">So then, please proclaim in the {hearing}<note>Literally "ears"</note> of the troops, saying, 'Whoever <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fearful and trembling, let him return and depart from the Mount of Gilead.'" About twenty-two thousand troops returned, and ten thousand remained.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Yahweh said to Gideon, "There <transChange type="added">are</transChange> still too many troops; bring them down to the water, and I will sift through them<note>Or "test them"</note> for you there. For whomever I say to you, 'This <transChange type="added">one</transChange> will go with you,' he will go with you; and for all whom I say to you, 'This <transChange type="added">one</transChange> will not go with you,' he will not go."</verse>
    <verse num="5">So he brought down the troops to the water, and Yahweh said to Gideon, "You must separate everyone who laps up the water to drink with his tongue like a dog from those {who kneel}."<note>Literally "who kneels to his knees"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">The number of those lapping up <transChange type="added">the water</transChange> with their hand to their mouth was three hundred men; all the rest of the troops kneeled to drink the water.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And Yahweh said to Gideon, "I will deliver you with the three hundred men lapping up <transChange type="added">the water</transChange>; I will give Midian into your hand, so let the <transChange type="added">other</transChange> troops go, each to his own place.</verse>
    <verse num="8">So they took their provisions and their trumpets into their hand, and he sent all the men of Israel, each one, to his tent; but three hundred of the men he kept; the camp of Midian was below him in the valley. </verse>
    <verse num="9">And that night Yahweh said to him, "Get up; go down against the camp, for I have given it into your hand.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But if you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> afraid, go down to the camp with Purah your servant,</verse>
    <verse num="11">and you will hear what they say; and afterward {you will have courage},<note>Literally "your hands will be strong"</note> and you will go down against the camp." Then he went down with Purah his servant to the outpost of the armed men<note>Or "edge of the men lined up in array"</note> that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the camp.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Midianites,<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> Amalekites,<note>Hebrew "Amalekite"</note> and all the people of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east <transChange type="added">were</transChange> lying in the valley, like a great multitude of locusts; their camels were without number, as numerous as the sand that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on the shore of the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="13">When Gideon came, a man <transChange type="added">was</transChange> recounting a dream<note>Or "telling a dream"</note> to his friend, and he said, "Behold, {I had a dream};<note>Literally "I dreamed a dream"</note> a round loaf of barley bread <transChange type="added">was</transChange> tumbling into the camp of Midian, and it came up to the tent, it struck it, and it fell and turned it upside down so that the tent fell."</verse>
    <verse num="14">His friend answered him and said, "This cannot be anything except the sword of Gideon son of Jehoash, a man of Israel; God has given Midian and the entire camp into his hand." </verse>
    <verse num="15">When Gideon heard the recounting of the dream<note>Or "telling of the dream"</note> and its interpretation, he bowed down and returned to the camp of Israel; and he said, "Get up, for Yahweh has given the camp of Midian into your hand."</verse>
    <verse num="16">He divided the three hundred men <transChange type="added">into</transChange> three companies,<note>Or "divisions"</note> and he put trumpets and empty jars in everyone's hand, with torches inside the jars.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And he said to them, "Watch me and do the same. When I come to the edge of the camp, {do just as I do}.<note>Literally "just as I will do, you must do"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">When I and all who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with me blow on the trumpet, you must also blow on the trumpets and surround the camp, and you must say, 'To Yahweh and to Gideon!'" </verse>
    <verse num="19">So Gideon and the hundred men who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him came to the edge of the camp <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the beginning of the middle night-watch, when they had just finished setting up the guards, and they blew on the trumpets and smashed the jars that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in their hands.<note>Hebrew "hand"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">When three companies<note>Or "divisions"</note> blew on the trumpets and broke the jars, they held in their left hand the torches and in their right hand the trumpets for blowing, and they cried, "A sword for Yahweh and for Gideon!"</verse>
    <verse num="21">And each stood {in his place}<note>Literally "under him"</note> all around the camp, and all the camp ran, and they cried out as they fled.</verse>
    <verse num="22">When they blew the three hundred trumpets, Yahweh set <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword of each one against his neighbor throughout the whole camp, and the camp<note>Or "army"</note> fled as far as Beth Shittah toward Zererah, up to Abel Meholah, the border by Tabbath.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And the men of Israel were called from Naphtali, from Asher, and from all of Manasseh, and they pursued after Midian. </verse>
    <verse num="24">And Gideon sent messengers throughout all the hill country of Ephraim, saying, "Come down to oppose<note>Or "meet"</note> Midian, and capture from them the waters up to Beth Barah and the Jordan." He called out all the men of Ephraim, and they captured the waters up to Beth Barah and the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And they captured the two commanders of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb, and they killed Oreb at the rock of Oreb, and they killed Zeeb at the wine press of Zeeb, while they chased Midian; and they brought the heads<note>Hebrew "head"</note> of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon from beyond the Jordan. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">The men of Ephraim said to him, "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this thing you have done to us, not calling us when you went to fight against the Midianites?"<note>Hebrew "Midianite"</note> And they quarreled with him severely.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he said to them, "What I have done now in comparison with you? Are not the gleanings of Ephraim better than the grape harvest of Abiezer?</verse>
    <verse num="3">God has given into your hand the commanders of Midian, Oreb, and Zeeb. What have I been able to do in comparison with you?" And their {anger}<note>Literally "spirit"</note> against him subsided when {he said that}.<note>Literally "he said this thing/word"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="4">Then Gideon came to the Jordan, crossing it with the three hundred men who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him, weary and pursuing.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He said to the men of Succoth, "Please give loaves of bread to the people who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {following me},<note>Literally "at my feet"</note> for they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> weary, and I am pursuing Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian."</verse>
    <verse num="6">The officials of Succoth said, "Is the hand<note>Or "palm"</note> of Zebah and Zalmunna in your hand now, that we should give bread to your army?"</verse>
    <verse num="7">Gideon said, "Well then, when Yahweh gives Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, I will trample your flesh with the thorns and briers of the wilderness."</verse>
    <verse num="8">He went from there <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Penuel, and he spoke similarly to them; and the men of Penuel answered him just as the men of Succoth answered.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And he said also to the men of Penuel, saying, "When I return {safely},<note>Literally "in peace"</note> I will tear down this tower." </verse>
    <verse num="10">Now Zebah and Zalmunna <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in Karkor, and their armies with them, about fifteen thousand men remained from the entire army<note>Or "camp"</note> of the people of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> east; those that fell <transChange type="added">in battle were</transChange> one hundred and twenty thousand {swordsmen}.<note>Literally "sword-drawing men"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And Gideon went up the route of those who dwell in tents on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and he attacked the army<note>Or "camp"</note> when it was off its guard.<note>Or "unsuspecting"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">And Zebah and Zalmunna fled, and he pursued them and captured the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and he routed<note>Or "he frightened" or "he threw into panic"</note> the entire army.<note>Or "camp"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then Gideon son of Jehoash returned from the battle {by way of}<note>Literally "from"</note> the ascent of Heres.<note>Or "pass of Heres"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">He captured a young man {from Succoth}<note>Literally "from the men of Succoth"</note> and questioned him. <transChange type="added">The young man</transChange> listed<note>Or "wrote down"</note> for him the commanders of Succoth and its elders, seventy-seven men.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He came to the men of Succoth, and he said, "Here <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Zebah and Zalmunna, about whom you taunted me, saying, '<transChange type="added">Is</transChange> the palm<note>Or "hand"</note> of Zebah and Zalmunna in your hand now, that we should give food to your weary men?'"</verse>
    <verse num="16">He took the elders of the city and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> thorn bushes and briers of the wilderness, and {he trampled}<note>Literally "he taught," but see v. 7</note> the men of Succoth with them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">He broke down the tower of Penuel, and he killed the men of the city. </verse>
    <verse num="18">And he said to Zebah and Zalmunna, "What type <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the men whom you killed at Tabor?" And they said, "{They were like you};<note>Literally, "like you, like them"</note> each <transChange type="added">one of them</transChange> had the appearance of the sons of the king."</verse>
    <verse num="19">He said, "They <transChange type="added">were</transChange> my brothers, the sons of my mother. As Yahweh lives, if you had kept them alive I would not kill you."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And he said to Jether, his firstborn, "Get up, kill them." But the boy did not draw his sword, for he was afraid because he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> still a boy.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Zebah and Zalmunna said, "Get up yourself, and strike us, for as <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the man, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his power."<note>Or "strength"</note> So Gideon got up and killed Zebah and Zalmunna, and he took the crescent ornaments that were on the necks of their camels. </verse>
    <verse num="22">The men of Israel said to Gideon, "Rule over us, both you and your sons, and your sons' son, for you have delivered us from the hand of Midian.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But Gideon said to them, "I will not rule over you, and my son will not rule over you; Yahweh will rule over you."</verse>
    <verse num="24">And Gideon said to them, "{Let me make a request of you},<note>Literally "Let me ask from you a request"</note> that each of you give to me an ornamental ring from his plunder." (They <transChange type="added">had</transChange> ornamental rings of gold, because they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Ishmaelites.)</verse>
    <verse num="25">They said, "We will gladly give <transChange type="added">them</transChange>," and they spread out a garment, and everyone threw there an ornamental ring of his plunder.</verse>
    <verse num="26">The weight of the ornamental rings of gold that he requested <transChange type="added">was</transChange> one thousand seven hundred <transChange type="added">shekels of</transChange> gold, apart from the crescents, pendants, and purple garments that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on the kings of Midian, and apart from the pendants that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on the necks of their camels.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Gideon made an ephod <transChange type="added">out of</transChange> it, and he put it in his town in Ophrah, and all Israel prostituted <transChange type="added">themselves</transChange> to it there, and it became a snare to Gideon and his family.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And Midian was subdued before the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and they did not again lift up their head, and the land rested for forty years in the days of Gideon. </verse>
    <verse num="29">Jerub-Baal son of Joash lived in his own house.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Now Gideon had seventy sons, {his own offspring},<note>Literally "from his own loins"</note> for he had many wives.</verse>
    <verse num="31">His concubine who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Shechem also bore for him a son, and {he named him}<note>Literally "he set his name"</note> Abimelech.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And Gideon son of Joash died at a good old age, and he was buried in the tomb of Jehoash his father, in Ophrah <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the Abiezrites.<note>Hebrew "Abiezrite"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="33">And it happened, as soon as Gideon died, the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> returned and prostituted <transChange type="added">themselves</transChange> after the Baals, and they made for themselves Baal-Berith as god.</verse>
    <verse num="34">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did not remember Yahweh their God, who had delivered them from the hand of their enemies from all around,</verse>
    <verse num="35">nor did they show favor<note>Or "loyalty"</note> to the house of Jerub-Baal (<transChange type="added">that is</transChange>, Gideon) in accordance with all the good that he did for Israel. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">And Abimelech son of Jerub-Baal went to Shechem, to the relatives of his mother, and he said to them and to the house of his mother's father,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"{Speak to}<note>Literally "Speak into the ears"</note> the lords of Shechem, 'What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> better for you, that seventy men all from the sons of Jerub-Baal rule over you, or that one man rules over you?' Remember that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> your bone and your flesh."</verse>
    <verse num="3">And his mother's relatives spoke all these words concerning him {to}<note>Literally "in the ears of"</note> all the lords of Shechem; and {they supported Abimelech},<note>Literally "it reached their heart after Abimelech"</note> for they said, "He is our relative."<note>Or "brother"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And they gave to him seventy <transChange type="added">pieces of</transChange> silver from the temple<note>Or "house"</note> of Baal-Berith, and Abimelech hired with them<note>That is, the pieces of silver</note> worthless and reckless men, and {they followed him}.<note>Literally "They went after him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And he went to his father's house at Ophrah, and he killed his brothers, the sons of Jerub-Baal, seventy men, on one stone. But Jotham the youngest son of Jerub-Baal survived, because he hid himself.</verse>
    <verse num="6">All the lords of Shechem and Beth-Millo gathered, and they went and made Abimelech as king, near <transChange type="added">the</transChange> oak<note>Or "terebinth"</note> of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> pillar that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> at Shechem. </verse>
    <verse num="7">And they told Jotham, and he went up and stood on the top of Mount Gerizim, and {he cried out loud}<note>Literally "he lifted his voice and called"</note> and said to them, "Listen to me, lords of Shechem, so that God may listen to you. </verse>
    <verse num="8">"The trees went certainly, to anoint a king over themselves. And they said to the olive tree, 'Rule over us.'</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the olive tree replied, 'Should I stop <transChange type="added">producing</transChange> my oil, which by me gods and men are honored, to go sway over the trees?'</verse>
    <verse num="10">Then the trees said to the fig tree, 'You, come rule over us.'</verse>
    <verse num="11">But the fig tree said to them, 'Should I stop <transChange type="added">producing</transChange> my sweetness, and my good crop, to go sway over the trees?'</verse>
    <verse num="12">And the trees said to the vine, 'You, come rule over us.'</verse>
    <verse num="13">But the vine said to them, 'Should I stop <transChange type="added">producing</transChange> my wine that makes the gods and men happy, to go sway over the trees?'</verse>
    <verse num="14">So all the trees said to the thornbush, 'You, come rule over us.'</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the thornbush said to the trees, 'If in good faith<note>Or "honesty"</note> you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> anointing me as king over you, then come and take refuge in my shade; if not, may fire go out from the thornbush and devour the cedars of Lebanon.'</verse>
    <verse num="16">"So then, if you have acted in good faith<note>Or "honesty"</note> and sincerity in making Abimelech king, and if you have dealt well with Jerub-Baal and his house, and have dealt with him {according to his accomplishments}<note>Literally "according to the dealings of his hand"</note>--</verse>
    <verse num="17">for my father fought and {risked his life}<note>Literally "he threw his life in front"</note> for you and delivered you from the hand of Midian;</verse>
    <verse num="18">but today you have risen against the house of my father and killed his sons, seventy men on one stone, and you have made Abimelech, the son of his slave woman, a king over the lords of Shechem, because he is your relative<note>Or "brother"</note>--</verse>
    <verse num="19">if you have acted in good faith<note>Or "honesty"</note> and sincerity with Jerub-Baal and his house this day, then rejoice in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you.</verse>
    <verse num="20">But if not, let a fire come out from Abimelech and let it devour the lords of Shechem and Beth-Millo; and let a fire come out from the lords of Shechem, and from Beth-Millo, and let it devour Abimelech."</verse>
    <verse num="21">And Jotham escaped and fled, and went to Beer; he remained there because of Abimelech his brother. </verse>
    <verse num="22">Abimelech ruled over Israel three years.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the lords of Shechem, and the lords of Shechem dealt treacherously with Abimelech,</verse>
    <verse num="24">so that the violence done to the seventy brothers of Abimelech would be avenged and their blood be placed on Abimelech their brother, who killed them, and on the lords of Shechem, {who helped}<note>Literally "who strengthened his hands"</note> to kill his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And the lords of Shechem set for him ambushes on the top of the mountains, and they robbed all who passed by them along the road; and it was reported to Abimelech. </verse>
    <verse num="26">And Gaal son of Ebel and his relatives came, and they crossed over into Shechem, and the lords of Shechem {gave him confidence}.<note>Literally "put confidence into him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">They went out <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the field and harvested their vineyards and trod <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, and they {held a festival}.<note>Literally "made a rejoicing"</note> And they went <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the temple<note>Or "house"</note> of their god, and they ate and drank and cursed Abimelech.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Then Gaal son of Ebed said, "Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Abimelech, and who <transChange type="added">are we of</transChange> Shechem that we should serve him? Is he not the son of Jerub-Baal, and <transChange type="added">is not</transChange> Zebul his chief officer?<note>Or "overseer"</note> Serve the men of Hamor the father of Shechem. Why should we serve him?<note>That is, Abimelech</note></verse>
    <verse num="29">If only this people {were in my command}!<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">were</transChange> in my hand"</note> Then I would remove Abimelech, and I would have said,<note>Hebrew "he said"; the translation "I would have said" follows the LXX</note> 'Increase your army and come out!'" </verse>
    <verse num="30">When Zebul the commander of the city heard the words of Gaal son of Ebed, {he became angry},<note>Literally "his nose became hot"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">and he sent messengers to Abimelech in Tormah, saying, "Look, Gaal son of Ebed and his relatives <transChange type="added">are</transChange> coming to Shechem, and they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> stirring up the city against you.</verse>
    <verse num="32">So then, get up <transChange type="added">by</transChange> night, you and the army that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with you, and lie in ambush in the field.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And in the morning at sunrise, get up and rush the city; and look, when he and the troops who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with him come out to you, {you must act according to whatever opportunity offers itself}.<note>Literally "you must do to him just as it will find your hand"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="34">So Abimelech and all the army that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him got up <transChange type="added">by</transChange> night, and they lay in ambush against Shechem <transChange type="added">in</transChange> four divisions.<note>Or "companies"</note></verse>
    <verse num="35">Gaal son of Ebed went out and stood <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the city gate, and Abimelech and the army that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him got up from the ambush.</verse>
    <verse num="36">When Gaal saw the army, he said to Zebul, "Look, people <transChange type="added">are</transChange> coming down from the top of the mountains!" And Zebul said to him, "{The shadows of the mountains look like people to you}."<note>Literally "the shadows of the mountains you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> seeing as men"</note></verse>
    <verse num="37">{And Gaal spoke again}<note>Literally "And he did again again Gaal to speak"</note> and said, "Look, people <transChange type="added">are</transChange> coming down from Tabbur-erez, and one division<note>Or "company"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> coming from the direction of Elon-meonenim."<note>Or "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sorcerer's Oak"</note></verse>
    <verse num="38">And Zebul said to him, "Where then {is your boast},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">is</transChange> your mouth"</note> <transChange type="added">you</transChange> who said, 'Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Abimelech that we should serve him?' <transChange type="added">Is</transChange> this not the army that you rejected? Please, go out now and fight against them."<note>Hebrew "against him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="39">So Gaal went out before the lords of Shechem and fought against Abimelech.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And Abimelech chased him, and he fled before him; many fell slain up to the entrance of the gate.</verse>
    <verse num="41">So Abimelech resided at Arumah, and Zebul drove out Gaal and his relatives<note>Or "brothers"</note> from living in Shechem. </verse>
    <verse num="42">On the next day the people went out <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the field; and it was reported to Abimelech,</verse>
    <verse num="43">so he took the army and divided them into three divisions,<note>Or "companies"</note> and he laid an ambush in the field. And he saw the people <transChange type="added">were</transChange> coming out from the city, and he arose against them and killed them.</verse>
    <verse num="44">Then Abimelech and the divisions<note>Or "companies"</note> that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him dashed out and stood <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the city gate, and the two divisions dashed out against all who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the field, and they killed them.</verse>
    <verse num="45">Abimelech fought against the city all that day, and he captured the city and killed the people that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it; then he broke down the city and sowed it <transChange type="added">with</transChange> salt. </verse>
    <verse num="46">When all the lords of the tower of Shechem heard, they went to the vault<note>Or "cellar"</note> of the temple<note>Or "house"</note> of El-Berith.</verse>
    <verse num="47">It was told to Abimelech that all the lords of the tower of Shechem had gathered.</verse>
    <verse num="48">So Abimelech went up Mount Zalmon, he and all his army that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him, and Abimelech took the ax<note>Hebrew "axes"</note> in his hand and cut down a bundle of brushwood, and he lifted it and put <transChange type="added">it</transChange> on his shoulder. And he said to the army that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him, "What you have seen me do, quickly do also."</verse>
    <verse num="49">So the whole army cut down each one branch for himself and followed Abimelech, and they put <transChange type="added">them</transChange> against the vault<note>Or "cellar"</note> and set the vault ablaze with fire on those <transChange type="added">inside</transChange>, so that all the men of the tower of Shechem died, about a thousand men and women. </verse>
    <verse num="50">Then Abimelech went to Thebez, and he encamped against Thebez and captured it.</verse>
    <verse num="51">But there was a strong tower in the middle of the city, and all the men, women, and lords of the city fled there and shut themselves in; and they went up to the roof of the tower.</verse>
    <verse num="52">Abimelech came up to the tower and fought against it, and he came near the entrance of the tower to burn it with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="53">But a certain woman<note>Or "But one woman"</note> threw an upper millstone on Abimelech's head and cracked open his skull.</verse>
    <verse num="54">He called quickly to the young man carrying his weapons, and he said to him, "Draw your sword and kill me, so that they will not say of me, 'A woman killed him.'" So the young man<note>Hebrew "his young man"</note> stabbed him, and he died.</verse>
    <verse num="55">When the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, each one went to his home.<note>Or "place"</note></verse>
    <verse num="56">So God repaid<note>Or "returned"</note> the wickedness<note>Or "evil"</note> that Abimelech committed against his father by killing his seventy brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="57">And God also repaid all the wickedness<note>Or "evil"</note> of the men of Shechem on their heads, and the curse of Jotham son of Jerub-Baal fell on them. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">After Abimelech, Tola son of Puah son of Dod, a man of Issachar, rose up to deliver Israel; and he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> living at Shamir in the hill country of Ephraim.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he judged Israel twenty-three years. And he died and was buried in Shamir.</verse>
    <verse num="3">After him Jair the Gileadite rose up, and he judged Israel twenty-two years.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And he had thirty sons who would ride on thirty donkeys, and they had thirty towns that <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the land of Gilead that they called Havvoth Jair until this day.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Jair died and was buried in Kamon. </verse>
    <verse num="6">And again, the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh. They served the Baals, the Ashtaroth, the gods of Aram, Sidon, Moab, and the gods of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and Philistines; they abandoned Yahweh and did not serve him.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And {the anger of Yahweh burned}<note>Literally "the nose of Yahweh became hot"</note> against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines and the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">They crushed and oppressed the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> in that year; for eighteen years they <transChange type="added">crushed</transChange> all the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> beyond the Jordan, in the land of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> crossed the Jordan to fight also against Judah, Benjamin, and the house of Ephraim; and Israel was very distressed. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Then the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> cried out to Yahweh, saying, "We have sinned against you; we have abandoned our God and served the Baals."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Yahweh said to the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> "<transChange type="added">Did I</transChange> not <transChange type="added">deliver you</transChange> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Egyptians,<note>Hebrew "from Egypt"</note> the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> from the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and from the Philistines?<note>Hebrew "Philistine"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">And when <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sidonians, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Amalekites,<note>Hebrew "Amalekite"</note> and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Maonites<note>Hebrew "Maonite"</note> oppressed you, you cried out to me, and I delivered you from their hand.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Yet you have abandoned me and served other gods. Therefore I will no longer deliver you.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Go and cry out to the gods whom you have chosen; let them deliver you in the time of your trouble."</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> said to Yahweh, "We have sinned; {do to us accordingly as you see fit};<note>Literally "do to us according to the good in your eyes"</note> only please deliver us this day."</verse>
    <verse num="16">So they removed the foreign gods from their midst and served Yahweh; and {he could no longer bear}<note>Literally "his soul was short with"</note> the misery of Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="17">And the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> were summoned,<note>Or "were called to arms"</note> and they camped in Gilead. And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gathered and camped at Mizpah.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The people, the ones commanding Gilead, {said to each other},<note>Literally "said each to his neighbor"</note> "Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the man that will begin to fight against the {Ammonites}?<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> He will be as head over all the inhabitants of Gilead." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty warrior; he was the son of a prostitute, and {Gilead was his father}.<note>Literally "Gilead fathered Jephthah"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Gilead's wife also bore for him sons; and the sons of <transChange type="added">his</transChange> wife grew up and drove Jephthah away, and they said to him, "You will not inherit the house of our father because you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the son of another woman."</verse>
    <verse num="3">So Jephthah fled from the presence of his brothers, and he lived in the land of Tob. And {outlaws}<note>Literally "unprincipled/worthless men"</note> gathered around Jephthah and went with him. </verse>
    <verse num="4">After a time the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> made war with Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="5">When the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> made war with Israel, the elders of Gilead went to bring Jephthah from the land of Tob.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And they said to Jephthah, "Come and be our commander, so that we may make war against the {Ammonites}."<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Jephthah said to the elders, "Did you not shun me and drive me out from the house of my father? Why do you come to me now when you have trouble?"</verse>
    <verse num="8">And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, "That being so, we have now returned to you, that you may go with us {to fight}<note>Literally "to make war"</note> against the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and become for us as head of all the inhabitants of Gilead."</verse>
    <verse num="9">So Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, "If you bring me back {to fight}<note>Literally "to make war"</note> against the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and Yahweh gives them {over to me},<note>Literally "before me"</note> will I be your head?"</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, "Yahweh will be a {witness}<note>Literally "hearer"</note> between us; we will act according to your word."</verse>
    <verse num="11">So Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and commander over them. And Jephthah spoke all his words before Yahweh at Mizpah. </verse>
    <verse num="12">And Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> saying, "What <transChange type="added">is between</transChange> you and me that you have come to me to make war against my land?"</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the king of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> said to Jephthah's messengers, "Because Israel took my land from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Arnon up to the Jabbok and the Jordan when they came up from Egypt; so then, restore it peacefully."</verse>
    <verse num="14">Once again Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">and he said to him, "Thus says Jephthah, 'Israel did not take the land of Moab or the land of the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">because when they came up from Egypt, Israel went through the wilderness to the {Red Sea}<note>Literally "sea of reed"</note> and went to Kadesh.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, "Please let us cross through your land," but the king of Edom would not listen. And they also sent <transChange type="added">messengers</transChange> to the king of Moab, but he was not willing. So Israel stayed in Kadesh.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then they traveled through the wilderness, went around the land of Edom and Moab, and came to {the east}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">from</transChange> rise of sun"</note> side of the land of Moab, and they<note>Hebrew "he"</note> encamped beyond <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Arnon; and they did not go into the territory of Moab because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Arnon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the border of Moab.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites,<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> king of Heshbon; and Israel said to him, 'Please let us cross through your land {to our country}.'<note>Literally "to our place"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">But Sihon did not trust Israel to cross through his territory, so Sihon gathered all his people and then encamped at Jahaz; and he made war with Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And Yahweh, the God of Israel, gave Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they defeated them; and Israel occupied all the land of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> inhabiting that land.</verse>
    <verse num="22">They occupied all the territory of the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Arnon up to the Jabbok, and from the wilderness up to the Jordan.</verse>
    <verse num="23">So then Yahweh, the God of Israel, has driven out the Amorites<note>Hebrew "Amorite"</note> from before his people Israel, and you want to possess it?</verse>
    <verse num="24">Do you not possess what Chemosh your god gave you to possess? Whoever Yahweh our God has driven out before us, we will possess it.</verse>
    <verse num="25">So then, <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you any better than Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever quarrel with Israel, or did he ever make war against them?</verse>
    <verse num="26">When Israel lived in Heshbon and its villages, and in Aroer and its villages, and in all the towns that <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {along the Arnon},<note>Literally "on the hands of the Arnon"</note> for three hundred years,<note>Hebrew "year"</note> why did you not recover <transChange type="added">them</transChange> at that time?</verse>
    <verse num="27">I have not sinned against you; but you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the one who is doing wrong by making war against me. {Let Yahweh judge}<note>Literally "Let Yahweh the judge, judge"</note> today between the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and the {Ammonites}."<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28">But the king of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> did not listen to the message that Jephthah sent to him. </verse>
    <verse num="29">And the Spirit of Yahweh came upon Jephthah, and he passed through Gilead and Manasseh. He passed through Mizpah of Gilead, and from Mizpah of Gilead he passed through <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="30">And Jephthah made a vow to Yahweh, and he said, "If indeed you will give the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> into my hand,</verse>
    <verse num="31">whatever<note>Or "whoever"</note> comes out from the doors of my house to meet me when I return safely from the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> will be Yahweh's, and I will offer it <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a burnt offering."</verse>
    <verse num="32">And Jephthah crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> to the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> to make war against them; and Yahweh gave them into his hand.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And he defeated them <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a very great blow, from Aroer as far as Minnith, twenty towns,<note>Hebrew "town"</note> up to Abel Keramim. And the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> were subdued before the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="34">Jephthah came to Mizpah, to his house, and behold his daughter came out to meet him with tambourines and dancing. She <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his only child; he did not have a son or daughter except her.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And the moment he saw her, he tore his clothes and said, "Ah! My daughter, you have caused me to bow down, and you have become my trouble. {I made an oath}<note>Literally "I have opened wide my mouth"</note> to Yahweh, and I cannot take <transChange type="added">it</transChange> back."</verse>
    <verse num="36">She said to him, "My father, {you made an oath}<note>Literally "you have opened wide your mouth"</note> to Yahweh. Do to me according to what has gone out from your mouth, since Yahweh gave vengeance to you against your enemies, the {Ammonites}."<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="37">And she said to her father, "Let this thing be done for me: grant me two months so that I may go wander<note>Hebrew "down"</note> on the mountains and lament over my virginity, I and my companions.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And he said, "Go." He sent her away <transChange type="added">for</transChange> two months, and she went with her friends, and she lamented over her virginity on the mountains.</verse>
    <verse num="39">At the end of the two months she returned to her father, and he did to her <transChange type="added">according to</transChange> his vow; and {she did not sleep with a man}.<note>Literally "she did not know a man"</note> And it became an annual custom in Israel</verse>
    <verse num="40">for the daughters of Israel to go and lament the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite for forty days of the year. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">The men of Ephraim were called to arms, and they crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> to Zaphon and said to Jephthah, "Why did you cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange> and make war against the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and why did you not call us to go with you? We will burn down your house over you with fire."</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Jephthah said to them, "I and my people were engaged in great conflict with the {Ammonites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> I called you, but you did not deliver me from their hand.</verse>
    <verse num="3">I saw that you would not deliver <transChange type="added">us</transChange>; {I risked my own life},<note>Literally "I put my life in my hand"</note> and I crossed <transChange type="added">over</transChange> to the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Ammon"</note> and Yahweh gave them into my hand. Why have you come up to me this day to fight against me?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">Jephthah gathered all the men of Gilead, and he made war with Ephraim; and the men of Gilead defeated Ephraim because they said, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> fugitives of Ephraim, you Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim and Manasseh."</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then Gilead captured the fords of the Jordan from Ephraim, and whenever a fugitive of Ephraim said, "Let me cross <transChange type="added">over</transChange>," the men of Gilead said to him, "<transChange type="added">Are</transChange> you an Ephraimite?" <transChange type="added">When</transChange> he said, "No,"</verse>
    <verse num="6">they said to him, "Please say Shibboleth," and <transChange type="added">if</transChange> he said, "Sibboleth"--because he could not {pronounce it}<note>Literally "speak it"</note> correctly--they grabbed him and executed him at the fords of Jordan. At that time forty-two thousand from Ephraim fell. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died, and he was buried in <transChange type="added">one of</transChange> the cities of Gilead. </verse>
    <verse num="8">After him Ibzan from Bethlehem judged Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He had thirty sons. He gave his thirty daughters away in marriage outside <transChange type="added">his clan</transChange> and brought in from outside thirty young women for his sons. He judged Israel for seven years.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Then<note>Or "And"</note> Ibzan died and was buried in Bethlehem. </verse>
    <verse num="11">After him Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel, and he judged Israel ten years.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Then<note>Or "And"</note> Elon the Zebulunite died and was buried in Aijalon in the land of Zebulun. </verse>
    <verse num="13">After him Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="14">He had forty sons and thirty grandsons that rode on seventy male donkeys. He judged Israel for eight years.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Then<note>Or "And"</note> Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died and was buried in Pirathon, in the land of Ephraim in the hill country of the Amalekites.<note>Hebrew "Amalekite"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">And again, the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> did evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and Yahweh gave them into the hand of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines forty years. </verse>
    <verse num="2">There was a certain man from Zorah, from the tribe of the Danites, and his name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Manoah; his wife <transChange type="added">was</transChange> infertile and did not bear children.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And an angel of Yahweh appeared to the woman, and he said to her, "Behold, you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> infertile and have not borne <transChange type="added">children</transChange>, but you will conceive and bear a son.</verse>
    <verse num="4">So then, be careful and do not drink wine or strong drink, and do not eat anything unclean,</verse>
    <verse num="5">because you <transChange type="added">will</transChange> conceive and bear a son. No razor {will touch}<note>Literally "will go upon"</note> his head, because the boy will be a {Nazirite of God}<note>Literally "consecrated of God" or "devoted of God"</note> {from birth}.<note>Literally "from the womb"</note> And it is he who will begin to deliver Israel from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hand of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And the woman came and told her husband, saying, "A man of God came to me, and his appearance <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like the appearance of an angel of God, very awesome. I did not ask him from where he <transChange type="added">came</transChange>, and he did not tell me his name.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And he said to me, 'Look, you <transChange type="added">will</transChange> conceive and bear a son, so then, do not drink wine or strong drink, and do not eat anything unclean, for the boy will be a Nazirite of God from birth<note>Or "the womb"</note> until the day of his death.'" </verse>
    <verse num="8">Then Manoah prayed to Yahweh and said, "Excuse me, my Lord, please let the man of God whom you sent again come to us and teach us what we should do concerning the boy who will be born."</verse>
    <verse num="9">And God listened to the voice of Manoah, and an angel of God came again to the woman; she <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sitting in the field, but Manoah her husband was not with her.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The woman quickly ran and told her husband, and she said to him, "Look! The man who came to me the <transChange type="added">other</transChange> day appeared to me."</verse>
    <verse num="11">So Manoah got up and went after his wife, and he came to the man and said to him, "<transChange type="added">Are</transChange> you the man that spoke to the woman?" And he said, "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Manoah said to him, "Now {when your words come true},<note>Literally "when your words will come"</note> what will be the boy's {manner of life}<note>Literally "measure"</note> and work?"</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the angel of Yahweh said to Manoah, "Let the woman be attentive to all that I said.</verse>
    <verse num="14">She should not eat of anything that comes from the vine, or drink wine or strong drink, or eat anything unclean; she should keep all that I commanded." </verse>
    <verse num="15">And Manoah said to the angel of Yahweh, "{Please stay},<note>Literally "Please, let us hold you back"</note> and let us prepare a {young goat}<note>Literally "kid of goat"</note> for you."</verse>
    <verse num="16">The angel of Yahweh said to Manoah, "If you keep me, I will not eat your food, but if you prepare a burnt offering for Yahweh, you can offer it (for Manoah did not know that he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> an angel of Yahweh)."</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Manoah said to the angel of Yahweh, "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your name so that when your words come <transChange type="added">true</transChange> we may honor you?"</verse>
    <verse num="18">But the angel of Yahweh said to him, "Why do you ask my name? It <transChange type="added">is too</transChange> wonderful." </verse>
    <verse num="19">And Manoah took the {young goat}<note>Literally "kid of goat"</note> and the grain offering, and he offered <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to Yahweh on the rock, to the one who performs miracles.<note>Or "the one who works wonders"</note> And Manoah and his wife <transChange type="added">were</transChange> watching.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And when the flame went up toward the heaven from the altar, the angel of Yahweh went up in the flame of the altar to heaven while Manoah and his wife <transChange type="added">were</transChange> watching. And they fell on their faces to the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The angel of Yahweh did not appear again to Manoah and his wife, and then Manoah knew that he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a messenger<note>Or "angel"</note> of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Manoah said to his wife, "We will certainly die because we have seen God."</verse>
    <verse num="23">But his wife said to him, "If Yahweh wanted to kill us he would not have taken<note>Or "accepted"</note> from our hand the burnt offering and the grain offering, or shown us all these things, or now announced to us things such as these." </verse>
    <verse num="24">The woman bore a son, and she called him Samson; the boy grew big, and Yahweh blessed him.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And the Spirit of Yahweh began to stir him in the camp of Dan, between Zorah and Eshtaol. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">And Samson went down to Timnah, and he saw a woman in Timnah from the daughters of the Philistines.</verse>
    <verse num="2">He went up and told his father and mother, and he said, "I saw a woman in Timnah from the daughters of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines; so then, take her for me as a wife."</verse>
    <verse num="3">But his father and mother said to him, "Is there not a wife among the daughters of your relatives, or among all our<note>Hebrew "my"</note> people, that you must take a wife from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> uncircumcised Philistines?" But Samson said to his father, "Take her for me because {she pleases me}."<note>Literally "she is right in my eyes"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">His father and mother did not know that this <transChange type="added">was</transChange> from Yahweh; he was seeking for an occasion against <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines. Now at that time <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">were</transChange> ruling<note>Or "having control"</note> in Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="5">And Samson and his father and mother went down to Timnah, and they came to the vineyards of Timnah, and suddenly a young lion <transChange type="added">came</transChange> roaring to meet him.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And the Spirit of Yahweh rushed upon him, and he tore the lion apart as one might tear apart a male kid goat ({he was bare-handed}).<note>Literally "there was nothing in his hand"</note> But he did not tell his father and mother what he had done.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then he went down and talked to the woman, and {she pleased Samson}.<note>Literally "she did what was right in the eyes of Samson"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">And he returned after awhile {to marry her},<note>Literally "to take her"</note> and he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion, and there <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a swarm of wild honey bees in the body of the lion, and honey.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He scraped it out into his hands, and he went on, eating <transChange type="added">it</transChange> as he went. And he went to his father and mother and gave <transChange type="added">some</transChange> to them, and they ate it. But he did not tell them that he had scraped the honey from the body of the lion. </verse>
    <verse num="10">His father went down to the woman, and Samson prepared there a feast, as young men were accustomed to doing this.</verse>
    <verse num="11">When they saw him, they took thirty companions, and they were with him.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Samson said to them, "Let me tell you a riddle. If you can fully explain it to me within the seven days of the feast, and find <transChange type="added">it out</transChange>, I will give to you thirty linen garments and thirty festal garments.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But if you are unable to explain it to me, you must give me thirty linen garments and thirty festal garments." So they said to him, "Tell your riddle; let us hear it."</verse>
    <verse num="14">He said to them, </verse>
    <verse num="15">When it was the fourth<note>Hebrew "seventh"; other ancient translations have "fourth"</note> day, they said to Samson's wife, "Entice your husband and tell us the riddle, or we will burn you and your father's house with fire. Have you invited us to rob us?"</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Samson's wife wept before him, and she said, "You must hate me; you do not love me. You told the riddle to {my people},<note>Literally "the sons/children of my people"</note> but you have not explained <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to me." He said to her, "I have not explained <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to my father and mother. <transChange type="added">Why</transChange> should I explain it to you?"</verse>
    <verse num="17">She wept before him the seven days of their feast; and it happened, because she nagged him, on the seventh day he explained <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to her, and she told the riddle to {her people}.<note>Literally "the sons/children of her people"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">The men of the city said to him on the seventh day before the sun went <transChange type="added">down</transChange>, </verse>
    <verse num="19">And the Spirit of Yahweh rushed on him, and he went down to Ashkelon. He killed thirty men from them, and he took their belongings, and he gave festal garments to the ones that explained the riddle. {He was angry},<note>Literally "his nose was hot"</note> and he went up to his father's house.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Samson's wife was <transChange type="added">given</transChange> to his companion who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his best man.<note>Or "friend"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">After a while, at the time of the wheat harvest, Samson visited his wife with a {young goat}.<note>Literally "kid of goat"</note> He said, "I want to go to my wife's private room." But her father would not allow him to enter.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Her father said, "I really thought that you hated her, so I gave her to your companion. <transChange type="added">Is</transChange> not her younger sister more beautiful than she? Please, {take her instead}."<note>Literally "let her be in the place of her"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And Samson said to them, "This time, as far as the Philistines are concerned, when I do something evil I am without blame."</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Samson went and captured three hundred foxes, and he took torches. He turned <transChange type="added">them</transChange> tail to tail, and he put one torch between two tails.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He set fire to the torches and let <transChange type="added">the foxes</transChange> go into the standing grain of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines, and he burned both the stacks<note>Hebrew "stack"</note> of sheaves and the standing grain, up to the vineyards<note>Hebrew "vineyard"</note> of olive groves.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines said, "Who has done this?" And they said, "Samson the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he took his wife and gave her to his companion." And <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines went up and burned her and her father with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Samson said to them, "If you want to behave like this, <transChange type="added">I swear</transChange> I will not rest unless I have taken revenge on you."</verse>
    <verse num="8">And {he gave them a thorough beating},<note>Literally "he struck them hip and thigh <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a great blow"</note> and he went down and stayed in the cleft of the rock of Etam. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Then <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines came up and encamped in Judah, and they overran Lehi.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the men of Judah said, "Why have you come up against us?" And they said, "To bind Samson; to do to him just as he did to us."</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then three thousand men from Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and they said to Samson, "Do you not know that the Philistines <transChange type="added">are</transChange> ruling over us? What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this <transChange type="added">that</transChange> you have done to us?" And he said to them, "Just as they did to me, so I have done to them."</verse>
    <verse num="12">They said to him, "We have come down to bind you and give you over into the hand of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines." And Samson said to them, "Swear to me that you will not attack me yourselves."</verse>
    <verse num="13">They said to him, "No, we will only bind you and give you into their hand; we will certainly not kill you." So they bound him with two new ropes, and they brought him up from the rock. </verse>
    <verse num="14">As he came up to Lehi, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines came shouting to meet him; and the Spirit of Yahweh rushed on him, and the ropes that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on his arms became like flax that has burned with fire, and his bindings melted from his hands.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And he found a fresh jawbone of a donkey; he reached down and took it and killed one thousand men with it.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Samson said, </verse>
    <verse num="17">And it happened, when he finished speaking he threw the jawbone from his hand; and he called that place Ramath Lehi.<note>That is, "Hill of the Jawbone"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="18">And he was very thirsty, and he called to Yahweh and said, "You gave this great victory into the hand of your servant, but now I must die of thirst and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?"</verse>
    <verse num="19">So God split the hollow place that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> at Lehi, and water came out from it; and he drank, and his spirit returned, and he was revived. Thus he called its name {The Spring of Ha-Qore},<note>Literally "the spring of the one who called" or "En-hakkore"</note> which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> at Lehi to this day.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And he judged Israel in the days of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines twenty years. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">Samson went down to Gaza; there he saw a prostitute and {had sex with her}.<note>Literally "went into her"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">The Gazites <transChange type="added">were told</transChange>, "Samson has come here," so they surrounded <transChange type="added">the place</transChange> and lay in ambush for him all night at the city gate. They kept silent all night, saying, "<transChange type="added">We will wait</transChange> until the morning light, and then we will kill him."</verse>
    <verse num="3">But Samson lay until the middle of the night; he got up in the middle of the night and took hold of the doors of the city gate and the two door posts, tore them loose with the bar, put them on his shoulders, and carried them up to the top of the hill that is {in front of}<note>Literally "on the face of"</note> Hebron. </verse>
    <verse num="4">After this he fell in love <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a woman in the wadi<note>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</note> of Sorek, and her name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Delilah.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines came up to her and said, "Entice him and find out what makes his strength so great, and how we can overpower him, so that we may bind him up in order to subdue him; each of us will give you eleven hundred pieces of silver.</verse>
    <verse num="6">So Delilah said to Samson, "Please tell me what makes your strength so great, and with what can you be tied up to subdue you?"</verse>
    <verse num="7">Samson said to her, "If you tie me up with seven fresh bowstrings that are not dried up, I will become weak like everyone else."</verse>
    <verse num="8">So the rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines brought up to her seven fresh bowstrings that were not dried up, and she tied him up with them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The ambush <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sitting <transChange type="added">in wait</transChange> for her in an inner room. And she said to him, "<transChange type="added">The</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">are</transChange> upon you Samson!" And he snapped the bowstrings just as flax fiber snaps when it comes close to fire. And <transChange type="added">the secret of</transChange> his strength remained unknown.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Delilah said to Samson, "Look, you have mocked me and told me lies. Please tell me how you can be bound."</verse>
    <verse num="11">He said to her, "If they tie me tightly with new ropes that have not been used, I will become weak and be like everyone else."</verse>
    <verse num="12">So Delilah took new ropes and tied him up with them, and she said to him, "<transChange type="added">The</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">are</transChange> upon you, Samson!" (The ambush <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sitting in an inner room.) But he snapped them from his arms like thread. </verse>
    <verse num="13">And Delilah said to Samson, "Until now you have mocked me and told lies to me. Tell me how you can be bound." And he said to her, "If you weave seven locks of my head with warp-threads."<note>Many modern translations include an additional phrase found in the Greek translation: "and fasten it with a pin, then I will become weak and be like everyone else. So while he slept, Delilah took the seven locks of his head and wove them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">She fastened <transChange type="added">it</transChange> with the pin and said to him, "<transChange type="added">The</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">are</transChange> upon you, Samson!" And Samson woke up from his sleep and tore loose the loom pin of the web and the warp-threads.<note>Hebrew "warp-thread"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="15">And she said to him, "How can you say, 'I love you,' when your heart is not with me? You have mocked me these three times, and you have not told me how your strength is <transChange type="added">so</transChange> great."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And because she nagged him day after day with her words, and pestered him, {his soul grew impatient to the point of death}.<note>Literally "his inner self grew tired/impatient to death"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">So {he confided everything to her},<note>Literally "he told her all his heart"</note> and he said to her, "A razor {has never touched}<note>Literally "has never gone up"</note> my head, for I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a {Nazirite of God}<note>Literally "consecrated of God" or "devoted of God"</note> {from birth}.<note>Literally "from the womb of my mother"</note> If I am shaved my strength will leave me, and I will become weak, like everyone else. </verse>
    <verse num="18">Delilah realized that {he had confided in her},<note>Literally "he had told her all his heart"</note> so she sent and called the rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines, saying, "Come up one more time, for {he has confided in me}."<note>Literally "he has told me all his heart"</note> And the rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines came up, and they brought the money {with them}.<note>Literally "in their hand"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">And she put him to sleep on her lap; then she called the men<note>Hebrew "man"</note> and shaved off seven locks of his head. Then she began to subdue him,<note>Or "humiliate him"</note> and his strength went away from him.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And she said to him, "<transChange type="added">The</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">are</transChange> upon you, Samson!" And he woke up from his sleep and said, "I will go out just like every other time and shake myself free," but he did not know that Yahweh had left him.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines seized him, gouged his eyes, and brought him to Gaza. They tied him up with bronze shackles, and he became a grinder {in the prison}.<note>Literally "in the house of the prisoners"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">But the hair of his head began to grow back after it had been shaved off. </verse>
    <verse num="23">The rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines had gathered to sacrifice a great sacrifice to Dagon their god and to rejoice. And they said, "Our god has given Samson our enemy into our hand."</verse>
    <verse num="24">And the people saw him, and they praised their god, for they said, "Our god has given into our hand those who hate us, devastate our land, and have {killed many of us}."<note>Literally "made numerous our slain"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">After awhile, when their hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> were merry, they said, "Call Samson and let him entertain us." And they called Samson {from the prison},<note>Literally "from the house of the prisoner"</note> and {he entertained them}.<note>Literally "he made sport before them"</note> And they made him stand between the pillars.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then Samson said to the servant who was holding him by his hand, "Position me so that I can touch the pillars on which the house<note>Or "temple"</note> rests, so I can lean on them."</verse>
    <verse num="27">And the house<note>Or "temple"</note> was full of men and women, and all of the rulers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines <transChange type="added">were</transChange> there--about three thousand men and women were on the roof watching the performance of Samson. </verse>
    <verse num="28">And Samson called to Yahweh and said, "My Lord Yahweh, remember me! Please give me strength this one time, O God, so that I can repay <transChange type="added">with</transChange> one act of revenge to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Philistines for my eyes."</verse>
    <verse num="29">And Samson reached out and held two of the middle pillars on which the house<note>Or "temple"</note> <transChange type="added">was</transChange> resting, and he leaned on them, one on his right and one on his left.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And Samson said, "Let me die with the Philistines." And he pushed<note>Or "he caused to bend"</note> with <transChange type="added">all his</transChange> strength, and the house<note>Or "temple"</note> fell on the rulers and all of the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him. And the dead whom he killed in his death were more than those he killed in his life. </verse>
    <verse num="31">His brothers and {his whole family}<note>Literally "all the house of his father"</note> came down and picked him up; and they brought him up and buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the tomb of Manoah his father; he judged Israel twenty years. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">There was a man from the hill country of Ephraim; his name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Micah.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he said to his mother, "The eleven hundred <transChange type="added">pieces</transChange> of silver that were taken from you, and about which you also pronounced a curse {in my hearing},<note>Literally "In my ears"</note> are with me; I took it." And his mother said, "Blessed be my son by Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="3">He returned the eleven hundred pieces<note>Hebrew "piece"</note> of silver to his mother, and his mother thought, "I will certainly consecrate to Yahweh the pieces<note>Hebrew "piece"</note> of silver from my hand for my son to make an idol of cast metal; now then, I will return them<note>Hebrew "it"</note> to you."</verse>
    <verse num="4">When he returned the pieces<note>Hebrew "piece"</note> of silver to his mother, his mother took two hundred pieces<note>Hebrew "piece"</note> of silver, and she gave it to the smith, and he made it <transChange type="added">into</transChange> an idol of cast metal; and it was in the house of Micah.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The man Micah had for himself {a shrine},<note>Literally "a house of god"</note> and he made an ephod and teraphim, and {he appointed one of his sons}<note>Literally "he filled the hand of one of his sons"</note> who became a priest for him.</verse>
    <verse num="6">In those days there was no king in Israel, and each one did what was right in his own eyes. </verse>
    <verse num="7">There was a young man from Bethlehem in Judah, from the clan of Judah; he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a Levite and <transChange type="added">was</transChange> dwelling as a foreigner<note>Or "alien"</note> there.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And the man went from the town of Bethlehem in Judah to live as a foreigner<note>Or "alien"</note> wherever he could find <transChange type="added">a place</transChange>. And he came <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, to continue his journey.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Micah said to him, "From where do you come?" And he said to him, "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a Levite from Bethlehem in Judah; I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> going to dwell as a foreigner<note>Or "alien"</note> wherever I can find <transChange type="added">a place</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Micah said to him, "Stay with me and be to me a father and a priest, and I will give to you ten pieces<note>Hebrew "piece"</note> of silver a year, a set of clothes, and your food." So the Levite went <transChange type="added">with him</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The Levite agreed to stay with the man; and the young man became as one of his sons.</verse>
    <verse num="12">So Micah {appointed the Levite},<note>Literally "filled the hand of the Levite"</note> and the young man became a priest for him; and he was in the house of Micah.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And Micah said, "Now I know Yahweh will make me prosperous, because the Levite has become my priest." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">In those days there was no king in Israel. And in those days the tribe of the Danites <transChange type="added">was</transChange> seeking territory for itself to live in, because until that day it had not been allotted territory among the tribes of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan sent from the whole number of their clan five {capable men}<note>Literally "sons of physical strength"</note> from Zorah and Eshtaol to spy out the land and to explore it. And they said to them, "Go, explore the land." And they went to the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, and they spent the night there.<note>Or "they lodged there"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">While they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with the house of Micah, they recognized the voice of the young Levite, and they turned aside there and said to him, "Who brought you here? What <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you doing in this place, and {what is your business here}?"<note>Literally "What is for you here?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And he said to them, "Micah did such and such for me and hired me, and I became his priest."</verse>
    <verse num="5">And they said to him, "Please inquire of God that we may know whether our journey that we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> going on will be successful."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And the priest said to them, "Go in peace. Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in front of you on the journey you want to go on." </verse>
    <verse num="7">And the five men went and came to Laish, and they observed the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> living according to the customs of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sidonians, quiet and unsuspecting, and lacking nothing in the land, and possessing restraint.<note>Or perhaps "prosperity"; the Hebrew of this word is uncertain</note> And they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> far from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sidonians and had no word with anyone.</verse>
    <verse num="8">They came to their relatives<note>Or "brothers"</note> <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Zorah and Eshtaol, and their relatives<note>Or "brothers"</note> said to them, "What <transChange type="added">do</transChange> you <transChange type="added">report</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="9">And they said to them, "Come, let us go up against them; for we have seen the land, and <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> very good. Will you do nothing? Do not hesitate to go, to enter, to possess the land.</verse>
    <verse num="10">When you go you will come to an unsuspecting people, and the land {is spread out on all sides};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">is</transChange> wide of hands"</note> God has given a place into your hands where there is no lack of anything that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on the earth." </verse>
    <verse num="11">Six hundred men from the clan of the Danites from Zorah and Eshtaol, armed <transChange type="added">with</transChange> weapons of war, set out from there.</verse>
    <verse num="12">They went up and encamped at Kiriath Jearim in Judah. Therefore they called this place Camp of Dan<note>That is "Mahaneh-dan"</note> to this day; it is west of Kiriath Jearim.</verse>
    <verse num="13">From there they crossed <transChange type="added">over to</transChange> the hill country of Ephraim, and they came to the house of Micah. </verse>
    <verse num="14">And the five men that went out to spy out the land (<transChange type="added">that is</transChange>, Laish) responded and said to their relatives,<note>Or "brothers"</note> "Do you know that there are in these houses an ephod, teraphim, and an idol of cast metal? So then, consider what you must do."</verse>
    <verse num="15">So they turned to that direction, and they came to the house of the young Levite, the house of Micah, and {they greeted him}.<note>Literally "they asked for him in peace"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">And six hundred men from the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan, armed <transChange type="added">with</transChange> their weapons of war, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> standing <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the gate.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the five men that went to spy out the land went up, and they entered there <transChange type="added">and</transChange> took the carved divine image, ephod, teraphim, and the molten image. The priest <transChange type="added">was</transChange> standing <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the gate <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the six hundred men armed <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the weapons of war.</verse>
    <verse num="18">When these went to Micah's house, they took the divine carved image, ephod, the teraphim, and the molten image, and the priest asked them, "What <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you doing?"</verse>
    <verse num="19">And they said to him, "Keep quiet! Put your hand on your mouth and come with us and be for us a father and a priest. Is it better being a priest for a house of one man or being a priest for a tribe and clan in Israel?"</verse>
    <verse num="20">{The priest accepted the offer},<note>Literally "It was good in the heart of the priest"</note> and he took the ephod, teraphim, and molten image and went along with the people. </verse>
    <verse num="21">And they turned<note>Or "resumed their journey"</note> and went and put the little children, the livestock, and the valuable property in front of them.</verse>
    <verse num="22">When they were at a distance from the house, Micah and the men who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the houses that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> near the house of Micah cried out, and they overtook the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And they called to the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan, who turned around to face them, and they said to Micah, "What is the matter with you that you assembled together?"</verse>
    <verse num="24">He said, "You took away my gods that I had made, and the priest, and then you go <transChange type="added">away</transChange>. What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> now left for me? How can you say to me, 'What is the matter?'"</verse>
    <verse num="25">And the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan said to him, "You should not let your voice be heard among us, so that {ill-tempered men}<note>Literally "men of bitter soul"</note> {will not attack you},<note>Literally "will not fall on you"</note> {and take your life}<note>Literally "and you will lose your life"</note> and the lives of your household."</verse>
    <verse num="26">And the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan went their way. When Micah saw that they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> stronger than him, he turned to return to his house. </verse>
    <verse num="27">And they took what Micah had made, and his priest, and they came to Laish, to a quiet and unsuspecting people, and {they put them to the sword}<note>Literally "they put them to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and burned the city with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="28">There was no deliverer, because it <transChange type="added">was</transChange> far from Sidon, and {they had had no dealings with anyone}.<note>Literally "a thing was not for them with anyone"</note> It <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in the valley that belonged to Beth-rehob, and they rebuilt<note>Hebrew "built"</note> the city and lived in it.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And they called the name of the city Dan, after Dan their ancestor,<note>Or "father"</note> who was born to Israel; but the former name of the city <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Laish.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Dan set up for themselves the carved divine image, and Jonathan son of Gershom, son of Manasseh,<note>Other ancient versions read "Moses"</note> he and his sons were priests for the tribe of the Danites until the time of the captivity of the land.</verse>
    <verse num="31">So they set up for themselves the carved divine image that Micah had made, all the days that the house of God <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in Shiloh. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">In those days there was no king in Israel; there was a man, a Levite, who dwelled as a foreigner<note>Or "alien"</note> in the remote areas of the hill country of Ephraim. And he took for himself a concubine from Bethlehem in Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="2">But his concubine felt repugnance toward him,<note>Other modern translations read "his concubine played the harlot against him"</note> and she left him and went to her father's house, to Bethlehem in Judah; she was there some four months.</verse>
    <verse num="3">So her husband set out, and he went after her to speak {tenderly to her},<note>Literally "to her heart"</note> to bring her back. He took with him his servant and a pair of donkeys. And she brought him <transChange type="added">to</transChange> her father's house, and the father of the young woman saw him and was glad to meet him.</verse>
    <verse num="4">His father-in-law, the young woman's father, urged him to stay with him three days; and they ate and drank, and they spent the night there.</verse>
    <verse num="5">On the fourth day, they rose early in the morning, and he prepared to go, but the father of the young woman said to his son-in-law, "{Refresh yourself}<note>Literally "Refresh your heart"</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a bit of food, and afterward you may go."</verse>
    <verse num="6">So the two of them sat and ate and drank together, and the father of the young woman said to the man, "Please, agree to spend the night and {enjoy yourself}."<note>Literally "and let your heart be good"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">The man got up to go, but his father-in-law urged him, and he returned and spent the night there.</verse>
    <verse num="8">On the fifth day he rose early in the morning to go, and the father of the young woman said, "Please, {enjoy yourself},"<note>Literally "and let your heart be good"</note> and they lingered until the day declined, and the two of them ate.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the man got up to go--he, his concubine, and his servant--but his father-in-law, the father of the young woman, said to him, "Please, the day has worn on to evening; please, spend the night, the day has drawn to a close. Spend the night here and {enjoy yourself}.<note>Literally "and let your heart be good"</note> You can rise early tomorrow for your journey and {go to your home}."<note>Literally "go to your tent"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="10">But the man was not willing to spend the night, and he got up and went; and he arrived opposite Jebus (that is, Jerusalem). <transChange type="added">He had</transChange> with him a pair of saddled donkeys and his concubine.</verse>
    <verse num="11">They <transChange type="added">were</transChange> near Jebus, and {the day was far spent},<note>Literally "the day went down very"</note> and the servant said to his master, "Please, come, let us turn aside to this city of the Jebusites,<note>Hebrew "Jebusite"</note> and let us spend the night in it."</verse>
    <verse num="12">But his master said to him, "We will not turn aside to the city of foreigners,<note>Hebrew "foreigner"</note> who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not from the {Israelites};<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> we will cross over up to Gibeah."</verse>
    <verse num="13">And he said to his servant, "Come, let us approach one of these places; we will spend the night in Gibeah or in Ramah."</verse>
    <verse num="14">So they crossed over and went their way, and the sun went down on them beside Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And they turned aside there to enter <transChange type="added">and</transChange> to spend the night at Gibeah. And they went and sat in the open square of the city, but no one {took them in to spend the night}.<note>Literally "was receiving them to <transChange type="added">their</transChange> house to spend the night"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="16">Then behold, an old man <transChange type="added">was</transChange> coming from his work from the field in the evening, and the man <transChange type="added">was</transChange> from the hill country of Ephraim, and he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> dwelling as a foreigner<note>Or "alien"</note> in Gibeah. (The people of the place <transChange type="added">were</transChange> descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin.)</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the old man raised his eyes and saw the traveler in the open square of the city, and he said, "Where are you going, and from where do you come?"</verse>
    <verse num="18">And he said to him, "We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> crossing over from Bethlehem in Judah up to the remote areas of the hill country of Ephraim, where I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> from. I went to Bethlehem in Judah, but <transChange type="added">now</transChange> I am going to Yahweh's house,<note>Or "my house," according to the LXX and some modern translations (NASB, NRSV)</note> but no one {took me in to spend the night}.<note>Literally "was receiving me to <transChange type="added">their</transChange> house"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">There is both straw and fodder for our donkeys, and also bread and wine for me, for your servant,<note>That is, the concubine</note> and for the young man who is with your servant; there is no lack of anything."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And the old man said, "Peace to you. I will take care of your needs; however, you must not spend the night in the open square."</verse>
    <verse num="21">So he brought him to his house, and he fed the donkeys; they washed their feet, ate, and drank. </verse>
    <verse num="22">While {they were enjoying themselves},<note>Literally "their hearts <transChange type="added">were</transChange> being good"</note> behold, the men of the city, {the perverse lot},<note>Literally "sons of uselessness"</note> surrounded the house, pounding on the door. And they said to the old man, the owner of the house, "Bring out the man who came to your house so that {we may have sex with him}."<note>Literally "we may know him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">So the man, the owner of the house, went out to them and said to them, "No, my brothers, do not act wickedly; since this man has come into my house, do not do this disgraceful thing.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Here is my virgin daughter and his concubine. Please, let me bring them out; do violence to them,<note>Or "rape them"</note> and do to them {whatever you please}.<note>Literally "the good in your eyes"</note> Do not do this disgraceful thing to this man."</verse>
    <verse num="25">But the men were not willing to listen to him, and the man seized his concubine and brought <transChange type="added">her</transChange> out to them; and they had intercourse with her, and they abused her all night until the morning; they let her go at the approach of dawn.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And the woman came as the morning appeared, and she fell <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the man's house where her master was, until daylight.<note>Hebrew "light"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="27">In the morning her master got up, and he opened the doors of the house and went out to go on his journey, and behold, his concubine <transChange type="added">was</transChange> falling<note>Or "spread out"</note> <transChange type="added">at</transChange> the entrance of the house, with her hand on the threshold.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And he said to her, "Get up, let us go," but there was no answer. So he put her on the donkey, and the man got up and went to his place.</verse>
    <verse num="29">When he entered his house he took a knife, and he grasped his concubine and cut her into twelve pieces; and he sent her throughout the whole territory of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="30">All who saw <transChange type="added">it</transChange> said, "Nothing like this has <transChange type="added">ever</transChange> been since the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went up from the land of Egypt until this day. Take note of it, consider <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, and speak <transChange type="added">up</transChange>." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">All the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went out, from Dan to Beersheba, including the land of Gilead, and they gathered as one body<note>Hebrew "man"</note> to Yahweh <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Mizpah.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And the leaders of all the people, all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand sword-bearing infantry.</verse>
    <verse num="3">(The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin heard that the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> had gone up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Mizpah.) And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons of Israel" or "children of "Israel"</note> said, "Tell us, how did this evil act occur?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">The Levite, the husband of the murdered woman, answered and said, "I came to Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to spend the night.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The lords of Gibeah rose up against me and surrounded the house at night. They intended to kill me, and they raped my concubine, and she died.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then I grabbed my concubine and cut her into pieces, and I sent her throughout all the territory of Israel's inheritance; for they committed a shameful and disgraceful thing in Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Look, all you {Israelites}!<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> {Make your decision}<note>Literally "give your word"</note> and advice here." </verse>
    <verse num="8">All the people got up as one body,<note>Hebrew "man"</note> saying, "Not one of us will go to his tent, or will any of us return to his house.</verse>
    <verse num="9">So then, this is what we will do to Gibeah: <transChange type="added">we will go up</transChange> against her by lot.</verse>
    <verse num="10">We will take ten men of one hundred from all the tribes of Israel, and one hundred of one thousand, and one thousand of ten thousand, to bring provisions to the troops, to repay <transChange type="added">them</transChange> when they come to Gibeah<note>Hebrew "Geba"</note> of Benjamin for all the disgraceful things<note>Hebrew "thing"</note> they did in Israel."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And all the men of Israel were gathered to the city as one body<note>Hebrew "man"</note> united. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Then the tribes of Israel sent men throughout all the tribes of Benjamin, saying, "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this wickedness that happened among you?</verse>
    <verse num="13">So then, hand over the men, {the perverse lot},<note>Literally "sons of uselessness"</note> who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in Gibeah, so that we may kill them and purge <transChange type="added">this</transChange> wickedness from Israel." But the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin were not willing to listen to the voice of their relatives,<note>Or "brothers"</note> the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">And the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin were gathered from the cities to Gibeah to go out for battle against the {Israelites}.<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">From the cities the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin were counted on that day twenty-six thousand {sword-wielding men},<note>Literally "men drawing sword"</note> besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who were counted seven hundred well-trained<note>Or "chosen"</note> men.</verse>
    <verse num="16">From all these troops <transChange type="added">were</transChange> seven hundred well-trained<note>Or "choice/chosen"</note> men {who were left-handed};<note>Literally "bound <transChange type="added">by</transChange> his right hand"</note> each one could sling with a stone at a hair and not miss.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the men of Israel besides Benjamin were counted four hundred thousand {sword-wielding men};<note>Literally "men drawing sword"</note> {all were warriors}.<note>Literally "all were men of war"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="18">Then the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> got up and went up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Bethel, and they inquired of God, saying, "Who will go up first for the battle against the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin?" And Yahweh said, "Judah <transChange type="added">will go</transChange> first."</verse>
    <verse num="19">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> got up in the morning, and they encamped against Gibeah.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Then the men of Israel marched out for the battle against Benjamin, and the men of Israel took up positions against them <transChange type="added">for</transChange> battle at Gibeah.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin went out from Gibeah, and they struck down on that day twenty-two thousand men of Israel to the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="22">But the troops, the men of Israel, {encouraged themselves},<note>Literally "took heart"</note> and again they arranged <transChange type="added">their</transChange> battle <transChange type="added">lines</transChange> in the place where they had arranged themselves the first day.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went up and wept before Yahweh until evening and inquired of Yahweh, saying, "Should we again draw near from the battle against the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin, our relatives?"<note>Hebrew "my brother"</note> And Yahweh said, "Go up against them."<note>Hebrew "him"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="24">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> drew near to the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin on the second day.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And Benjamin went out from Gibeah to meet them on the second day, and they struck down the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> again, eighteen thousand men to the ground; all of these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> {sword-wielding}.<note>Literally "drawers of sword"</note></verse>
    <verse num="26">And all the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> and all the troops went up and came to Bethel and wept; and they sat there before Yahweh and fasted on that day until evening; and they offered burnt offerings and fellowship offerings before Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> inquired of Yahweh (In those days the ark of the covenant of God <transChange type="added">was</transChange> there,</verse>
    <verse num="28">and Phinehas son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> standing {before it}<note>Literally "before presence of it/him"</note> <transChange type="added">to minister</transChange> in those days), saying, "Should we go out once more to battle against the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin our relatives,<note>Hebrew "my brother"</note> or should we stop?" And Yahweh said, "Go up tomorrow; I will give them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> into your hand." </verse>
    <verse num="29">So Israel stationed an ambush all around Gibeah.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> went up against the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin on the third day, and they took up positions against Gibeah as before.</verse>
    <verse num="31">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin went out to meet the troops, and they lured <transChange type="added">them</transChange> away from the city and began to inflict casualties on the troops as before, on the main road, one of which goes up <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Bethel, the other to Gibeah; <transChange type="added">and</transChange> in the field <transChange type="added">there were</transChange> about thirty men of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin thought,<note>Or "said"</note> "They <transChange type="added">are</transChange> being defeated before us {as previously},"<note>Literally "on the first"</note> and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> said, "Let us flee and lure them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> away from the city to the main roads."</verse>
    <verse num="33">And all the men of Israel got up from their places<note>Hebrew "place"</note> and took up positions in Baal Tamar; and the ambush of Israel charged from their places,<note>Hebrew "place"</note> from the vicinity of Gibeah.<note>Hebrew "Geba"</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">Then ten thousand well-trained<note>Or "choice/chosen"</note> men from all Israel came out against Gibeah, and the battle became fierce;<note>Or "the battle became heavy"</note> they did not know that disaster <transChange type="added">was about to</transChange> {close in}<note>Literally "touching"</note> on them.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And Yahweh defeated Benjamin in the presence of Israel, and the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> destroyed on that day twenty-five thousand one hundred men of Benjamin, all of them {sword-wielding}.<note>Literally "drawing sword"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="36">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin saw that they were defeated, and the men of Israel gave ground<note>Or "a place" or "space"</note> to Benjamin because they trusted the ambush that they had set against Gibeah.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And the ambush came quickly and advanced against Gibeah, and it {put the whole city to the sword}.<note>Literally "struck the whole city with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note></verse>
    <verse num="38">Now the appointed time for the men of Israel with the ambush was that they sent up for them a great amount of smoke from the city.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And the men of Israel turned in the battle, and Benjamin began to inflict casualties on about thirty men of Israel because they thought,<note>Or "said"</note> "They will be completely defeated before us as in the first battle."</verse>
    <verse num="40">And the cloud of smoke began to go up from the city in a column of smoke, and Benjamin turned backward, and behold, the whole city was going up {in smoke}!<note>Literally "to heaven"</note></verse>
    <verse num="41">And the men of Israel turned, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed because they saw that disaster was {closing in}<note>Literally "touching"</note> on them.</verse>
    <verse num="42">And they retreated from before the men of Israel to the way of the wilderness, but the battle caught up to them, and <transChange type="added">those</transChange> who <transChange type="added">came</transChange> from the cities<note>Other ancient translations "city"</note> destroyed them in the midst of them.</verse>
    <verse num="43">They surrounded Benjamin; they pursued them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> without rest<note>Or "<transChange type="added">at</transChange> Nohah," a location</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> trod them<note>Hebrew "him"</note> down opposite Gibeah to the east.</verse>
    <verse num="44">And eighteen thousand men from Benjamin fell, all of them {able men}.<note>Literally "men of strength"</note></verse>
    <verse num="45">And they turned and fled toward the wilderness, to the rock of Rimmon, but they cut down on the main roads five thousand men; and they pursued after them up to Gidom, and they struck down two thousand men.</verse>
    <verse num="46">So all of Benjamin who fell on that day were twenty-five thousand {sword-wielding men};<note>Literally "men drawing sword"</note> all of these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> {able men}.<note>Literally "men of strength"</note></verse>
    <verse num="47">But six hundred turned and fled toward the wilderness, to the rock of Rimmon, and they remained at the rock of Rimmon <transChange type="added">for</transChange> four months.</verse>
    <verse num="48">And the men of Israel returned to the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin, and they put them to {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally <transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> both the inhabitants of city and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> animals that were found; they also set on fire all the cities that they found. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">The men of Israel had sworn at Mizpah, saying, "None of us will give his daughter to Benjamin as a wife."</verse>
    <verse num="2">And the people of Bethel came and sat there until evening before God, and they lifted their voices and {wept bitterly}.<note>Literally "they cried a great weeping"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And they said, "Why, Yahweh, God of Israel, has it happened today in Israel that one tribe is lacking from Israel?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">On the next day the people rose early, and they built there an altar and sacrificed burnt offerings and fellowship offerings.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> said, "Who in the assembly has not come up from all the tribes of Israel to Yahweh?" For a solemn oath was <transChange type="added">taken</transChange> concerning whoever did not come up to Yahweh at Mizpah, saying, "He will certainly be put to death."</verse>
    <verse num="6">But the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> had compassion for Benjamin, their relatives,<note>Hebrew "his brother"</note> and they said, "Today one tribe is cut off from Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="7">What will we do for them--for the <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> being left over--for wives? For we have sworn by Yahweh not to give to them our daughters as wives." </verse>
    <verse num="8">They asked, "Which one is there from the tribes of Israel who did not come up to Yahweh at Mizpah?" And behold, no one came from Jabesh-gilead to the camp, to the assembly.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The people were counted, and no one was there from the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the congregation sent there twelve thousand men from the troops, and they commanded them, saying, "Go, strike the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead with {the edge of the sword},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> mouth of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sword"</note> and the women and children.</verse>
    <verse num="11">This is the thing you will do: {you will destroy}<note>Literally "you will devote to destruction"</note> every man and {every woman who had sex with a man}."<note>Literally "every woman who knows the bed of a man"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">And they found among the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead four hundred young virgins<note>Hebrew "virgin"</note> who had not {had sex with a man},<note>Literally "known a man, as far as <transChange type="added">the</transChange> bed of a male"</note> and they brought them to the camp at Shiloh, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the land of Canaan. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Then the congregation sent and spoke all <transChange type="added">this</transChange> to the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> at the rock of Rimmon, and {they assured them they would not be hurt}.<note>Literally "they proclaimed peace to them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">And Benjamin returned at that time, and they gave to them the women whom they kept alive from Jabesh-gilead; but they were not enough for them. </verse>
    <verse num="15">And the people felt sorry for Benjamin because {Yahweh weakened the tribes of Israel}.<note>Literally "Yahweh make a breach with the tribes of Israel"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">So the elders of the congregation said, "What should we do for the remaining <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> for wives, since the women from Benjamin have been destroyed?"</verse>
    <verse num="17">And they said, "<transChange type="added">There must be</transChange> a remnant for Benjamin, so that a tribe will not be blotted out from Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But we cannot give them wives from our daughters." (For the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> swore, saying, "Cursed be <transChange type="added">anyone</transChange> who gives a wife to Benjamin.")</verse>
    <verse num="19">And they said, "Look, the annual feast of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in Shiloh, which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to the north of Bethel, {east}<note>Literally "rising of the sun"</note> of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> main road that goes up from Bethel to Shechem, and south of Lebonah.</verse>
    <verse num="20">They instructed the descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin, saying, "Go, lie in ambush in the vineyards,</verse>
    <verse num="21">and watch and look; when the daughters of Shiloh dance in the dances, come out from the vineyards and seize for yourselves a wife from the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And if their fathers or their brothers complain to us, we will say to them, 'Allow us to have them, because we did not capture a wife for each man in the battle, and because you did not give <transChange type="added">them</transChange> to them, {or else}<note>Literally "as the time"</note> you would have been guilty.'"</verse>
    <verse num="23">The descendants<note>Or "sons/children"</note> of Benjamin did likewise, and they took wives for each of them from the dancers whom they seized, and they went and returned to their territory, and they rebuilt the cities and they lived in them.</verse>
    <verse num="24">So the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> dispersed from there at that time according to tribe and family; and they went out from there, each one to their own territory.</verse>
    <verse num="25">In those days there was no king in Israel; each one did what was right in his own eyes. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>