<book num="1Cor">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul, called <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother,</verse>
    <verse num="2">to the church of God sanctified in Christ Jesus that is in Corinth,<note>Some manuscripts have "to the church of God that is in Corinth, sanctified in Christ Jesus"</note> called <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> saints, together with all those who call upon the name of our Lord Jesus Christ in every place, their <transChange type="added">Lord</transChange><note>*Here "Lord" must be supplied to indicate the referent; otherwise this could be understood as "their place and ours"</note> and ours.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="4">I give thanks to my God always concerning you, because of the grace of God which was given to you in Christ Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="5">that<note>*Or "because"; the conjunction either (1) introduces a content clause ("that") giving the content of Paul's thanks, or (2) introduces a causal clause ("because") giving the reason for Paul's thanks</note> in everything you were made rich in him, in all speech and all knowledge,</verse>
    <verse num="6">just as the testimony about Christ has been confirmed in you,</verse>
    <verse num="7">so that you do not lack in any spiritual gift <transChange type="added">as you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("eagerly await") which is understood as temporal</note> eagerly await the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="8">who will also confirm you until the end, blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="9">God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> faithful, by whom you were called to fellowship with his Son Jesus Christ our Lord. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Now I exhort you, brothers, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you all say the same <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> and there not be divisions among you, and that you be made complete in the same mind and with the same purpose.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For it has been made clear to me concerning you, my brothers, by {Chloe's people}<note>Literally "those of Chloe"</note>, that there are quarrels among you.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But I say this, that each of you is saying, "I am with Paul," and "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with Apollos," and "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with Cephas," and "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with Christ."</verse>
    <verse num="13">Has Christ been divided? Paul was not crucified for you, was he?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?</verse>
    <verse num="14">I give thanks<note>Some manuscripts have "I give thanks to God"</note> that I baptized none of you except Crispus and Gaius,</verse>
    <verse num="15">lest anyone should say that you were baptized in my name.</verse>
    <verse num="16">(Now I also baptized the household of Stephanas. Beyond that I do not know if I baptized anyone else.)</verse>
    <verse num="17">For Christ did not send me to baptize, but to proclaim the gospel, not with {clever speech}<note>Literally "wisdom of word"</note>, lest the cross of Christ be emptied. </verse>
    <verse num="18">For the message about the cross is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is the power of God.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For it is written, </verse>
    <verse num="20">Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the wise person? Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the scribe? Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the debater of this age? Has not God made foolish the wisdom of the world?</verse>
    <verse num="21">For since, in the wisdom of God, the world through its wisdom did not know God, God was pleased through the foolishness of preaching to save those who believe.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For indeed, Jews ask for sign miracles and Greeks seek wisdom,</verse>
    <verse num="23">but we preach Christ crucified, to the Jews a cause for stumbling, but to the Gentiles foolishness,</verse>
    <verse num="24">but to those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the power of God and the wisdom of God.</verse>
    <verse num="25">For the foolishness of God is wiser than human <transChange type="added">wisdom</transChange>,<note>Literally "man"</note> and the weakness of God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> stronger than human <transChange type="added">strength</transChange>.<note>Literally "man"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="26">For consider your calling, brothers, that not many <transChange type="added">were</transChange> wise according to human standards,<note>Literally "according to flesh"</note> not many <transChange type="added">were</transChange> powerful, not many <transChange type="added">were</transChange> well born.</verse>
    <verse num="27">But the foolish <transChange type="added">things</transChange> of the world God chose in order that he might put to shame the wise, and the weak <transChange type="added">things</transChange> of the world God chose in order that he might put to shame the strong,</verse>
    <verse num="28">and the insignificant of the world, and the despised, God chose, the things that are not, in order that he might abolish the things that are,</verse>
    <verse num="29">so that all flesh may not boast before God.</verse>
    <verse num="30">But from him you are in Christ Jesus, who became wisdom to us from God, and righteousness and sanctification and redemption,</verse>
    <verse num="31">so that, just as it is written, "The one who boasts, let him boast in the Lord."<note>A quotation from Jer 9:24</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">And I, <transChange type="added">when I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("came") which is understood as temporal</note> came to you, brothers, did not come with superiority of speech or of wisdom, proclaiming to you the testimony<note>Some manuscripts have "mystery"</note> of God.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For I decided not to know anything among you except Jesus Christ and him crucified.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And I came to you in weakness and in fear and with much trembling,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and my speech and my preaching <transChange type="added">were</transChange> not with the persuasiveness<note>Some manuscripts have "with persuasive words"</note> of wisdom, but with a demonstration of the Spirit and power,</verse>
    <verse num="5">in order that your faith would not be in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Now we do speak wisdom among the mature, but wisdom not of this age or of the rulers of this age, who are perishing,</verse>
    <verse num="7">but we speak the hidden wisdom of God in a mystery, which God predestined before the ages for our glory,</verse>
    <verse num="8">which none of the rulers of this age knew. For if they had known <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.</verse>
    <verse num="9">But just as it is written, </verse>
    <verse num="10">For<note>Some manuscripts have "But to us God has revealed <transChange type="added">them</transChange>"</note> to us God has revealed <transChange type="added">them</transChange> through the Spirit. For the Spirit searches all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, even the depths of God.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For who among men knows the things of a man, except the spirit of the man that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in him? Thus also no one knows the things of God except the Spirit of God.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now we have received not the spirit of the world, but the Spirit who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from God, in order that we may know the things freely given to us by God,</verse>
    <verse num="13"><transChange type="added">things</transChange> which we also speak, not in words taught by human wisdom, but in <transChange type="added">words</transChange> taught by the Spirit, explaining spiritual <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to spiritual <transChange type="added">people</transChange>.<note>Or "in spiritual <transChange type="added">words</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">But the natural man does not accept the things of the Spirit of God, for they are foolishness to him, and he is not able to understand <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, because they are spiritually discerned.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Now the spiritual <transChange type="added">person</transChange> discerns all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, but he himself is judged by no one.</verse>
    <verse num="16">"For who has known the mind of the Lord; who has advised him?"<note>A quotation from Isa 40:13</note> But we have the mind of Christ. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">And I, brothers, was not able to speak to you as to spiritual <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, but as to fleshly <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, as to infants in Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="2">I gave you milk to drink, not solid food, for you were not yet able <transChange type="added">to eat it</transChange>. But now you are still not able,</verse>
    <verse num="3">for you are still fleshly. For where <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> jealousy and strife among you, are you not fleshly, and do you not live like <transChange type="added">unregenerate</transChange> people?<note>That is, like people who do not possess the Spirit at all</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">For whenever anyone says, "I am with Paul," and another, "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with Apollos," are you not <transChange type="added">merely</transChange> human? </verse>
    <verse num="5">Therefore, what is Apollos and what is Paul? Servants through whom you believed, and to each as the Lord gave.</verse>
    <verse num="6">I planted, Apollos watered, but God was causing <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to grow.</verse>
    <verse num="7">So then, neither the one who plants nor the one who waters is anything, but God who is causing <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to grow.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Now the one who plants and the one who waters are one, but each one will receive his own reward according to his own labor.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For we are God's fellow workers; you are God's field, God's building. </verse>
    <verse num="10">According to the grace of God given to me, like a skilled master builder I laid a foundation, and another is building upon <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. But each one must direct his attention to how he is building upon <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For no one is able to lay another foundation than the one which is laid, which is Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now if anyone builds upon the foundation <transChange type="added">with</transChange> gold, silver, precious stones, wood, grass, straw,</verse>
    <verse num="13">the work of each one will become evident. For the day will reveal <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, because it will be revealed with fire, and the fire itself will test the work of each one, of what sort it is.</verse>
    <verse num="14">If anyone's work that he has built upon <transChange type="added">it</transChange> remains, he will receive a reward.</verse>
    <verse num="15">If anyone's work is burned up, he will suffer loss, but he himself will be saved, but so as through fire. </verse>
    <verse num="16">Do you not know that you are God's temple and the Spirit of God dwells in you?</verse>
    <verse num="17">If anyone destroys God's temple, God will destroy this one. For God's temple is holy, which you are. </verse>
    <verse num="18">Let no one deceive himself. If anyone thinks <transChange type="added">himself</transChange> to be wise among you in this age, let him become a fool, in order that he may become wise.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written, "The one who catches the wise in their craftiness,"<note>A quotation from Job 5:13</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">and again, "The Lord knows the thoughts of the wise, that they are futile."<note>A quotation from Ps 94:11</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">So then, let no one boast in people. For all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are yours,</verse>
    <verse num="22">whether Paul or Apollos or Cephas or the world or life or death or things present or things to come, all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> yours,</verse>
    <verse num="23">and you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> Christ's, and Christ <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God's. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Thus let a person consider us as servants of Christ and stewards of God's mysteries.</verse>
    <verse num="2">In this case, moreover, it is sought in stewards that one be found faithful.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But to me it is a very little matter that I be judged by you or by a human court,<note>Literally "day"</note> but I do not <transChange type="added">even</transChange> judge myself.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For I am conscious of nothing against myself, but not by this am I vindicated. But the one who judges me is the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Therefore do not judge anything before the time, until the Lord should come, who will both enlighten the hidden things of darkness and will reveal the counsels of hearts, and then praise will come to each one from God. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Now I have applied these things, brothers, to myself and Apollos for your sake, in order that in us you may learn not <transChange type="added">to go</transChange> beyond what is written, lest someone be inflated with pride on behalf of one <transChange type="added">person</transChange> against the other.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For who concedes you <transChange type="added">superiority</transChange>? And what do you have that you did not receive? But if indeed you received <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, why do you boast as <transChange type="added">if you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("receive") which is understood as conditional</note> did not receive <transChange type="added">it</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="8">Already you are satiated! Already you are rich! Apart from us you reign as kings! And would that indeed you reigned as kings, in order that we also might reign as kings with you!</verse>
    <verse num="9">For, I think, God has exhibited us apostles last of all, as condemned to death, because we have become a spectacle to the world and to angels and to people.</verse>
    <verse num="10">We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> fools for the sake of Christ, but you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> prudent in Christ! We <transChange type="added">are</transChange> weak, but you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> strong! You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> honored, but we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> dishonored!</verse>
    <verse num="11">Until the present hour we are both hungry and thirsty and poorly clothed and roughly treated and homeless,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and we toil, working with our own hands. <transChange type="added">When we are</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("reviled") which is understood as temporal</note> reviled, we bless; <transChange type="added">when we are</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("persecuted") which is understood as temporal</note> persecuted, we endure;</verse>
    <verse num="13"><transChange type="added">when we are</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("slandered") which is understood as temporal</note> slandered, we encourage. We have become like the refuse of the world, the offscouring of all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, until now. </verse>
    <verse num="14">I am not writing these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to shame you, but admonishing <transChange type="added">you</transChange> as my dear children.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For if you have ten thousand guardians in Christ, yet <transChange type="added">you do</transChange> not <transChange type="added">have</transChange> many fathers, for in Christ Jesus I fathered you through the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Therefore I exhort you, become imitators of me.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Because of this, I have sent to you Timothy, who is my dear and faithful child in the Lord, who will remind you of my ways in Christ Jesus, just as I teach everywhere in every church.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But some have become arrogant, as <transChange type="added">if</transChange> I were not coming to you.</verse>
    <verse num="19">But I am coming to you soon, if the Lord wills, and I will know not the talk of the ones who have become arrogant, but the power.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For the kingdom of God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not with talk, but with power.</verse>
    <verse num="21">What do you want? Shall I come to you with a rod, or with love and a spirit of gentleness? </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">It is reported everywhere <transChange type="added">that there</transChange> is sexual immorality among you, and sexual immorality of such a kind which <transChange type="added">does</transChange> not <transChange type="added">even exist</transChange> among the Gentiles, so that someone has the wife of <transChange type="added">his</transChange> father.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And you are inflated with pride, and should you not rather have mourned, so that the one who has done this deed would be removed from your midst?</verse>
    <verse num="3">For <transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am absent") which is understood as concessive</note> am absent in body but present in spirit, I have already passed judgment on the one who has done this in this way, as <transChange type="added">if I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were present") which is understood as conditional</note> were present.</verse>
    <verse num="4">In the name of our Lord Jesus, <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("are assembled")</note> you are assembled, and my spirit, together with the power of our Lord Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">I have decided</transChange><note>*The words "I have decided" are implied from the statement "I have already passed judgment" in v. 3</note> to hand over such a person to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, in order that his spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Your boasting <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not good. Do you not know that a little leaven leavens the whole batch of dough?</verse>
    <verse num="7">Clean out the old leaven in order that you may be a new batch of dough, just as you are unleavened. For Christ our Passover has been sacrificed.</verse>
    <verse num="8">So then, let us celebrate the feast, not with the old leaven or with the leaven of wickedness and sinfulness, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth. </verse>
    <verse num="9">I wrote to you in the letter not to associate with sexually immoral people.</verse>
    <verse num="10">By no means <transChange type="added">did I mean</transChange> the sexually immoral people of this world or the greedy people and swindlers or idolaters, since then you would have to depart out of the world.</verse>
    <verse num="11">But now I have written to you not to associate with any so-called brother, if he is a sexually immoral person or a greedy person or an idolater or an abusive person or a drunkard or a swindler--with such a person not even to eat.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For what <transChange type="added">is it</transChange> to me to judge those outside? Should you not judge those inside?</verse>
    <verse num="13">But those outside God will judge. Remove the evil person {from among yourselves}<note>Literally "from you of them"</note>. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Does anyone among you, <transChange type="added">if he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("has") which is understood as conditional</note> has a matter against someone else, dare to go to court before the unrighteous, and not before the saints?</verse>
    <verse num="2">Or do you not know that the saints will judge the world? And if by you the world is judged, are you unworthy of the most insignificant courts?</verse>
    <verse num="3">Do you not know that we will judge angels, not to mention ordinary matters?</verse>
    <verse num="4">Therefore, if you have courts with regard to ordinary matters, do you seat<note>Or "seat" (imperative); the Greek verb can be either indicative mood or imperative mood by its form</note> these despised <transChange type="added">people</transChange> in the church?</verse>
    <verse num="5">I say <transChange type="added">this</transChange> to your shame. So is there not anyone wise among you who will be able to render a decision between his brothers?</verse>
    <verse num="6">But brother goes to court with brother, and this before unbelievers!</verse>
    <verse num="7">Therefore it is already completely a loss for you that you have lawsuits with one another. Why not rather be wronged? Why not rather be defrauded?</verse>
    <verse num="8">But you wrong and defraud, and <transChange type="added">do</transChange> this <transChange type="added">to</transChange> brothers! </verse>
    <verse num="9">Or do you not know that the unrighteous will not inherit the kingdom of God? Do not be deceived! Neither sexually immoral people, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor passive homosexual partners, nor dominant homosexual partners,</verse>
    <verse num="10">nor thieves, nor greedy persons, not drunkards, not abusive persons, not swindlers will inherit the kingdom of God.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And some of you were these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, but you were washed, but you were sanctified, but you were justified in the name of the Lord Jesus<note>Some manuscripts have "of the Lord Jesus Christ"</note> and by the Spirit of our God. </verse>
    <verse num="12">All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are permitted for me, but not all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are profitable. All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are permitted for me, but I will not be controlled by anything.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Food <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the stomach, and the stomach for food, but God will abolish {both of them}<note>Literally "both this and these"</note>. Now the body <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not for sexual immorality, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And God both raised up the Lord and will raise us up by his power.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Do you not know that your bodies are members of Christ? Therefore, shall I take away the members of Christ <transChange type="added">and</transChange> make <transChange type="added">them</transChange> members of a prostitute? May it never be!</verse>
    <verse num="16">Or do you not know that the one who joins himself to a prostitute is one body <transChange type="added">with her</transChange>? For it says, "The two will become one flesh."<note>A quotation from Gen 2:24</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">But the one who joins himself to the Lord is one spirit <transChange type="added">with him</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Flee sexual immorality. Every sin that a person commits is outside his body, but the one who commits sexual immorality sins against his own body.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Or do you not know that your body is the temple of the Holy Spirit <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> in you, whom you have from God, and you are not your own?</verse>
    <verse num="20">For you were bought at a price; therefore glorify God with your body. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">Now concerning <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> about which you wrote: "<transChange type="added">It is</transChange> good for a man not to touch<note>I.e., in a sexual sense</note> a woman."</verse>
    <verse num="2">But because of sexual immorality, let each man have<note>I.e., in the sense of "have sexual relations with"</note> his own wife and let each woman have her own husband.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The husband must fulfill his obligation to his wife, and likewise also the wife to her husband.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The wife does not have authority over her own body, but her husband <transChange type="added">does</transChange>. And likewise also the husband does not have authority over his own body, but his wife <transChange type="added">does</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Do not defraud one another, except perhaps by agreement, for a time, in order that you may devote yourselves to prayer, and <transChange type="added">then</transChange> you should be {together}<note>Literally "at the same"</note> again, lest Satan tempt you because of your lack of self control.</verse>
    <verse num="6">But I say this as a concession, not as a command.</verse>
    <verse num="7">I wish all people could be like myself, but each one has his own gift from God, one in this way and another in that way. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Now I say to the unmarried and to the widows: <transChange type="added">It is</transChange> good for them if they remain as I <transChange type="added">am</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">But if they cannot control themselves, they should marry, for it is better to marry than to burn <transChange type="added">with sexual desire</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="10">To the married I command--not I, but the Lord--a wife must not separate from <transChange type="added">her</transChange> husband.</verse>
    <verse num="11">But if indeed she does separate, she must remain unmarried or be reconciled to her husband. And a husband must not divorce <transChange type="added">his</transChange> wife. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Now to the rest I say--not the Lord--if any brother has an unbelieving wife and she consents to live with him, he must not divorce her.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And if any wife has an unbelieving husband and he consents to live with her, she must not divorce her husband.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the brother, since otherwise your children are unclean, but now they are holy.</verse>
    <verse num="15">But if the unbeliever leaves, let him leave. The brother or the sister is not bound in such <transChange type="added">cases</transChange>. But God has called us<note>Some manuscripts have "you" (plural)</note> in peace.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For how do you know, wife, whether you will save your husband? Or how do you know, husband, whether you will save your wife? </verse>
    <verse num="17">But to each one as the Lord has apportioned. As God has called each one, thus let him live--and thus I order in all the churches.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Was anyone called <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being circumcised") which is understood as temporal</note> being circumcised? He must not undo his circumcision. Was anyone called in uncircumcision? He must not become circumcised.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Circumcision is nothing and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Each one in the calling in which he was called--in this he should remain.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Were you called <transChange type="added">while</transChange> a slave? Do not let it be a concern to you. But if indeed you are able to become free, rather make use of <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For the one who is called in the Lord <transChange type="added">while</transChange> a slave is the Lord's freedperson. Likewise the one who is called <transChange type="added">while</transChange> free is a slave of Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="23">You were bought at a price; do not become slaves of men.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Each one in <transChange type="added">the situation</transChange> in which he was called, brothers--in this he should remain with God. </verse>
    <verse num="25">Now concerning virgins I do not have a command from the Lord, but I am giving an opinion as one shown mercy by the Lord to be trustworthy.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Therefore, I consider this to be good because of the impending distress, that <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> good for a man to be thus.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Are you bound to a wife? Do not seek release. Are you free from a wife? Do not seek a wife.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But if you marry, you have not sinned, and if the virgin marries, she has not sinned. But such people will have affliction in the flesh, and I would spare you.</verse>
    <verse num="29">But I say this, brothers: the time is shortened, that from now on even those who have wives should be as <transChange type="added">if they</transChange> do not have <transChange type="added">wives</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="30">and those who weep as <transChange type="added">if they</transChange> do not weep, and those who rejoice as <transChange type="added">if they</transChange> do not rejoice, and those who buy as <transChange type="added">if they</transChange> do not possess,</verse>
    <verse num="31">and those who make use of the world as <transChange type="added">if they</transChange> do not make full use of <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. For the present form of this world is passing away. </verse>
    <verse num="32">But I want you to be free from care. The unmarried person cares for the things of the Lord, how he may please the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="33">But the one who is married cares for the things of the world, how he may please his wife,</verse>
    <verse num="34">and he is divided. And the unmarried woman or the virgin cares for the things of the Lord, in order that she may be holy both in body and in spirit. But the married woman cares for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Now I am saying this for your own benefit, not that I may put a restriction on you, but to promote appropriate and devoted service to the Lord without distraction. </verse>
    <verse num="36">But if anyone thinks he is behaving dishonorably concerning his virgin, if she is past her prime<note>Or "if his passions are strong" (it is not clear in context whether this term refers to the man or to the woman)</note> and it ought to be thus, let him do what he wishes. He does not sin. Let them marry.</verse>
    <verse num="37">But he who stands firm in his heart, not having necessity, but has authority concerning his own will, and has decided this in his own heart, to keep his own virgin, he will do well.</verse>
    <verse num="38">So then, the one who marries<note>Or perhaps "the one who gives in marriage"</note> his own virgin does well, and the one who does not marry <transChange type="added">her</transChange> will do better. </verse>
    <verse num="39">A wife is bound for as long a time <transChange type="added">as</transChange> her husband lives. But if her husband {dies}<note>Literally "falls asleep"</note>, she is free to marry whomever she wishes, only in the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="40">But she is happier if she remains thus, according to my opinion--and I think I have the Spirit of God. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">Now concerning food sacrificed to idols, we know that "we all have knowledge."<note>Considered by many interpreters to be a slogan used by the Corinthians to justify their behavior</note> Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up.</verse>
    <verse num="2">If anyone thinks he knows anything, he has not yet known as it is necessary to know.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But if anyone loves God, this one is known by him. </verse>
    <verse num="4">Therefore, concerning the eating of food sacrificed to idols, we know that "an idol <transChange type="added">is</transChange> nothing in the world" and that "<transChange type="added">there is</transChange> no God except one."<note>Considered by many interpreters to be slogans used by the Corinthians to justify their behavior</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">For even if after all <transChange type="added">there</transChange> are so-called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, just as <transChange type="added">there</transChange> are many gods and many lords, </verse>
    <verse num="6">yet to us <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> one God, the Father, from whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> for him, and <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> through him.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But this knowledge <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not in everyone. But some, being accustomed until now to the idol, eat <transChange type="added">this food</transChange> as food sacrificed to idols, and their conscience, <transChange type="added">because it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("is") which is understood as causal</note> is weak, is defiled.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But food does not bring us close to God. For neither if we eat do we have more, nor if we do not eat do we lack.<note>Some manuscripts omit "For" and have "Neither if we do not eat do we lack, nor if we do eat do we have more"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">But watch out lest somehow this right of yours becomes a cause for stumbling to the weak.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For if someone should see you who has knowledge reclining for a meal in an idol's temple, will not his conscience, <transChange type="added">because it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("is") which is understood as causal</note> is weak, be strengthened so that <transChange type="added">he</transChange> eats the food sacrificed to idols?</verse>
    <verse num="11">For the one who is weak--the brother for whom Christ died--is destroyed by your knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now <transChange type="added">if you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("sin") which is understood as conditional</note> sin in this way against the brothers and wound their conscience, which is weak, you sin against Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Therefore, if food causes my brother to sin, I will never eat meat {forever}<note>Literally "for the age"</note>, in order that I may not cause my brother to sin. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord? Are you not my work in the Lord?</verse>
    <verse num="2">If to others I am not an apostle, yet indeed I am to you, for you are my seal of apostleship in the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="3">My defense to those who examine me is this:</verse>
    <verse num="4">Do we not have the right to eat and drink?</verse>
    <verse num="5">Do we not have the right to take along a sister <transChange type="added">as</transChange> wife, like the rest of the apostles and the brothers of the Lord and Cephas?</verse>
    <verse num="6">Or do only I and Barnabas not have the right {to refrain from working}<note>Literally "not to work"</note>?</verse>
    <verse num="7">Who ever serves as a soldier at his own expense? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat the fruit of it? Who<note>Some manuscripts have "Or who"</note> shepherds a flock and does not drink<note>Literally "eat"</note> from the milk of the flock?</verse>
    <verse num="8">I am not saying these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> according to a human perspective. Or does the law not also say these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="9">For in the law of Moses it is written, "You must not muzzle an ox <transChange type="added">while it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("threshing") which is understood as temporal</note> is threshing."<note>A quotation from Deut 25:4</note> It is not about oxen God is concerned, is it?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Or doubtless does he speak {for our sake}<note>Literally "for the sake of us"</note>? For it is written {for our sake}<note>Literally "for the sake of us"</note>, because the one who plows ought to plow in hope and the one who threshes <transChange type="added">ought to do so</transChange> in hope of a share.</verse>
    <verse num="11">If we have sown spiritual <transChange type="added">things</transChange> among you, <transChange type="added">is it too</transChange> great <transChange type="added">a thing</transChange> if we reap material <transChange type="added">things</transChange> from you?</verse>
    <verse num="12">If others share this right over you, do we not <transChange type="added">do so</transChange> even more? Yet we have not made use of this right, but we endure all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, in order that we may not cause any hindrance to the gospel of Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Do you not know that those performing the holy services eat the things from the temple, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> those attending to the altar have a share with the altar?</verse>
    <verse num="14">In the <transChange type="added">same</transChange> way also the Lord ordered those who proclaim the gospel to live from the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">But I have not made use of any of these <transChange type="added">rights</transChange>. And I am not writing these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in order that it may be thus with me. For <transChange type="added">it would be</transChange> better to me rather to die than <transChange type="added">for</transChange> anyone to deprive me of my reason for boasting.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For if I proclaim the gospel, it is not to me a reason for boasting, for necessity is imposed on me. For woe is to me if I do not proclaim the gospel.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For if I do this voluntarily, I have a reward, but if <transChange type="added">I do so</transChange> unwillingly, I have been entrusted with a stewardship.</verse>
    <verse num="18">What then is my reward? That <transChange type="added">when I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("proclaim the gospel") which is understood as temporal</note> proclaim the gospel, I may offer the gospel free of charge, in order not to make full use of my right in the gospel. </verse>
    <verse num="19">For <transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am") which is understood as concessive</note> am free from all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, I have enslaved myself to all, in order that I may gain more.</verse>
    <verse num="20">I have become like a Jew to the Jews, in order that I may gain the Jews. To those under the law <transChange type="added">I became</transChange> as under the law (<transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am") which is understood as concessive</note> myself am not under the law) in order that I may gain those under the law.</verse>
    <verse num="21">To those outside the law <transChange type="added">I became</transChange> as outside the law (<transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am") which is understood as concessive</note> am not outside the law of God, but subject to the law of Christ) in order that I may gain those outside the law.</verse>
    <verse num="22">To the weak I became weak, in order that I may gain the weak. I have become all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, in order that by all means I may save some.</verse>
    <verse num="23">I do all <transChange type="added">this</transChange> for the sake of the gospel, in order that I may become a participant with it. </verse>
    <verse num="24">Do you not know that those who run in the stadium all run, but one receives the prize? Run in such a way that you may win.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And everyone who competes exercises self-control in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>. Thus those <transChange type="added">do so</transChange> in order that they may receive a perishable crown, but we an imperishable <transChange type="added">one</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Therefore I run in this way, not as <transChange type="added">running</transChange> aimlessly; I box in this way, not as beating the air.</verse>
    <verse num="27">But I discipline my body and subjugate <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, lest somehow <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("preaching") which is understood as temporal</note> preaching to others, <transChange type="added">I</transChange> myself should become disqualified. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">For I do not want you to be ignorant, brothers, that our fathers were all under the cloud and all went through the sea,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and all were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea,</verse>
    <verse num="3">and all ate the same spiritual food,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and all drank the same spiritual drink. For they drank from the spiritual rock that followed <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, and the rock was Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="5">But God was not pleased with the majority of them, for they were struck down in the desert. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Now these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> happened <transChange type="added">as</transChange> examples for us, so that we should not be desirers of evil <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, just as those also desired <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and not become idolaters, as some of them <transChange type="added">did</transChange>, just as it is written, "The people sat down to eat and drink, and stood up to play,"<note>A quotation from Exod 32:6</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">nor commit sexual immorality, as some of them committed sexual immorality, and twenty-three thousand fell in one day,</verse>
    <verse num="9">nor put Christ to the test, as some of them tested <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, and were destroyed by snakes,</verse>
    <verse num="10">nor grumble, just as some of them grumbled, and were destroyed by the destroyer.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Now these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> happened to those <transChange type="added">people</transChange> as an example, but are written for our instruction, on whom the ends of the ages have come.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore, the one who thinks that he stands must watch out lest he fall.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Temptation has not come upon you except <transChange type="added">what is</transChange> common to humanity. But God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> faithful, who will not permit you to be tempted beyond what you are able, but will also make a way out together with the temptation, <transChange type="added">so that you</transChange> may be able to endure <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="14">Therefore, my dear friends, flee from idolatry.</verse>
    <verse num="15">I am speaking as to sensible <transChange type="added">people</transChange>; you judge what I am saying.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not a participation in the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not a participation in the body of Christ?</verse>
    <verse num="17">Because <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> one bread, <transChange type="added">we</transChange> who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> many are one body, for <transChange type="added">we</transChange> all share from the one bread.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Consider Israel according to the flesh: are not the ones who eat the sacrifices sharers in the altar?</verse>
    <verse num="19">Therefore, what am I saying? That food sacrificed to idols is anything, or that an idol is anything?</verse>
    <verse num="20"><transChange type="added">No</transChange>, but that <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which they sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God, and I do not want you to become sharers with demons.</verse>
    <verse num="21">You are not able to drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons. You are not able to share the table of the Lord and the table of demons.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Or are we attempting to provoke the Lord to jealousy? We are not stronger than he <transChange type="added">is, are we</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> </verse>
    <verse num="23">All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are permitted, but not all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are profitable. All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are permitted, but not all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> build up.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Let no one seek {his own good}<note>Literally "the <transChange type="added">-</transChange> of himself"; "good" is implied</note> but the <transChange type="added">good</transChange> of the other.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Eat everything that is sold in the meat market, {asking no questions}<note>Literally "questioning nothing"</note> for the sake of the conscience,</verse>
    <verse num="26">for "the earth <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the Lord's, and its fullness."<note>A quotation from Ps 24:1, and an allusion to Ps 50:12; 89:11</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">If any of the unbelievers invites you, and you want to go, eat everything that is set before you, {asking no questions}<note>Literally "questioning nothing"</note> for the sake of the conscience.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But if someone says to you, "This is offered to idols," do not eat <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, for the sake of that one who informed <transChange type="added">you</transChange> and the conscience.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Now I am not speaking about your own conscience, but the <transChange type="added">conscience</transChange> of the other <transChange type="added">person</transChange>. For why <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my freedom judged by another's conscience?</verse>
    <verse num="30">If I partake with thankfulness, why am I slandered concerning that for which I give thanks? </verse>
    <verse num="31">Therefore, whether you eat or you drink or whatever you do, do all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> for the glory of God.</verse>
    <verse num="32">{Give no offense}<note>Literally "be blameless"</note> both to Jews and to Greeks and to the church of God,</verse>
    <verse num="33">just as I also please all <transChange type="added">people</transChange> in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, not seeking my own benefit, but the <transChange type="added">benefit</transChange> of the many, in order that they may be saved. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Become imitators of me, just as I also <transChange type="added">am</transChange> of Christ. </verse>
    <verse num="2">Now I praise you that you remember me <transChange type="added">in</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and just as I handed over to you the traditions, you hold fast to <transChange type="added">them</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But I want you to know that Christ is the head of every man, and the man <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> head of the woman, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> head of Christ <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Every man who prays or prophesies <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("having") which is understood as temporal</note> having <transChange type="added">something</transChange><note>*Here the direct object must be supplied from context, but the exact nature of the object is not clear from the context, so "<transChange type="added">something</transChange>" is used in the English translation</note> on <transChange type="added">his</transChange> head dishonors his head,</verse>
    <verse num="5">but every woman who prays or prophesies with uncovered head dishonors her head, for she is one and the same with the one whose <transChange type="added">head</transChange> is shaved.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For if a woman does not cover herself, let her <transChange type="added">hair</transChange> be shorn off. But if <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> shameful for a woman to <transChange type="added">have her head</transChange><note>Literally "to be"</note> shorn or shaved, let her cover her <transChange type="added">head</transChange>.<note>Literally "herself"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">For indeed a man ought not to cover his head, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("is") which is understood as causal</note> is the image and glory of God, but the woman is the glory of the man.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For man is not from woman, but woman from man.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For indeed man was not created for the sake of the woman, but woman for the sake of the man.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Because of this, the woman ought to have <transChange type="added">a symbol of</transChange> authority on her head, on account of the angels.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Nevertheless, neither <transChange type="added">is</transChange> woman <transChange type="added">anything</transChange> apart from man, nor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> man <transChange type="added">anything</transChange> apart from woman in the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For just as the woman <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from the man, thus also the man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> through the woman. But all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> from God.</verse>
    <verse num="13">You judge {for yourselves}<note>Literally "in you yourselves"</note>: is it fitting for a woman to pray to God <transChange type="added">with her head</transChange><note>*Here the words "<transChange type="added">with her head</transChange>" have been supplied as a necessary clarification</note> uncovered?</verse>
    <verse num="14">And does not nature itself teach you that a man, if he wears long hair, it is a dishonor to him?</verse>
    <verse num="15">But a woman, if she wears long hair, it is her glory, because her hair is given<note>Some manuscripts have "is given to her"</note> for a covering.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But if anyone is disposed to be contentious, we have no such custom, nor do the churches of God. </verse>
    <verse num="17">But in giving this instruction I do not praise <transChange type="added">you</transChange>, because you come together not for the better but for the worse.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For in the first place, <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("come together")</note> come together as a church, I hear there are divisions among you, and in part I believe it.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For indeed it is necessary that there be factions among you, in order that those who are approved may become evident among you.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Therefore, <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("come together")</note> you come together in the same <transChange type="added">place</transChange>, it is not to eat the Lord's supper.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "when" is supplied as a component of the temporal infinitive ("eat")</note> eat <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, each one of you goes ahead to take his own supper, and one is hungry and another is drunk.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For do you not have houses for eating and drinking? Or do you despise the church of God and humiliate those who do not have <transChange type="added">anything</transChange>? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you? In this I will not praise <transChange type="added">you</transChange>! </verse>
    <verse num="23">For I received from the Lord what I also passed on to you, that the Lord Jesus, on the night in which he was betrayed, took bread,</verse>
    <verse num="24">and <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had given thanks") which is understood as temporal</note> had given thanks, he broke <transChange type="added">it</transChange> and said, "This is my body which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for you. Do this in remembrance of me."</verse>
    <verse num="25">Likewise also the cup, after they had eaten, saying, "This cup is the new covenant in my blood. Do this, as often as you drink <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, in remembrance of me."</verse>
    <verse num="26">For as often as you eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the Lord's death until he comes.</verse>
    <verse num="27">So then, whoever eats the bread or drinks the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner will be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But let a person examine himself, and in this way let him eat from the bread and let him drink from the cup.</verse>
    <verse num="29">For the one who eats and drinks, <transChange type="added">if he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("recognize") which is understood as conditional</note> does not recognize the body, eats and drinks judgment against himself.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Because of this, many <transChange type="added">are</transChange> weak and sick among you, and quite a few {have died}<note>Literally "have fallen asleep"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="31">But if we were evaluating ourselves, we would not be judged.</verse>
    <verse num="32">But <transChange type="added">if we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are judged") which is understood as conditional</note> are judged by the Lord, we are being disciplined, in order that we will not be condemned with the world. </verse>
    <verse num="33">So then, my brothers, <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("come together") which is understood as temporal</note> come together in order to eat <transChange type="added">the Lord's supper</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object ("the Lord's supper") is supplied from context in the English translation</note> wait for one another.</verse>
    <verse num="34">If anyone is hungry, let him eat at home, lest you come together for judgment. And I will give directions about the remaining <transChange type="added">matters</transChange> whenever I come. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">Now concerning spiritual <transChange type="added">gifts</transChange>,<note>Or "spiritual <transChange type="added">things</transChange>"; possibly "those who possess spiritual gifts"</note> brothers, I do not want you to be ignorant.</verse>
    <verse num="2">You know that when you were pagans, you were led astray to the speechless idols, however you were led.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Therefore I make known to you that no one speaking by the Spirit of God says, "Jesus <transChange type="added">is</transChange> accursed," and no one is able to say "Jesus <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Lord" except by the Holy Spirit. </verse>
    <verse num="4">Now there are varieties of gifts, but the same Spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="5">and there are varieties of ministries, and the same Lord,</verse>
    <verse num="6">and there are varieties of activities, but the same God, who works all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But to each one is given the manifestation of the Spirit for what is beneficial <transChange type="added">to all</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For to one is given a word of wisdom through the Spirit, and to another a word of knowledge by the same Spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="9">to another faith by the same Spirit, to another<note>Some manuscripts have "and to another"</note> gifts of healing by the one Spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="10">to another<note>Some manuscripts have "and to another"</note> {miraculous powers}<note>Literally "activities of power"</note>, to another<note>Some manuscripts have "and to another"</note> prophecy, to another<note>Some manuscripts have "and to another"</note> distinguishing of spirits, to another kinds of tongues, to another<note>Some manuscripts have "and to another"</note> interpretation of tongues.</verse>
    <verse num="11">But in all these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> one and the same Spirit is at work, distributing to each one individually just as he wishes. </verse>
    <verse num="12">For just as the body is one and has many members, but all the members of the body, <transChange type="added">although they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as concessive</note> are many, are one body, thus also Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="13">For by<note>Or "in"</note> one Spirit we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether slaves or free <transChange type="added">persons</transChange>, and all were made to drink one Spirit.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For the body is not one member, but many.</verse>
    <verse num="15">If the foot should say, "Because I am not a hand, I am not <transChange type="added">a part</transChange> of the body," not because of this is it not <transChange type="added">a part</transChange> of the body.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And if the ear should say, "Because I am not an eye, I am not <transChange type="added">a part</transChange> of the body, not because of this is it not <transChange type="added">a part</transChange> of the body.</verse>
    <verse num="17">If the whole body <transChange type="added">were</transChange> an eye, where <transChange type="added">would</transChange> the hearing <transChange type="added">be</transChange>? If the whole <transChange type="added">were</transChange> hearing, where <transChange type="added">would</transChange> the sense of smell <transChange type="added">be</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="18">But now God has placed the members, each one of them, in the body just as he wanted.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And if they all were one member, where <transChange type="added">would</transChange> the body <transChange type="added">be</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="20">But now <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> many members, but one body. </verse>
    <verse num="21">Now the eye is not able to say to the hand, "I do not have need of you," or again, the head to the feet, "I do not have need of you."</verse>
    <verse num="22">But by much more the members of the body which are thought to be weaker are necessary,</verse>
    <verse num="23">and <transChange type="added">the parts</transChange> of the body which we think to be less honorable, these we clothe with more abundant honor, and our unpresentable <transChange type="added">parts</transChange> come to have more abundant presentability,</verse>
    <verse num="24">but our presentable <transChange type="added">parts</transChange> do not have need <transChange type="added">of this</transChange>. Yet God composed the body by giving more abundant honor to the part which lacked <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="25">in order that there not be a division in the body, but the members would have the same concern for one another.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And if one member suffers, all the members suffer together; if a member<note>Some manuscripts have "one member"</note> is honored, all the members rejoice with <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="27">Now you are the body of Christ, and members {of it individually}<note>Literally "by part"</note>,</verse>
    <verse num="28">and whom God has appointed in the church: first, apostles, second, prophets, third, teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healing, helps, administrations, kinds of tongues.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Not all <transChange type="added">are</transChange> apostles, <transChange type="added">are they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <transChange type="added">are</transChange> prophets, <transChange type="added">are they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <transChange type="added">are</transChange> teachers, <transChange type="added">are they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all <transChange type="added">are workers of</transChange> miracles, <transChange type="added">are they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note></verse>
    <verse num="30">Not all have gifts of healing, <transChange type="added">do they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all speak with tongues, <transChange type="added">do they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note> Not all interpret, <transChange type="added">do they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">But strive<note>Or "you are striving" (some understand the form of this verb to be indicative mood rather than imperative mood)</note> for the greater gifts. And I will show you a still more excellent way. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">If I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but do not have love, I have become a ringing brass gong or a clashing cymbal.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And if I have <transChange type="added">the gift of</transChange> prophecy and I know all mysteries and all knowledge, and if I have all faith so that <transChange type="added">I can</transChange> remove mountains, but do not have love, I am nothing.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And if I parcel out all my possessions, and if I hand over my body in order that I will be burned,<note>Some manuscripts have "in order that I may boast"</note> but do not have love, it benefits <transChange type="added">me</transChange> nothing. </verse>
    <verse num="4">Love is patient, love is kind, love is not jealous, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not boast, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not become conceited,</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not behave dishonorably, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> {is not selfish}<note>Literally "does not seek the things of itself"</note>, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not become angry, <transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not keep a record of wrongs,</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">it</transChange> does not rejoice at unrighteousness, but rejoices with the truth,</verse>
    <verse num="7">bears all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, believes all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, hopes all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, endures all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Love never ends. But if <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> prophecies, they will pass away. If <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> tongues, they will cease. If <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> knowledge, it will pass away.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For we know in part and we prophesy in part,</verse>
    <verse num="10">but whenever the perfect comes, the partial will pass away.</verse>
    <verse num="11">When I was a child, I spoke like a child, I thought like a child, I reasoned like a child. When I became a man, I set aside the things of a child.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For now we see through a mirror {indirectly}<note>Literally "in an indirect image"</note>, but then face to face. Now I know in part, but then I will know completely, just as I have also been completely known.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And now these three <transChange type="added">things</transChange> remain: faith, hope, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> love. But the greatest of these <transChange type="added">is</transChange> love. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">Pursue love, and strive for spiritual <transChange type="added">gifts</transChange>, but especially that you may prophesy.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For the one who speaks in a tongue does not speak to people but to God, because no one understands, but by the Spirit<note>Or "in the Spirit"; or "in <transChange type="added">his</transChange> spirit"</note> he speaks mysteries.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But the one who prophesies speaks to people edification and encouragement and consolation.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The one who speaks in a tongue edifies himself, but the one who prophesies edifies the church.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Now I want you all to speak with tongues, but even more that you may prophesy. The one who prophesies <transChange type="added">is</transChange> greater than the one who speaks with tongues, unless he interprets, in order that the church may receive edification. </verse>
    <verse num="6">But now, brothers, if I come to you speaking with tongues, how do I benefit you, unless I speak to you either with a revelation or with knowledge or with a prophecy or with a teaching?</verse>
    <verse num="7">Likewise, the inanimate things which produce a sound, whether flute or lyre, if they do not produce a distinction in the tones, how will it be known what is played on the flute or on the lyre?</verse>
    <verse num="8">For indeed, if the trumpet produces an indistinct sound, who will prepare for battle?</verse>
    <verse num="9">And so you through the tongue, unless you produce a clear message, how will it be known what is spoken? For you will be speaking into the air.</verse>
    <verse num="10">There are probably so many kinds of languages in the world, and none without meaning.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Therefore, if I do not know the meaning of the language, I will be a barbarian to the one who is speaking, and the one who is speaking <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> a barbarian in my <transChange type="added">judgment</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="12">In this way also you, since you are zealous of spiritual <transChange type="added">gifts</transChange>, seek for the edification of the church, in order that you may abound. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Therefore the one who speaks in a tongue must pray that he may interpret.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For if I pray in a tongue, my spirit prays but my mind is unproductive.</verse>
    <verse num="15">{Therefore what should I do}<note>Literally "what therefore is it"</note>? I will pray with my spirit, but I will also pray with my mind. I will sing praise with my spirit, but I will also sing praise with my mind.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For otherwise, if you praise in <transChange type="added">your</transChange> spirit, how will the one who fills the place of the outsider say the "amen" at your thanksgiving, because he does not know what you are saying?</verse>
    <verse num="17">For indeed you are giving thanks well, but the other person is not edified.</verse>
    <verse num="18">I give thanks to God <transChange type="added">that</transChange> I speak with tongues more than all of you,</verse>
    <verse num="19">but in the church I prefer to speak five words with my mind, in order that I may instruct other <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, than ten thousand words in a tongue. </verse>
    <verse num="20">Brothers, do not become children in <transChange type="added">your</transChange> understanding, but with respect to wickedness be as a child, and in <transChange type="added">your</transChange> understanding be mature.</verse>
    <verse num="21">In the law it is written: </verse>
    <verse num="22">So then, tongues are for a sign not to those who believe, but to unbelievers, but prophecy <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not for unbelievers, but for those who believe.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Therefore, if the whole church comes together at the same <transChange type="added">time</transChange> and all speak with tongues, and outsiders or unbelievers enter, will they not say that you are out of your minds?</verse>
    <verse num="24">But if all prophesy, and some unbeliever or outsider enters, he is convicted by all, he is judged by all,</verse>
    <verse num="25">the secret things of his heart become evident, and so, falling on <transChange type="added">his</transChange> face, he will worship God, proclaiming, "God is truly among you!" </verse>
    <verse num="26">{Therefore what should you do}<note>Literally "what therefore is it"</note>, brothers? Whenever you come together, each one of you has a psalm, has a teaching, has a revelation, has a tongue, has an interpretation. All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> must be <transChange type="added">done</transChange> for edification.</verse>
    <verse num="27">If anyone speaks in a tongue, <transChange type="added">it must be</transChange> on one occasion two or at most three, and {one after the other}<note>Literally "in turn"</note>, and one must interpret.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But if there is no interpreter, he must be silent in the church, but let him speak to himself and to God.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Let two or three prophets speak, and the others evaluate.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And if <transChange type="added">something</transChange> is revealed to another who is seated, the first must be silent.</verse>
    <verse num="31">For you are all able to prophesy {in turn}<note>Literally "one at a time</note>, in order that all may learn and all may be encouraged,</verse>
    <verse num="32">and the spirits of prophets are subject to prophets.</verse>
    <verse num="33">For God is not <transChange type="added">a God of</transChange> disorder but of peace. </verse>
    <verse num="34">the women must be silent in the churches, for it is not permitted for them to speak, but they must be in submission, just as the law also says.</verse>
    <verse num="35">But if they want to learn something, let them ask their own husbands at home, for it is shameful for a woman to speak in church.</verse>
    <verse num="36">Or has the word of God gone out from you, or has it come to you only? </verse>
    <verse num="37">If anyone thinks he is a prophet or spiritual,<note>Or "or one who possesses the Spirit"</note> he should recognize that <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which I am writing to you are of the Lord.<note>Some manuscripts have "are a command of the Lord"</note></verse>
    <verse num="38">But if anyone ignores <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, he is ignored.<note>Or "if anyone is ignorant, let him be ignorant"</note></verse>
    <verse num="39">So then, my brothers, desire to prophesy, and do not prevent speaking with tongues.</verse>
    <verse num="40">But let all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> be <transChange type="added">done</transChange> decently and according to proper procedure. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">Now I make known to you, brothers, the gospel which I proclaimed to you, which you have also received, in which you also stand,</verse>
    <verse num="2">by which you are also being saved, if you hold fast to the message I proclaimed to you, unless you believed to no purpose.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For I passed on to you {as of first importance}<note>Literally "among the first <transChange type="added">things</transChange>"</note> what I also received, that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and that he was buried, and that he was raised up on the third day according to the scriptures,</verse>
    <verse num="5">and that he appeared to Cephas, then to the twelve,</verse>
    <verse num="6">then he appeared to more than five hundred brothers at once, the majority of whom remain until now, but some have fallen asleep.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then he appeared to James, then to all the apostles,</verse>
    <verse num="8">and last of all, as it were to one born at the wrong time, he appeared also to me.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For I am the least of the apostles, not worthy to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But by the grace of God I am what I am, and his grace to me has not been in vain, but I labored even more than all of them, and not I, but the grace of God with me.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Therefore whether I or those, in this way we preached, and in this way you believed. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Now if Christ is preached as raised up from the dead, how do some among you say that <transChange type="added">there</transChange> is no resurrection of the dead?</verse>
    <verse num="13">But if <transChange type="added">there</transChange> is no resurrection of the dead, Christ has not been raised <transChange type="added">either</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But if Christ has not been raised, then<note>Some manuscripts have "then both"</note> our preaching <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in vain, and your faith <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in vain.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And also we are found <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> false witnesses of God, because we testified against God that he raised Christ, whom he did not raise if after all, then, the dead are not raised.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For if the dead are not raised, Christ has not been raised <transChange type="added">either</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But if Christ has not been raised, your faith <transChange type="added">is</transChange> empty; you are still in your sins.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And as a further result, those who have fallen asleep in Christ have perished.</verse>
    <verse num="19">If {we have put our hope}<note>Literally "we are having put our hope"</note> in Christ in this life only, we are of all people most pitiable. </verse>
    <verse num="20">But now Christ has been raised from the dead, the first fruits of those who have fallen asleep.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For since through a man <transChange type="added">came</transChange> death, also through a man <transChange type="added">came</transChange> the resurrection of the dead.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For just as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all will be made alive.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But each in his own group: Christ the first fruits, then those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> Christ's at his coming,</verse>
    <verse num="24">then the end, when he hands over the kingdom to the God and Father, when he has abolished all rule and all authority and power.</verse>
    <verse num="25">For it is necessary for him to reign until he has put all his enemies under his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="26">The last enemy to be abolished <transChange type="added">is</transChange> death.</verse>
    <verse num="27">For "he subjected all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> under his feet."<note>A quotation from Ps 8:6</note> But when it says "all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>" are subjected, <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> clear that the one who subjected all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to him <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not included.</verse>
    <verse num="28">But whenever all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are subjected to him, then the Son himself will be subjected<note>Some manuscripts have "also will be subjected"</note> to the one who subjected all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to him, in order that God may be all in all. </verse>
    <verse num="29">Otherwise, why do they do <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, those who are being baptized on behalf of the dead? If the dead are not raised at all, why indeed are they being baptized on behalf of them?</verse>
    <verse num="30">And why are we in danger every hour?</verse>
    <verse num="31">I die every day--yes indeed, by my boasting in you,<note>Some manuscripts have "in you, brothers,"</note> which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord!</verse>
    <verse num="32">If according to a human perspective I fought wild beasts at Ephesus, what benefit <transChange type="added">is it</transChange> to me? If the dead are not raised, let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.<note>An allusion to Isa 22:13; 56:12</note></verse>
    <verse num="33">Do not be deceived! "Bad company corrupts good morals."<note>A quotation from the Greek poet Menander's comedy Thais, 218</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">Sober up correctly and {stop sinning}<note>Literally "do not sin"</note>, for some have no knowledge of God--I say <transChange type="added">this</transChange> to your shame. </verse>
    <verse num="35">But someone will say, "How are the dead raised? And with what sort of body do they come?"</verse>
    <verse num="36">Foolish person! What you sow does not come to life unless it dies.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And what you sow <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not the body which it will become, but you sow the bare seed, whether perhaps of wheat or of some of the rest.</verse>
    <verse num="38">But God gives to it a body just as he wishes, and to each one of the seeds its own body.</verse>
    <verse num="39">Not all flesh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the same, but <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> one flesh of human beings, and another flesh of animals, and another flesh of birds, and another of fish,</verse>
    <verse num="40">and heavenly bodies and earthly bodies. But the glory of the heavenly <transChange type="added">bodies</transChange> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> of one kind, and the <transChange type="added">glory</transChange> of the earthly <transChange type="added">bodies</transChange> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> of another kind.</verse>
    <verse num="41"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars, for star differs from star in glory. </verse>
    <verse num="42">Thus also <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption, it is raised in incorruptibility.</verse>
    <verse num="43">It is sown in dishonor, it is raised in glory. It is sown in weakness, it is raised in power.</verse>
    <verse num="44">It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body. If <transChange type="added">there</transChange> is a natural body, <transChange type="added">there</transChange> is also a spiritual <transChange type="added">body</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="45">Thus also it is written, "The first man, Adam, became a living soul";<note>A quotation from Gen 2:7</note> the last Adam <transChange type="added">became</transChange> a life-giving spirit.</verse>
    <verse num="46">But the spiritual <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not first, but the natural; then the spiritual.</verse>
    <verse num="47">The first man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from the earth, made of earth; the second man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from heaven.</verse>
    <verse num="48">As the one <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> made of earth, so also <transChange type="added">are</transChange> those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> made of earth, and as the heavenly, so also <transChange type="added">are</transChange> those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> heavenly.</verse>
    <verse num="49">And just as we have borne the image of the <transChange type="added">one who is</transChange> made of earth, we will also bear the image of the heavenly. </verse>
    <verse num="50">But I say this, brothers, that flesh and blood is not able to inherit the kingdom of God, nor can corruption inherit incorruptibility.</verse>
    <verse num="51">Behold, I tell you a mystery: we will not all fall asleep, but we will all be changed,</verse>
    <verse num="52">in a moment, in the blink of an eye, at the last trumpet. For the trumpet will sound, and the dead will be raised imperishable, and we will be changed.</verse>
    <verse num="53">For it is necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> this perishable <transChange type="added">body</transChange> to put on incorruptibility, and this mortal <transChange type="added">body</transChange> to put on immortality.</verse>
    <verse num="54">But whenever this perishable <transChange type="added">body</transChange> puts on incorruptibility and this mortal <transChange type="added">body</transChange> puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will take place: </verse>
    <verse num="55">Where, O death, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your victory? Where, O death, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your sting?</verse>
    <verse num="56">Now the sting of death <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sin, and the power of sin <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the law.</verse>
    <verse num="57">But thanks <transChange type="added">be</transChange> to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ!</verse>
    <verse num="58">So then, my dear brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know that your labor is not <transChange type="added">in</transChange> vain in the Lord. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">Now concerning the collection for the saints: just as I gave directions about <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to the churches of Galatia, so you do also.</verse>
    <verse num="2">On the first <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the week, each one of you {put aside}<note>Literally "put from himself"</note> <transChange type="added">something</transChange>, saving up {to whatever extent he has prospered}<note>Literally "whatever if anything he has been prospered"</note>, in order that whenever I come, at that time collections do not take place.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And whenever I arrive, whomever you approve by letters, I will send these to take your gift to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And if it is worthwhile for me to go also, they will travel with me. </verse>
    <verse num="5">But I will come to you whenever I go through Macedonia (for I am going through Macedonia),</verse>
    <verse num="6">and perhaps I will stay with you, or even spend the winter, so that you may send me on my way wherever I may go.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For I do not want to see you now in passing, for I hope to remain some time with you, if the Lord allows <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But I will remain in Ephesus until Pentecost,</verse>
    <verse num="9">for a great and effective door has opened for me, and <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> many opponents. </verse>
    <verse num="10">But if Timothy comes, see that he is with you without cause to fear, for he is carrying out the Lord's work, as I also <transChange type="added">am</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Therefore do not let anyone disdain him, but send him <transChange type="added">on his way</transChange> in peace in order that he may come to me, for I am expecting him with the brothers. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Now concerning Apollos our brother, I urged him many <transChange type="added">times</transChange> that he should come to you with the brothers, and he was not at all willing that he should come now, but he will come whenever he has <transChange type="added">an</transChange> opportunity. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Be on the alert, stand firm in the faith, act courageously, be strong.</verse>
    <verse num="14">All your <transChange type="added">actions</transChange> must be done in love. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Now I urge you, brothers--you know about the household of Stephanas, that they are the first fruits of Achaia, and they have devoted themselves to the ministry for the saints--</verse>
    <verse num="16">that you also be subject to such people, and to all those who work together and labor.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Now I rejoice over the arrival of Stephanas and Fortunatus and Achaicus, because these make up for your absence,</verse>
    <verse num="18">for they have refreshed my spirit and yours. Therefore recognize such people. </verse>
    <verse num="19">The churches of <transChange type="added">the province of</transChange> Asia<note>That is, the Roman province of Asia, known today as Asia Minor</note> greet you. Aquila and Prisca greet you in the Lord many <transChange type="added">times</transChange>, together with the church in their house.</verse>
    <verse num="20">All the brothers greet you. Greet one another with a holy kiss. </verse>
    <verse num="21">The greeting <transChange type="added">is</transChange> by my hand--Paul's.</verse>
    <verse num="22">If anyone does not love the Lord, let him be accursed. O Lord, come!<note>The Aramaic expression marana tha ("O Lord, come!") can also be rendered maran atha ("our Lord has come"); it is used here by Paul without explanation</note> </verse>
    <verse num="23">The grace of the Lord Jesus <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with you.</verse>
    <verse num="24">My love <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with all of you in Christ Jesus. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>