<book num="Prov">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Proverbs of Solomon, son of David, king of Israel:</verse>
    <verse num="2">To know wisdom and instruction, to understand sayings of understanding,</verse>
    <verse num="3">to gain {insightful instruction},<note>Literally "the instruction of insight"</note> righteousness and justice and equity,</verse>
    <verse num="4">to give shrewdness<note>Or "cleverness," or "prudence"</note> to the simple, knowledge and purpose<note>Or "plan"</note> to the young,</verse>
    <verse num="5">may the wise hear and increase learning, and the one who understands gain direction,<note>Or "guidance"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">to understand a proverb and an expression, words of wisdom and their riddles.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Fear of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> beginning of knowledge; wisdom and instruction, fools despise.</verse>
    <verse num="8">My child, may you keep<note>Or "obey," or "hear"</note> your father's instruction, and do not reject your mother's teachings,</verse>
    <verse num="9">for they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a garland of favor for your head, and pendants for your neck.</verse>
    <verse num="10">My child, if sinners entice you, do not consent.</verse>
    <verse num="11">If they say, "Come with us! We shall lie in wait for blood; we shall ambush the innocent without cause.<note>Or "wantonly," or "for nothing"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">Like Sheol,<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> we will swallow them alive and whole, {like those who descend to the pit}.<note>Literally "like the descenders of a pit"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">We shall find all precious wealth, we shall fill our houses <transChange type="added">with</transChange> booty,</verse>
    <verse num="14">you shall throw your lot in our midst, there will be one purse for all of us."</verse>
    <verse num="15">My child, do not walk in their way.<note>Or "on their road"</note> Keep your foot from their paths,</verse>
    <verse num="16">for their feet run to evil, and they hurry to shed blood,</verse>
    <verse num="17">for "in vain<note>Or "without cause," or "for nothing"</note> is the net scattered, in the sight of any {winged bird}."<note>Literally "bird of wing"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">They lie in wait for their <transChange type="added">own</transChange> blood. They ambush their <transChange type="added">own</transChange> lives.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Thus are the ways of all who are greedy <transChange type="added">for</transChange> gain-- it will take the life of its possessors.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Wisdom calls out in the streets, in the squares she raises her voice.</verse>
    <verse num="21">On a {busy corner}<note>Literally "head of commotion," or "head of stirring, bustling"</note> she cries out, at the entrances of the gates in the city, she speaks her sayings:</verse>
    <verse num="22">"{How long},<note>Literally "Until when"</note> O simple ones, will you love simplicity? And <transChange type="added">how long</transChange> will scoffers delight in their scoffing, and fools hate knowledge?</verse>
    <verse num="23">May you turn to my argument!<note>Or "turn at my reproach"</note> Behold, I shall pour out my spirit upon you; I will make my words known to you.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Because I called out and you refused me, I stretched out my hand, yet there is none who heeds.</verse>
    <verse num="25">You have ignored all my counsel, and my reproof you are not willing <transChange type="added">to accept</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="26">I will also laugh at your calamity;<note>Or "downfall"</note> I will mock when panic<note>Or "dread, fear"</note> comes <transChange type="added">upon</transChange> you.</verse>
    <verse num="27">When your panic comes like a storm, and your calamity arrives like a whirlwind, when distress and anguish come upon you,</verse>
    <verse num="28">then they will call<note>Or "cry out <transChange type="added">to</transChange>"</note> me, but I will not answer; they will seek me diligently but not find me.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Since they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of Yahweh,</verse>
    <verse num="30">they were not willing <transChange type="added">to accept</transChange> my counsel, they despised all my reproof.</verse>
    <verse num="31">They shall eat from the fruit of their way, and they shall be sated from their own schemes,</verse>
    <verse num="32">for the waywardness of the simple ones will kill them, and the complacency of fools will destroy them.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Whoever listens to me will dwell in security and rest securely<note>Or "be at ease, peace"</note> from dread and disaster."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">My child, if you will receive<note>Or "take, seize"</note> my sayings, and hide my commands with you,</verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to incline your ear toward wisdom, <transChange type="added">then</transChange> you shall apply your heart to understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For if you cry out for understanding,<note>Or "call to understanding"</note> <transChange type="added">if</transChange> you lift<note>Or "carry, give"</note> your voice for insight,</verse>
    <verse num="4">if you seek her like silver and search her out {like treasure},<note>Literally "like the treasures"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">then you will understand the fear of Yahweh, and the knowledge of God you will find.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For Yahweh will give wisdom; from his mouth <transChange type="added">come</transChange> knowledge and understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For the upright, he stores<note>Or "hides, keeps"</note> sound judgment, a shield for those who walk uprightly,</verse>
    <verse num="8"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to guard paths of justice and keep<note>Or "preserve, guard, watch"</note> the way of his faithful <transChange type="added">ones</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Then you will understand righteousness and justice and uprightness--every good course--</verse>
    <verse num="10">for wisdom will enter your heart, and knowledge will be pleasing to your soul.<note>Or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Discretion will watch over you; understanding will protect you,</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to deliver you from the way of evil,<note>Or "evildoer"</note> from a man who speaks devious things--</verse>
    <verse num="13">those who forsake the paths of uprightness to walk in ways of darkness,</verse>
    <verse num="14">those who are happy to do evil, <transChange type="added">for</transChange> they delight in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> deviousness of evil,</verse>
    <verse num="15">{who are crooked in their ways},<note>Literally "that <transChange type="added">in</transChange> their ways are crooked"</note> and devious in their paths;</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to deliver you from a strange woman, from a foreign woman <transChange type="added">who</transChange> flatters<note>Or "makes smooth"</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> her sayings,</verse>
    <verse num="17">she who forsakes the partner of her youth and has forgotten the covenant of her God,</verse>
    <verse num="18">for her house sinks to death, and to the dead<note>Or "Rephaim"</note> are her paths.</verse>
    <verse num="19"><transChange type="added">Of</transChange> all who go to her, none shall return, nor do they reach paths of life.</verse>
    <verse num="20">So that you will walk on the road of those who are good, and the paths of those who are righteous you shall keep.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For those who are upright will dwell <transChange type="added">in the</transChange> land,<note>Or "earth"</note> and those who are blameless<note>Or "innocent"</note> will remain in it.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And those who are wicked will be cut off from the land, and those who are treacherous will be uprooted from it.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">My child, do not forget my instruction, and may your heart guard my commands.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For length of days, years of life, and peace they<note>That is, "my commands" (3:1)</note> shall add to you.</verse>
    <verse num="3">May loyal love<note>Or "kindness, mercy"</note> and truth not forsake you; bind them around your neck, write them upon your heart.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And you shall find favor and good sense<note>Or "understanding, prudence"</note> in the eyes of God and humankind.</verse>
    <verse num="5">{Trust Yahweh}<note>Literally "trust toward Yahweh"</note> with all your heart; do not lean toward your own understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="6">In all your ways acknowledge him, and he will straighten your paths.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Do not be wise in your own eyes; fear Yahweh and retreat from evil.</verse>
    <verse num="8">There shall be healing for your {flesh},<note>Literally "navel"</note> and refreshment for your body.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Honor Yahweh from your substance,<note>Or "wealth, property"</note> and from the firstfruits of all that will come to you,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and your barns shall be full of plenty, and your vats shall burst <transChange type="added">with</transChange> new wine.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Do not despise the discipline of Yahweh, my child. Do not be weary of his reproof</verse>
    <verse num="12">because whomever Yahweh will love, he will rebuke, as a father delights in his son.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Happy <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {the one}<note>Literally "a man"</note> who finds wisdom, and one who obtains understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For her<note>Or "its"; both "wisdom" and "understanding" are feminine nouns and can be read as either "she" or "it"</note> income is better than the income of silver, and her revenue than <transChange type="added">that of</transChange> gold.</verse>
    <verse num="15">She is more precious than rubies, and all your desires shall not compare with her.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Length of days <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in her right hand; in her left hand <transChange type="added">are</transChange> riches and honor.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Her ways <transChange type="added">are</transChange> ways of pleasantness, and all her paths <transChange type="added">are</transChange> peace.</verse>
    <verse num="18">She is a tree of life for those who seize her; those who take hold of her are considered happy.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Yahweh in wisdom founded the earth; he established the heavens in understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="20">With his knowledge, depths broke open, and clouds dropped dew.</verse>
    <verse num="21">My child, may they<note>Grammatically, "they" most likely refers to clouds (3:20). In context, "they" may refer to wisdom and understanding (3:13).</note> not escape from your {sight};<note>Literally "eyes"</note> may you keep sound wisdom and prudence.</verse>
    <verse num="22">They shall be life for your soul<note>Or "inner self"</note> and adornment<note>Or "favor"</note> for your neck.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Then you will walk in the confidence of your ways, and your foot will not stumble.</verse>
    <verse num="24">If you sit down, you will not panic,<note>Or "fear, dread"</note> and <transChange type="added">if</transChange> you lie down, then your sleep shall be sweet.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Do not be afraid of sudden panic,<note>Or "fear, dread"</note> or the storm of wickedness that will come.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Yahweh will be {your confidence}<note>Literally "in your confidence"</note> and guard your foot from capture.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Do not withhold good from its owner<note>Or "lord"</note> when it is in the power of your hand to do.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Do not say to your neighbor, "Go and return and tomorrow I will give <transChange type="added">it</transChange>," {when it is with you}.<note>Literally "and there is with you"</note></verse>
    <verse num="29">Do not plot harm against your neighbor <transChange type="added">who</transChange> dwells in confidence beside you.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Do not quarrel with anyone without cause, when he did not do you harm.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Do not envy a man of violence, and do not choose any of his ways,</verse>
    <verse num="32">for he who is perverse <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an abomination of Yahweh, but those who are upright <transChange type="added">are</transChange> his confidence.</verse>
    <verse num="33">The curse of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on the house of the wicked, and the abode of the righteous ones he blesses.</verse>
    <verse num="34">With those who scorn, he is scornful, but to those who are humble, he gives favor.</verse>
    <verse num="35">They will inherit the honor of the wise, but stubborn fools, disgrace.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Children, listen <transChange type="added">to the</transChange> instruction of a father, and be attentive <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to know insight.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For I have given you good instruction; do not forsake my teaching.</verse>
    <verse num="3">When I was a son to my father, tender and alone before my mother,</verse>
    <verse num="4">he taught me and said to me, "May your heart hold fast <transChange type="added">to</transChange> my words; guard my commandments and live.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Get wisdom and insight; do not forget and do not turn from the sayings of my mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Do not forsake her--then she will guard you; love her and she will keep you.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The beginning of wisdom: Get wisdom! With all <transChange type="added">that is in</transChange> your possession, gain insight.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Cherish her and she will exalt you; she will honor you if you embrace her.</verse>
    <verse num="9">She will give a garland for your head; she shall bestow a crown of glory upon you."</verse>
    <verse num="10">Listen, my child, take my sayings, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> years of your life shall be great.</verse>
    <verse num="11">In the way of wisdom I have instructed you; I have led you in the path of uprightness.</verse>
    <verse num="12">{When you walk},<note>Literally "In your walking"</note> your step will not be hampered, and if you run, you will not stumble.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Seize the instruction! Do not let go! Guard her, for she is your life.</verse>
    <verse num="14">In the path of the wicked do not go; do not walk in the way of those who do evil.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Avoid it; do not transgress it; turn away from it and pass by.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For they will not sleep if they have not done wrong, and they are robbed of their sleep if they do not cause stumbling.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For they ate the bread of wickedness, and they drank the wine of violence.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But the path of the righteous ones <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the light of dawn, leading and shining until the day {is full}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">is</transChange> correct"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">The way of the wicked ones <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like deep darkness; they do not know what they stumble over.</verse>
    <verse num="20">My child, be attentive to my words; to my sayings incline your ear.</verse>
    <verse num="21">May they not escape from your {sight};<note>Literally "eyes"</note> keep them in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> midst of your heart.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For they are life to those who find them and healing {to the entire body}.<note>Literally "for all his flesh"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">With all vigilance, keep your heart, for from it <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> the source<note>Or "extremity"</note> of life.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Remove from yourself {deceitful speech},<note>Literally "crookedness of mouth"</note> and abolish {devious talk}<note>Literally "deviousness of lips"</note> from yourself.</verse>
    <verse num="25">May your eyes look forward<note>Or "opposite"</note> and your gaze be straight before you.</verse>
    <verse num="26">May the path of your foot be balanced and all your ways be sure.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Do not swerve right or left; remove your foot from evil.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">My child, be attentive to my wisdom, and to my understanding incline your ear;</verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to keep prudence, and knowledge will guard your lips.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For the lips of the strange woman will drip honey, and smoother than oil is her mouth.<note>Or "palate"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">But her end is bitter as the wormwood, sharp as a two-edged sword.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Her feet go down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> death; her steps take hold <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Sheol.<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">She does not observe<note>Or "examine, weigh"</note> the path of life; her ways wander, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> she does not know <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Now, O children, listen to me; do not depart from the sayings of my mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Keep your paths far from her, and do not go near to the door of her house,</verse>
    <verse num="9">lest you give your honor to the others, and your years to the merciless,</verse>
    <verse num="10">lest strangers take <transChange type="added">their</transChange> fill of your strength, and your labors <transChange type="added">go</transChange> to the house of a foreigner,</verse>
    <verse num="11">and you groan at your end, when your flesh and body are consumed,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and say "How I hated discipline, and I despised reproof!"</verse>
    <verse num="13">and "I did not listen to the voice of my teachers, and I did not incline my ear to my instructors!</verse>
    <verse num="14">I was almost at utter<note>Or "all, every, whole"</note> ruin<note>Or "evil"</note> in the midst of the assembly and congregation."</verse>
    <verse num="15">Drink water from your <transChange type="added">own</transChange> cistern and flowing waters from inside your own well.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Shall your springs be scattered outward? In the streets, <transChange type="added">shall there be</transChange> streams of water?</verse>
    <verse num="17">May they be yours alone, and not for strangers <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> with you.</verse>
    <verse num="18">May your fountain be blessed, and rejoice in the wife<note>Or "woman"</note> of your youth.</verse>
    <verse num="19"><transChange type="added">She is</transChange> a deer of love and a doe of grace; may her breasts satisfy you {always};<note>Literally "at all time"</note> by her love may you be intoxicated continually.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Why should you be intoxicated, my child, by a strange woman, and embrace the bosom of a foreigner?</verse>
    <verse num="21">For before the eyes of Yahweh <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {human ways},<note>Literally "the ways of man/humankind"</note> and all his paths he examines.</verse>
    <verse num="22">His iniquities shall ensnare him, the evildoer, and in the vanity of his sin he shall be caught.</verse>
    <verse num="23">He shall die {for lack of}<note>Literally "with there is no"</note> discipline, and in the greatness of his folly he shall be lost.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">My child, if you have pledged to your neighbor, <transChange type="added">if</transChange> you have bound {yourself}<note>Literally "palms of your hands"</note> to the stranger,</verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">if</transChange> you are snared by the sayings of your mouth, <transChange type="added">if</transChange> you are caught by the sayings of your mouth,</verse>
    <verse num="3">do this, then, my child, and save yourself, for you have come into {the palm of your neighbor's hand}:<note>Literally "the palm of the hand of your neighbor"</note> Go, humble yourself, plead with your neighbor.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Do not give sleep to your eyes, or slumber to your eyelids.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Save yourself like a gazelle from a hand, or like a bird from the hand of a fowler.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Go to the ant, lazy! Consider its ways and be wise.</verse>
    <verse num="7">It has no chief, officer, or ruler.</verse>
    <verse num="8">In the summer, it prepares its food; in the harvest, it gathers its sustenance.</verse>
    <verse num="9">How long will you lie down, lazy? When will you rise up from your sleep?</verse>
    <verse num="10">A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands for rest--</verse>
    <verse num="11">like a {robber}<note>Literally "one who walks," that is, a vagabond</note> shall your poverty come, and what you lack like an armed man.</verse>
    <verse num="12">A worthless man, an evil man, goes around with {deceitful speech}.<note>Literally "crookedness of mouth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">Winking in his eye, shuffling in his foot, pointing in his fingers,</verse>
    <verse num="14">perversion in his heart, he devises evil; at all times he will send out discord.<note>Or "quarrels"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">Upon {such a man},<note>Literally "thus"</note> suddenly shall his calamity come; in a moment he will be damaged and there is no healing.<note>Or "repair"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">There are six <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Yahweh hates, and seven <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> abominations of his soul:<note>Or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,</verse>
    <verse num="18">a devising heart, plans of deception, feet that hurry to run to evil,<note>Hebrew "the evil"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">a false witness who breathes lies and sends out discord<note>Or "quarrels"</note> between brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="20">My child, keep <transChange type="added">the</transChange> commandment of your father, and do not disregard <transChange type="added">the</transChange> instruction of your mother.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Bind them on your heart continually; tie them upon your neck.</verse>
    <verse num="22">{When you walk},<note>Literally "In your walking"</note> she<note>That is, "commandment" and "instruction"</note> will lead you, {When you lie down},<note>Literally "In your lying down"</note> she will watch over you, and <transChange type="added">when</transChange> you awake, she will converse <transChange type="added">with</transChange> you.</verse>
    <verse num="23">For <transChange type="added">like</transChange> a lamp <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a commandment, and instruction <transChange type="added">is</transChange> light, and the way of life<note>Hebrew "lives"</note> <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> reproof of discipline,</verse>
    <verse num="24"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to preserve you from an evil woman,<note>Or "wife"</note> from the smoothness of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> tongue of {an adulteress}.<note>Literally "a foreign woman"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">Do not desire her beauty in your heart; may she not capture you with her eyelashes.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For <transChange type="added">the</transChange> price of a woman, a prostitute,<note>Or "whore"</note> <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> price of a loaf of bread, but the {woman belonging to a man}<note>Literally "the woman of a man"</note> hunts precious life.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Can a man carry fire in his lap, and his clothes not burn?</verse>
    <verse num="28">If a man walks upon the hot coals, will his feet not be burned?</verse>
    <verse num="29">Thus, he who goes to the wife of his neighbor, any who touches her shall not go unpunished.</verse>
    <verse num="30"><transChange type="added">People</transChange> do not despise a thief when he steals to fill himself<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> when he is hungry.</verse>
    <verse num="31">But <transChange type="added">if</transChange> he is found, he will pay sevenfold, every possession of his house he shall give.</verse>
    <verse num="32">He who commits adultery <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a woman lacks {sense},<note>Literally "heart"</note> he destroys himself<note>Or "his soul," or "his life"</note> who does it.</verse>
    <verse num="33">A wound and dishonor he will find, and his disgrace will not be wiped out.</verse>
    <verse num="34">For jealousy <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> fury of a husband, and he will not show restraint on the day of revenge.</verse>
    <verse num="35">He will not accept {any compensation},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> face of any compensation"</note> and he will not be willing, though the bribe is large.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">My child, guard my sayings; store my commandments with you.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Keep my commands and live, and my teaching like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> {apple of your eye}.<note>A single word meaning "pupil of the eye"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Bind them on your fingers; write them on the tablet of your heart.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Say to wisdom,<note>Hebrew "the wisdom"</note> "you are my sister," and you shall call insight,<note>Hebrew "the insight"</note> "{intimate friend}."<note>Literally "one who is known." To "know" is often a euphemism for intercourse. Therefore "intimate friend" may also be read "lover."</note></verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">In order</transChange> to guard yourself from {an adulteress},<note>Literally "a strange woman"</note> from the foreigner who {makes her words smooth}.<note>Literally "causes to be smooth her words"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">For at the window of my house, through my lattice, I looked down.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And I saw among the simple, I observed among the youth, a young man lacking {sense},<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">passing on the street {at}<note>Literally "at the place of"</note> her corner, and he takes the road <transChange type="added">to</transChange> her house,</verse>
    <verse num="9">at twilight, at <transChange type="added">the</transChange> day's evening, in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> midst of night and the darkness.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Then behold! A woman <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> to meet him <transChange type="added">with the</transChange> garment of a prostitute<note>Or "whore"</note> and {a secret heart}.<note>Literally "secret of heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">She is loud and stubborn; her feet do not stay at her house.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Now in the street, now in the square, {at}<note>Literally "at the place of"</note> every corner she lies in wait.</verse>
    <verse num="13">She took hold of <note>Or "strengthened"</note> him and kissed him. Her face was impudent, and she said to him,</verse>
    <verse num="14">"Sacrifices of peace offerings <transChange type="added">are</transChange> upon me; {today}<note>Literally "the day"</note> I completed my vows.</verse>
    <verse num="15">So<note>Hebrew "thus"</note> I have come out to meet you, to seek your face, and I have found you.</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">With</transChange> coverings I have adorned my couch, spreads of the linen of Egypt;</verse>
    <verse num="17">I have perfumed my bed <transChange type="added">with</transChange> myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Come, let us take <transChange type="added">our</transChange> fill of love making, until the morning let us delight in love.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For there is no man<note>Or "husband"</note> in his home; he has gone on a {long journey}.<note>Literally "a journey from far"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">The bag of money he took in his hand, for <transChange type="added">on</transChange> the day of the full moon he will come home."</verse>
    <verse num="21">She persuades him with the greatness of her teachings; with her smooth lips she compels him.</verse>
    <verse num="22">He goes after her suddenly; like an ox to the slaughter he goes, and like a stag to the instruction of a fool,</verse>
    <verse num="23">until an arrow pierces his {entrails},<note>Literally "heaviness," often referring to the liver</note> like a bird rushing into a snare, but he does not know that {it will cost him his life}.<note>Literally "it is against his life"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">And now, my children, listen to me, and be attentive to the sayings of my mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="25">May your heart not turn aside to her ways; do not stray into her path.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For many slain she has laid low, and countless<note>Or "strong men"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all of her killings.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The ways of Sheol<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> her house, descending to chambers of death.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">Does not wisdom call, and understanding raise its voice?</verse>
    <verse num="2">{Atop the heights}<note>Literally "At a head of the heights"</note> beside the road, at the crossroads she stands.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Beside gates, before towns, <transChange type="added">at the</transChange> entrance of doors, she cries out:</verse>
    <verse num="4">"To you, O {people},<note>Literally "men"</note> I call, and my cry is to the children of humankind.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Learn prudence, O simple ones; fools, learn {intelligence}.<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Listen! For noble things I will speak, and upright things from the opening of my lips.</verse>
    <verse num="7">My mouth will utter truth, and wickedness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an abomination to my lips.</verse>
    <verse num="8">All sayings of my mouth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in righteousness; none of them are twisted and crooked.</verse>
    <verse num="9">All of them are straight to him who understands, and upright to those who find knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Take my teaching and not silver; may you choose knowledge rather than choice gold.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For wisdom is better than jewels, and all desires shall not compare with her.</verse>
    <verse num="12">I, wisdom, live with prudence, and I find knowledge and discretion.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The fear of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> hatred of evil, pride, and arrogance and an evil way. And I hate a mouth of perversity.</verse>
    <verse num="14">{Advice and sound judgment}<note>Literally "To/for me are advice and sound judgment"</note> are mine; I am understanding, {strength is mine}.<note>Literally "to/for me is strength"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">By me kings reign, and rulers decree righteousness.</verse>
    <verse num="16">By me rulers rule, and nobles--all judges of righteousness.</verse>
    <verse num="17">I love {those who love me},<note>Literally "her lovers"</note> and those who seek me diligently shall find me.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Fortune and glory <transChange type="added">are</transChange> with me, enduring wealth and righteousness.</verse>
    <verse num="19">My fruit is better than gold,<note>Literally "fine gold"</note> even refined gold, and my yield than choice silver.</verse>
    <verse num="20">In the way of righteousness I walk, in the midst of paths of justice,</verse>
    <verse num="21"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to endow those who love me <transChange type="added">with</transChange> wealth, and I will fill their treasuries.</verse>
    <verse num="22">"Yahweh possessed<note>Or "gained," or "acquired"</note> me, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> first of his ways, before his acts {of old}.<note>Literally "from before" or "from then"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">From eternity, I was set up from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> first, from the beginning<note>Hebrew "beginnings"</note> of the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="24">When there were no depths, I was brought forth, when there were no springs of {abounding}<note>Literally "made heavy"</note> water.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Before mountains had been shaped, before hills, I was brought forth.</verse>
    <verse num="26">When he had not yet made earth and fields, or the first dust of the world,</verse>
    <verse num="27">{when he established}<note>Literally "in his establishing"</note> the heavens, there I <transChange type="added">was</transChange>, {when he drew}<note>Literally "in his drawing"</note> a circle upon the face of the deep,</verse>
    <verse num="28">{when he made}<note>Literally "in his making"</note> skies from above, when he founded fountains of the deep,</verse>
    <verse num="29">{when he assigned}<note>Literally "in his assigning"</note> his limits to the sea, that waters shall not transgress his {command},<note>Literally "mouth"</note> {when he marked}<note>Literally "in his marking"</note> the foundations of the earth,</verse>
    <verse num="30">I was {beside}<note>Literally "at the place of"</note> him, a master workman, and I was delighting day by day, rejoicing before him {always},<note>Literally "in all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> time"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">rejoicing in the world of his earth, and my delight <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with the children of humankind.</verse>
    <verse num="32">"And now, children, listen to me; happy <transChange type="added">are</transChange> those who will keep my ways.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Hear teaching and be wise; do not neglect <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="34">Happy <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> person who listens to me, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to keep watch at my doors day by day, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to guard the frames of my entrances.</verse>
    <verse num="35">For he who finds me <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who finds<note>Hebrew "those who find"</note> life, and he obtains favor from Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="36">But he who misses me injures himself.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> All those who hate me love death."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">Wisdom has built her house; she has hewn her seven pillars.</verse>
    <verse num="2">She has slaughtered her slaughtering, mixed her wine, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> also set her table.</verse>
    <verse num="3">She has sent her servant girls,<note>Or "young maidens"</note> she calls upon the wings of the high places of town,</verse>
    <verse num="4">"Whoever <transChange type="added">is</transChange> simple, let him turn here." As for the one who lacks {sense},<note>Literally "heart"</note> she says to him,</verse>
    <verse num="5">"Come, eat with my bread; drink with the wine I have mixed.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Lay aside simplicity and live; walk in the way of understanding."</verse>
    <verse num="7">He who corrects a scoffer gains abuse for himself, and he who rebukes the wicked {gets hurt}.<note>Literally "abuse him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Do not rebuke a scoffer, lest he hate you; rebuke the wise and he will love you.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Give to a wise one and he will become more wise; {teach}<note>Literally "make known to"</note> a righteous one and he will increase learning.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The start of wisdom is fear of Yahweh, and knowledge of the Holy One,<note>Or "holy ones"</note> insight.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For by me your days shall increase, and years of life shall multiply for you.</verse>
    <verse num="12">If you are wise, you are wise for yourself, and <transChange type="added">if</transChange> you scoff, alone you shall bear <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A woman of foolishness is loud, simple, and does not know {it}.<note>Literally "what"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">She sits at the door of her house, upon a throne <transChange type="added">at the</transChange> high places of town,</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to call to those who pass by the road, those who go straight <transChange type="added">on</transChange> their way:</verse>
    <verse num="16">"Whoever is simple, may he turn here!" As for he who lacks {sense},<note>Literally "heart"</note> she says to him,</verse>
    <verse num="17">"Stolen waters are sweet, and bread of secrecy is pleasant."</verse>
    <verse num="18">But he does not know that the dead<note>Or "Rephaim"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> there, in the depths of Sheol<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> her guests.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">The proverbs of Solomon: A wise child makes a father glad, but a foolish child grieves his mother.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Treasures of wickedness do not profit, but righteousness delivers from death.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Yahweh will not cause a righteous person<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> to go hungry, but the craving of the wicked he will thwart.</verse>
    <verse num="4">A slack hand causes poverty, but the hand of the diligent enriches.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He who gathers in the summer <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a child who is prudent; he who sleeps at the harvest <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a child who brings shame.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Blessings <transChange type="added">belong</transChange> to the head of the righteous, but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The memory of righteousness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a blessing, but the name of the wicked will rot.</verse>
    <verse num="8">A heart of wisdom will heed commandments, but a babbling fool will come to ruin.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Whoever walks in integrity<note>Hebrew "in the integrity"</note> will walk securely, but whoever follows perversity, his ways will be made known.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The winking of an eye causes<note>Or "gives, sets up"</note> trouble, and the foolishness of lips comes to ruin.</verse>
    <verse num="11">A fountain of life <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a mouth of righteousness, and a mouth of wickedness conceals violence.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Hatred stirs up strife, but love covers over all offenses.</verse>
    <verse num="13">On the lips of one who has understanding, wisdom is found, but a rod <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the back of one who lacks {sense}.<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">Those who are wise lay up knowledge, but <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the mouth of the fool, ruin draws near.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The wealth of the rich <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the city of his strength; the ruin of the poor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their poverty.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The wage of the righteous <transChange type="added">leads</transChange> to life; the gain of the wicked to sin.</verse>
    <verse num="17"><transChange type="added">On</transChange> the path to life is he who guards instruction, but he who rejects rebuke goes astray.</verse>
    <verse num="18">He who conceals hatred <transChange type="added">has</transChange> lips of deceit, and he who utters slander--he is a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="19">In many words, transgression is not lacking, but he who restrains his lips is prudent.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Choice silver is a tongue of righteousness, a heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of wickedness is {of little worth}.<note>Literally "like a little"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">Lips of righteousness feed many, but fools {die for lack of sense}.<note>Literally "in the lack of heart, they die"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">The blessing of Yahweh makes <transChange type="added">one</transChange> rich, and he does not increase sorrow with it.</verse>
    <verse num="23"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> like a sport for a fool to do wrong, wisdom for a person of understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The dread of the wicked will come upon him, but the desire of the righteous will be granted.</verse>
    <verse num="25">With the passing of the tempest, there is no wickedness, but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> righteous have a foundation forever.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Like vinegar to the tooth and like smoke to the eyes, thus <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the lazy to one who employs<note>Or "sends"</note> him.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The fear of Yahweh adds life, but the years of the wicked are shortened.</verse>
    <verse num="28">The hope of the righteous <transChange type="added">is</transChange> gladness, but the expectation of the wicked comes to nothing.</verse>
    <verse num="29">A stronghold for the upright is the way of Yahweh, but ruin <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to {evildoers}.<note>Literally "them who do evil"</note></verse>
    <verse num="30">The righteous one is forever; he will not be removed. But the wicked will not remain in the land.<note>Or "earth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">The mouth of the righteous brings forth wisdom, but a tongue of perversity will be cut off.</verse>
    <verse num="32">The lips of the righteous know <transChange type="added">the</transChange> acceptable, but the mouth of the wicked, the perverse.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Balances of deceit <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an abomination of Yahweh, but {an accurate weight}<note>Literally "a full stone" or "a pure stone"</note> delights him.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Pride comes, then disgrace comes, but wisdom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with the humble.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The integrity of the upright guides them, but the crookedness of the treacherous destroys them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Wealth does not profit on the day of wrath, but righteousness will deliver from death.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The righteousness of the blameless will keep his ways straight, but the wicked will fall by his wickedness.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The righteousness of the upright will save them, but by a scheme the treacherous will be taken captive.</verse>
    <verse num="7">With the death of a wicked person, hope will die, and the expectation of the godless perishes.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The righteous is delivered from trouble, but the wicked enters into it.</verse>
    <verse num="9">With a mouth, the godless shall destroy his neighbor, but by knowledge the righteous are delivered.</verse>
    <verse num="10">When good <transChange type="added">is with</transChange> the righteous, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> city rejoices, and with the perishing of the wicked, jubilation.</verse>
    <verse num="11">By the blessing of the upright, a city will be exalted, but by the mouth of the wicked, it will be overthrown.</verse>
    <verse num="12">He who lacks {sense}<note>Literally "heart"</note> belittles his neighbor, but a person of intelligence will remain silent.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A gossip walks <transChange type="added">about</transChange> telling a secret, but the trustworthy in spirit keeps <transChange type="added">the</transChange> matter.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Where there is no guidance, a nation<note>Or "people"</note> shall fall, but <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> safety in an abundance of counsel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He will suffer trouble when he loans to a stranger, but he who refuses a pledge is safe.</verse>
    <verse num="16">A woman of grace receives honor, but the ruthless gets wealth.</verse>
    <verse num="17">A person of kindness rewards himself,<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> but a cruel <transChange type="added">person</transChange> harms his own flesh.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The wicked earns<note>Or "does, makes"</note> {deceptive gain},<note>Literally "gain of deception"</note> but he who sows righteousness, a {true reward}.<note>Literally "a reward of truth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">He who is steadfast in righteousness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to life as<note>Hebrew "and"</note> he who pursues evil <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to death.</verse>
    <verse num="20">An abomination of Yahweh <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the {crooked of heart},<note>Literally "crooked ones of heart"; "heart" may also be translated "mind"</note> but his delight <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {those with blameless ways}.<note>Literally "blameless ones of ways"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">{Rest assured},<note>Literally "Hand to hand"</note> the wicked will not go unpunished, but the offspring<note>Or "seed"</note> of the righteous will escape.</verse>
    <verse num="22">A ring of gold in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> snout of a pig <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a woman <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> beautiful but without discretion.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The desire of the righteous <transChange type="added">is</transChange> only good, but the expectation of the wicked, wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="24">There is one who gives yet {grows richer},<note>Literally "adding more"</note> but he who withholds {what is right}<note>Literally "from what is right"</note> only <transChange type="added">finds</transChange> need.</verse>
    <verse num="25">A person of blessing will be enriched, and he who gives water also will be refreshed.</verse>
    <verse num="26">He who withholds grain, the people curse him, but a blessing <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the head of him who sells.</verse>
    <verse num="27">He who diligently seeks good seeks favor, but he who inquires of evil, it will come to him.</verse>
    <verse num="28">He who trusts in his wealth <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who will fall, but like a green leaf the righteous will flourish.</verse>
    <verse num="29">He who brings trouble <transChange type="added">to</transChange> his household, he will inherit wind,<note>Or "breath, spirit"</note> and a fool will serve the wise of heart.</verse>
    <verse num="30">The fruit of righteousness is a tree of life, and he who captures souls<note>Or "persons," or "inner selves"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wise.</verse>
    <verse num="31">If the righteous on earth will be repaid, {how much more}<note>Literally "more for"</note> the wicked and sinner.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">He who loves discipline loves knowledge, but he who hates rebuke <transChange type="added">is</transChange> stupid.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The good obtains favor from Yahweh, but anyone who schemes, he condemns.</verse>
    <verse num="3">A person will not be established by wickedness, but the root of the righteous will not be moved.</verse>
    <verse num="4">A woman of strength<note>Or "honor"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the crown of her master,<note>Or "lord, owner"</note> but like rot in his bones is she who brings shame.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The thoughts of the righteous are<note>Hebrew "is"</note> just; the advice of the wicked is treacherous.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The words of the wicked <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an ambush of blood, but the mouth of the upright delivers them.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The wicked are overthrown and {are no more},<note>Literally "there is no them"</note> but the house of the righteous shall stand.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For his mouth of good sense, a man will be recommended, but he who is of perverse {mind}<note>Literally "heart"</note> will be despised.</verse>
    <verse num="9">It is better to be lowly and a servant {to someone}<note>Literally "for him," "<transChange type="added">belonging</transChange> to him"</note> than self-glorifying and lacking food.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The righteous knows the life<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> of his animal, but the compassion<note>Hebrew "compassions"</note> of the wicked is cruel.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He who works his land will have plenty of food, but he who follows worthless things lacks {sense}.<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">The wicked covets the proceeds of evil, but the root of the righteous {bears fruit}.<note>Literally "gives, sets up"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">By the transgression of lips, evil is ensnared, but the righteous escapes from trouble.</verse>
    <verse num="14">From the fruit of the mouth of a man, he is filled with good, and the reward of {a man's labor}<note>Literally "the hands of a man"</note> will return to him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The way of a fool is upright in his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> eyes, but he who listens to advice <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wise.</verse>
    <verse num="16">As for a fool, {on that very day}<note>Literally "on the day"</note> he makes his anger known, but he who ignores an insult <transChange type="added">is</transChange> prudent.</verse>
    <verse num="17">He who will speak truth will reveal righteousness, but the witness of falsehood, deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="18">There is one who speaks rashly, like the thrust of a sword, but the tongue of the wise brings healing.</verse>
    <verse num="19">A lip of truth endures forever, but a tongue of deception lasts only a moment.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Deceit <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of {those who plan}<note>Literally "the planners of"</note> evil, but to {those who plan}<note>Literally "the planners of"</note> peace, <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> joy.</verse>
    <verse num="21">{No evil will happen}<note>Literally "All evil will not happen"</note> to the righteous, but the wicked are filled <transChange type="added">with</transChange> trouble.</verse>
    <verse num="22">An abomination of Yahweh are lips of deceit, but they who act faithfully <transChange type="added">are</transChange> his delight.</verse>
    <verse num="23">A clever person conceals knowledge, but the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a fool<note>Hebrew "fools"</note> announces folly.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The hand of the diligent ones will rule, but the lazy will belong to forced labor.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Anxiety in the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a man will weigh him down, but a good word will cheer him.</verse>
    <verse num="26">A righteous person will seek out his neighbor, but the way of the wicked will lead them astray.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The lazy will not roast his game, but diligence is the precious wealth of a man.</verse>
    <verse num="28">On the road of righteousness is life, and <transChange type="added">on</transChange> the way of the path, <transChange type="added">may there be</transChange> no death.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">A wise child <transChange type="added">hears</transChange> the discipline of a father, but a scoffer does not listen to a rebuke.</verse>
    <verse num="2">From the fruit of the mouth of a man, he shall eat what is good, but the desire<note>Or "soul"</note> of the treacherous, wrongdoing.</verse>
    <verse num="3">He who keeps his mouth guards his life;<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> he who opens his lips, ruin <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to him.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The soul<note>Or "life"</note> of the lazy craves, but there is nothing, but the person of diligence is richly supplied.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The righteous hates a word of falsehood; the wicked will bring shame and {disgrace}.<note>Literally "he will bring disgrace"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Righteousness will guard the upright of way, but wickedness will overthrow sin.</verse>
    <verse num="7">There is one who acts rich but {has nothing};<note>Literally "there is no"</note> another who pretends to be poor but <transChange type="added">has</transChange> wealth.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The ransom of the life of a man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his wealth, but the poor does not receive a threat.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The light of the righteous will rejoice, but the lamp of the wicked will die out.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Only by insolence is strife set up, and wisdom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with those who take advice.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Wealth <transChange type="added">gained</transChange> from haste<note>Or "vanity"</note> will dwindle, but he who gathers {little by little}<note>Literally "upon the hand"</note> will increase it.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Hope that is deferred makes the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> sick, but a desire fulfilled <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a tree of life.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He who despises a word will bring destruction on himself, but he who respects a commandment will be rewarded.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The teaching of the wise <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fountain of life, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to avoid the snares of death.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Good sense grants favor, but the way of the faithless is coarse.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Anyone who is clever will act with intelligence, but the fool will display folly.</verse>
    <verse num="17">A messenger of wickedness will fall into trouble, but an envoy of the faithful <transChange type="added">brings</transChange> healing.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Poverty and disgrace <transChange type="added">belong to</transChange> him who ignores instruction, but he who guards reproof will be honored.</verse>
    <verse num="19">A desire {fulfilled}<note>Literally "made to be," "brought about"</note> will be sweet to the soul, but an abomination of fools is turning from evil.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Walk with the wise and be wise, but as for the companion of fools, he will suffer harm.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Misfortune will pursue sinners, but the righteous {will be rewarded with prosperity}.<note>Literally "it will reward prosperity"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">He who is good will leave an inheritance to {his grandchildren},<note>Literally "sons of sons"</note> and stored up for the righteous <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the wealth of a sinner.</verse>
    <verse num="23"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> much food <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the field of the poor, but {it is swept away}<note>Literally "there is sweeping away"</note> by {injustice}.<note>Literally "no justice"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">He who withholds his rod hates his child, but he who loves him {gives him}<note>Literally "visits him"</note> discipline.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The righteous eats to satisfy his life,<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> but the belly of the wicked will lack.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">The {wisest of women}<note>Literally "wise ones of women"</note> builds her house, but the foolish tears it down with her hands.</verse>
    <verse num="2">He who walks in uprightness fears Yahweh, but he who is devious <transChange type="added">in</transChange> his ways displeases him.</verse>
    <verse num="3">In the mouth of a fool is the rod of pride, but the lips of the wise preserve them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">{When there are no}<note>Literally "In there is no"</note> oxen the manger is empty, but an abundance of crops <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> by the strength of an ox.<note>Hebrew "bull"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">A faithful witness does not lie, but he who breathes out falsehood is a witness of deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="6">A scoffer seeks wisdom, but there is none, but knowledge {comes easily to him who understands}.<note>Literally "to one who understands it comes easy"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Leave {the presence of a foolish man},<note>Literally "from the presence <transChange type="added">belonging</transChange> to a man of foolishness"</note> <transChange type="added">for</transChange> you will not <transChange type="added">come to</transChange> know {words of knowledge}.<note>Literally "lips of knowledge"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">The wisdom of the clever is understanding his ways, but the folly of fools is deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Fools mock<note>Hebrew "he mocks"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> guilt offering, but among the upright, it is favorable.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The heart<note>Or "mind"</note> knows the bitterness of its soul,<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note> but in its joy, it will not share itself with a stranger.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The house of the wicked will be destroyed, but the tent of the upright will flourish.</verse>
    <verse num="12">There is a way <transChange type="added">that seems</transChange> upright {to}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> a man, but its end <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the way of death.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Even in laughter, a heart may be sad, and the end of joy <transChange type="added">may be</transChange> grief.</verse>
    <verse num="14">From his ways, the perverse of heart will be satisfied, and {from his own},<note>Literally "from upon him"</note> <transChange type="added">so shall</transChange> a good man.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The simple will believe every word, but the clever will consider his step.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The wise is cautious and turns from evil, but the fool throws off restraint and is confident.</verse>
    <verse num="17">He who is short of {temper}<note>Literally "nostril"</note> will act foolishly, and the man who schemes will be hated.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The simple are adorned <transChange type="added">with</transChange> folly, but the clever are crowned with knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The evil bow down before the good, and the wicked at the gates of the righteous.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The poor is disliked even by his neighbor, but the lovers of the rich are many.</verse>
    <verse num="21">He who despises his neighbor is a sinner, but he who has mercy on the poor blesses him.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Have they not erred, those who plan evil? But loyalty and faithfulness <transChange type="added">belong to</transChange> those who plan good.</verse>
    <verse num="23">In all toil, there is profit, but the {talk}<note>Literally "word, matter, thing"</note> of lips <transChange type="added">leads</transChange> only to poverty.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The crown of the wise <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their wealth; the folly of fools is folly.</verse>
    <verse num="25">He who saves lives<note>Or "souls," or "inner selves"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a witness of truth, but he who utters lies <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a betrayer.</verse>
    <verse num="26">In the fear of Yahweh, there is confidence of strength, and for his children, there will be refuge.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The fear of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fountain of life, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to turn from the snares of death.</verse>
    <verse num="28">In the multitude of people is the glory of the king, but without a population, a prince <transChange type="added">is</transChange> ruined.</verse>
    <verse num="29"><transChange type="added">He who is</transChange> slow to anger <transChange type="added">has</transChange> great understanding, but the hasty of spirit<note>Or "breath"</note> exalts folly.</verse>
    <verse num="30">A heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of tranquility<note>Or "he who heals"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> life <transChange type="added">to the</transChange> flesh, but causes bones of passion to rot.</verse>
    <verse num="31">He who oppresses the poor insults him who made him, but he who has mercy on the poor honors him.</verse>
    <verse num="32">By his evildoing, the wicked will be overthrown, and the righteous will find refuge in his death.</verse>
    <verse num="33">In the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of him who has understanding, wisdom rests, but <transChange type="added">even</transChange> in the midst of fools it becomes known.</verse>
    <verse num="34">Righteousness will exalt a nation, but sin <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a reproach to a people.</verse>
    <verse num="35">The favor of a king <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the servant who deals wisely, but his wrath will be <transChange type="added">on</transChange> him who acts shamefully.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">A soft answer will turn away wrath, but a word of trouble will stir {anger}.<note>Literally "nostril"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">The tongue of the wise will dispense knowledge, but the mouth of fools will pour out folly.</verse>
    <verse num="3">In every place, the eyes of Yahweh keep watch over the evil and the good.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Gentleness<note>Or "Healing"</note> of tongue is a tree of life, but perverseness in it<note>That is, the tongue</note> <transChange type="added">causes</transChange> a break in spirit.</verse>
    <verse num="5">A fool will despise the instruction of his father, but he who guards reproof is prudent.</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">In</transChange> the house of the righteous <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> much treasure, but the income of the wicked brings trouble.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The lips of the wise will spread knowledge, but the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of fools, not so.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination of Yahweh, but the prayer of the upright <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his delight.</verse>
    <verse num="9">An abomination of Yahweh is the way of the wicked, but he who pursues righteousness he will love.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Severe discipline <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to him who forsakes the way; he who hates a rebuke will die.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Sheol<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> and Abaddon<note>Poetic synonym for "Sheol." Only mentioned in the ot in relation to Sheol, the grave, or death.</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> before Yahweh, {how much more}<note>Literally "more for"</note> the hearts of the children of men!</verse>
    <verse num="12">A scoffer does not like {his rebuke};<note>Literally "rebuke <transChange type="added">belonging</transChange> to him"</note> to the wise he will not go.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of gladness will make good {countenance},<note>Literally "faces"</note> but in sorrow of heart<note>Or "mind"</note> a spirit is broken.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The heart of him who understands will seek knowledge, but the faces of fools, they<note>Hebrew "he/it"</note> will feed on folly.</verse>
    <verse num="15">All the days of the poor <transChange type="added">are</transChange> hard, but goodness of heart<note>Or "mind"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a continuous feast.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Better <transChange type="added">is</transChange> little with the fear of Yahweh than great treasure and trouble with it.<note>Or "him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">Better <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a dinner of vegetables when<note>Hebrew "and"</note> love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> there than a fattened ox and hatred with it.<note>Or "him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">A man who is hot-tempered will stir up strife, but he who is slow <transChange type="added">to</transChange> {anger},<note>Literally "nostrils"</note> he will calm contention.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The way of the lazy is like a hedge of thorns,<note>Hebrew "thorn"</note> but the path of the upright <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a highway.</verse>
    <verse num="20">A child of wisdom will make a father glad, but a {foolish person},<note>Literally "foolishness of humankind"</note> he despises his mother.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Folly is a joy to him who lacks {sense},<note>Literally "heart"</note> and a person of understanding {will walk upright}.<note>Literally "he will walk upright walking"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">Plans go wrong when there is no counsel, but with many advisors it will succeed.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Joy <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to a man with answers in his mouth, and a word in its time, how good <transChange type="added">it is</transChange>!</verse>
    <verse num="24">The path of life <transChange type="added">leads</transChange> upward for him who has insight, in order to turn away from Sheol below.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The house of the proud, Yahweh will tear <transChange type="added">it</transChange> down, but he will maintain the {property line}<note>Literally "boundary"</note> of the widow.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Plans of evil <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an abomination of Yahweh, but gracious words are pure.</verse>
    <verse num="27">He who makes trouble for his house <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who is greedy for unjust gain, but he who hates bribes will live.</verse>
    <verse num="28">A heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of righteousness will ponder the answer, but a mouth of wickedness will pour out deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Yahweh is far from the wicked, but the prayers of the righteous he will hear.</verse>
    <verse num="30">From the light of the eyes, the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> will rejoice, and good news will enliven the bones.<note>Hebrew "bone"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">The ear of him who listens <transChange type="added">to</transChange> admonitions of life, in the midst of the wise it will lodge.</verse>
    <verse num="32">He who ignores instruction despises himself,<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> but he who hears admonition gains heart.<note>Or "mind"</note></verse>
    <verse num="33">Fear of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the instruction of the wise, and before honor <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> humility.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">To mortals <transChange type="added">belong</transChange> the plans of the heart, but from Yahweh <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> the answer of the tongue.</verse>
    <verse num="2">All the ways of a man <transChange type="added">are</transChange> pure in his own eyes, but Yahweh weighs the spirit.<note>Or "breath"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Commit your work to Yahweh, and your plans will be established.</verse>
    <verse num="4">All Yahweh has made <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for his<note>Or "its"</note> purpose, and even the wicked for the day of trouble.</verse>
    <verse num="5">An abomination of Yahweh <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all who are arrogant of heart;<note>Or "mind"</note> {rest assured},<note>Literally "hand to hand"</note> he will not go unpunished.</verse>
    <verse num="6">By loyalty and faithfulness, iniquity will be covered over,<note>Or "atoned for"</note> and by fear of Yahweh {one turns}<note>Literally "turning"</note> from evil.</verse>
    <verse num="7">When the ways of a man are pleasing <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Yahweh, even his enemies he will cause to make peace with him.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Better is little with righteousness than great income with no justice.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The {mind}<note>Literally "heart"</note> of a person will plan his ways, and Yahweh will direct his steps.</verse>
    <verse num="10">A decision is upon the lips of a king; in judgment his mouth will not sin.</verse>
    <verse num="11">A balance and scales of justice <transChange type="added">belong</transChange> to Yahweh; all the weights of the bag <transChange type="added">are</transChange> his work.</verse>
    <verse num="12">An abomination to kings <transChange type="added">is</transChange> doing evil, for by righteousness the throne will be established.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The delight of kings <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the lips of righteousness, and he who speaks what is upright he will love.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The wrath of a king <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a messenger of death, but one who is wise will appease<note>Or "atone, cover over"</note> it.</verse>
    <verse num="15">In the light of the face of the king <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> life, and his favor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a cloud of spring rain.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Getting wisdom: {how much}<note>Literally "what"</note> better than gold! And getting understanding: it is chosen {over}<note>Literally "from"</note> silver.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The highway of the upright, it turns from evil, he who guards himself<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> keeps his way.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Before destruction <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> pride, and before a fall, a haughty spirit.<note>Hebrew "a haughty of spirit"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">Better a lowly spirit with the poor than dividing the spoil with the proud.</verse>
    <verse num="20">He who is attentive to a matter will find goodness, and he who trusts in Yahweh, his own happiness.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The wise of heart<note>Or "mind"</note> is called perceptive, but he who is pleasant of lips will increase persuasiveness.</verse>
    <verse num="22">A fountain of life is wisdom for its owner,<note>Or "master"</note> but the instruction<note>Or "punishment"</note> of fools is folly.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of the wise will make his mouth judicious, and upon his lips, it<note>Or "he"</note> will add persuasiveness.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Pleasant sayings <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a honeycomb, sweetness to the soul and healing to the bones.</verse>
    <verse num="25">There is a way <transChange type="added">that seems</transChange> upright {to}<note>Literally "to the face of"</note> a man, but its end <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the way of death.</verse>
    <verse num="26">The life<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> of a worker works for him, for his {hunger}<note>Literally "mouth"</note> urges him.</verse>
    <verse num="27">A man of wickedness concocts evil, and his lips <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like a scorching fire.</verse>
    <verse num="28">A person of perversity will spread dissent, and he who whispers separates a close friend.</verse>
    <verse num="29">A person of violence will entice his neighbor and cause him to walk on a way <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> not good.</verse>
    <verse num="30">He who winks his eyes <transChange type="added">does so in order</transChange> to plan perverse things; he who purses his lips will bring evil to pass.</verse>
    <verse num="31">A crown of glory is gray hair; by a righteous life it is gained.</verse>
    <verse num="32">He who is slow to anger<note>Literally "nostrils"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> better than him who is mighty, and he who controls his spirit than him who captures a city.</verse>
    <verse num="33">The lot will be cast into the lap, but all of its decisions are from Yahweh.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">Better a dry morsel and quiet with it than a house filled <transChange type="added">with</transChange> feasts of strife.</verse>
    <verse num="2">A slave who deals wisely will rule over a child who acts shamefully, and in the midst of brothers he will share his inheritance.</verse>
    <verse num="3">A crucible <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the silver, and a furnace <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the gold, but Yahweh will test hearts.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He who does evil listens to lips of wickedness, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the liar gives heed to the tongue of mischief.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He who mocks the poor insults him who made him; he who rejoices at calamity will not go unpunished.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The crown of the elderly <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {grandchildren},<note>Literally "sons of sons"</note> and the glory of children <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their fathers.</verse>
    <verse num="7">{Fine speech}<note>Literally "A lip of fine<transChange type="added">ness</transChange>"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not becoming a fool, {still less}<note>Literally "only for"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {false speech}<note>Literally "lip of deceit"</note> for a ruler.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The bribe <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a stone of magic in the eyes of its owner;<note>Or "master"</note> {everywhere}<note>Literally "to all which"</note> he will turn, he will prosper.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He who forgives an affront fosters love, but he who waits on a matter will alienate a friend.</verse>
    <verse num="10">A rebuke strikes him who understands deeper than one hundred blows to a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="11">An evil person will seek only rebellion, and a cruel messenger will be sent against him.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">May</transChange> a man meet a she-bear robbed of offspring and not a fool in his folly.</verse>
    <verse num="13"><transChange type="added">For</transChange> he who returns evil for good, evil will not depart from his house.</verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> the release of water <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the beginning of strife; before it breaks out, stop the quarrel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">He who justifies the wicked and he who condemns the righteous, the two of them <transChange type="added">are</transChange> both abominations of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Why <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this? A price in the hand of a fool, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to buy wisdom where<note>Hebrew "and"</note> there is no {sense}.<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">The friend loves at all times<note>Hebrew "time"</note>, but a brother is born for adversity.</verse>
    <verse num="18">A person who lacks {sense}<note>Literally "heart"</note> {pledges};<note>Literally "pledges a hand"</note> he becomes security before his neighbor.</verse>
    <verse num="19">He who loves transgression loves strife; he who builds his high thresholds seeks destruction.</verse>
    <verse num="20">He who is crooked of heart<note>Or "mind"</note> will not find goodness, and he who is perverse, by his tongue he will fall into calamity.</verse>
    <verse num="21">He who begets a fool, <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> trouble for him; the father of a fool will not rejoice.</verse>
    <verse num="22">A cheerful heart is good medicine, but a downcast spirit will dry out bones.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The wicked will accept a bribe from the lap, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to pervert the ways of justice.</verse>
    <verse num="24">He who understands sets <transChange type="added">his</transChange> face <transChange type="added">toward</transChange> wisdom, but the eyes of a fool, to the end of the earth.<note>Or "land"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">A grief to his father <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the child of a fool, and bitterness to her who bore him.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Also, imposing a fine on the righteous is not good, <transChange type="added">nor</transChange> to flog nobles for uprightness.</verse>
    <verse num="27">He who spares his sayings knows knowledge, and a cool spirit is a man of understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Even a fool who keeps silent {shall be considered wise};<note>Literally "wise, he shall be considered"</note> he who closes his lips <transChange type="added">is</transChange> intelligent.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">He who is selfish seeks a craving;<note>Or "boundary"</note> against all sound judgment he shows contempt.</verse>
    <verse num="2">A fool will not take pleasure in understanding, but in expressing his heart.<note>Or "mind"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">With the coming of wickedness comes contempt also, and with dishonor, disgrace.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Deep waters <transChange type="added">are</transChange> words of the mouth of a man; a gushing stream <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fountain of wisdom.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Being partial <transChange type="added">to</transChange> faces of evil <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not good, <transChange type="added">nor</transChange> to subvert the righteous at the judgment.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The lips of a fool will bring strife, and his mouth calls out for a flogging.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The mouth of a fool <transChange type="added">is</transChange> ruin to him, and his lips <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a snare to his soul.<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">The words of a whisper <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like delicious morsels, and they themselves go down <transChange type="added">to</transChange> inner parts of the body.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Even he who is slack in his work, he is brother to a master<note>Or "owner"</note> of destruction.</verse>
    <verse num="10">A tower of strength is the name of Yahweh; into him<note>Or "it"</note> the righteous will run and be safe.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The wealth of the rich <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {his strong city},<note>Literally "a city of his strength"</note> and like a wall, it is high in his imagination.</verse>
    <verse num="12">In the presence of destruction, the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a man will be haughty, but in the presence of honor, humble.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He who returns a word before he will hear, folly itself <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> to him as well as<note>Hebrew "and"</note> shame.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The spirit of a man will endure his sickness, but a broken spirit, who may bear it?</verse>
    <verse num="15">An intelligent {mind}<note>Literally "heart"</note> will acquire knowledge, and the ear of the wise will seek knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The gift of a person will open doors for him, and before the great, it gives him access.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The first in his dispute is <transChange type="added">deemed</transChange> righteous, <transChange type="added">but</transChange> his neighbor will come and examine him.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The lot will put an end to disputes, and between powerful contenders it will decide.</verse>
    <verse num="19">A brother who is offended <transChange type="added">is worse</transChange> than a city of strength, and quarrels <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like the bars of a fortification.</verse>
    <verse num="20">From the fruit of a man's mouth, his stomach will be satisfied, as for the yield of his lips, it will satisfy.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Death and life <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the {power}<note>Literally "hand"</note> of the tongue, and those who love her<note>That is, the power of the tongue</note> will eat of her fruit.</verse>
    <verse num="22">He who finds a wife<note>Or "woman"</note> finds good, and he will obtain favor from Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The poor may speak entreaties, but the rich will answer roughly.</verse>
    <verse num="24">A man of <transChange type="added">many</transChange> friends will come to ruin, but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">Better a poor person walking in integrity than one who is perverse {in his speech}<note>Literally "in his lips"</note> and is a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Also, a life<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> without knowledge is not good, and he who moves quickly with <transChange type="added">his</transChange> feet {misses the mark}.<note>Or "sins"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">As for the folly of humankind, its way leads to ruin, and against Yahweh his heart<note>Or "mind"</note> will rage.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Wealth adds many friends, but the poor will be left by his friends.</verse>
    <verse num="5">A witness of falsehood will not go unpunished, and he who breathes lies will not escape.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Many will seek favor before the generous, and everyone <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the friend of a man of gifts.<note>Hebrew "gift"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">All the brothers of the poor, <transChange type="added">if</transChange> they hate him, how much more will his friends keep away from him. He pursues <transChange type="added">them with</transChange> words, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> they are gone.<note>Or "<transChange type="added">when</transChange> he pursues words <transChange type="added">and</transChange> not them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">He who acquires wisdom loves himself;<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> he who guards understanding <transChange type="added">loves</transChange> to find good.</verse>
    <verse num="9">A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who breathes lies will perish.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For a fool living in luxury is not fitting, <transChange type="added">any</transChange> more <transChange type="added">than it is</transChange> for a slave to rule over princes.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The understanding of a person makes him slow to his {anger},<note>Literally "nostril"</note> and his glory overlooks offense.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The rage of a king growls like a lion, but his favor is like dew on the grass.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A foolish child is a ruin to his father, and the quarreling of a woman<note>Or "wife"</note> is a continuous dripping.</verse>
    <verse num="14">A house and wealth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an inheritance <transChange type="added">from</transChange> fathers, but from Yahweh <transChange type="added">comes</transChange> a woman<note>Or "wife"</note> who is prudent.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Laziness will bring on a deep sleep, and a person<note>Or "soul," or "life"</note> of idleness will suffer hunger.</verse>
    <verse num="16">He who guards commandments guards his life;<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> he who is careless of his ways will be killed.</verse>
    <verse num="17">He who lends to Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who is kind to the poor, and his benefits he will repay to him.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Discipline your child, for there is hope, but on his destruction do not set your desire.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">A hot-tempered person pays a penalty; if you rescue <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, you will do <transChange type="added">it</transChange> yet again.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Listen <transChange type="added">to</transChange> advice and accept instruction so that you will gain wisdom for your {future}.<note>Literally "after <transChange type="added">things</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">Many plans <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a man, but the purpose of Yahweh will be established.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The craving of a man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his steadfast loyalty, and <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> better <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> poor than a {liar}.<note>Literally "man of lying"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">Fear of Yahweh <transChange type="added">leads</transChange> to life; he who is filled <transChange type="added">with it</transChange> will rest--he will not suffer harm.</verse>
    <verse num="24">A lazy person buries his hand in the dish, and even to his mouth he will not bring it back.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The scoffer you shall strike, and the simple, may they learn prudence, and reprove the intelligent <transChange type="added">and</transChange> he will gain knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="26">He who does violence to a father, he who chases away a mother, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a child who causes shame and brings reproach.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Cease to listen to instruction, my child, {and you will stray}<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to stray"</note> from sayings of knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="28">A worthless witness will mock justice, and the mouth of the wicked will devour iniquity.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Judgments<note>Or "Punishments," or "Condemnations"</note> are prepared for the scoffers, and flogging for the back of fools.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">Wine <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a mocker, strong drink a brawler, and any who go astray by it are not wise.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Roaring like the lion <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> dreaded anger of a king; he who provokes him forfeits his life.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> honorable for the man to refrain from strife, but every fool will be quick to quarrel.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The lazy person will not plow in season; he will expect at the harvest, but there <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> nothing.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Deep waters <transChange type="added">are like</transChange> purpose in the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a man, and a man of understanding will draw it<note>Or "her"; referring to "purpose"</note> out.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Many a person will proclaim his loyalty <transChange type="added">for</transChange> himself, but a man <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> trustworthy, who can find?</verse>
    <verse num="7">He who walks in his integrity <transChange type="added">is</transChange> righteous; happy are his children who follow him.</verse>
    <verse num="8">A king who sits on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> throne of judgment winnows all evil with his eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Who will say "I have made my heart<note>Or "mind"</note> clean; I am pure from my sin"?</verse>
    <verse num="10">Stone and stone, measure and measure, {both of them}<note>Literally "also <transChange type="added">the</transChange> two of them"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an abomination of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Even by his acts, a {young man}<note>Or "young boy," or "adolescent"</note> will make himself known, whether his acts are pure and upright.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The ear that hears and the eye that sees, Yahweh has made {them both}.<note>Literally "also <transChange type="added">the</transChange> two of them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">Do not love sleep, lest you become poor; open your eyes <transChange type="added">and</transChange> have plenty bread.</verse>
    <verse num="14">"Bad, bad," the buyer will say, but <transChange type="added">when</transChange> one goes to him, then he will boast.</verse>
    <verse num="15">There is gold and many costly stones, but precious jewels are lips of knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Take his garment, for he has given security <transChange type="added">to</transChange> a stranger, and on behalf of a foreigner--take it as pledge.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Bread gained by deceit is sweet for the man, but afterward, his mouth will be filled <transChange type="added">with</transChange> gravel.</verse>
    <verse num="18">A plan<note>Hebrew "plans"</note> will be established by advice, and with guidance make war.</verse>
    <verse num="19">He reveals a secret, he who walks <transChange type="added">about with</transChange> gossip, and do not associate with a babbler's lips.</verse>
    <verse num="20">He who curses his father and his mother, his lamp will be extinguished {in the midst of darkness}.<note>Literally "in a pupil of darkness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">An inheritance acquired <transChange type="added">hastily</transChange> {at the beginning}<note>Literally "at the first"</note> will not be blessed at its end.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Do not say "I will repay evil"; wait for Yahweh and he will deliver you.</verse>
    <verse num="23">An abomination of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {a stone and a weight},<note>Literally "a stone and a stone"</note> and scales of falsehood are not good.</verse>
    <verse num="24"><transChange type="added">Away</transChange> from Yahweh are the steps of a strong man, and how will humankind understand his ways?</verse>
    <verse num="25"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> a snare to humankind to say rashly "<transChange type="added">It is</transChange> holy," and after vows, to scrutinize.</verse>
    <verse num="26">A wise king winnows the wicked, and he will drive a wheel over them.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The lamp of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the spirit<note>Or "soul"</note> of humankind, he who searches every {innermost part}.<note>Literally "parts of the inmost"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28">Loyalty and faithfulness will preserve a king, and he is upheld with the righteousness of his throne.</verse>
    <verse num="29">The glory of young men <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their strength,<note>Or "strengthens them"</note> but the beauty of the aged <transChange type="added">is</transChange> gray hair.</verse>
    <verse num="30">The blows of a wound will cleanse evil, as will<note>Hebrew "and"</note> beatings of the {innermost part}.<note>Literally "parts of the inmost"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">Streams of water <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a king in the hand of Yahweh; {wherever}<note>Literally "upon all that"</note> he will desire, he will turn.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Every way of a man is upright in his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> eyes, but Yahweh weighs hearts.<note>Or "minds"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Doing righteousness and justice is <transChange type="added">more</transChange> acceptable to Yahweh than sacrifice.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Haughtiness of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> eyes and pride of heart, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lamp of the wicked <transChange type="added">are</transChange> sin.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The plans of the diligent only <transChange type="added">lead</transChange> to abundance, but all who are hasty, only to want.</verse>
    <verse num="6">He who makes treasure by a lying tongue <transChange type="added">is a</transChange> fleeting vapor <transChange type="added">and</transChange> seeker<note>Hebrew "seekers"</note> of death.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The violence of the wicked will sweep them away, for they refuse to do justice.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Crooked is the way of a man and a foreigner, but the pure <transChange type="added">is</transChange> upright <transChange type="added">in</transChange> his conduct.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Better to dwell on the corner of a roof than <transChange type="added">to</transChange> share a house with a woman<note>Or "wife"</note> of contention.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The soul<note>Or "soul, life, throat"</note> of the wicked desires evil; his neighbor will not find mercy in his eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="11">With the punishment of a scoffer, the simple will become wise, and with the instruction of the wise, he will obtain knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The righteous observes the house of the wicked; he throws the wicked to ruin.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He who closes his ear from the cry of the poor, he also will cry out and not be heard.</verse>
    <verse num="14">A gift in secret<note>Hebrew "the secret"</note> will avert {anger},<note>Literally "nostril"</note> and a {concealed bribe},<note>Literally "bribe in the bosom"</note> strong wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> a joy to the righteous to do justice, but dismay to those who do evil.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Whoever wanders from the way of understanding, in the assembly of the dead<note>Or "Rephaim"</note> he will rest.</verse>
    <verse num="17">A man of want <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who loves pleasure; he who loves wine and oil<note>Or "fat"</note> will not become rich.</verse>
    <verse num="18">A ransom for the righteous is the wicked, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> faithless instead of the upright.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Better to live in a land of wilderness than <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a wife of quarrels and provocation.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Precious treasure and oil <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the house of the wise, but the foolish person<note>Or "foolish of mankind"</note> will devour them.<note>Literally "it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">He who pursues righteousness and kindness will find life, righteousness, and honor.</verse>
    <verse num="22">To a city of warriors, the wise ascends, and he will bring down the stronghold--its object of trust.</verse>
    <verse num="23">He who guards his mouth and his tongue, he guards his life<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> from danger.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The proud, haughty one: "scoffer" <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his name; he acts with arrogance of pride.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The craving of a lazy person will kill him, for his hands refuse to work.<note>Or "make"</note></verse>
    <verse num="26">{All day}<note>Literally "All the day"</note> he craves a craving, but the righteous will give and not hold back.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The sacrifice of the wicked <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an abomination; how much more when he brings it in divisiveness!</verse>
    <verse num="28">A false witness will perish, but a man who listens will testify with<note>Hebrew "to the"</note> success.</verse>
    <verse num="29">A wicked man is strong in {his countenance},<note>Literally "his face"</note> but the upright will appoint his paths.</verse>
    <verse num="30">There is no wisdom, nor understanding, nor counsel to oppose Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="31">A horse is prepared for the day of battle, but to Yahweh <transChange type="added">belongs</transChange> the victory.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">A {reputation}<note>Literally "name"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to be chosen {rather than}<note>Literally "from"</note> great riches; {favor is better than silver and gold}.<note>Literally "from silver and from gold, favor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> better"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Rich and poor have <transChange type="added">much</transChange> in common; Yahweh is the maker of all of them.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The clever sees danger and hides, but the simple go on and suffer.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The reward of humility <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the fear of Yahweh-- wealth and honor and life.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Thorns <transChange type="added">and</transChange> snares <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in the way of the perverse; he who guards himself<note>Or "soul," or "life"</note> will keep away from them.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Train the child {concerning his way};<note>Literally "on the mouth of his way"</note> even when he is old, he will not stray from it.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The rich will rule over the poor, and the borrower is a slave of {the lender}.<note>Literally "the borrower <transChange type="added">belonging</transChange> to a man"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">He who sows injustice will reap calamity, and the rod of his anger will fail.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He <transChange type="added">who</transChange> {is generous}<note>Literally "the generous of eye"</note> will be blessed, for he gives to the poor from his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> bread.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Drive out a scoffer and strife will go out; quarrel and abuse will cease.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He who loves purity of heart <transChange type="added">and has</transChange>{gracious speech},<note>Literally "grace of his lips"</note> his friend <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> king.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The eyes of Yahweh keep watch over knowledge, but he will overthrow the words of the faithless.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A lazy person says "A lion in the street! In the middle of the highway, I shall be killed!"</verse>
    <verse num="14">A deep pit is the mouth of an {adulteress},<note>Literally "a strange woman"</note> <transChange type="added">he with whom</transChange> Yahweh is angry will fall there.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Folly is bound up in the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of a boy;<note>Or "young man," or "adolescent"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rod of discipline will drive it<note>That is, folly</note> from him.</verse>
    <verse num="16">He who oppresses the poor <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to enrich himself, <transChange type="added">or</transChange> gives to the rich, {will come to poverty}.<note>Literally "only loss"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">Incline your ear and hear the words of the wise; you shall apply your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> to my teaching.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> pleasant if you guard them {within you};<note>Literally "in your belly/womb"</note> together they will be ready upon your lips.</verse>
    <verse num="19"><transChange type="added">In order</transChange> for your trust to be in Yahweh, I have made <transChange type="added">them</transChange> known to you {today}<note>Literally "the day"</note>--even<note>Or "only"</note> you.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Have I not written for you thirty <transChange type="added">sayings</transChange> with admonitions and knowledge?</verse>
    <verse num="21"><transChange type="added">In order</transChange> to show you what is right--sayings of truth-- <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to return a true saying to him who sent you.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Do not rob the poor because he is poor, and do not crush the afflicted at the gate;</verse>
    <verse num="23">For Yahweh will plead their case and despoil those who despoil them of life.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">Do not befriend an owner<note>Or "master"</note> of {anger},<note>Literally "nostril"</note> and with a man of wrath you shall not associate;</verse>
    <verse num="25">lest you learn his way and become entangled in a snare to yourself.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="26">Do not be with those who {give a pledge}<note>Literally "strike a hand"</note> {by becoming}<note>Literally "in the becomings of"</note> surety.</verse>
    <verse num="27">If there is nothing for you to pay,<note>Or "complete"</note> why will he take your bed from under you?</verse>
    <verse num="28">Do not remove an ancient boundary marker which your ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> made.</verse>
    <verse num="29">A man who is skillful in his work, you shall see: before kings, he will serve; he will not serve before the commoners.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">When you sit to eat with a ruler, you shall surely observe what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> before you,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and you shall put a knife to your throat if you have a {big appetite}.<note>Literally "lord/master of life"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">Do not desire his delicacies, for<note>Hebrew "and"</note> it is food of deception.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Do not tire <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to become rich; out of your understanding, <transChange type="added">may you</transChange> desist.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Your eyes will {alight}<note>Literally "cause to fly"</note> on it, but there is nothing <transChange type="added">to</transChange> it, for suddenly it will make for itself wings like an eagle and it will be exhausted <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the heavens.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Do not eat the bread of {the stingy},<note>Literally "stingy of eye"</note> and do not desire his delicacies.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For, like hair in his {throat},<note>Literally "soul," or "inner self"</note> so it is.<note>Or "is he"</note> "Eat and drink!" he will say to you, but his heart will not be with you.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Your morsel you have eaten, you will vomit it up, and you will waste your pleasant words.</verse>
    <verse num="9">In the ears of a fool do not speak, for he will despise the wisdom of your words.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Do not remove an ancient boundary marker, and on the fields of orphans do not encroach;</verse>
    <verse num="11">For their redeemer is strong, he himself will plead their cause against you.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Apply your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> to instruction, and your ear to sayings of knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Do not withhold discipline from a child, if you will beat him with the rod, he will not die.</verse>
    <verse num="14">As for you, with the rod you shall beat him, and his life<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> you will save from Sheol.<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">My child, if your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> is wise, my heart will be glad--even me!</verse>
    <verse num="16">And my {insides}<note>Literally "kidneys"</note> will rejoice when your lips speak what is upright.</verse>
    <verse num="17">May your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> not envy the sinners, but <transChange type="added">live</transChange> in fear of Yahweh {all day}.<note>Literally "all the day"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">{Surely}<note>Literally "For if"</note> there is a future, and your hope will not be cut off.</verse>
    <verse num="19">You, my child, hear and be wise, and direct your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> on the road.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Do not be among drinkers of wine, among gluttonous eaters of {their meat}.<note>Literally "meat for them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">For the drunkard and gluttonous, they will become poor, and <transChange type="added">with</transChange> rags, drowsiness will clothe them.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Listen to your father--he who {gave you life},<note>Literally "caused you to be born"</note> and do not despise your mother when<note>Or "for, because"</note> she is old.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Buy truth and do not sell <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, wisdom and instruction and understanding.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The father of the righteous will surely rejoice; he who bears a wise person will be happy with him.</verse>
    <verse num="25">May your father and your mother be glad, and may she who bore you rejoice.</verse>
    <verse num="26">My child, may you give your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> to me, and may your eyes delight in my ways.</verse>
    <verse num="27">For a deep pit is a prostitute,<note>Or "whore"</note> and a narrow well is {an adulteress}.<note>Literally "a foreign woman"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28">She <transChange type="added">is</transChange> also like a robber lying in wait, and the faithless among mankind she increases.</verse>
    <verse num="29">To whom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> woe? To whom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sorrow? To whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> quarrels? To whom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> complaint? To whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> wounds without cause? To whom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> redness of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> eyes?</verse>
    <verse num="30">To those who linger over wine, to those who come to try mixed wine.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Do not look at wine when it is red, when it {sparkles}<note>Literally "gives its eye"</note> on the cup, going down smoothly.</verse>
    <verse num="32">{In the end},<note>Literally "end him"</note> it will bite like a serpent, and it will sting like an adder.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Your eyes will see strange things, and your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> will speak perverse things.</verse>
    <verse num="34">And you will be like him who lies down in the heart of the sea, and like him who lies down on top of a mast.</verse>
    <verse num="35">"They struck me; I was not hurt. They beat me; I did not know <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. When I will awake, I will continue; I will seek it again."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">Do not envy men of evil, and do not desire to be with them.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For their minds will devise violence, and their lips will speak mischief.</verse>
    <verse num="3">By wisdom a house is built, and by understanding it is established.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And by knowledge, rooms are filled <transChange type="added">with</transChange> all riches, precious and pleasant.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The warrior of wisdom <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in strength, and a man of knowledge is strong <transChange type="added">in</transChange> power.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For with wise guidance you shall make war for yourself, and victory <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in an abundance of counsel.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Wisdom <transChange type="added">is too</transChange> high for fools; at the gate he will not open his mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="8">He who plans to do evil for<note>Or "to"</note> himself, they will call <transChange type="added">him</transChange> "master<note>Or "owner"</note> of mischief."</verse>
    <verse num="9">Devising folly <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a sin, and an abomination to humankind <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a scoffer.</verse>
    <verse num="10"><transChange type="added">If</transChange> you faint on the day of adversity, little <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your strength.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Rescue those who are led away to the death and those who stagger to the slaughter. If you hold back,</verse>
    <verse num="12">if you say, "Look, we do not know this," does not he who weighs hearts perceive <transChange type="added">it</transChange>? And he who keeps your soul,<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note> he knows and will repay humankind according to his deeds.</verse>
    <verse num="13">My child, eat honey, for <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> good, and the dripping of the honeycomb <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sweet to your taste.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Thus know wisdom for <transChange type="added">the sake of</transChange> your soul,<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note> if you find <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, then there is a future, and your hope will not be cut off.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Do not lie in wait <transChange type="added">like</transChange> an outlaw against the home of the righteous; do not do violence <transChange type="added">to</transChange> his dwelling place.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For seven <transChange type="added">times</transChange> the righteous will fall, but he will rise, but the wicked will be overthrown by calamity.</verse>
    <verse num="17">While your enemies are falling, do not rejoice; when he trips himself, may your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> not be glad</verse>
    <verse num="18">lest Yahweh see and <transChange type="added">it</transChange> be evil in his eyes, and turn his anger away from him.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Do not fret because of the evildoers; do not envy the wicked.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For there will not be a future for the evil; the lamp of the wicked will die out.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Fear Yahweh, my son, and the king; with those who change, do not associate.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For suddenly their disaster will come, and the ruin of {both of them},<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">the</transChange> two of them"</note> who knows?</verse>
    <verse num="23">These <transChange type="added">sayings</transChange> are also for the wise: {Partiality}<note>Literally "acknowledge faces"</note> in judgment is not good.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Whoever says to the guilty, "You are righteous," the people will curse him; the nations will abhor him.</verse>
    <verse num="25">But they who rebuke will have delight, and upon them blessings of goodness will come.</verse>
    <verse num="26">He will kiss <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lips, he who gives an honest answer.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Prepare your work in the street and get it ready for yourself in the field; afterward, then<note>Hebrew "and"</note> you shall build your house.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Do not be a witness without cause against your neighbor nor deceive with your lips.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Do not say, "Just as he has done to me, so shall I do to him; I will pay back the man according to his deed."</verse>
    <verse num="30">I passed by the field of a lazy person, and over the vineyard of a person lacking {sense};<note>Literally "heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">and behold, it was overgrown--all of it was covered <transChange type="added">with</transChange> thorns, its surface with nettles, and {its stone wall}<note>Literally "a wall of his/its stones"</note> was broken down.</verse>
    <verse num="32">Then I myself saw and my heart<note>Or "mind"</note> considered; I looked, and I took hold of instruction:</verse>
    <verse num="33">A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands for rest,</verse>
    <verse num="34">and your poverty will come running, and your lack like an armed warrior.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">These are also proverbs of Solomon which officials of Hezekiah king of Judah copied:</verse>
    <verse num="2">The glory of God<note>Or "gods"</note> conceals things, but the glory of kings searches out things.</verse>
    <verse num="3">As heaven is to height and the earth is to depth, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the heart<note>Or "mind"</note> of kings--there is no searching.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Remove the dross from silver, and it will become a vessel for the smith.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Remove the wicked before a king, and his throne will be established in righteousness.<note>Hebrew "in the righteousness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Do not promote yourself before the king, and in the place of the great ones do not stand.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> better <transChange type="added">that</transChange> he say to you, "Ascend here," than he humble you before a noble. What your eyes have seen,</verse>
    <verse num="8">do not hastily bring out to court, for<note>Or "lest"</note> what will you do at its end, when your neighbor puts you to shame?</verse>
    <verse num="9">Argue your argument with your neighbor <transChange type="added">himself</transChange>, the secret of another do not disclose,</verse>
    <verse num="10">lest he who hears shame you and your ill repute will not end.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Apples of gold in a setting of silver is a matter spoken at<note>Hebrew "on"</note> its proper time.</verse>
    <verse num="12">A ring of gold and an ornament of fine gold <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a rebuke of the wise to the ear of a listener.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Like the cold of snow on a day<note>Or "at a season"</note> of harvest <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a faithful messenger to those who send him, and the soul<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note> of his master is refreshed.<note>Or "returned"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> clouds and wind when there is no rain, <transChange type="added">so too is</transChange> a man who boasts in a gift of deception.</verse>
    <verse num="15">{With patience}<note>Literally "With length of face"</note> a ruler may be persuaded, and a soft tongue will break a bone.<note>Or "strength"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">If</transChange> you find honey, eat what is sufficient for you, lest you have your fill of it and vomit it out.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Make your foot scarce in the house of your neighbor, lest he become weary of you and hate you.</verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> a club and sword and a sharp arrow <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a man who bears false witness against his neighbor.</verse>
    <verse num="19">A bad tooth and a lame foot <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the trust of a faithless person {in a time}<note>Literally "on a day"</note> of trouble.</verse>
    <verse num="20"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> one who removes a garment on a cold day, <transChange type="added">or like</transChange> vinegar on natron,<note>A mineral salt found on dry lake beds often used as a preservative.</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who sings songs to a heavy heart.</verse>
    <verse num="21">If your enemy <transChange type="added">is</transChange> hungry, feed him bread, and if thirsty, let him drink water.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For coals of fire you will heap upon his head, and Yahweh will reward you.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The wind of the north produces rain, and a backbiting tongue, angry faces.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Better to live upon the corner of a roof than <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a woman<note>Or "wife"</note> of contention and <transChange type="added">in a</transChange> shared house.</verse>
    <verse num="25"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> cold water<note>Hebrew "waters"</note> upon a weary soul,<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note> <transChange type="added">so too is</transChange> good news from a distant place.</verse>
    <verse num="26"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> a muddied spring or a polluted fountain is the righteous who gives way before the wicked.</verse>
    <verse num="27">To eat much honey is not good, nor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> seeking one's honor<note>Hebrew "their honor"</note> honorable.</verse>
    <verse num="28">A breached city <transChange type="added">where</transChange> there is no wall <transChange type="added">is like</transChange> a man who {has no}<note>Literally "there is no"</note> self-control for his spirit.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">Like snow in the summer and like rain at the harvest, so honor is not fitting for a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Like the sparrow <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to fluttering and like the swallow <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to flying, so an undeserved curse does not go forth.</verse>
    <verse num="3">A whip for the horse, a bridle for the donkey, and a rod for the back of fools.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Do not answer a fool according to his folly lest you become like him--even you.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Answer a fool according to his folly, or else he will be wise in his own eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> cutting off feet <transChange type="added">or</transChange> drinking violence, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who sends messages in the hand of a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="7"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> legs that hang limp from a lame person, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a proverb in the mouth of fools.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Like binding a stone in a sling, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> giving honor to a fool.</verse>
    <verse num="9"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> a thorn that goes up in the hand of a drunkard, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a proverb in the mouth of fools.</verse>
    <verse num="10"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> an archer who wounds everyone, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> he who hires a fool or he who hires passersby.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Like a dog returning to his vomit <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a fool reverting to his folly.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">Do</transChange> you see a man wise in his own eyes? <transChange type="added">There is more</transChange> hope for a fool than for him.</verse>
    <verse num="13">A lazy person says "A lion <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in the road! A lion among the streets!"</verse>
    <verse num="14">The door turns on its hinge, and a lazy person on his bed.</verse>
    <verse num="15">A lazy person buries his hands in the dish; he is <transChange type="added">too</transChange> tired to return it to his mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="16">A lazy person is wiser in his eyes than seven who answer discreetly.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Grabbing onto the ears of a dog passing by <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one who meddles in a quarrel <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> not his own.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Like a maniac who shoots firebrands, arrows, and death,</verse>
    <verse num="19">so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a man who deceives his neighbor, but says "Am I not joking?"</verse>
    <verse num="20">For lack of wood, a fire goes out, and where there is no whisperer, quarreling will cease.</verse>
    <verse num="21"><transChange type="added">As</transChange> charcoal <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to hot embers and wood <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to fire, so a man of quarrels <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to kindling strife.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The words of a whisperer <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like delicious morsels, and they go down to the inner parts of the body.</verse>
    <verse num="23"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> {impure silver}<note>Literally "silver of impurities"</note> which overlays an earthen vessel, <transChange type="added">so are</transChange> smooth lips and an evil heart<note>Or "mind"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="24">On his lips, an enemy will pretend, but {inside}<note>Literally "in his midst"</note> he will harbor deceit.</verse>
    <verse num="25">When he makes his voice gracious, do not believe him, for seven abominations <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in his heart.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Though hatred is covered with guile, its evil will be exposed in the assembly.</verse>
    <verse num="27">He who digs a pit, in it he will fall, and he who rolls a stone, on him it will come back.</verse>
    <verse num="28">A tongue of deceit hates its victim, and a flattering mouth makes ruin.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">Do not boast {about tomorrow},<note>Literally "on the day of tomorrow"</note> for you do not know what the day will bring.</verse>
    <verse num="2">May another praise you and not your own mouth, a stranger and not your own lips.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Heavy <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a stone and weighty <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sand, but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> provocation of a fool <transChange type="added">is</transChange> heavier than both of them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Cruel <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wrath and overwhelming <transChange type="added">is</transChange> anger, but who will stand before jealousy?</verse>
    <verse num="5">Better a rebuke that is open than a love that is hidden.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The wounds of a friend mean well, but the kisses of an enemy are profane.</verse>
    <verse num="7">An {appetite}<note>Literally "soul"</note> that is sated spurns honey, but <transChange type="added">to</transChange> an {appetite}<note>Literally "soul"</note> that is ravenous, all bitterness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sweet.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Like a bird that strays from its nest, so is a man who strays from his place.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Perfume and incense will gladden a heart, and the pleasantness of one's friend <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {personal advice}.<note>Literally "because of advice of a person"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">As for your friend and a friend of your father, do not forsake <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, and the house of your brother, do not enter on the day of your calamity. Better is a close neighbor than a distant brother.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Be wise, my child, and make my heart glad, and I will answer him who reproaches me <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a word.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">When</transChange> the clever sees danger, he hides; the simple go on <transChange type="added">and</transChange> suffer.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Take his garment, for he gives surety <transChange type="added">to</transChange> a stranger, and to {an adulteress}<note>Literally "a foreign woman"</note>--<transChange type="added">so</transChange> take his pledge.</verse>
    <verse num="14">He who blesses his neighbor with a loud voice early in the morning, a curse will be reckoned to him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Dripping constantly on a day of heavy rain and a woman<note>Or "wife"</note> of contention are alike.</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">In</transChange> restraining her, he restrains wind,<note>Or "breath, or "spirit"</note> and his right hand will grasp oil<note>Or "fat"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="17"><transChange type="added">As</transChange> iron sharpens<note>Or "is united with"</note> iron, so {one man sharpens another}.<note>Literally "a man sharpens <transChange type="added">the</transChange> faces of his friend"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">He who tends a fig tree will eat its fruit, and he who guards his master<note>Or "lord"</note> will be honored.</verse>
    <verse num="19">As the waters <transChange type="added">reflect</transChange> {face to face},<note>Literally "the faces to the faces"</note> so the heart of a person <transChange type="added">reflects</transChange> the person.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Sheol<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> and Abaddon<note>Poetic synonym for "Sheol." Only mentioned in the ot in relation to Sheol, the grave, or death.</note> will not be satisfied, and the eyes of a person will not be satisfied <transChange type="added">either</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="21">A crucible <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for the silver, and a furnace for the gold, but a man <transChange type="added">is tested by</transChange> the mouth of him who praises him.</verse>
    <verse num="22">If you crush a fool in the mortar with the pestle {along with}<note>Or "in the midst of"</note> the crushed grain, it will not drive folly from upon him.</verse>
    <verse num="23">You will surely know the {condition}<note>Literally "faces"</note> of your flock; your heart<note>Or "mind"</note> attends to the herds.</verse>
    <verse num="24">For riches <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not forever, nor a crown for generation <transChange type="added">after</transChange> generation.</verse>
    <verse num="25">When the grass is gone, then green growth will appear, and the herbs of the mountains will be gathered.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Lambs <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> your clothing, and goats the price of the field.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And <transChange type="added">there will be</transChange> enough goats' milk for your food, for <transChange type="added">the</transChange> food of your household and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> {nourishment}<note>Literally "life"</note> of your maidservants.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">The wicked flee, but no one pursues, but the righteous is bold like a lion.</verse>
    <verse num="2">By the rebellion of a land, her rulers increase, but by a person of intelligence who knows justice, it will last.</verse>
    <verse num="3">A man <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> poor and oppresses the impoverished <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a beating rain {that leaves}<note>Literally "and there is"</note> no food.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Those who forsake instruction will praise the wicked, but they who guard instruction will struggle against them.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Men of evil do not understand justice, but seekers of Yahweh understand completely.<note>Or "everything"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Better <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> poor and walking in one's integrity than to be crooked of ways when one <transChange type="added">is</transChange> rich.</verse>
    <verse num="7">He who keeps instruction <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a child of understanding, but the companion of gluttons will shame his father.</verse>
    <verse num="8">He who augments his wealth with interest and with usury gathers it for him who is kind to the poor.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He who turns his ear from listening to instruction, even his prayer <transChange type="added">is</transChange> an abomination.</verse>
    <verse num="10">He who misleads the upright onto the way of evil, into his pits he will fall. But as for the blameless, they will inherit good.</verse>
    <verse num="11">A man of wealth <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wise in his own eyes, but the intelligent poor sees through him.</verse>
    <verse num="12">When the righteous triumphs, great <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the glory, but with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rising of the wicked, a person will be hidden.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He who conceals his transgression will not prosper, but he who confesses and forsakes will obtain mercy.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Happy is the person who fears continuously, but he who is stubborn of heart,<note>Or "mind"</note> will fall into calamity.</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">Like</transChange> a roaring lion and a charging bear <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a wicked ruler over a poor people.</verse>
    <verse num="16">A ruler who lacks understanding is<note>Hebrew "and"</note> a cruel oppressor, <transChange type="added">but</transChange> those who hate unjust gain will have long<note>Or "prolong"</note> days.</verse>
    <verse num="17">A person who is burdened with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> blood of {another},<note>Literally "life"</note> until death he will flee; do not take hold of him.</verse>
    <verse num="18">He who walks in integrity will be safe, but he who takes crooked paths will fall in one.</verse>
    <verse num="19">He who tills his ground will have plenty bread, but he who follows fantasies will have plenty <transChange type="added">of</transChange> poverty.</verse>
    <verse num="20">A man of faithfulness <transChange type="added">has</transChange> abundant blessings, but he who hurries to become rich will not go unpunished.</verse>
    <verse num="21">{Showing partiality}<note>Literally "Recognizing faces"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not good, and over a morsel of bread, a strong man will do wrong.</verse>
    <verse num="22">He who hurries for wealth is {a man with an evil eye},<note>Literally "a man of evil of eye"</note> but he does not know that poverty will come upon him.</verse>
    <verse num="23">He who rebukes a person will afterward find <transChange type="added">more</transChange> favor than he who flatters <transChange type="added">with the</transChange> tongue.</verse>
    <verse num="24">He who robs his father and his mother and says, "There is no crime," is partner to a man who corrupts.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The {greedy person}<note>Literally "wide soul"</note> will stir up strife, but he who trusts in Yahweh will be enriched.</verse>
    <verse num="26">He who trusts in his own heart<note>Or "mind," or "sense"</note> is a fool, but he who walks in wisdom will be saved.</verse>
    <verse num="27"><transChange type="added">For</transChange> he who gives to the poor, there is no lacking, but <transChange type="added">for</transChange> he<note>Hebrew "those"</note> who turns his eyes, <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> many curses.</verse>
    <verse num="28">With <transChange type="added">the</transChange> rising of the wicked, humankind will be hidden, and with their perishing, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> righteous will multiply.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">A man who is reproved, being stubborn of neck-- suddenly he will be broken, and there will not be healing.</verse>
    <verse num="2">When the righteous are numerous, the people will rejoice, but when the wicked are ruling, people will groan.</verse>
    <verse num="3">A man who loves wisdom will make his parents glad, but the friend of prostitutes<note>Or "whores"</note> will squander his wealth.</verse>
    <verse num="4">By justice a king gives stability <transChange type="added">to</transChange> a land, but a man of bribes will ruin it.</verse>
    <verse num="5">A strong man who flatters his neighbor is spreading a net for his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="6">In transgression, an evil man <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a snare, but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> righteous will sing and rejoice.<note>Hebrew "he will rejoice"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> righteous knows <transChange type="added">the</transChange> case of the poor, but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wicked does not understand knowledge.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Men of scoffing set a city aflame, but the wise turn away wrath.</verse>
    <verse num="9"><transChange type="added">If</transChange> a wise man goes to court with a foolish man, then there is rankling and ridicule,<note>Hebrew "there is ridicule"</note> but there is no relief.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Men of blood hate <transChange type="added">the</transChange> blameless, and they seek the life of the upright.<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">A fool gives all his breath,<note>Or "spirit"</note> but <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wise holds back in quiet.</verse>
    <verse num="12">A ruler listening to a word of falsehood, all his officials are wicked.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The poor and a man of oppression have <transChange type="added">this</transChange> in common: Yahweh gives {light to the eyes of them both}.<note>Literally "light of the eyes of the two of them"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">A king who judges with truthfulness <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the poor, his throne will be established forever.</verse>
    <verse num="15">As for a rod and reproof, they<note>Hebrew "it"</note> will give wisdom, but a neglected child is disgraced <transChange type="added">by</transChange> his mother.</verse>
    <verse num="16">With the increase of the wicked, transgression will increase, but the righteous will look on his downfall.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Discipline your children, and they will give you rest, and they will give delight to your soul.<note>Or "life," or "inner self"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">When there is no prophecy, the people cast off restraint, but as for he who guards instruction, happiness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his.</verse>
    <verse num="19">By words, a servant is not disciplined, for he will understand, but there is no giving heed.</verse>
    <verse num="20">You see a man who is hasty in his words: <transChange type="added">there is more</transChange> hope for a fool than him.</verse>
    <verse num="21">He who pampers his servant from childhood, {arrogance will be his end}.<note>Literally "and its/his end will be arrogance"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">A man of anger will stir strife, and the owner of anger, much transgression.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The pride of a person will bring him humiliation, and the lowly of spirit will obtain honor.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Being a partner with a thief is hating one's life;<note>Or "soul," or "inner self"</note> a curse he will hear, but not disclose.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The fear of a person will lay a snare, but he who trusts in Yahweh will be secure.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Many are those who seek the {favor}<note>Literally "faces"</note> of a ruler, but from Yahweh {one obtains justice}.<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">comes</transChange> justice for a man"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">A man of injustice is an abomination to the righteous, but the {upright}<note>Literally "upright of way"</note> is an abomination to the wicked.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">The words of Agur, son of Yakeh, the oracle. Thus says the man to Ithiel, to Ithiel, and Ucal:<note>Or "I am weary, O God; I am weary, O God, and worn out"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">Certainly I <transChange type="added">am more</transChange> stupid than a man, and the understanding of humankind <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not for me.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And I have not learned wisdom, nor will I know knowledge of the Holy One.<note>Or "holy ones"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">Who has ascended <transChange type="added">to</transChange> heaven and come down? Who has gathered <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wind in the hollow of his hand? Who has wrapped water in a<note>Hebrew "the"</note> garment? Who has established all the ends of the earth? What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> his name and what is the name of his child? For <transChange type="added">surely</transChange> you know.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Every word of God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> flawless; he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a shield for him who takes refuge in him.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Do not add to his words lest he rebuke you and you be found a liar.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Two things I ask from you; do not deny me before I die:</verse>
    <verse num="8">Keep falsehood and a {lying word}<note>Literally "word of a lie"</note> far from me; do not give me poverty or wealth; provide me <transChange type="added">with</transChange> food <transChange type="added">only for</transChange> my need.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Or else I will be satisfied and will deny <transChange type="added">him</transChange> and say "Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Yahweh?" Or<note>Or "Lest"</note> I will be poor and will steal and profane the name of my God.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Do not slander a servant to his master, or else he will curse you and you will be guilty.</verse>
    <verse num="11"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> a generation <transChange type="added">that</transChange> will curse its father, and its mother it will not bless.</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> a generation <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> pure in its own eyes, but from its filthiness it will not be cleansed.</verse>
    <verse num="13"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> a generation--how lofty <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their eyes! And their eyelids they will lift.</verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">There is</transChange> a generation whose teeth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> swords, and its jawbones, knives, <transChange type="added">in order</transChange> to devour the poor from the earth<note>Or "land"</note> and the needy from humankind.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For the leech, <transChange type="added">there are</transChange> two daughters; "Give, give!" <transChange type="added">they cry</transChange>. As for three of these, they are not satisfied; as for four, they do not say enough.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Sheol<note>A term for the place where the dead reside, i.e., the Underworld</note> and barrenness of womb, the land is not satisfied <transChange type="added">with</transChange> water, and fire does not say "enough!"</verse>
    <verse num="17">The eye <transChange type="added">that</transChange> mocks a father and scorns the obedience of a mother-- the ravens of the valley will peck it out, and the offspring of vultures will eat it.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Three of these are <transChange type="added">too</transChange> wonderful for me, and four, I do not understand them:</verse>
    <verse num="19">the way of the eagle in the sky, the way of a snake on a rock, the way of a ship in the heart of the sea, and the way of a man with a young woman.</verse>
    <verse num="20">This is the way of a woman committing adultery: she eats and wipes her mouth, and says "I have not done wrong."</verse>
    <verse num="21">Under three <transChange type="added">things</transChange> the earth<note>Or "land"</note> trembles, and under four, it is not able to bear up:</verse>
    <verse num="22">under a slave when he becomes king, and a fool when he is satisfied <transChange type="added">with</transChange> food;</verse>
    <verse num="23">under an unloved woman when she gets married, and a maid when she succeeds her mistress.</verse>
    <verse num="24">There <transChange type="added">are</transChange> four small things on the earth, and they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {exceedingly wise}:<note>Literally "wise <transChange type="added">ones</transChange> from wise <transChange type="added">ones</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">The ants <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a people <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> not strong, yet they prepare their food in the summer;</verse>
    <verse num="26">the badgers <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a people <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> not mighty, yet they set their house on the rock;</verse>
    <verse num="27">there is no king for the locust, yet it marches in rank;</verse>
    <verse num="28">a lizard you <transChange type="added">can</transChange> seize with hands, yet it is in palaces of kings.</verse>
    <verse num="29">There <transChange type="added">are</transChange> three <transChange type="added">things</transChange> that are magnificent of stride, and four that are magnificent <transChange type="added">when</transChange> moving:</verse>
    <verse num="30">a mighty lion among the beasts,<note>Hebrew "beasts"</note> but he will not turn back from {any face};<note>Literally "faces of all"</note></verse>
    <verse num="31">a strutting rooster or he-goat, and a king <transChange type="added">whose</transChange> army <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with him.</verse>
    <verse num="32">If you have been foolish by exalting yourself, and if you have devised evil, <transChange type="added">put your</transChange> hand to <transChange type="added">your</transChange> mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="33">For pressing milk produces curd, and pressing the nose produces blood, so pressing {anger}<note>Literally "nostrils"</note> produces strife.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">The words of Lemuel, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> king--an oracle that his mother taught him:</verse>
    <verse num="2">What, my son? And what, my son in my womb? And what, son of my vows?</verse>
    <verse num="3">Do not give your strength to the women, and your ways to destroy kings.</verse>
    <verse num="4"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> not for the kings, O Lemuel; drinking wine <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not for the kings, nor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> strong drink for rulers.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Or else he will drink and forget what has been decreed, and he will pervert the rights<note>Hebrew "right"</note> of all the {afflicted}.<note>Literally "sons of affliction"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Give strong drink to him who is perishing, and wine to those {in bitter distress}.<note>Literally "to bitterness of soul"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">He will drink and forget his poverty, and his misery he will not remember <transChange type="added">any</transChange> more.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Open your mouth for the mute, for the rights<note>Hebrew "right"</note> of all the {needy}.<note>Literally "the sons of the needy"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Open your mouth, judge righteousness, and defend <transChange type="added">the</transChange> poor and needy.</verse>
    <verse num="10">A woman<note>Or "wife"</note> of excellence,<note>Or "strength," or "valor," or "ability," or "efficiency"</note> who will find? For her worth <transChange type="added">is</transChange> far more than precious jewels.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The heart of her husband<note>Or "lord"</note> trusts in her, and gain he will not lack.</verse>
    <verse num="12">She does him good, but not harm all the days of her life.</verse>
    <verse num="13">She seeks wool and flax, and she works with the diligence of {her hands}.<note>Literally "her palms"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">She is like the ships of a merchant; from far off she brings her food;<note>Or "bread"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">And she arises while <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> still night, and gives food to her household, and tasks to her servant girls.</verse>
    <verse num="16">She considers a field and buys it, from the fruit of {her hand}<note>Literally "her palm"</note> she plants a vineyard.</verse>
    <verse num="17">She girds her waist in strength, and makes her arms strong.</verse>
    <verse num="18">She perceives that her merchandise <transChange type="added">is</transChange> good; her lamp does not go out in the night.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Her hands she puts onto the distaff,<note>A stick or spindle onto which wool or flax is wound in preparation for spinning</note> and her palms hold a spindle.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Her palm she opens to the poor, and her hand she reaches <transChange type="added">out</transChange> to the needy.</verse>
    <verse num="21">She does not fear for her house <transChange type="added">when</transChange> it snows, for {her entire household}<note>Literally "all her house, household"</note> is clothed <transChange type="added">in</transChange> crimson.</verse>
    <verse num="22">She makes for herself coverings; her clothing <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fine linen and purple.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Her husband<note>Or "lord"</note> is known at the gates, in his seat among the elders of the land.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Linen garments she makes and sells, and she supplies sashes for the merchants.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Strength and dignity are her clothing, and she laughs {at the future}.<note>Literally "to the day/time coming after"</note></verse>
    <verse num="26">She opens her mouth with wisdom, and instruction of kindness <transChange type="added">is</transChange> upon her tongue.</verse>
    <verse num="27">She looks after the ways of her household, and the bread of idleness she will not eat.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Her children rise and consider her happy, her husband<note>Or "lord"</note> <transChange type="added">also</transChange>, and he praises her;</verse>
    <verse num="29">"Many daughters have done excellence,<note>Or "strength," or "valor," or "ability," or "efficiency"</note> but {you surpass}<note>Literally "you ascend over"</note> all of them."</verse>
    <verse num="30">Charm<note>Hebrew "The charm"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> deceit and beauty<note>Hebrew "the beauty"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> vain;<note>Or "vapor," or "emptiness," or "breath"</note> <transChange type="added">but</transChange> a woman who fears Yahweh shall be praised.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Give to her from the fruit of her hand, and may they praise her works in the city gates.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>