<book num="Titus">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul, a slave of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ for the faith of the chosen of God and the knowledge of the truth that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> according to godliness,</verse>
    <verse num="2">in the hope of eternal life which God, who does not lie, promised before eternal ages,</verse>
    <verse num="3">but at the proper time has disclosed his message in the proclamation <transChange type="added">with</transChange> which I was entrusted according to the command of God our Savior,</verse>
    <verse num="4">to Titus, <transChange type="added">my</transChange> true child according to a common faith. Grace and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior. </verse>
    <verse num="5">On account of this, I left you behind in Crete, in order that what remains may be set in order and you may appoint elders in every town, as I ordered you.</verse>
    <verse num="6">If anyone is blameless, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> husband of one wife, having faithful<note>Or "believing"</note> children, not {accused of dissipation}<note>Literally "with an accusation of dissipation"</note> or rebellious.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For it is necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the overseer to be blameless as God's steward, not self-willed, not quick-tempered, not addicted to wine, not violent, not greedy for dishonest gain,</verse>
    <verse num="8">but hospitable, loving what is good, prudent, just, devout, self-controlled,</verse>
    <verse num="9">holding fast to the faithful message according to the teaching, in order that he may be able both to exhort with sound instruction and to reprove those who speak against <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="10">For there are many rebellious <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, idle talkers and deceivers, especially those of the circumcision,</verse>
    <verse num="11">whom it is necessary to silence, whoever are ruining whole families <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("teaching") which is understood as means</note> teaching <transChange type="added">things</transChange> which must not be <transChange type="added">taught</transChange> for the sake of dishonest gain.</verse>
    <verse num="12">A certain one of them, <transChange type="added">one of</transChange> their own prophets, has said, "Cretans <transChange type="added">are</transChange> always liars, evil beasts, lazy gluttons."</verse>
    <verse num="13">This testimony is true, for which reason reprove them severely, in order that they may be sound in the faith,</verse>
    <verse num="14">not paying attention to Jewish myths and commandments of people who turn away from the truth.</verse>
    <verse num="15">To the pure all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> pure, but to those who are defiled and unbelieving nothing <transChange type="added">is</transChange> pure, but both their mind and conscience are defiled.</verse>
    <verse num="16">They profess to know God, but by their deeds they deny <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as causal</note> are detestable and disobedient, and unfit for every good deed. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">But you, speak <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which are fitting for sound instruction.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Older men are to be temperate, worthy of respect, self-controlled, sound in faith, in love, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> in endurance.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Older women likewise <transChange type="added">are to be</transChange> reverent in <transChange type="added">their</transChange> behavior, not slanderous, not enslaved to much wine, teaching what is good,</verse>
    <verse num="4">in order that they may encourage the young women to love their husbands <transChange type="added">and to</transChange> love their children,</verse>
    <verse num="5"><transChange type="added">to be</transChange> self-controlled, pure, busy at home, good, being subject to their own husbands, in order that the word of God may not be slandered.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Likewise, exhort the young men to be self-controlled,</verse>
    <verse num="7">concerning everything showing yourself <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> an example of good deeds, in your teaching <transChange type="added">demonstrating</transChange> soundness, dignity,</verse>
    <verse num="8"><transChange type="added">a</transChange> sound message beyond reproach, in order that {an opponent}<note>Literally "one from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> opposed"</note> may be put to shame, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("has") which is understood as causal</note> has nothing bad to say concerning us. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Slaves must be subject to their own masters in everything, to be well-pleasing, not to talk back,</verse>
    <verse num="10">not stealing, but demonstrating all good faith, in order that they may do credit to the teaching of God our Savior in everything.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For the grace of God has appeared, bringing salvation to all people,</verse>
    <verse num="12">training us in order that, denying impiety and worldly desires, we may live self-controlled and righteously and godly in the present age,</verse>
    <verse num="13">looking forward to the blessed hope and the glorious appearing of our great God and Savior Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="14">who gave himself for us, in order that he might redeem us from all lawlessness and purify for himself a people for his own possession, zealous for good deeds.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Speak these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> and exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no one disregard you. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Remind them to be subject to the rulers <transChange type="added">and</transChange> to the authorities, to obey, to be prepared for every good work,</verse>
    <verse num="2">to speak evil of no one, to be peaceable, gentle, showing all courtesy to all people.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For we also were once foolish, disobedient, led astray, enslaved to various desires and pleasures, spending our lives in wickedness and envy, despicable, hating one another.</verse>
    <verse num="4">But when the kindness and love for mankind of God our Savior appeared,</verse>
    <verse num="5">he saved us, not by deeds of righteousness that we have done, but because of his mercy, through the washing of regeneration and renewal by the Holy Spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="6">whom he poured out on us abundantly through Jesus Christ our Savior,</verse>
    <verse num="7">so that, having been justified by his grace, we may become heirs according to the hope of eternal life. </verse>
    <verse num="8">The saying <transChange type="added">is</transChange> trustworthy, and I want you to insist concerning these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, so that those who have believed in God may be careful to engage in good deeds. These things are good and beneficial for people.</verse>
    <verse num="9">But avoid foolish controversies and genealogies and contentions and quarrels about the law, for they are useless and fruitless.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Reject a divisive person after a first and second admonition,</verse>
    <verse num="11">knowing that such a person is perverted and is sinning, being self-condemned. </verse>
    <verse num="12">When I send Artemas or Tychicus to you, make haste to come to me in Nicopolis, for I have decided to spend the winter there.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Diligently send on their way Zenas the lawyer and Apollos, so that {they may lack nothing}<note>Literally "nothing may lack to them"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But also our <transChange type="added">people</transChange> must learn to engage in good deeds for necessary needs, so that they will not be unfruitful.</verse>
    <verse num="15">All those with me greet you. Greet those who love us in the faith. Grace <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with all of you. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>