<book num="Hag">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">In the second year of King Darius, in the sixth month, on <transChange type="added">the</transChange> first day, the word of Yahweh came {through}<note>Literally "through the hand of"</note> Haggai the prophet to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"Thus says Yahweh of hosts: 'This people says, "{The time has not come to rebuild the temple of Yahweh}.'" <note>Literally "The time is not coming, the time for the house of Yahweh to be built"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">And the word of Yahweh came {through}<note>Literally "through the hand of"</note> Haggai the prophet, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="4">"<transChange type="added">Is it</transChange> a time for you yourselves to dwell in your houses that have been paneled <transChange type="added">while</transChange> this house<note>That is, the temple</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> desolate?"</verse>
    <verse num="5">And so then, thus says Yahweh of hosts: '{Consider your ways}!<note>Literally "Set your heart on your ways"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">You have sown much but have harvested little. You have eaten without <transChange type="added">being</transChange> satisfied; {you have drunk without being satiated};<note>Literally "You have drunk, without becoming drunk"</note> you have worn clothes without <transChange type="added">being</transChange> warm; the one who earns wages puts it in {a pouch with holes}.'<note>Literally "a pierced pouch"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Thus says Yahweh of hosts: '{Consider your ways}!<note>Literally "Set your heart on your ways"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Go up the mountain and bring wood and build the house<note>That is, the temple</note> so that I may be pleased with it and honored,' says Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="9">'You have looked for much, and look! <transChange type="added">It came</transChange> to little; and <transChange type="added">when</transChange> you brought <transChange type="added">it</transChange> home, I blew it <transChange type="added">away</transChange>. Why?' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of "</note> Yahweh of hosts. 'Because my house <transChange type="added">is</transChange> desolate and you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> running each to your own house!</verse>
    <verse num="10">Therefore, because of you <transChange type="added">the</transChange> heavens have withheld <transChange type="added">the</transChange> dew and the earth has withheld its produce.</verse>
    <verse num="11">I have called for a drought on the land and the hills,<note>Or mountains</note> on the grain, the new wine, the olive oil, on what the soil produces, on human beings and wild animals,<note>Hebrew "animal"</note> and on {all their labor}.'"<note>Literally "all the labor of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> hands"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="12">Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and all the remnant of the people gave heed to the voice of Yahweh their God and to the words of Haggai the prophet, as Yahweh their God had sent him, {and the people feared Yahweh}.<note>Literally "and the people feared from before Yahweh"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">And Haggai the messenger of Yahweh spoke to the people with the message of Yahweh, saying, " 'I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with you' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people. And they came and did <transChange type="added">the</transChange> work on the house of Yahweh of hosts, their God,</verse>
    <verse num="15">on the twenty-fourth day of the sixth month in the second year of King Darius. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">In the seventh <transChange type="added">month</transChange> on the twenty-first day, the word of Yahweh {came through}<note>Literally "came through the hand of"</note> Haggai the prophet, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="2">"Speak now to Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="3">'Who among you <transChange type="added">is</transChange> left that saw this house in its former glory? And how do you see it now? Does it seem like nothing {to you}?<note>Literally "in your eyes"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">'But now take courage,<note>Or "be strong"</note> Zerubbabel,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh. 'Take courage,<note>Or "Be strong"</note> Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and take courage,<note>Or "be strong"</note> all the people of the land,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh. 'Do the work, because I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> with you,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts,</verse>
    <verse num="5">'according to {the promise}<note>Literally "the word"</note> that {I covenanted}<note>Literally "I cut"</note> with you when you came out of Egypt. My spirit {is with you};<note>Literally "<transChange type="added">is</transChange> standing in your midst"</note> do not be afraid.'</verse>
    <verse num="6">For thus says Yahweh of hosts: 'Once again, in a little while, I will shake the heavens and the earth and the sea and dry land.</verse>
    <verse num="7">I will shake all the nations so that the treasure of all the nations will come, and I will fill this house<note>That is, the temple</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> glory,' says Yahweh of hosts.</verse>
    <verse num="8">'The silver <transChange type="added">is</transChange> mine and the gold <transChange type="added">is</transChange> mine,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts.</verse>
    <verse num="9">'The latter glory of this house will be greater than the former,' says Yahweh of hosts, 'and in this place I will give peace' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts.'" </verse>
    <verse num="10">On <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-fourth <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the ninth <transChange type="added">month</transChange>, in the second year of Darius, the word of Yahweh came to the prophet Haggai, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="11">"Thus says Yahweh of hosts: 'Ask now the priests <transChange type="added">for</transChange> a ruling:<note>Or "a torah," or "a law"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">If a man carries<note>Literally "lifts"</note> consecrated meat in the hem of his garment, and his hem touches bread, or stew, or wine, or olive oil, or any kind of food, will it become holy?'" The priests answered, "No."</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then Haggai said, "If one who is unclean from contact with a corpse touches any of these, will it become unclean?" The priests answered, "Yes, it will be become unclean."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Haggai answered and said, " 'So <transChange type="added">it is with</transChange> this people, and <transChange type="added">with</transChange> this nation before me,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh, 'and so <transChange type="added">it is with</transChange> every kind of work of their hands; and what they offer there <transChange type="added">is</transChange> unclean.</verse>
    <verse num="15">But now, please {consider}<note>Literally "set your heart"</note> from this day forward, before one stone was placed on another in the temple of Yahweh,</verse>
    <verse num="16">{from that time when}<note>Or "from their being," or "from the time they were then"</note> one came to a heap of twenty <transChange type="added">measures</transChange>, there were <transChange type="added">only</transChange> ten, and <transChange type="added">when</transChange> one came to the wine vat to draw out fifty measures,<note>Hebrew "measure"</note> there were <transChange type="added">only</transChange> twenty.</verse>
    <verse num="17">I struck you with blight, and with plant mildew, and hail, all the work of your hands. But {you did not come back to me},'<note>Literally "there were none of you to me"</note> {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="18">'{Please consider}<note>Literally "Please set your heart"</note> from this day forward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth <transChange type="added">month</transChange>, from the day that the foundation of Yahweh's temple was laid,<note>Or "placed," or "set"</note> {consider}:<note>Literally "set your heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19"><transChange type="added">Is there</transChange> still seed in the store chamber? Do the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree still produce nothing? From this day <transChange type="added">forward</transChange> I will bless <transChange type="added">you</transChange>.'" </verse>
    <verse num="20">And the word of Yahweh came to Haggai a second time on the twenty-fourth <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the month saying,</verse>
    <verse num="21">"Say to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah: I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> going to shake the heavens and the earth,</verse>
    <verse num="22">and I will overthrow the thrones of kingdoms and destroy the military strength of the kingdoms of the nations. I will overthrow chariots and their drivers; horses and their riders will fall, every one by the sword of another!</verse>
    <verse num="23">'On that day,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts, 'I will take you, Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, my servant,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh, 'and I will make you a signet ring, for I have chosen you,' {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts." </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>