<book num="John">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</verse>
    <verse num="2">This one was in the beginning with God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">All <transChange type="added">things</transChange> came into being through him, and apart from him not one <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> came into being that<note>Or "came into being. What ...," beginning a new sentence connected with the following verse. A major punctuation problem is involved, since the earliest manuscripts have no punctuation, but some important later ones place the punctuation before this phrase, effectively connecting it to v. 4: "What has come into being was life in him"</note> has come into being.</verse>
    <verse num="4">In him was life, and the life was the light of humanity.<note>Or "humankind"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not overcome<note>Or "comprehend" (if primarily referring to people in the world)</note> it. </verse>
    <verse num="6">A man came, sent from God, {whose name was}<note>Literally "the name to him"</note> John.</verse>
    <verse num="7">This one came for a witness, in order that he could testify about the light, so that all would believe through him.</verse>
    <verse num="8">That one was not the light, but <transChange type="added">came</transChange><note>The verb is implied from the previous verse, and must be supplied in the English translation</note> in order that he could testify about the light.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The true light, who gives light to every person, was coming into the world.</verse>
    <verse num="10">He was in the world, and the world came into being through him, and the world did not recognize<note>Or "acknowledge"</note> him.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He came to his own <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and his own <transChange type="added">people</transChange> did not receive him.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But as many as received him--to those who believe in his name--he gave to them authority to become children of God,</verse>
    <verse num="13">who were born not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of a husband, but of God. </verse>
    <verse num="14">And the Word became flesh and took up residence among us, and we saw his glory, glory as of the one and only from the Father, full of grace and truth.</verse>
    <verse num="15">John testified about him and cried out, saying, "This one was <transChange type="added">he about</transChange> whom I said, 'The one who comes after me is ahead of me, because he existed before me.'"</verse>
    <verse num="16">For from his fullness we have all received, and grace after grace.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For the law was given through Moses; grace and truth came about through Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="18">No one has seen God at any time; the one and only, God, the one who is in the bosom of the Father--that one has made <transChange type="added">him</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> known. </verse>
    <verse num="19">And this is the testimony of John, when the Jews sent<note>Some manuscripts have "sent to him"</note> priests and Levites from Jerusalem so that they could ask him, "Who are you?"</verse>
    <verse num="20">And he confessed--and he did not deny, and confessed--"I am not the Christ!"</verse>
    <verse num="21">And they asked him, "Then who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you? Are you Elijah?" And he said, "I am not!" "Are you the Prophet?"<note>A reference to the "Prophet like Moses" of Deut 18:15 (see Acts 3:22)</note> And he answered, "No!"</verse>
    <verse num="22">Then they said to him, "Who are you, so that we can give an answer to those who sent us? What do you say about yourself?" </verse>
    <verse num="23">He said, </verse>
    <verse num="24">(And they had been sent from the Pharisees.)</verse>
    <verse num="25">And they asked him and said to him, "Why then are you baptizing, if you are not the Christ, nor Elijah, nor the Prophet?" </verse>
    <verse num="26">John answered them, saying, "I baptize with water. In your midst stands <transChange type="added">one</transChange> whom you do not know--</verse>
    <verse num="27">the one who comes after me, of whom I am not worthy {to untie}<note>Literally "that I might untie"</note> the strap of his sandal!"</verse>
    <verse num="28">These <transChange type="added">things</transChange> took place in Bethany on the other side of the Jordan, where John was baptizing. </verse>
    <verse num="29">On the next day he saw Jesus coming to him and said, "Look! The Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world!</verse>
    <verse num="30">This one is <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> about whom I said, 'After me is coming a man who is ahead of me, because he existed before me.'</verse>
    <verse num="31">And I did not know him, but in order that he could be revealed to Israel, because of this I came baptizing with water." </verse>
    <verse num="32">And John testified, saying, "I have seen the Spirit descending like a dove from heaven and remaining upon him.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And I did not know him, but the one who sent me to baptize with water, that one said to me, '<transChange type="added">The one</transChange> upon whom you see the Spirit descending and remaining upon him--this one is the one who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.'</verse>
    <verse num="34">And I have seen and testify that this one is the Chosen One<note>Some manuscripts have "the Son of God"</note> of God. </verse>
    <verse num="35">On the next day again John was standing <transChange type="added">there</transChange>,<note>*The word "<transChange type="added">there</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> and two of his disciples,</verse>
    <verse num="36">and looking at Jesus <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("walking by") which is understood as temporal</note> was walking by, he said, "Look! The Lamb of God!"</verse>
    <verse num="37">And the two disciples heard him speaking, and they followed Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And Jesus, turning around and seeing them following <transChange type="added">him</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said to them, "What do you seek?" And they said to him, "Rabbi" (which means <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("translated") which is understood as temporal</note> translated "Teacher"), "where are you staying?"</verse>
    <verse num="39">He said to them, "Come and you will see!" So they came and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day (it was about the tenth hour). </verse>
    <verse num="40">Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard John and followed him.</verse>
    <verse num="41">This one first found his own brother Simon and said to him, "We have found the Messiah!" (which is translated "Christ").</verse>
    <verse num="42">He brought him to Jesus. Looking at him, Jesus said, "You are Simon the son of John. You will be called Cephas" (which is interpreted "Peter"). </verse>
    <verse num="43">On the next day he wanted to depart for Galilee, and he found Philip. And Jesus said to him, "Follow me!"</verse>
    <verse num="44">(Now Philip was from Bethsaida, the town of Andrew and Peter.)</verse>
    <verse num="45">Philip found Nathanael and said to him, "We have found <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom Moses wrote <transChange type="added">about</transChange> in the law, and the prophets wrote <transChange type="added">about</transChange>--Jesus son of Joseph from Nazareth!"</verse>
    <verse num="46">And Nathanael said to him, "Can anything good come out of Nazareth?" Philip said to him, "Come and see!" </verse>
    <verse num="47">Jesus saw Nathanael coming toward him and said about him, "Look! {A true Israelite}<note>Literally "truly an Israelite"</note> in whom is no deceit!"</verse>
    <verse num="48">Nathanael said to him, "From where do you know me?" Jesus answered and said to him, "Before Philip called you, <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were") which is understood as temporal</note> were under the fig tree, I saw you."</verse>
    <verse num="49">Nathanael answered him, "Rabbi, you are the Son of God! You are the king of Israel!"</verse>
    <verse num="50">Jesus answered and said to him, "Because I said to you that I saw you under the fig tree, do you believe? You will see greater <transChange type="added">things</transChange> than these!"</verse>
    <verse num="51">And he said to him, "Truly, truly I say to all of you, you will see heaven opened and the angels of God ascending and descending upon the Son of Man." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">And on the third day, there was a wedding at Cana in Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And both Jesus and his disciples were invited to the wedding.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And <transChange type="added">when the</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("ran out")</note> wine ran out, the mother of Jesus said to him, "They have no wine!"</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Jesus said to her, "What {does your concern have to do with me},<note>Literally "to me and to you"</note> woman? My hour has not yet come."</verse>
    <verse num="5">His mother said to the servants, "Whatever he says to you, do <transChange type="added">it</transChange>!"<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </verse>
    <verse num="6">Now six stone water jars were set there, in accordance with the ceremonial cleansing of the Jews, each holding two or three measures.<note>A "measure" was about 9 gallons (40 liters)</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Jesus said to them, "Fill the water jars with water." And they filled them to the brim.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And he said to them, "Now draw <transChange type="added">some</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> out and take <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to the head steward. So they took <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">Now when the head steward tasted the water which had become wine and did not know where it was from--but the servants who had drawn the water knew--the head steward summoned the bridegroom</verse>
    <verse num="10">and said to him, "{Everyone}<note>Literally "every man"</note> serves the good wine first, and whenever they are drunk, the inferior. You have kept the good wine until now!"</verse>
    <verse num="11">This beginning of signs Jesus performed at Cana in Galilee, and revealed his glory, and his disciples believed in him. </verse>
    <verse num="12">After this he went down to Capernaum, and his mother and brothers<note>Some manuscripts have "his brothers"</note> and his disciples, and they stayed there {a few}<note>Literally "not many"</note> days.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And the Passover of the Jews was near, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. </verse>
    <verse num="14">And he found in the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> those who were selling oxen and sheep and doves, and the money changers seated.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And he made a whip of cords <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("made") has been translated as a finite verb</note> drove <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> all out of the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>,<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> both the sheep and the oxen, and he poured out the coins of the money changers and overturned their<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> tables.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And to the ones selling the doves he said, "Take these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> away from here! Do not make my Father's house {a marketplace}!"<note>Literally "a market house"; or "a house of merchants" (an allusion to Zech 14:21)</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">His disciples remembered that it is written, "Zeal for your house will consume me."<note>A quotation from Ps 69:9</note> </verse>
    <verse num="18">So the Jews answered and said to him, "What sign do you show to us, because you are doing these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="19">Jesus answered and said to them, "Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up!"</verse>
    <verse num="20">Then the Jews said, "This temple has been under construction<note>This translation of the aorist verb is based on a very close parallel in Ezra 5:16 (LXX), where it is clear from the following verb that the construction had not yet been completed</note> forty-six years, and will you raise it up in three days?"</verse>
    <verse num="21">But he was speaking about the temple of his body.</verse>
    <verse num="22">So when he was raised from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this, and they believed the scripture and the saying that Jesus had spoken. </verse>
    <verse num="23">Now while he was in Jerusalem at the Passover, during the feast, many believed in his name <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as causal</note> saw his signs which he was doing.</verse>
    <verse num="24">But Jesus himself did not entrust himself to them, because he knew all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>,<note>The Greek term is masculine and thus refers to "all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>" rather than "all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>" (which would be neuter)</note></verse>
    <verse num="25">and because he did not {need}<note>Literally "have need that"</note> anyone {to testify}<note>Literally "should testify"</note> about man, for he himself knew what was in man.<note>*Here "man" has been retained rather than the generic "people" to maintain the connection with the following verse</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Now there was a man of the Pharisees {whose name was}<note>Literally "the name to him"</note> Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews.</verse>
    <verse num="2">This man came to him at night and said to him, "Rabbi, we know that <transChange type="added">you are</transChange><note>*Here both the pronoun and verb are understood in Greek and are supplied in the translation</note> a teacher who has come from God, for no one is able to perform these signs that you are performing unless God were with him."</verse>
    <verse num="3">Jesus answered and said to him, "Truly, truly I say to you, unless someone is born from above,<note>The same Greek word can mean either "from above" or "again," which allows for the misunderstanding by Nicodemus here; Jesus was speaking of new birth "from above," while Nicodemus misunderstood him to mean a second physical birth</note> he is not able to see the kingdom of God."</verse>
    <verse num="4">Nicodemus said to him, "How can a man be born <transChange type="added">when he</transChange> is an old man? He is not able to enter into his mother's womb for the second time and be born, <transChange type="added">can he</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">can he</transChange>"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="5">Jesus answered, "Truly, truly I say to you, unless someone is born of water and spirit, he is not able to enter into the kingdom of God.</verse>
    <verse num="6">What is born of the flesh is flesh, and what is born of the Spirit is spirit.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Do not be astonished that I said to you, 'It is necessary for you to be born from above.'<note>The same Greek word can mean either "from above" or "again" (see also v. 3)</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">The wind blows wherever it wishes, and you hear the sound of it, but you do not know where it comes from and where it is going. So is everyone who is born of the Spirit." </verse>
    <verse num="9">Nicodemus answered and said to him, "How can these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> be?"</verse>
    <verse num="10">Jesus answered and said to him, "Are you the teacher of Israel, and you do not understand these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>?</verse>
    <verse num="11">Truly, truly I say to you, we speak what we know, and we testify <transChange type="added">about</transChange> what we have seen, and you do not accept our testimony!</verse>
    <verse num="12">If I tell you earthly things and you do not believe, how will you believe if I tell you heavenly things?</verse>
    <verse num="13">And no one has ascended into heaven except the one who descended from heaven--the Son of Man.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And just as Moses lifted up the snake in the wilderness,<note>An allusion to Num 21:5-9</note> thus it is necessary <transChange type="added">that</transChange> the Son of Man be lifted up,</verse>
    <verse num="15">so that everyone who believes in him will have eternal life."<note>Some interpreters and Bible translations extend the quotation of Jesus' words through v. 21</note> </verse>
    <verse num="16">For in this way God loved the world, so that he gave his one and only Son, in order that everyone who believes in him will not perish, but will have eternal life.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For God did not send his Son into the world in order that he should judge<note>Or "he should condemn"</note> the world, but in order that the world should be saved through him.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The one who believes in him is not judged,<note>Or "condemned"</note> but the one who does not believe has already been judged,<note>Or "been condemned"</note> because he has not believed in the name of the one and only Son of God.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And this is the judgment: that the light has come into the world, and people loved the darkness rather than the light, because their deeds were evil.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For everyone who practices evil hates the light and does not come to the light, lest his deeds be exposed.</verse>
    <verse num="21">But the one who practices the truth comes to the light, in order that his deeds may be revealed, that they are done in God. </verse>
    <verse num="22">After these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Jesus and his disciples came into Judean territory, and there he spent time with them and was baptizing.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Now John was also baptizing at Aenon near Salim, because water was plentiful there, and they were coming and were being baptized.</verse>
    <verse num="24">(For John had not yet been thrown into prison.) </verse>
    <verse num="25">So a dispute occurred on the part of John's disciples with a Jew<note>Some significant early manuscripts read "the Jews"</note> concerning purification.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And they came to John and said to him, "Rabbi, he who was with you on the other side of the Jordan, about whom you testified--look, this one is baptizing, and all are coming to him!" </verse>
    <verse num="27">John answered and said, "A man can receive not one <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> unless it is granted to him from heaven!</verse>
    <verse num="28">You yourselves testify about me that I said, 'I am not the Christ, but I am sent before that one.'</verse>
    <verse num="29">The one who has the bride is the bridegroom. But the friend of the bridegroom, who stands and hears him, rejoices {greatly}<note>Literally "with joy"</note> because of the bridegroom's voice. So this joy of mine is complete.</verse>
    <verse num="30">It is necessary for that one to increase, but <transChange type="added">for</transChange> me to decrease." </verse>
    <verse num="31">The one who comes from above is over all. The one who is from the earth is from the earth and speaks from the earth; the one who comes from heaven is over all.</verse>
    <verse num="32">What he has seen and heard, this he testifies, and no one accepts his testimony.</verse>
    <verse num="33">The one who accepts his testimony has attested that God is true.</verse>
    <verse num="34">For <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom God sent speaks the words of God, for he does not give the Spirit by measure.</verse>
    <verse num="35">The Father loves the Son and has given all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> into his hand.</verse>
    <verse num="36">The one who believes in the Son has eternal life, but the one who disobeys the Son will not see life--but the wrath of God remains on him.<note>Some interpreters and Bible translations extend the quotation of John the Baptist's words through v. 36</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Now when Jesus knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John</verse>
    <verse num="2">(although Jesus himself was not baptizing, but his disciples),</verse>
    <verse num="3">he left Judea and departed again for Galilee.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And it was necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> him to go through Samaria. </verse>
    <verse num="5">Now he came to a town of Samaria called Sychar, near the piece of land that Jacob had given to his son Joseph.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And Jacob's well was there, so Jesus, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange> had become tired from the journey, simply sat down at the well. It was about the sixth hour. </verse>
    <verse num="7">A woman of Samaria came to draw water. Jesus said to her, "Give me <transChange type="added">water</transChange><note>*Here "water" is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb "give"</note> to drink."</verse>
    <verse num="8">(For his disciples had gone away into the town so that they could buy food.)</verse>
    <verse num="9">So the Samaritan woman said to him, "How do you, being a Jew, ask from me <transChange type="added">water</transChange><note>*Here "water" is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb "ask"</note> to drink, <transChange type="added">since I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">since</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("am") which is understood as causal</note> am a Samaritan woman?" (For Jews have no dealings with Samaritans.) </verse>
    <verse num="10">Jesus answered and said to her, "If you had known the gift of God and who it is who says to you, 'Give me <transChange type="added">water</transChange><note>*Here "water" is supplied in the translation as the understood direct object of the verb "give"</note> to drink,' you would have asked him, and he would have given you living water."</verse>
    <verse num="11">The woman said to him, "Sir, you have no bucket and the well is deep! From where then do you get this living water?</verse>
    <verse num="12">You are not greater than our father Jacob, <transChange type="added">are you</transChange>,<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by the supplied phrase "<transChange type="added">are you</transChange>" in the translation</note> who gave us the well and drank from it himself, and his sons and his livestock?" </verse>
    <verse num="13">Jesus answered and said to her, "Everyone who drinks of this water will be thirsty again.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But whoever drinks of this water which I will give to him will never be thirsty for eternity, but the water which I will give to him will become in him a well of water springing up to eternal life."</verse>
    <verse num="15">The woman said to him, "Sir, give me this water, so that I will not be thirsty or come here to draw <transChange type="added">water</transChange>!"<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">He said to her, "Go, call your husband and come here."</verse>
    <verse num="17">The woman answered and said to him, "I do not have a husband." Jesus said to her, "You have said rightly, 'I do not have a husband,'</verse>
    <verse num="18">for you have had five husbands, and <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom you have now is not your husband; this you have said truthfully!" </verse>
    <verse num="19">The woman said to him, "Sir, I see that you are a prophet.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Our fathers worshiped on this mountain, and you <transChange type="added">people</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">people</transChange>" is supplied in the translation because the Greek pronoun is plural</note> say that in Jerusalem is the place where it is necessary to worship."</verse>
    <verse num="21">Jesus said to her, "Believe me, woman, that an hour is coming when neither on this mountain nor in Jerusalem will you worship the Father.</verse>
    <verse num="22">You worship what you do not know. We worship what we know, because salvation is from the Jews.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But an hour is coming--and now is <transChange type="added">here</transChange><note>*The word "<transChange type="added">here</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note>--when the true worshipers will worship the Father in spirit and truth, for indeed the Father seeks such <transChange type="added">people</transChange> <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> his worshipers.</verse>
    <verse num="24">God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> spirit, and the ones who worship him must worship in spirit and truth."</verse>
    <verse num="25">The woman said to him, "I know that Messiah is coming" (the one called Christ); "whenever that one comes, he will proclaim all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to us."</verse>
    <verse num="26">Jesus said to her, "I, the one speaking to you, am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>.<note>*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </verse>
    <verse num="27">And at this <transChange type="added">point</transChange><note>*The word "<transChange type="added">point</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> his disciples came, and they were astonished that he was speaking with a woman. However, no one said, "What do you seek?" or "Why are you speaking with her?"</verse>
    <verse num="28">So the woman left her water jar and went away into the town and said to the people,<note>Assuming the term is used here in a generic sense to refer to persons of either gender, it should be translated "people"; if instead the term here refers only to the town leaders or elders who met at the town gate, then "men" would be appropriate</note></verse>
    <verse num="29">"Come, see a man who told me everything I have ever done! Perhaps this one is the Christ?"</verse>
    <verse num="30">They went out from the town and were coming to him. </verse>
    <verse num="31">In the meanwhile the disciples were asking him, saying, "Rabbi, eat <transChange type="added">something</transChange>!"<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="32">But he said to them, "I have food to eat that you do not know about."</verse>
    <verse num="33">So the disciples began to say<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> to one another, "No one brought him <transChange type="added">anything</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to eat, <transChange type="added">did they</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated by the supplied phrase "<transChange type="added">did they</transChange>" in the translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">Jesus said to them, "My food is that I do the will of the one who sent me and complete his work.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Do you not say, 'There are yet four months and the harvest comes'? Behold, I say to you, lift up your eyes and look at the fields, that they are white for harvest already.<note>Some interpreters and Bible translations place the word "already" at the beginning of the next verse: "Already the one who reaps receives wages ..."</note></verse>
    <verse num="36">The one who reaps receives wages and gathers fruit for eternal life, in order that the one who sows and the one who reaps can rejoice together.</verse>
    <verse num="37">For in this <transChange type="added">instance</transChange><note>*The word "<transChange type="added">point</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> the saying is true, 'It is one who sows and another who reaps.'</verse>
    <verse num="38">I sent you to reap what you did not work for; others have worked, and you have entered into their work." </verse>
    <verse num="39">Now from that town many of the Samaritans believed in him because of the word of the woman who testified, "He told me everything that I have done."</verse>
    <verse num="40">So when the Samaritans came to him, they began asking<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began asking")</note> him to stay with them. And he stayed there two days.</verse>
    <verse num="41">And many more believed because of his word,</verse>
    <verse num="42">And they were saying to the woman, "No longer because of {what you said}<note>Literally "your speaking"</note> do we believe, for we ourselves have heard, and we know that this one is truly the Savior of the world!" </verse>
    <verse num="43">And after the two days he departed from there into Galilee.</verse>
    <verse num="44">For Jesus himself testified that a prophet has no honor in his own homeland.</verse>
    <verse num="45">So when he came to Galilee, the Galileans welcomed him, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had seen") which is understood as causal</note> had seen all <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> he had done in Jerusalem at the feast (for they themselves had also come to the feast). </verse>
    <verse num="46">Now he came again to Cana in Galilee, where he had made the water wine. And <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was at Capernaum a certain royal official whose son was sick.</verse>
    <verse num="47">This man, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Jesus had come from Judea into Galilee, went to him and asked that he come down and heal his son, for he was about to die.</verse>
    <verse num="48">So Jesus said to him, "Unless you <transChange type="added">people</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">people</transChange>" is supplied in the translation because the Greek verb ("see") is plural</note> see signs and wonders, you will never believe!"</verse>
    <verse num="49">The royal official said to him, "Sir, come down before my child dies!"</verse>
    <verse num="50">Jesus said to him, "Go, your son will live." The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and he departed. </verse>
    <verse num="51">Now <transChange type="added">as</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was going down")</note> he was going down, his slaves met him, saying that his child was alive.</verse>
    <verse num="52">So he inquired from them the hour at which he had gotten better. Then they said to him, "Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him."</verse>
    <verse num="53">So the father knew that <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> that<note>Some manuscripts have "that <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> at that same hour"</note> same hour at which Jesus said to him, "Your son will live," and he himself believed, and his whole household.</verse>
    <verse num="54">Now this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> again a second sign Jesus performed <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("came") which is understood as temporal</note> came from Judea into Galilee. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">After these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was a feast of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Now there is in Jerusalem near the Sheep Gate a pool called in Aramaic Bethzatha,<note>The majority of later manuscripts read "Bethesda," while other early manuscripts read "Bethsaida"</note> which has five porticoes.</verse>
    <verse num="3">In these were lying a large number of those who were sick, blind, lame, paralyzed.<note>The majority of later manuscripts add the following words: "waiting for the moving of the water. 4 For an angel of the Lord from time to time went down in the pool and stirred up the water. So the one who went in first after the stirring of the water was healed of whatever disease he suffered."</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And a certain man was there who had <transChange type="added">been</transChange> thirty-eight years in his sickness.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Jesus, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as temporal</note> saw this one lying <transChange type="added">there</transChange> and knew that he had <transChange type="added">been sick</transChange><note>*The phrase "<transChange type="added">been sick</transChange>" is not in the Greek text, but is supplied from the context</note> a long time already, said to him, "Do you want to become well?"</verse>
    <verse num="7">The one who was sick answered him, "Sir, I do not have anyone that, whenever the water is stirred up, could put me into the pool. But {while}<note>Literally "during which <transChange type="added">time</transChange>"</note> I am coming, another goes down before me."</verse>
    <verse num="8">Jesus said to him, "Get up! Pick up your mat and walk!"</verse>
    <verse num="9">And immediately the man became well and picked up his mat and began to walk.<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to walk")</note> (Now it was the Sabbath on that day.) </verse>
    <verse num="10">So the Jews were saying to the one who had been healed, "It is the Sabbath, and it is not permitted for you to pick up the mat!"<note>Some manuscripts have "your mat"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">But he answered them, "The one who made me well--that one said to me, 'Pick up your mat and walk!'"</verse>
    <verse num="12">So they asked him,<note>Some manuscripts have "They asked him"</note> "Who is the man who said to you, 'Pick up <transChange type="added">your mat</transChange><note>*In Greek the direct object ("<transChange type="added">your mat</transChange>") is not in the Greek text but the repetition is implied from the previous verse</note> and walk?'"</verse>
    <verse num="13">But the one who was healed did not know who it was, for Jesus had withdrawn <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was")</note> a crowd was in the place. </verse>
    <verse num="14">After these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Jesus found him at the temple and said to him, "Look, you have become well! Sin no longer, lest something worse happen to you."</verse>
    <verse num="15">The man went and reported to the Jews that Jesus was the one who made him well.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And on account of this the Jews began to persecute<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to persecute")</note> Jesus, because he was doing these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> on the Sabbath.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But he answered<note>Some manuscripts have "Jesus answered"</note> them, "My Father is working until now, and I am working."</verse>
    <verse num="18">So on account of this the Jews were seeking even more to kill him, because he not only was breaking the Sabbath, but also was calling God his own Father, <transChange type="added">thus</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">thus</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("making") which is understood as result</note> making himself equal with God. </verse>
    <verse num="19">So Jesus answered and said to them, "Truly, truly I say to you, the Son can do nothing from himself except what he sees the Father doing. For whatever that one does, these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> also the Son does likewise.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For the Father loves the Son and shows him everything that he himself is doing. And greater works than these he will show him, so that you will be astonished.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For just as the Father raises the dead and makes <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> alive, thus also the Son makes alive whomever he wishes.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For the Father does not judge anyone, but he has given all judgment to the Son,</verse>
    <verse num="23">in order that all <transChange type="added">people</transChange><note>*The word "<transChange type="added">people</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> will honor the Son, just as they honor the Father. The one who does not honor the Son does not honor the Father who sent him.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Truly, truly I say to you that the one who hears my word and who believes the one who sent me has eternal life, and does not come into judgment, but has passed from death into life. </verse>
    <verse num="25">"Truly, truly I say to you, that an hour is coming--and now is <transChange type="added">here</transChange>--when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God, and the ones who hear will live.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For just as the Father has life in himself, thus also he has granted to the Son to have life in himself.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And he has granted him authority to carry out judgment, because he is the Son of Man. </verse>
    <verse num="28">"Do not be astonished <transChange type="added">at</transChange> this, because an hour is coming in which all those in the tombs will hear his voice</verse>
    <verse num="29">and they will come out--those who have done good <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to a resurrection of life, but those who have practiced evil <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to a resurrection of judgment.</verse>
    <verse num="30">I am able to do nothing from myself. Just as I hear, I judge, and my judgment is just, because I do not seek my <transChange type="added">own</transChange> will, but the will of the one who sent me. </verse>
    <verse num="31">"If I testify about myself, my testimony is not true.</verse>
    <verse num="32">There is another who testifies about me, and I know that the testimony which he testifies about me is true.</verse>
    <verse num="33">You have sent to John and he has testified to the truth.</verse>
    <verse num="34">(And I do not receive testimony from people, but I say these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in order that you may be saved.)</verse>
    <verse num="35">That one was the lamp <transChange type="added">which was</transChange> burning and shining, and you wanted to rejoice for an hour in his light. </verse>
    <verse num="36">"But I have a testimony greater than John's, for the works which the Father has given to me that I should complete them--the very works which I am doing--<transChange type="added">these</transChange> testify about me, that the Father has sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And the Father who sent me, that one has testified about me. You have neither heard his voice at any time nor seen his form.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And you do not have his word residing in yourselves, because the one whom that one sent, in this one you do not believe.</verse>
    <verse num="39">You search<note>Or "Search" (an imperative)</note> the scriptures because you think that you have eternal life in them, and it is these that testify about me.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And you are not willing to come to me so that you may have life. </verse>
    <verse num="41">"I do not accept glory<note>Or "honor"</note> from people,</verse>
    <verse num="42">but I know you, that you do not have the love of God in yourselves.</verse>
    <verse num="43">I have come in my Father's name, and you do not accept me. If another should come in his own name, you would accept that one!</verse>
    <verse num="44">How are you able to believe, <transChange type="added">if you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("accept") which is understood as conditional</note> accept glory from one another, and do not seek the glory <transChange type="added">which is</transChange> from the only God?</verse>
    <verse num="45">Do not think that I will accuse you before the Father! The one who accuses you is Moses, in whom you have put your hope!</verse>
    <verse num="46">For if you had believed Moses, you would believe me, for that one wrote about me.</verse>
    <verse num="47">But if you do not believe that one's writings, how will you believe my words?" </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">After these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Jesus went away to the other side of the sea of Galilee (that is, Tiberias).</verse>
    <verse num="2">And a large crowd was following him because they were observing the signs that he was doing on those who were sick.</verse>
    <verse num="3">So Jesus went up on the mountain and sat down there with his disciples.</verse>
    <verse num="4">(Now the Passover, the feast of the Jews, was near.)</verse>
    <verse num="5">{Then Jesus, when he looked up}<note>Literally "then Jesus lifting up the eyes"</note> <note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" in the translation is supplied as a component of the participle "lifting up" which is understood as temporal</note> and saw that a large crowd was coming to him, said to Philip, "Where can we buy bread so that these <transChange type="added">people</transChange> can eat?"</verse>
    <verse num="6">(Now he said this to test him, because he knew what he was going to do.)</verse>
    <verse num="7">Philip replied to him, "Two hundred denarii <transChange type="added">worth of</transChange> bread would not be enough for them, in order that each one could receive a little."</verse>
    <verse num="8">One of his disciples, Andrew the brother of Simon Peter, said to him,</verse>
    <verse num="9">"Here is a boy who has five barley loaves and two fish, but what are these for so many <transChange type="added">people</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="10">Jesus said, "Make the people recline." (Now <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was a lot of grass in the place.) So the men reclined, approximately five thousand <transChange type="added">in</transChange> number.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then Jesus took the bread, and <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had given thanks") which is understood as temporal</note> had given thanks, he distributed <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to those who were reclining--likewise also of the fish, as much as they wanted.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And when they were satisfied, he said to his disciples, "Gather the remaining fragments so that nothing is lost."</verse>
    <verse num="13">So they gathered <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and filled twelve baskets with fragments from the five barley loaves which were left over by those who had eaten. </verse>
    <verse num="14">Now <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as temporal</note> the people saw the sign that he performed, they began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "This one is truly the Prophet who is to come into the world!"</verse>
    <verse num="15">Then Jesus, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew that they were about to come and seize him in order to make <transChange type="added">him</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> king, withdrew again up the mountain <transChange type="added">by</transChange> himself alone. </verse>
    <verse num="16">Now when evening came, his disciples went down to the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And getting into a boat, they began to go<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to go")</note> to the other side of the sea, to Capernaum. And it had already become dark, and Jesus had not yet come to them.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And the sea began to be stirred up<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to be stirred up")</note> <transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was blowing") which is understood as causal</note> a strong wind was blowing.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Then <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had rowed") which is understood as temporal</note> had rowed about twenty-five or thirty stadia,<note>A "stade" or "stadium" (plur. "stadia") is about 607 ft (187 m), so this was around 3 miles (5 km)</note> they saw Jesus walking on the sea and coming near the boat, and they were afraid.</verse>
    <verse num="20">But he said to them, "<transChange type="added">It</transChange> is I! Do not be afraid!"</verse>
    <verse num="21">So they were wanting to take him into the boat, and immediately the boat came to the land to which they were going. </verse>
    <verse num="22">On the next day, the crowd that was on the other side of the sea saw that other boats were not there (except one), and that Jesus had not entered with his disciples into the boat, but his disciples had departed alone.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Other boats from Tiberias came near the place where they had eaten the bread <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("had given thanks")</note> the Lord had given thanks.</verse>
    <verse num="24">So when the crowd saw that Jesus was not there, nor his disciples, they themselves got into the boats and came to Capernaum seeking Jesus. </verse>
    <verse num="25">And <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("found") which is understood as temporal</note> found him on the other side of the sea, they said to him, "Rabbi, when did you get here?"</verse>
    <verse num="26">Jesus replied to them and said, "Truly, truly I say to you, you seek me not because you saw signs, but because you ate of the loaves and were satisfied!</verse>
    <verse num="27">Do not work for the food that perishes, but the food that remains to eternal life, which the Son of Man will give to you. For God the Father has set his seal on this one." </verse>
    <verse num="28">So they said to him, "What shall we do that we can accomplish the works of God?"</verse>
    <verse num="29">Jesus answered and said to them, "This is the work of God: that you believe in <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom that one sent."</verse>
    <verse num="30">So they said to him, "Then what sign will you perform, so that we can see <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and believe you? What will you do?</verse>
    <verse num="31">Our fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, just as it is written, 'He gave them bread from heaven to eat.'<note>A quotation from Ps 78:24 which refers to the events of Exod 16:4-36</note> </verse>
    <verse num="32">Then Jesus said to them, "Truly, truly I say to you, Moses did not give you bread from heaven, but my Father is giving you the true bread from heaven!</verse>
    <verse num="33">For the bread of God is the one who comes down from heaven and gives life to the world."</verse>
    <verse num="34">So they said to him, "Sir, always give us this bread!" </verse>
    <verse num="35">Jesus said to them, "I am the bread of life. The one who comes to me will never be hungry, and the one who believes in me will never be thirsty again.</verse>
    <verse num="36">But I said to you that you have seen me and do not believe.</verse>
    <verse num="37">Everyone whom the Father gives to me will come to me, and the one who comes to me I will never throw out,</verse>
    <verse num="38">because I have come down from heaven not that I should do my will, but the will of the one who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="39">Now this is the will of the one who sent me: that everyone whom he has given me, I would not lose <transChange type="added">any</transChange> of them,<note>This pronoun is neuter singular in Greek, but is collective</note> but raise them<note>This pronoun is neuter singular in Greek, but is collective</note> up on the last day.</verse>
    <verse num="40">For this is the will of my Father, that everyone who looks at the Son and believes in him would have eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day." </verse>
    <verse num="41">Now the Jews began to grumble<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to grumble")</note> about him because he said, "I am the bread that came down from heaven,"</verse>
    <verse num="42">and they were saying, "Is this one not Jesus the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? How does he now say, 'I have come down from heaven'?"</verse>
    <verse num="43">Jesus answered and said to them, "Do not grumble {among yourselves}!<note>Literally "with one another"</note></verse>
    <verse num="44">No one is able to come to me unless the Father who sent me draws him, and I will raise him up on the last day.</verse>
    <verse num="45">It is written in the prophets, 'And they will all be taught by God.'<note>A quotation from Isa 54:13</note> Everyone who hears from the Father and learns comes to me.</verse>
    <verse num="46">(Not that anyone has seen the Father except the one who is from God--this one has seen the Father.)<note>The switch from first person in vv. 44-45 to third person here and back to first person in vv. 47-51 suggests that this verse is a parenthetical comment by the author rather than the words of Jesus</note></verse>
    <verse num="47">Truly, truly I say to you, the one who believes has eternal life.</verse>
    <verse num="48">I am the bread of life.</verse>
    <verse num="49">Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness and they died.</verse>
    <verse num="50">This is the bread that comes down from heaven so that someone may eat from it and not die.</verse>
    <verse num="51">I am the living bread that came down from heaven. If anyone eats from this bread, he will live {forever}.<note>Literally "for the age"</note> And the bread that I will give for the life of the world is my flesh." </verse>
    <verse num="52">So the Jews began to quarrel<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to quarrel")</note> {among themselves},<note>Literally "with one another"</note> saying, "How can this man give us his flesh to eat?"</verse>
    <verse num="53">Then Jesus said to them, "Truly, truly I say to you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink his blood, you do not have life in yourselves!</verse>
    <verse num="54">The one who eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day.</verse>
    <verse num="55">For my flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink.</verse>
    <verse num="56">The one who eats<note>*This term is somewhat graphic and typically used for animals feeding, but the distinction from other Greek verbs for eating is difficult to convey in English</note> my flesh and drinks my blood resides in me and I in him.</verse>
    <verse num="57">Just as the living Father sent me, and I live because of the Father, <transChange type="added">so</transChange> also the one who eats<note>*This term is somewhat graphic and typically used for animals feeding, but the distinction from other Greek verbs for eating is difficult to convey in English</note> me--that one will live because of me.</verse>
    <verse num="58">This is the bread that came down from heaven, not as the fathers ate and died. The one who eats<note>*This term is somewhat graphic and typically used for animals feeding, but the distinction from other Greek verbs for eating is difficult to convey in English</note> this bread will live {forever}."<note>Literally "for the age"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="59">He said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("teaching") which is understood as temporal</note> teaching in the synagogue in Capernaum.</verse>
    <verse num="60">Thus many of his disciples, <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said, "This saying is hard! Who can understand it?"</verse>
    <verse num="61">But Jesus, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew within himself that his disciples were grumbling about this, said to them, "Does this cause you to be offended?</verse>
    <verse num="62">Then <transChange type="added">what</transChange> if you see the Son of Man ascending where he was before?</verse>
    <verse num="63">The Spirit is the one who gives life; the flesh profits nothing. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and are life.</verse>
    <verse num="64">But there are some of you who do not believe." (For Jesus knew from the beginning who they were who did not believe, and who it was who would betray him.)</verse>
    <verse num="65">And he said, "Because of this I said to you that no one can come to me unless it has been granted to him by the Father." </verse>
    <verse num="66">For this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> many of his disciples {drew back}<note>Literally "went away to the things behind"</note> and were not walking with him any longer.</verse>
    <verse num="67">So Jesus said to the twelve, "You do not want to go away also, <transChange type="added">do you</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">do you</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="68">Simon Peter answered him, "Lord, to whom would we go? You have the words of eternal life.</verse>
    <verse num="69">And we have believed, and have come to know, that you are the Holy One of God."</verse>
    <verse num="70">Jesus replied to them, "Did I not choose you, the twelve, and one of you is the devil?"</verse>
    <verse num="71">(Now he was speaking about Judas <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of Simon Iscariot, because this one--one of the twelve--was going to betray him.) </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">And after these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Jesus was going about in Galilee. For he did not want to go about in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill him.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Now the feast of the Jews--the <transChange type="added">feast of</transChange> Tabernacles--was near.</verse>
    <verse num="3">So his brothers said to him, "Depart from here and go to Judea, so that your disciples also can see your works that you are doing.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For no one does anything in secret and <transChange type="added">yet</transChange> he himself desires to be {publicly recognized}.<note>Literally "with openness"</note> If you are doing these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, reveal yourself to the world!"</verse>
    <verse num="5">(For not even his brothers believed in him.) </verse>
    <verse num="6">So Jesus said to them, "My time has not yet come, but your time is always ready.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The world cannot hate you, but it hates me, because I am testifying about it, that its deeds are evil.</verse>
    <verse num="8">You go up to the feast. I am not<note>Most manuscripts read "not yet" here, but this is obviously an easier reading intended to reconcile the statement with Jesus' later actions</note> going up to this feast, because my time is not yet completed.<note>Or "fulfilled"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, he remained in Galilee. </verse>
    <verse num="10">But when his brothers had gone up to the feast, then he also went up, not openly, but (as it were) in secret.</verse>
    <verse num="11">So the Jews were looking for him at the feast, and were saying, "Where is he?"</verse>
    <verse num="12">And there was a lot of grumbling concerning him among the crowds; some were saying, "He is a good <transChange type="added">man</transChange>," but others were saying, "No, but he deceives the crowd."</verse>
    <verse num="13">However, no one was speaking openly about him for fear of the Jews. </verse>
    <verse num="14">{Now when the feast was already half over},<note>Literally "now it being already in the middle of the feast"</note> Jesus went to the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and began to teach.<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to teach")</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">Then the Jews were astonished, saying, "How does this man {possess knowledge},<note>Literally "know letters"</note> <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("been taught") which is understood as causal</note> has not been taught?"</verse>
    <verse num="16">So Jesus answered them and said, "My teaching is not mine, but <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from the one who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="17">If anyone wants to do his will, he will know about my<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> teaching, whether it is from God or I am speaking from myself.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The one who speaks from himself seeks his own glory. But the one who seeks the glory of the one who sent him--this one is true, and there is no unrighteousness in him.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Has not Moses given you the law, and none of you carries out the law? Why do you seek to kill me?" </verse>
    <verse num="20">The crowd replied, "You have a demon! Who is seeking to kill you?"</verse>
    <verse num="21">Jesus answered and said to them, "I performed one work, and you are all astonished.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Because of this Moses has given you circumcision (not that it is from Moses, but from the fathers), and you circumcise a man on the Sabbath.</verse>
    <verse num="23">If a man receives circumcision on the Sabbath so that the law of Moses would not be broken, are you angry with me because I made a whole man well<note>Or "a man entirely well"</note> on the Sabbath?</verse>
    <verse num="24">Do not judge according to outward appearance, but judge according to righteous judgment!" </verse>
    <verse num="25">Then some of the inhabitants of Jerusalem began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "Is this not <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom they are seeking to kill?</verse>
    <verse num="26">And behold, he is speaking openly and they are saying nothing to him! Can it be that the rulers truly know that this man is the Christ?</verse>
    <verse num="27">Yet we know where this man is from, but the Christ, whenever he comes--no one knows where he is from!" </verse>
    <verse num="28">Then Jesus cried out in the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>,<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> teaching and saying, "You both know me and you know where I am from! And I have not come from myself, but the one who sent me is true, whom you do not know.</verse>
    <verse num="29">I know him, because I am from him and he sent me." </verse>
    <verse num="30">So they were seeking to seize him, and no one laid a hand on him, because his hour had not yet come.</verse>
    <verse num="31">But from the crowd many believed in him and were saying, "Whenever the Christ comes, he will not perform more signs than this man has done, <transChange type="added">will he</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">will he</transChange>"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="32">The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> about him, and the chief priests and the Pharisees sent officers in order {to take him into custody }.<note>Literally "that they could seize him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="33">Then Jesus said, "Yet a little time I am with you, and I am going to the one who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="34">You will seek me and will not find <transChange type="added">me</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state "me"</note> and where I am, you cannot come." </verse>
    <verse num="35">So the Jews said to one another, "Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this one going to go, that we will not find him? He is not going to go to the Dispersion among the Greeks and teach the Greeks, <transChange type="added">is he</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">is he</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="36">What is this saying that he said, 'You will seek me and will not find <transChange type="added">me</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state "me"</note> and where I am, you cannot come'?" </verse>
    <verse num="37">Now on the last day of the feast--the great <transChange type="added">day</transChange>--Jesus stood and cried out, saying, "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me, and let him drink,</verse>
    <verse num="38">the one who believes in me.<note>An alternative punctuation of vv. 37-38 reads: "If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and let him drink. 38 The one who believes in me, just as the scripture said, 'Out of his belly will flow rivers of living water.'"</note> Just as the scripture said, 'Out of his belly will flow rivers of living water.'"<note>A quotation from the Old Testament of uncertain origin; texts most often suggested are Isa 44:3; 55:1; 58:11; Zech 14:8</note></verse>
    <verse num="39">Now he said this concerning the Spirit, whom those who believed in him were about to receive. For the Spirit was not yet <transChange type="added">given</transChange>,<note>A few manuscripts supply the participle "given" here; while it is unlikely this represents the original reading, many English versions nevertheless supply "given" to avoid the impression that the Spirit did not exist prior to this point</note> because Jesus had not yet been glorified.) </verse>
    <verse num="40">Then, <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard these words, <transChange type="added">some</transChange> from the crowd began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "This man is truly the Prophet!"</verse>
    <verse num="41">Others were saying, "This man is the Christ!" But others were saying, "No, for the Christ does not come from Galilee, <transChange type="added">does he</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">does he</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="42">Has not the scripture said that the Christ comes from the descendants of David, and from Bethlehem, the village where David was?"</verse>
    <verse num="43">So there was a division in the crowd because of him.</verse>
    <verse num="44">And some of them were wanting to seize him, but no one laid hands on him. </verse>
    <verse num="45">So the officers came to the chief priests and Pharisees. And they said to them, "{Why}<note>Literally "because of what"</note> did you not bring him?"</verse>
    <verse num="46">The officers replied, "Never has a man spoken like this!"</verse>
    <verse num="47">Then the Pharisees replied to them, "You have not also been deceived, <transChange type="added">have you</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">have you</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="48">{None}<note>Literally "not anyone"</note> of the rulers or of the Pharisees have believed in him, <transChange type="added">have they</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">have they</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="49">But this crowd who does not know the law is accursed!" </verse>
    <verse num="50">Nicodemus, the one who came to him previously--who was one of them--said to them,</verse>
    <verse num="51">"Our law does not condemn a man unless it first hears from him and knows what he is doing, <transChange type="added">does it</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">does it</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="52">They answered and said to him, "You are not also from Galilee, <transChange type="added">are you</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">are you</transChange>"</note> Investigate and see that a prophet does not arise from Galilee!" [[</verse>
    <verse num="53">And each one went to his <transChange type="added">own</transChange> house.<note>John 7:53-8:11 is not found in the earliest and best manuscripts and was almost certainly not an original part of the Gospel of John; one significant group of Greek manuscripts places it after Luke 21:38</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">But Jesus went to the Mount of Olives.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Now early in the morning he came again to the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>.<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> And all the people were coming,<note>Some manuscripts have "were coming to him"</note> and he sat down <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("sat down") has been translated as a finite verb</note> began to teach<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to teach")</note> them. </verse>
    <verse num="3">Now the scribes and the Pharisees brought to him a woman<note>Some manuscripts have "brought a woman"</note> caught in adultery. And standing her in <transChange type="added">their</transChange> midst,</verse>
    <verse num="4">they said to him, testing <transChange type="added">him</transChange>,<note>Some manuscripts omit "testing <transChange type="added">him</transChange>"</note> "Teacher, this woman was caught in the very act of committing adultery!</verse>
    <verse num="5">Now in the law, Moses commanded us to stone such women. So what do you say?"</verse>
    <verse num="6">(Now they were saying this to test him, so that they would have <transChange type="added">an occasion</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to bring charges against him.) But Jesus, bending down, began to write<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to write")</note> with <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> finger on the ground, taking no notice.<note>Some manuscripts omit "taking no notice"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">And when they persisted in asking him, straightening up he said<note>Some manuscripts have "he straightened up and said"</note> to them, "The <transChange type="added">one</transChange> of you without sin, let him throw the first stone at her!"</verse>
    <verse num="8">And bending down again, he wrote on the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Now <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> being convicted by their conscience,<note>Some manuscripts omit "being convicted by their conscience"</note> they began to depart,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to depart")</note> one by one, beginning with the older ones, and Jesus<note>Some manuscripts have "he"</note> was left alone--and the woman who was in <transChange type="added">their</transChange> midst.</verse>
    <verse num="10">So Jesus, straightening up and seeing no one except the woman,<note>Some manuscripts omit "and seeing no one except the woman"</note> said to her, "Where are those accusers of yours?<note>Some manuscripts have "said to her, 'Woman, where are they?"</note> Does no one condemn you?"</verse>
    <verse num="11">And she said, "No one, Lord." So Jesus said, "Neither do I condemn you. Go, and<note>Some manuscripts have "and from now on"</note> sin no more."]]<note>John 7:53-8:11 is not found in the earliest and best manuscripts and was almost certainly not an original part of the Gospel of John; one significant group of Greek manuscripts places it after Luke 21:38</note> </verse>
    <verse num="12">Then Jesus spoke to them again, saying, "I am the light of the world! The one who follows me will never walk in darkness, but will have the light of life."</verse>
    <verse num="13">So the Pharisees said to him, "You testify concerning yourself! Your testimony is not true."</verse>
    <verse num="14">Jesus answered and said to them, "Even if I testify concerning myself, my testimony is true, because I know where I have come from and where I am going. But you do not know where I have come from or where I am going.</verse>
    <verse num="15">You judge according to externals; I do not judge anyone.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But even if I judge, my judgment is true, because I am not alone, but I and the Father who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And even in your law it is written that the testimony of two men is true.<note>An allusion to Deut 17:6</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">I am the one who testifies concerning myself, and the Father who sent me testifies concerning me." </verse>
    <verse num="19">So they were saying to him, "Where is your father?" Jesus replied, "You know neither me nor my Father! If you had known me, you would have known my Father also."</verse>
    <verse num="20">He spoke these words by the treasury <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("teaching") which is understood as temporal</note> teaching in the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>,<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> and no one seized him, because his hour had not yet come. </verse>
    <verse num="21">So he said to them again, "I am going away, and you will seek me and will die in your sin. Where I am going you cannot come!"</verse>
    <verse num="22">Then the Jews began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "Perhaps he will kill himself, because he is saying, 'Where I am going you cannot come.'"</verse>
    <verse num="23">And he said to them, "You are from below; I am from above. You are from this world; I am not from this world.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Thus I said to you that you will die in your sins. For if you do not believe that I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>, you will die in your sins." </verse>
    <verse num="25">So they began to say to him,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "Who are you?" Jesus said to them, "{What}<note>Literally "that which"</note> I have been saying to you <transChange type="added">from</transChange> the beginning.</verse>
    <verse num="26">I have many <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to say and to judge concerning you, but the one who sent me is true, and <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which I heard from him, these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> I say to the world."</verse>
    <verse num="27">(They did not know that he was speaking to them about the Father.) </verse>
    <verse num="28">Then Jesus said,<note>Some manuscripts have "said to them"</note> "When you lift up the Son of Man, then you will recognize that I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>, and I do nothing from myself, but just as the Father taught me, I say these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And the one who sent me is with me. He has not left me alone, because I always do the things that are pleasing to him."</verse>
    <verse num="30"><transChange type="added">While</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was saying")</note> he was saying these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, many believed in him. </verse>
    <verse num="31">Then Jesus said to those Jews who had believed him, "If you continue in my word you are truly my disciples,</verse>
    <verse num="32">and you will know the truth, and the truth will set you free."</verse>
    <verse num="33">They replied to him, "We are descendants of Abraham and have not been enslaved to anyone at any time. How do you say, 'You will become free'?"</verse>
    <verse num="34">Jesus replied to them, "Truly, truly I say to you, that everyone who commits sin is a slave of sin.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And the slave does not remain in the household {forever};<note>Literally "for the age"</note> the son remains {forever}.<note>Literally "for the age"</note></verse>
    <verse num="36">So if the son sets you free, you will be truly free.</verse>
    <verse num="37">I know that you are descendants of Abraham. But you are seeking to kill me, because my word makes no progress among you.</verse>
    <verse num="38">I speak <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> that I have seen with the Father; so also you do <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> that you have heard from the Father." </verse>
    <verse num="39">They answered and said to him, "Abraham is our father!" Jesus said to them, "If you are children of Abraham, do the deeds of Abraham!</verse>
    <verse num="40">But now you are seeking to kill me, a man who spoke to you the truth which I heard from God. This Abraham did not do.</verse>
    <verse num="41">You are doing the deeds of your father!" </verse>
    <verse num="42">Jesus said to them, "If God were your father, you would love me, for I have come forth from God and have come. For I have not come from myself, but that one sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="43">{Why}<note>Literally "because of what"</note> do you not understand my way of speaking? Because you are not able to listen to my message.</verse>
    <verse num="44">You are of your father the devil, and you want to do the desires of your father! That one was a murderer from the beginning, and does not stand firm in the truth, because truth is not in him. Whenever he speaks the lie, he speaks from his own <transChange type="added">nature</transChange>,<note>*The word "<transChange type="added">nature</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> because he is a liar and the father {of lies}.<note>Literally "of it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="45">But because I am telling the truth, you do not believe me.</verse>
    <verse num="46">Who among you convicts me concerning sin? If I am telling the truth, {why}<note>Literally "because of what"</note> do you not believe me?</verse>
    <verse num="47">The one who is from God listens to the words of God. Because of this you do not listen--because you are not of God." </verse>
    <verse num="48">The Jews answered and said to him, "Do we not correctly say that you are a Samaritan and have a demon?"</verse>
    <verse num="49">Jesus replied, "I do not have a demon, but I honor my Father, and you dishonor me!</verse>
    <verse num="50">But I do not seek my <transChange type="added">own</transChange> glory. There is one who seeks and judges!</verse>
    <verse num="51">Truly, truly I say to you, if anyone keeps my word, he will never experience death {forever}."<note>Literally "for the age"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="52">The Jews<note>Some manuscripts have "Then the Jews"</note> said to him, "Now we know that you have a demon! Abraham and the prophets died, and you say, 'If anyone keeps my word, he will never taste death {forever}.'<note>Literally "for the age"</note></verse>
    <verse num="53">You are not greater than our father Abraham who died, <transChange type="added">are you</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">are you</transChange>"</note> And the prophets died! Who do you make yourself <transChange type="added">to be</transChange>?"</verse>
    <verse num="54">Jesus replied, "If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. The one who glorifies me is my Father, <transChange type="added">about</transChange> whom you say, 'He is our God.'</verse>
    <verse num="55">And you have not known him, but I know him. And if I were to say that I do not know him, I would be a liar like you! But I know him and I keep his word.</verse>
    <verse num="56">Abraham your father rejoiced that he would see my day, and he saw <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and was glad." </verse>
    <verse num="57">So the Jews said to him, "{You are}<note>Literally "you have"</note> not yet fifty years <transChange type="added">old</transChange>, and have you seen Abraham?"</verse>
    <verse num="58">Jesus said to them, "Truly, truly I say to you, before Abraham was, I am!"</verse>
    <verse num="59">Then they picked up stones in order to throw <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> at him. But Jesus was hidden and went out of the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>.<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">And <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("went away") which is understood as temporal</note> went away, he saw a man blind from birth.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And his disciples asked him, saying, "Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, that he should be born blind?"</verse>
    <verse num="3">Jesus replied, "Neither this man sinned nor his parents, but <transChange type="added">it happened</transChange><note>*The words "<transChange type="added">it happened</transChange>" are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> so that the works of God could be revealed in him.</verse>
    <verse num="4">It is necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> us to do the deeds of the one who sent me while it is day; night is coming, when no one can work!</verse>
    <verse num="5">While I am in the world, I am the light of the world."</verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">When he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, he spat on the ground and made clay with the saliva, and smeared the clay on his eyes.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And he said to him, "Go, wash in the pool of Siloam" (which is translated "sent"). So he went and washed and came back seeing. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Then the neighbors and those who saw him previously (because he was a beggar) began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "Is this man not the one who used to sit and beg?"</verse>
    <verse num="9">Others were saying, "It is this man"; others were saying, "No, but he is like him." That one was saying, "I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>!"</verse>
    <verse num="10">So they began to say<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> to him, "How<note>Some manuscripts have "Then how"</note> were your eyes opened?"</verse>
    <verse num="11">He replied, "The man who is called Jesus made clay and smeared <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on my eyes and said to me, 'Go to Siloam and wash!' So I went, and I washed, <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the two previous participles ("went" and "washed") have been translated as finite verbs</note> I received sight."</verse>
    <verse num="12">And they said to him, "Where is that man?" He said, "I do not know." </verse>
    <verse num="13">They brought him--the one formerly blind--to the Pharisees.</verse>
    <verse num="14">(Now the day on which Jesus made the clay and opened his eyes was the Sabbath.)</verse>
    <verse num="15">So the Pharisees also were asking him again how he received sight. And he said to them, "He put clay on my eyes, and I washed, and I see."</verse>
    <verse num="16">So some of the Pharisees were saying, "This man is not from God, because he does not observe the Sabbath!" Others<note>Some manuscripts have "But others"</note> were saying, "How can a man <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> a sinner perform such signs?" And there was a division among them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">So they said to the blind man again, "What do you say about him, because he opened your eyes?" And he said, "He is a prophet." </verse>
    <verse num="18">So the Jews did not believe concerning him that he had been blind and received sight, until they summoned the parents of the one<note>Literally "of him"</note> who received sight.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And they asked them, saying, "Is this man your son, whom you say was born blind? Then how does he now see?"</verse>
    <verse num="20">So his parents answered and said, "We know that this man is our son, and that he was born blind.</verse>
    <verse num="21">But how he now sees we do not know, or who opened his eyes we do not know. Ask him! {He is a mature adult};<note>Literally "he has maturity"</note> he will speak for himself!"</verse>
    <verse num="22">(His parents said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> because they were afraid of the Jews, for the Jews had already decided that if anyone should confess him <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> Christ, he would be expelled from the synagogue.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Because of this his parents said, "{He is a mature adult};<note>Literally "he has maturity"</note> ask him.") </verse>
    <verse num="24">So they summoned the man who had been blind for the second time and said to him, "Give glory to God! We know that this man is a sinner!"</verse>
    <verse num="25">Then that man replied, "Whether he is a sinner I do not know. One <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> I know--that <transChange type="added">although I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was") which is understood as concessive</note> was blind, now I see!"</verse>
    <verse num="26">So they said to him, "What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?"</verse>
    <verse num="27">He replied to them, "I told you already and you did not listen! Why do you want to hear <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> again? You do not want to become his disciples also, <transChange type="added">do you</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">do you</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28">They reviled<note>Some manuscripts have "And they reviled"</note> him and said, "You are his disciple! But we are disciples of Moses!</verse>
    <verse num="29">We know that God has spoken to Moses, but we do not know where this man is from."</verse>
    <verse num="30">The man answered and said to them, "For the remarkable thing is this, that you do not know where he is from, and he opened my eyes!</verse>
    <verse num="31">We know that God does not listen to sinners, but if someone is devout and does his will, he listens to this one.</verse>
    <verse num="32">From {time immemorial}<note>Literally "the age"</note> it has not been heard that someone opened the eyes of one born blind.</verse>
    <verse num="33">If this man were not from God, he would not be able to do anything!"</verse>
    <verse num="34">They answered and said to him, "You were born completely in sin, and are you attempting to teach<note>*Here the present tense is translated as a conative present ("attempting to teach")</note> us?" And they threw him out. </verse>
    <verse num="35">Jesus heard that they had thrown him out, and finding him, he said, "Do you believe in the Son of Man?"</verse>
    <verse num="36">He answered and said, "And who is <transChange type="added">he</transChange>, sir, that I may believe in him?"</verse>
    <verse num="37">Jesus said to him, "You have both seen him, and he is the one who is speaking with you." [[</verse>
    <verse num="38">And he said, "I believe, Lord!" and he worshiped him.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And Jesus said,]]<note>A number of important manuscripts lack v. 38 and the first part of v. 39 ("and Jesus said")</note> "For judgment I have come into this world, so that those who do not see may see, and those who see may become blind!"</verse>
    <verse num="40"><transChange type="added">Some</transChange> of the Pharisees who were with him heard these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> and said to him, "We are not also blind, <transChange type="added">are we</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">are we</transChange>"</note></verse>
    <verse num="41">Jesus said to them, "If you were blind, you would not have sin. But now you say, 'We see,' your sin remains. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">"Truly, truly I say to you, the one who does not enter through the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbs up at some other place--that one is a thief and a robber.</verse>
    <verse num="2">But the one who enters through the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For this one the doorkeeper opens, and the sheep hear his voice, and he calls his own sheep by name and leads them out.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Whenever he sends out all his own, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him because they know his voice.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And they will never follow a stranger, but will flee from him, because they do not know the voice of strangers."</verse>
    <verse num="6">Jesus told them this parable, but they did not understand what it was that he was saying to them. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Then Jesus said to them<note>Some manuscripts omit "to them"</note> again, "Truly, truly, I say to you, I am the door of the sheep.</verse>
    <verse num="8">All those who came before me are thieves and robbers, but the sheep do not listen to them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">I am the door. If anyone enters through me, he will be saved, and will come in and will go out and will find pasture.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The thief {comes only}<note>Literally "does not come except"</note> so that he can steal and kill and destroy; I have come so that they may have life, and have <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> abundantly. </verse>
    <verse num="11">"I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The hired hand, who is not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, sees the wolf approaching and abandons the sheep and runs away--and the wolf seizes them and scatters <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note>--</verse>
    <verse num="13">because he is a hired hand and {he is not concerned}<note>Literally "it is not a concern to him"</note> about the sheep. </verse>
    <verse num="14">"I am the good shepherd, and I know my <transChange type="added">own</transChange>, and my <transChange type="added">own</transChange> know me,</verse>
    <verse num="15">just as the Father knows me and I know the Father, and I lay down my life for the sheep.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And I have other sheep which are not from this fold. I must bring these also, and they will hear my voice, and they will become one flock--one shepherd.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Because of this the Father loves me, because I lay down my life so that I may take possession of it again.</verse>
    <verse num="18">No one takes it from me, but I lay it down {voluntarily}.<note>Literally "from myself"</note> I have authority to lay it down, and I have authority to take possession of it again. This commandment I received from my Father." </verse>
    <verse num="19">Again there was a division among the Jews because of these words.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And many of them were saying, "He has a demon and is out of his mind! Why do you listen to him?"</verse>
    <verse num="21">Others were saying, "These are not the words of one who is possessed by a demon! A demon is not able to open the eyes of the blind, <transChange type="added">is it</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">is it</transChange>"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="22">Then the feast of the Dedication took place in Jerusalem. It was winter,</verse>
    <verse num="23">and Jesus was walking in the temple in the Portico of Solomon.</verse>
    <verse num="24">So the Jews surrounded him and began to say<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> to him, "{How long will you keep us in suspense}?<note>Literally "until when will you take away our life"</note> If you are the Christ, tell us plainly!"</verse>
    <verse num="25">Jesus answered them, "I told you and you do not believe! The deeds that I do in the name of my Father, these testify about me.</verse>
    <verse num="26">But you do not believe, because you are not of my sheep!</verse>
    <verse num="27">My sheep listen to my voice, and I know them, and they follow me.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And I give them eternal life, and they will never perish {forever},<note>Literally "for the age"</note> and no one will seize them out of my hand.</verse>
    <verse num="29">My Father, who has given <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to me, is greater than all, and no one can seize <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> from the Father's hand.</verse>
    <verse num="30">The Father and I are one." </verse>
    <verse num="31">Then<note>Some manuscripts omit "Then"</note> the Jews picked up stones again so that they could stone him.</verse>
    <verse num="32">Jesus answered them, "I have shown you many good deeds from the Father. For which one of them are you going to stone me?"</verse>
    <verse num="33">The Jews answered him, "We are not going to stone you concerning a good deed, but concerning blasphemy, and because you, <transChange type="added">although you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as concessive</note> are a man, make yourself <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> God!"</verse>
    <verse num="34">Jesus answered them, "Is it not written in your law, 'I said, "You are gods" '?<note>A quotation from Ps 82:6 (in common usage "law" could refer to the entire Old Testament)</note></verse>
    <verse num="35">If he called them 'gods' to whom the word of God came--and the scripture cannot be broken--</verse>
    <verse num="36">do you say about <transChange type="added">he</transChange> whom the Father set apart and sent into the world, 'You are blaspheming,' because I said, 'I am the Son of God'?</verse>
    <verse num="37">If I do not do the deeds of my Father, do not believe me.</verse>
    <verse num="38">But if I am doing <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> even if you do not believe me, believe the deeds, so that you may know and understand that the Father <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in me and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in the Father."</verse>
    <verse num="39">So they were seeking again to seize him, and he departed out of their hand. </verse>
    <verse num="40">And he went away again on the other side of the Jordan, to the place where John was baptizing at an earlier time, and he stayed there.</verse>
    <verse num="41">And many came to him and began to say,<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began to say")</note> "John performed no sign, but everything John said about this man was true!"</verse>
    <verse num="42">And many believed in him there. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Now a certain man was sick, Lazarus from Bethany, the village of Mary and her sister Martha.</verse>
    <verse num="2">(Now it was Mary who anointed the Lord with perfumed oil and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.)</verse>
    <verse num="3">So the sisters sent <transChange type="added">word</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him, saying, "Lord, behold, <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom you love is sick."</verse>
    <verse num="4">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> Jesus said, "This sickness is not to death, but for the glory of God, in order that the Son of God may be glorified through it."</verse>
    <verse num="5">(Now Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Lazarus.)</verse>
    <verse num="6">So when he heard that he was sick, then he remained in the place {where}<note>Literally "in which"</note> he was two days. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Then after this he said to the disciples, "Let us go to Judea again."</verse>
    <verse num="8">The disciples said to him, "Rabbi, the Jews were seeking just now to stone you, and are you going there again?"</verse>
    <verse num="9">Jesus replied, Are <transChange type="added">there</transChange> not twelve hours in the day? If anyone walks around in the daylight, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But if anyone walks around in the night, he stumbles, because the light is not in him.</verse>
    <verse num="11">He said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and after this he said to them, "Our friend Lazarus has fallen asleep, but I am going so that I can awaken him."</verse>
    <verse num="12">So the disciples said to him, "Lord, if he has fallen asleep, he will get well."</verse>
    <verse num="13">(Now Jesus had been speaking about his death, but they thought that he was speaking about {real sleep}.<note>Literally "the sleep of slumber"</note>)</verse>
    <verse num="14">So Jesus then said to them plainly, "Lazarus has died,</verse>
    <verse num="15">and I am glad {for your sake}<note>Literally "for the sake of you"</note> that I was not there, so that you may believe. But let us go to him."</verse>
    <verse num="16">Then Thomas (the one who is called Didymus)<note>"Didymus" means "the twin" in Greek</note> said to his fellow disciples, "Let us go also, so that we may die with him." </verse>
    <verse num="17">So <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("arrived") which is understood as temporal</note> arrived, Jesus found he had already <transChange type="added">been</transChange> four days in the tomb.</verse>
    <verse num="18">(Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia.<note>A "stade" or "stadium" (plur. "stadia") is about 607 ft (187 m), so this was just under two miles (3 km)</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">So many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary in order to console them concerning their<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> brother.)</verse>
    <verse num="20">Now Martha, when she heard that Jesus was coming, went to meet him, but Mary was sitting in the house.</verse>
    <verse num="21">So Martha said to Jesus, "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Even<note>Some manuscripts have "But even"</note> now I know that whatever you ask God, God will grant you."</verse>
    <verse num="23">Jesus said to her, "Your brother will rise again."</verse>
    <verse num="24">Martha said to him, "I know that he will rise again in the resurrection at the last day."</verse>
    <verse num="25">Jesus said to her, "I am the resurrection and the life. The one who believes in me, even if he dies, will live,</verse>
    <verse num="26">and everyone who lives and believes in me will never die {forever}.<note>Literally "for the age"</note> Do you believe this?"</verse>
    <verse num="27">She said to him, "Yes, Lord, I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of God, who comes into the world." </verse>
    <verse num="28">And <transChange type="added">when she</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, she went and called her sister Mary privately, saying, "The Teacher is here and is calling for you."</verse>
    <verse num="29">So that one, when she heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> got up quickly and went to him.</verse>
    <verse num="30">(Now Jesus has not yet come into the village, but was still in the place where Martha went to meet him.)</verse>
    <verse num="31">So the Jews who were with her in the house and were consoling her, <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as temporal</note> saw Mary--that she stood up quickly and went out--followed her, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("thought") which is understood as causal</note> thought that she was going to the tomb in order to weep there. </verse>
    <verse num="32">Then Mary, when she came where Jesus was <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the participle ("saw") has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> saw him, fell at his feet, saying to him, "Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died."</verse>
    <verse num="33">Then Jesus, when he saw her weeping and the Jews who came with her weeping, was deeply moved in spirit and was troubled within himself.</verse>
    <verse num="34">And he said, "Where have you laid him?" They said to him, "Lord, come and see."</verse>
    <verse num="35">Jesus wept.</verse>
    <verse num="36">So the Jews were saying, "See how he loved him!"</verse>
    <verse num="37">But some of them said, "Was not this man who opened the eyes of the blind able to do <transChange type="added">something</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that this man also would not have died?" </verse>
    <verse num="38">Then Jesus, deeply moved within himself again, came to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone was lying on it.</verse>
    <verse num="39">Jesus said, "Take away the stone." Martha, the sister of the one who had died, said to him, "Lord, he is stinking already, because it has been four days."</verse>
    <verse num="40">Jesus said to her, "Did I not say to you that if you believed, you would see the glory of God?"</verse>
    <verse num="41">So they took away the stone. And Jesus lifted up his<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> eyes above and said, "Father, I give thanks to you that you hear me.</verse>
    <verse num="42">And I know that you always hear me, but for the sake of the crowd standing around I said <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that they may believe that you sent me."</verse>
    <verse num="43">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, he cried out with a loud voice, "Lazarus, come out!"</verse>
    <verse num="44">The one who had died came out, his<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet and his<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands bound with strips of cloth, and his face wrapped with a facecloth. Jesus said to them, "Untie him and let him go." </verse>
    <verse num="45">Then many of the Jews who had come with Mary and saw <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which he did believed in him.</verse>
    <verse num="46">But some of them went to the Pharisees and told them <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which Jesus had done.</verse>
    <verse num="47">So the chief priests and the Pharisees called together the Sanhedrin and said, "What are we doing? For this man is performing many signs!</verse>
    <verse num="48">If we allow him <transChange type="added">to go on</transChange> in this way, everyone will believe in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place<note>Generally understood to be a reference to the Jerusalem temple</note> and our<note>Literally "both the place and the nation of us"; the possessive pronoun is repeated in the translation (rather than the article) in keeping with English style</note> nation." </verse>
    <verse num="49">But a certain one of them, Caiaphas (who was high priest in that year), said to them, "You do not know anything at all!</verse>
    <verse num="50">Nor do you consider that it is profitable for you that one man should die for the people, and the whole nation not perish."</verse>
    <verse num="51">(Now he did not say this from himself, but being high priest in that year, he prophesied that Jesus was going to die for the nation,</verse>
    <verse num="52">and not for the nation only, but also that the children of God who are scattered would be gathered into one.)</verse>
    <verse num="53">So from that day they resolved that they should kill him.</verse>
    <verse num="54">So Jesus was no longer walking openly among the Jews, but went away from there to the region near the wilderness, to a city called Ephraim, and there he stayed with the disciples. </verse>
    <verse num="55">Now the Passover of the Jews was near, and many went up to Jerusalem from the <transChange type="added">surrounding</transChange> country before the Passover, so that they could purify themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="56">So they were looking for Jesus, and were speaking with one another <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("standing") which is understood as temporal</note> standing in the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange>,<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> "What do you think? That he will not come to the feast?"</verse>
    <verse num="57">(Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had given orders that if anyone knew where he was, they should report <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in order that they could arrest him.) </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">Then, six days before the Passover, Jesus came to Bethany, where Lazarus was, whom Jesus had raised from the dead.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So they made him a dinner there, and Martha was serving, but Lazarus was one of the ones reclining at table with him.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then Mary took a pound<note>The Greek term refers to a Roman pound, 327.45 grams (approximately 12 ounces)</note> of ointment of very valuable genuine nard <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("took") has been translated as a finite verb</note> anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped his feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the fragrance of the ointment.</verse>
    <verse num="4">But Judas Iscariot, one of his disciples (the one who was going to betray him) said,</verse>
    <verse num="5">"{Why}<note>Literally "because of what"</note> was this ointment not sold for three hundred denarii and given to the poor?"</verse>
    <verse num="6">(Now he said this not because {he was concerned}<note>Literally "it was a concern to him"</note> about the poor, but because he was a thief, and having the money box, he used to steal what was put into <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.)<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">So Jesus said, "Leave her alone, so that she may keep it for the day of my preparation for burial.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For you have the poor with you always, but you do not always have me." </verse>
    <verse num="9">Now a large crowd<note>Some manuscripts have "the large crowd"</note> of Jews found out that he was there, and they came, not only because of Jesus, but so that they could see Lazarus also, whom he raised from the dead.</verse>
    <verse num="10">So the chief priests decided that they would kill Lazarus also,</verse>
    <verse num="11">because on account of him many of the Jews were going and believing in Jesus. </verse>
    <verse num="12">On the next day the large crowd who had come to the feast, <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem,</verse>
    <verse num="13">took the branches of palm trees and went out to meet him, and began crying out, </verse>
    <verse num="14">So Jesus found a young donkey <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("found") has been translated as a finite verb</note> sat on it, just as it is written, </verse>
    <verse num="15">"Do not be afraid, daughter of Zion! Behold, your king is coming, seated on the foal of a donkey!"<note>A quotation from Zech 9:9</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">(His disciples did not understand these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> at first, but when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> had been written about him and they did these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to him.)</verse>
    <verse num="17">So the crowd who was with him when he called Lazarus out of the tomb and raised him from the dead were continuing to testify.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Because of this also the crowd went to meet him, for they had heard <transChange type="added">that</transChange> he had performed this sign.</verse>
    <verse num="19">So the Pharisees said to one another, "You see that you are accomplishing nothing! Behold, the world has gone after him." </verse>
    <verse num="20">Now some Greeks were among those who had gone up in order to worship at the feast.</verse>
    <verse num="21">So these approached Philip, who was from Bethsaida in Galilee, and began asking him saying, "Sir, we want to see Jesus."</verse>
    <verse num="22">Philip went and told Andrew. Andrew and Philip went and told Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Jesus answered them, saying, "The hour has come that the Son of Man will be glorified.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Truly, truly I say to you, unless a grain of wheat falls into the earth <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("falls") has been translated as a finite verb</note> dies, it remains <transChange type="added">by</transChange> itself alone. But if it dies, it bears much fruit.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The one who loves his life loses it, and the one who hates his life in this world preserves it for eternal life.</verse>
    <verse num="26">If anyone serves me, he must follow me, and where I am, there my servant will be also. If anyone serves me, the Father will honor him. </verse>
    <verse num="27">"Now my soul is troubled, and what shall I say? 'Father, deliver me from this hour'? But for this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> I have come to this hour!</verse>
    <verse num="28">Father, glorify your name!" Then a voice came from heaven, "I have both glorified <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and I will glorify <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> again."</verse>
    <verse num="29">Now the crowd that stood <transChange type="added">there</transChange> and heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> said {it had thundered}.<note>Literally "thunder had happened"</note> Others were saying, "An angel has spoken to him!"</verse>
    <verse num="30">Jesus answered and said, "This voice has not happened for my sake, but <transChange type="added">for</transChange> your sake.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Now is the judgment of this world! Now the ruler of this world will be thrown out!</verse>
    <verse num="32">And I, when I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all <transChange type="added">people</transChange> to myself."</verse>
    <verse num="33">(Now he said this to indicate by what sort of death he was going to die.) </verse>
    <verse num="34">Then the crowd replied to him, "We have heard from the law that the Christ remains {forever}!<note>Literally "for the age"; probably an allusion to Ps 89:35-37 (in common usage "law" could refer to the entire Old Testament)</note> And how do you say that the Son of Man must be lifted up? Who is this Son of Man?"</verse>
    <verse num="35">So Jesus said to them, "Yet a little time the light is with you! Walk while you have the light, so that the darkness does not overtake you! And the one who walks in the darkness does not know where he is going.</verse>
    <verse num="36">While you have the light, believe in the light, in order that you may become sons of light." Jesus said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and <transChange type="added">then</transChange> he went away <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("went away") has been translated as a finite verb</note> was hidden from them. </verse>
    <verse num="37">But as many signs <transChange type="added">as</transChange> he had performed before them, they did not believe in him,</verse>
    <verse num="38">in order that the word of the prophet Isaiah would be fulfilled, who said, </verse>
    <verse num="39">For this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> they were not able to believe, because again Isaiah said, </verse>
    <verse num="40">"He has blinded their eyes and hardened their hearts, lest they see with <transChange type="added">their</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> eyes and understand with <transChange type="added">their</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hearts and turn, and I heal them."<note>A quotation from Isa 6:10</note></verse>
    <verse num="41">Isaiah said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> because he saw his glory, and he spoke about him. </verse>
    <verse num="42">Yet despite that, even many of the rulers believed in him, but because of the Pharisees they did not confess <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so that they would not be expelled from the synagogue.</verse>
    <verse num="43">For they loved the praise of men more than praise from God. </verse>
    <verse num="44">But Jesus cried out and said, "The one who believes in me does not believe in me, but in the one who sent me,</verse>
    <verse num="45">and the one who sees me sees the one who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="46">I have come <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a light into the world, in order that everyone who believes in me will not remain in the darkness.</verse>
    <verse num="47">And if anyone hears my words and does not observe <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> I will not judge him. For I have not come to judge the world, but to save the world.</verse>
    <verse num="48">The one who rejects me and does not accept my words has one who judges him; the word that I have spoken will judge him on the last day.</verse>
    <verse num="49">For I have not spoken from myself, but the Father himself who sent me {has commanded me}<note>Literally "has given me commandment"</note> what I should say and what I should speak.</verse>
    <verse num="50">And I know that his commandment is eternal life. So <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> that I say, just as the Father said to me, thus I say." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">Now before the feast of Passover, Jesus, knowing that his hour had come that he would depart from this world to the Father, <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied in keeping with English style</note> having loved <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> own in the world, loved them to the end.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And <transChange type="added">as</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was taking place")</note> a dinner was taking place, <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("put")</note> the devil had already put into the heart of Judas <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of Simon Iscariot that he should betray him,</verse>
    <verse num="3"><transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew that the Father had given him all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> into <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands, and that he had come forth from God and was going away to God,</verse>
    <verse num="4">he got up from the dinner and took off <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> outer clothing, and taking a towel, tied <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> around himself.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then he poured water into the washbasin and began to wash the feet of the disciples, and to wipe <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> dry with the towel {which he had tied around himself}.<note>Literally "with which he was girded"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="6">Then he came to Simon Peter. He said to him, "Lord, are you going to wash my feet?"</verse>
    <verse num="7">Jesus answered and said to him, "What I am doing you do not understand now, but you will understand after these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="8">Peter said to him, "You will never wash my feet {forever}!"<note>Literally "for the age"</note> Jesus replied to him, "Unless I wash you, you do not have a share with me."</verse>
    <verse num="9">Simon Peter said to him, "Lord, not my feet only, but also <transChange type="added">my</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands and <transChange type="added">my</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> head!"</verse>
    <verse num="10">Jesus said to him, "The one who has bathed {only needs}<note>Literally "does not have need except"</note> to wash <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> feet, but is completely clean. And you are clean, but not all <transChange type="added">of you</transChange>."</verse>
    <verse num="11">(For he knew the one who would betray him; because of this he said, "Not all <transChange type="added">of you</transChange> are clean.") </verse>
    <verse num="12">So when he had washed their feet and taken his outer clothing and reclined at table again, he said to them, "Do you understand what I have done for you?</verse>
    <verse num="13">You call me 'Teacher' and 'Lord,' and you speak correctly, for I am.</verse>
    <verse num="14">If then I--<transChange type="added">your</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> Lord and Teacher--wash your feet, you also ought to wash one another's feet.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For I have given you an example, that just as I have done for you, you also do.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Truly, truly I say to you, a slave is not greater than his master, nor a messenger greater than the one who sent him.</verse>
    <verse num="17">If you understand these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, you are blessed if you do them. </verse>
    <verse num="18">"I am not speaking about all of you. I know whom I have chosen, but in order that the scripture would be fulfilled, 'The one who eats my bread has lifted up his heel against me.'<note>A quotation from Ps 41:9</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">From now <transChange type="added">on</transChange> I am telling you before <transChange type="added">it</transChange> happens, in order that when <transChange type="added">it</transChange> happens you may believe that I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>.<note>*Here the predicate nominative ("<transChange type="added">he</transChange>") is understood, but must be supplied in the translation</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">Truly, truly I say to you, the one who receives anyone I send receives me, and the one who receives me receives the one who sent me." </verse>
    <verse num="21"><transChange type="added">When he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, Jesus was troubled in spirit and testified and said, "Truly, truly I say to you that one of you will betray me."</verse>
    <verse num="22">The disciples began looking<note>*The imperfect tense has been translated as ingressive here ("began looking")</note> at one another, uncertain about whom he was speaking.</verse>
    <verse num="23">One of his disciples--the one whom Jesus loved--was reclining {close beside}<note>Literally "in the bosom of" (a position dictated by ancient banqueting practice)</note> Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="24">So Simon Peter gestured for this one to inquire who it was about whom he was speaking.</verse>
    <verse num="25">He leaned back<note>Some manuscripts have "Then he leaned back"</note> accordingly against Jesus' chest <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("leaned back") has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, "Lord, who is it?"</verse>
    <verse num="26">Jesus replied, "It is he to whom I dip the piece of bread and give <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to him." Then <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("dipping") which is understood as temporal</note> dipping the piece of bread, he gave <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note><note>Some manuscripts have "after dipping the piece of bread, he took <transChange type="added">it</transChange> and gave <transChange type="added">it</transChange>"</note> to Judas <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of Simon Iscariot.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And after the piece of bread, then Satan entered into him. Then Jesus said to him, "What you are doing, do quickly!"</verse>
    <verse num="28">(Now no one of those reclining at table knew for what <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> he said this to him.</verse>
    <verse num="29">For some were thinking because Judas had the money box, Jesus was telling him, "Purchase {what we need}<note>Literally "of which we have need"</note> for the feast," or that he should give something to the poor.)</verse>
    <verse num="30">So <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had taken") which is understood as temporal</note> had taken the piece of bread, he went out immediately. And it was night. </verse>
    <verse num="31">Then, when he had gone out, Jesus said, "Now the Son of Man is glorified, and God is glorified in him.</verse>
    <verse num="32">If God is glorified in him, God will also glorify him in himself, and will glorify him immediately.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Children, yet a little <transChange type="added">time</transChange> I am with you. You will seek me and just as I said to the Jews, "Where I am going you cannot come," now I say also to you. </verse>
    <verse num="34">"A new commandment I give to you: that you love one another--just as I have loved you, that you also love one another.</verse>
    <verse num="35">By this everyone will know that you are my disciples--if you have love for one another." </verse>
    <verse num="36">Simon Peter said to him, "Lord, where are you going?" Jesus replied,<note>Some manuscripts have "replied to him"</note> "Where I am going you cannot follow me now, but you will follow later."</verse>
    <verse num="37">Peter said to him, "Lord, why am I not able to follow you now? I will lay down my life for you!"</verse>
    <verse num="38">Jesus replied, "Will you lay down your life for me? Truly, truly I say to you, the rooster will not crow until you have denied me three times! </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">"Do not let your hearts be troubled. You believe<note>Or simply "Believe"; the verb form can be either indicative (e.g., KJV, NAB, NLT) or imperative (e.g., NIV, NRSV, ESV)</note> in God; believe<note>Like the previous verb "believe" this form could also be either indicative or imperative, though most English versions regard it as imperative</note> also in me.</verse>
    <verse num="2">In my Father's house there are many dwelling places; but if not, I would have told you, because<note>A large number of manuscripts, many of them later, lack "because"</note> I am going away to prepare a place for you.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again and receive you to myself, so that where I am, you may be also.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And you know the way where I am going." </verse>
    <verse num="5">Thomas said to him, "Lord, we do not know where you are going. How are we able to know the way?"</verse>
    <verse num="6">Jesus said to him, "I am the way, and the truth, and the life. No one comes to the Father except through me.</verse>
    <verse num="7">If you had known me, you would have known<note>Some manuscripts have "If you have known me, you will know"</note> my Father also. From now on<note>Some manuscripts have "And from now on"</note> you know him and have seen him." </verse>
    <verse num="8">Philip said to him, "Lord, show us the Father, and it is enough for us."</verse>
    <verse num="9">Jesus said to him, "Am I with you so long a time and you have not known me, Philip? The one who has seen me has seen the Father! How can you say, 'Show us the Father?'</verse>
    <verse num="10">Do you not believe that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in the Father and the Father is in me? The words that I say to you I do not speak from myself, but the Father residing in me does his works.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Believe me that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in the Father and the Father <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in me; but if not, believe because of the works themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Truly, truly I say to you, the one who believes in me, the works that I am doing he will do also, and he will do greater <transChange type="added">works</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> than these because I am going to the Father.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And {whatever}<note>Literally "anything which"</note> you ask in my name, I will do this, in order that the Father may be glorified in the Son.</verse>
    <verse num="14">If you ask me anything in my name, I will do <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> </verse>
    <verse num="15">"If you love me, you will keep my commandments.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And I will ask the Father, and he will give you another Advocate, in order that he may be with you {forever}<note>Literally "for the age"</note>--</verse>
    <verse num="17">the Spirit of truth, whom the world is not able to receive, because it does not see him or know <transChange type="added">him</transChange>.<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> You know him, because he resides with you and will be in you. </verse>
    <verse num="18">"I will not leave you <transChange type="added">as</transChange> orphans; I am coming to you.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Yet a little <transChange type="added">time</transChange> and the world will see me no longer, but you will see me; because I live, you also will live.</verse>
    <verse num="20">On that day you will know that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in my Father, and you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in me, and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in you.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The one who has my commandments and keeps them--that one is the one who loves me. And the one who loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him and will reveal myself to him." </verse>
    <verse num="22">Judas (not Iscariot) said to him, "Lord, why<note>Some manuscripts have "and why"</note> is it that you are going to reveal yourself to us and not to the world?"</verse>
    <verse num="23">Jesus answered and said to him, "If anyone loves me he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him and {will take up residence with him}.<note>Literally "will make abode with him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">The one who does not love me does not keep my words, and the word that you hear is not mine, but the Father's who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="25">These <transChange type="added">things</transChange> I have spoken to you <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("residing") which is understood as temporal</note> residing with you.</verse>
    <verse num="26">But the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name--that one will teach you all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and will remind you of everything that I said to you. </verse>
    <verse num="27">"Peace I leave with you; my peace I give to you--not as the world gives, I give to you. Do not let your hearts be troubled, and do not let <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> be afraid.</verse>
    <verse num="28">You have heard that I said to you, 'I am going away, and I am coming to you.' If you loved me, you would have rejoiced that I am going to the Father, because the Father is greater than I <transChange type="added">am</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And now I have told you before <transChange type="added">it</transChange> happens, so that when it happens, you may believe.</verse>
    <verse num="30">I will no longer speak much with you, for the ruler of the world is coming, and he has {no power}<note>Literally "nothing"</note> {over}<note>Literally "in"</note> me.</verse>
    <verse num="31">But so that the world may know that I love the Father, and just as the Father has commanded me, thus I am doing. Get up, let us go from here! </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">"I am the true vine, and my Father is the vinedresser.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Every branch that does not bear fruit in me, he removes it, and every <transChange type="added">branch</transChange> that bears fruit, he prunes it in order that it may bear more fruit.</verse>
    <verse num="3">You are already clean because of the word that I have spoken to you.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Remain in me, and I in you. Just as the branch is not able to bear fruit from itself unless it remains in the vine, so neither <transChange type="added">can</transChange> you, unless you remain in me. </verse>
    <verse num="5">"I am the vine; you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the branches. The one who remains in me and I in him--this one bears much fruit, for apart from me you are not able to do anything.</verse>
    <verse num="6">If anyone does not remain in me, he is thrown out as a branch, and dries up, and they gather them and throw <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into the fire, and they are burned.</verse>
    <verse num="7">If you remain in me and my words remain in you, ask whatever you want and it will be done for you.</verse>
    <verse num="8">My Father is glorified by this: that you bear much fruit, and prove to be my disciples. </verse>
    <verse num="9">"Just as the Father has loved me, I also have loved you. Remain in my love.</verse>
    <verse num="10">If you keep my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have kept my Father's commandments and remain in his love.</verse>
    <verse num="11">I have spoken these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you in order that my joy may be in you, and your joy may be made complete.</verse>
    <verse num="12">This is my commandment: that you love one another just as I have loved you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">No one has greater love than this: that someone lay down his life for his friends.</verse>
    <verse num="14">You are my friends if you do what I command you.</verse>
    <verse num="15">No longer do I call you slaves, because the slave does not know what his master is doing. But I have called you friends, because everything that I have heard from my Father I have revealed to you.</verse>
    <verse num="16">You did not choose me, but I chose you and appointed you that you should go and bear fruit, and your fruit should remain, in order that whatever you ask the Father in my name he will give you.</verse>
    <verse num="17">These <transChange type="added">things</transChange> I command you: that you love one another. </verse>
    <verse num="18">If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before <transChange type="added">it hated</transChange><note>*Here the verb "<transChange type="added">hated</transChange>" is an understood repetition of the verb earlier in this verse</note> you.</verse>
    <verse num="19">If you were of the world, the world would love its own. But because you are not of the world, but I chose you out of the world, for this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> the world hates you.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Remember the word that I said to you: 'A slave is not greater than his master.' If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you. If they kept my word, they will keep yours also.</verse>
    <verse num="21">But they will do all these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you on account of my name, because they do not know the one who sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="22">If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not have sin. But now they do not have a valid excuse for their sin.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The one who hates me hates my Father also.</verse>
    <verse num="24">If I had not done among them the works that no one else did, they would not have sin. But now they have both seen and hated both me and my Father.</verse>
    <verse num="25">But <transChange type="added">this happened</transChange><note>*The phrase "<transChange type="added">this happened</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> so that the word that is written in their law would be fulfilled, 'They hated me without a reason.' </verse>
    <verse num="26">"When the Advocate comes, whom I will send to you from the Father--the Spirit of truth, who proceeds from the Father--that one will testify about me.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And you also will testify, because you have been with me from the beginning. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">"I have said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you so that you will not fall away.</verse>
    <verse num="2">{They will expel you from the synagogue},<note>Literally "they will make you expelled from the synagogue"</note> but an hour is coming that everyone who kills you will think they are offering service to God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And they will do these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> because they do not know the Father or me.</verse>
    <verse num="4">But I have said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you so that when their hour comes, you may remember that I told you about them. </verse>
    <verse num="5">But now I am going away to the one who sent me, and none of you is asking me, 'Where are you going?'</verse>
    <verse num="6">But because I have said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you, sorrow has filled your hearts.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But I tell you the truth, it is better for you that I go away. For if I do not go away, the Advocate will not come to you; but if I go, I will send him to you.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("comes") which is understood as temporal</note> comes, he will convict the world concerning sin and concerning righteousness and concerning judgment:</verse>
    <verse num="9">concerning sin, because they do not believe in me,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and concerning righteousness, because I am going away to the Father and you will see me no more,</verse>
    <verse num="11">and concerning judgment, because the ruler of this world has been condemned. </verse>
    <verse num="12">I still have many <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to say to you, but you are not able to bear <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> now.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But when he--the Spirit of truth--comes, he will guide you into all the truth. For he will not speak from himself, but whatever he hears he will speak, and he will proclaim to you the things to come.</verse>
    <verse num="14">He will glorify me, because he will take from what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> mine and will proclaim <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Everything that the Father has is mine. For this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> I said that he takes from what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> mine and will proclaim <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you. </verse>
    <verse num="16">"A little <transChange type="added">while</transChange> and you will see me no more, and again a little <transChange type="added">while</transChange> and you will see me.</verse>
    <verse num="17">So some of his disciples said to one another, "What is this that he is saying to us, 'A little <transChange type="added">while</transChange> and you will not see me, and again a little <transChange type="added">while</transChange> and you will see me,' and 'Because I am going away to the Father'?"</verse>
    <verse num="18">So they kept on saying, "What is this that he is saying, 'A little <transChange type="added">while</transChange>'? We do not understand what he is speaking about!" </verse>
    <verse num="19">Jesus knew that they were wanting to ask him, and he said to them, "Are you deliberating with one another about this--that I said, 'A little <transChange type="added">while</transChange>, and you will not see me, and again a little <transChange type="added">while</transChange> and you will see me'?</verse>
    <verse num="20">Truly, truly I say to you, that you will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice; you will become sorrowful, but your sorrow will change to joy.</verse>
    <verse num="21">A woman, when she gives birth, experiences pain because her hour has come. But when <transChange type="added">her</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> child is born, she no longer remembers the affliction, on account of the joy that a human being has been born into the world.</verse>
    <verse num="22">So you also are experiencing sorrow now, but I will see you again, and your hearts will rejoice, and no one will take away your joy from you.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And on that day you will ask me nothing. Truly, truly I say to you, whatever you ask the Father in my name, he will give you.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Until now you have asked nothing in my name. Ask and you will receive, so that your joy may be complete. </verse>
    <verse num="25">"I have said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you in figurative sayings. An hour is coming when I will speak to you in figurative sayings no longer, but I will tell you plainly about the Father.</verse>
    <verse num="26">On that day you will ask in my name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father on your behalf.</verse>
    <verse num="27">For the Father himself loves you, because you have loved me and have believed that I came from God.</verse>
    <verse num="28">I have gone out from the Father and have come into the world; again, I am leaving the world and am going to the Father." </verse>
    <verse num="29">His disciples said, "Behold, now you are speaking {plainly}<note>Literally "with plainness"</note> and are telling <transChange type="added">us</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> no figurative saying!</verse>
    <verse num="30">Now we know that you know everything and do not {need for}<note>Literally "have need that"</note> anyone to ask you <transChange type="added">questions</transChange>.<note>*Here the word "<transChange type="added">questions</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> By this we believe that you have come from God." </verse>
    <verse num="31">Jesus replied to them, "Now do you believe?</verse>
    <verse num="32">Behold, an hour is coming--and has come--that you will be scattered each one to his own <transChange type="added">home</transChange>,<note>Or "to his own things"; or "to his own people" (i.e., family); the Greek text is somewhat ambiguous here</note> and you will leave me alone. And I am not alone, because the Father is with me.</verse>
    <verse num="33">I have said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to you so that in me you may have peace. In the world you have affliction, but have courage! I have conquered the world." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">Jesus said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and lifting up his eyes to heaven he said, "Father, the hour has come! Glorify your Son, in order that your Son may glorify you--</verse>
    <verse num="2">just as you have given him authority over all flesh, in order that he would give eternal life to them--everyone whom you have given him.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Now this is eternal life: that they know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent.</verse>
    <verse num="4">I have glorified you on earth <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("completing") which is understood as means</note> completing the work that you have given me {to do}.<note>Literally "that I may do it"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">And now, Father, you glorify me {at your side}<note>Literally "by the side of yourself"</note> with the glory that I had {at your side}<note>Literally "by the side of you"</note> before the world existed. </verse>
    <verse num="6">"I have revealed your name to the men whom you gave me out of the world. They were yours, and you have given them to me, and they have kept your word.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Now they understand that all <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> that<note>Literally "whatever"</note> you have given me are from you,</verse>
    <verse num="8">because the words that you gave to me I have given to them, and they received <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and know truly that I have come from you, and they have believed that you have sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="9">I am asking on behalf of them. I am not asking on behalf of the world, but on behalf of those whom you have given me, because they are yours,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and all my <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are yours, and your <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> mine, and I have been glorified in<note>Or "by"; or "through"</note> them.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And I am no longer in the world, and they are in the world, and I am coming to you. Holy Father, keep them in your name, which you have given to me, so that they may be one, just as we <transChange type="added">are</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="12">When I was with them, I kept them in your name, which you have given to me, and guarded <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and none of them has perished except the son of destruction, in order that the scripture would be fulfilled.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And now I am coming to you, and I am saying these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in the world so that they may have my joy completed in themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="14">I have given them your word, and the world has hated them, because they are not of the world just as I am not of the world.</verse>
    <verse num="15">I do not ask that you take them out of the world, but that you protect them from the evil one.</verse>
    <verse num="16">They are not of the world, just as I am not of the world.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Sanctify them in the truth--your word is truth.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Just as you sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And for them I sanctify myself, so that <transChange type="added">they</transChange> themselves also may be sanctified in the truth. </verse>
    <verse num="20">"And I do not ask on behalf of these only, but also on behalf of those who believe in me through their word,</verse>
    <verse num="21">that they all may be one, just as you, Father, <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in me and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in you, that they also may be in us, in order that the world may believe that you sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And the glory that you have given to me, I have given to them, in order that they may be one, just as we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> one--</verse>
    <verse num="23">I in them, and you in me, in order that they may be completed in one, so that the world may know that you sent me, and you have loved them just as you have loved me. </verse>
    <verse num="24">"Father, <transChange type="added">those</transChange> whom you have given to me--I want that those also may be with me where I am, in order that they may see my glory that you have given me because you loved me before the foundation of the world.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Righteous Father, although the world does not know you, yet I have known you, and these <transChange type="added">men</transChange> have come to know that you sent me.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And I made known to them your name, and will make <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> known, in order that the love <transChange type="added">with</transChange> which you loved me may be in them, and I <transChange type="added">may be</transChange> in them." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1"><transChange type="added">When</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> Jesus had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, he went out with his disciples to the other side of the ravine of the Kidron, where <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was a garden into which he and his disciples entered.</verse>
    <verse num="2">(Now Judas, the one who betrayed him, also knew about the place, because Jesus often gathered there with his disciples.)</verse>
    <verse num="3">So Judas, taking the cohort and officers from the chief priests and from the Pharisees, came there with lanterns and torches and weapons.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then Jesus, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew all the things that were coming upon him, went out and said to them, "Who are you looking for?"</verse>
    <verse num="5">They replied to him, "Jesus the Nazarene." He said to them, "I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>."<note>*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> (Now Judas, the one who betrayed him, was also standing with them.)</verse>
    <verse num="6">So when he said to them, "I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>,"<note>*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> {they drew back}<note>Literally "they went to the back"</note> and fell to the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then he asked them again, "Who are you looking for?" And they said, "Jesus the Nazarene."</verse>
    <verse num="8">Jesus replied, "I said to you that I am <transChange type="added">he</transChange>!<note>*Here the predicate nominative is supplied from context in the English translation</note> So if you are looking for me, let these <transChange type="added">men</transChange> go,"</verse>
    <verse num="9">in order that the word that he had spoken would be fulfilled: "Those whom you have given to me--I have not lost anyone of them."<note>A paraphrase of the statement in John 17:12</note> </verse>
    <verse num="10">Then Simon Peter, who had a sword, drew it and struck the slave of the high priest and cut off his right ear. (Now the name of the slave was Malchus.)</verse>
    <verse num="11">So Jesus said to Peter, "Put the sword into <transChange type="added">its</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> sheath! The cup that the Father has given me--shall I not drink it?" </verse>
    <verse num="12">Then the cohort and the military tribune and the officers of the Jews seized Jesus and tied him up,</verse>
    <verse num="13">and brought <transChange type="added">him</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to Annas first, for he was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, who was high priest that year.</verse>
    <verse num="14">(Now it was Caiaphas who had advised the Jews that it was better <transChange type="added">that</transChange> one man die for the people.) </verse>
    <verse num="15">So Simon Peter and another disciple followed Jesus. (Now that disciple was known to the high priest, and entered with Jesus into the courtyard of the high priest.)</verse>
    <verse num="16">But Peter was standing by the door outside. So the other disciple <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> known to the high priest went out and spoke to the doorkeeper and brought Peter in.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Then the female slave <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> the doorkeeper said to Peter, "You are not also <transChange type="added">one</transChange> of the disciples of this man, <transChange type="added">are you</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">are you</transChange>"</note> He said, "I am not!"</verse>
    <verse num="18">(Now the slaves and the officers were standing there, having made a charcoal fire because it was cold, and they were warming themselves. And Peter was also standing there with them and warming himself.) </verse>
    <verse num="19">So the high priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and about his teaching.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Jesus replied to him, "I have spoken openly to the world. I always taught in the synagogue and in the temple <transChange type="added">courts</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">courts</transChange>" is supplied to distinguish this area from the interior of the temple building itself</note> where all the Jews assemble, and I have said nothing in secret.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Why are you asking me? Ask those who heard what I have said to them! Behold, these <transChange type="added">people</transChange> know what I said."</verse>
    <verse num="22">Now <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("had said")</note> he had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, one of the officers who was standing by gave a slap in the face to Jesus, saying, "Do you reply to the high priest in this way?"</verse>
    <verse num="23">Jesus replied to him, "If I have spoken wrongly, testify about what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> wrong! But if <transChange type="added">I have spoken</transChange><note>*The phrase "I have spoken" is an implied repetition of the earlier phrase in this verse</note> correctly, why do you strike me?"</verse>
    <verse num="24">Then Annas sent him, tied up, to Caiaphas the high priest. </verse>
    <verse num="25">Now Simon Peter was standing there and warming himself. So they said to him, "You are not also <transChange type="added">one</transChange> of his disciples, <transChange type="added">are you</transChange>?"<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">are you</transChange>"</note> He denied <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and said, "I am not!"</verse>
    <verse num="26">One of the slaves of the high priest, who was related to the one whose ear Peter had cut off, said, "Did I not see you in the garden with him?"</verse>
    <verse num="27">So Peter denied <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> again, and immediately a rooster crowed. </verse>
    <verse num="28">Then they brought Jesus from Caiaphas to the governor's residence. Now it was early, and they did not enter into the governor's residence so that they would not be defiled, but could eat the Passover.</verse>
    <verse num="29">So Pilate came outside to them and said, "What accusation do you bring against this man?"</verse>
    <verse num="30">They answered and said to him, "If this man were not doing evil, we would not have handed him over to you!"</verse>
    <verse num="31">So Pilate said to them, "You take him and judge him according to your law!" The Jews said to him, "It is not permitted for us to kill anyone,"</verse>
    <verse num="32">in order that the word of Jesus would be fulfilled that he had spoken, indicating by what sort of death he was going to die. </verse>
    <verse num="33">Then Pilate entered again into the governor's residence and summoned Jesus and said to him, "Are you the king of the Jews?"</verse>
    <verse num="34">Jesus replied, "Do you say this from yourself, or have others said <transChange type="added">this</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to you about me?"</verse>
    <verse num="35">Pilate replied, "I am not a Jew, <transChange type="added">am I</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">am I</transChange>"</note> Your people and the chief priests handed you over to me! What have you done?"</verse>
    <verse num="36">Jesus replied, "My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, my servants would be fighting so that I would not be handed over to the Jews. But now my kingdom is not from here."</verse>
    <verse num="37">Then Pilate said to him, "So then you are a king!" Jesus replied, "You say that I am a king. For this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> I was born, and for this reason I have come into the world: in order that I can testify to the truth. Everyone who is of the truth hears my voice."</verse>
    <verse num="38">Pilate said to him, "What is truth?" </verse>
    <verse num="39">But it is your custom that I release for you one <transChange type="added">prisoner</transChange><note>*The word "<transChange type="added">prisoner</transChange>" is not in the Greek text, but is implied</note> at the Passover. So do you want <transChange type="added">me</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to release for you the king of the Jews?"</verse>
    <verse num="40">Then they shouted again, saying, "Not this man, but Barabbas!" (Now Barabbas was a revolutionary.)<note>Or perhaps "robber"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">So then Pilate took Jesus and had him flogged.<note>*This verb has causative force in context; Pilate did not personally carry out the sentence</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">And the soldiers wove a crown of thorns and placed <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on his head, and put a purple robe on him,</verse>
    <verse num="3">and were coming up to him and saying, "Hail, king of the Jews!" and were giving him slaps in the face. </verse>
    <verse num="4">And Pilate came outside again and said to them, "Behold, I am bringing him outside to you, so that you will know that I find no basis for an accusation against him."</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then Jesus came outside wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe, and he said to them, "Behold the man!"</verse>
    <verse num="6">So when they saw him, the chief priests and the officers shouted, saying, "Crucify! Crucify!" Pilate said to them, "You take him and crucify <transChange type="added">him</transChange>!<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> For I do not find a basis for an accusation against him."</verse>
    <verse num="7">The Jews replied to him, "We have a law, and according to the law he ought to die, because he made himself out to be the Son of God!" </verse>
    <verse num="8">So when Pilate heard this statement, he was even more afraid,</verse>
    <verse num="9">and he entered into the governor's residence again and said to Jesus, "Where are you from?" But Jesus did not give him an answer.</verse>
    <verse num="10">So Pilate said to him, "Will you not speak to me? Do you not know that I have authority to release you, and I have authority to crucify you?"</verse>
    <verse num="11">Jesus replied to him, "You would not have any authority over me unless it was given to you from above. For this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> the one who handed me over to you has greater sin." </verse>
    <verse num="12">From this <transChange type="added">point on</transChange> Pilate was seeking to release him, but the Jews shouted, saying, "If you release this man, you are not a friend of Caesar! Everyone who makes himself out to be a king opposes Caesar!"</verse>
    <verse num="13">So Pilate, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard these words, brought Jesus outside and sat down on the judgment seat, in the place called The Stone Pavement (but Gabbatha in Aramaic).</verse>
    <verse num="14">(Now it was the day of preparation of the Passover; it was about the sixth hour.) And he said to the Jews, "Behold your king!" </verse>
    <verse num="15">Then those shouted, "Away <transChange type="added">with him</transChange>! Away <transChange type="added">with him</transChange>! Crucify him!" Pilate said to them, "Shall I crucify your king?" The chief priests replied, "We do not have a king except Caesar!"</verse>
    <verse num="16">So then he handed him over to them in order that he could be crucified. </verse>
    <verse num="17">and carrying for himself the cross, he went out to the <transChange type="added">place</transChange> called The Place of a Skull (which is called Golgotha in Aramaic),</verse>
    <verse num="18">where they crucified him, and with him two others, {one on each side},<note>Literally "from here and from here"</note> and Jesus in the middle.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Pilate also wrote a notice and placed <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> on the cross, and it was written: "Jesus the Nazarene, the king of the Jews."</verse>
    <verse num="20">So many of the Jews read this notice, because the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city. And it was written in Aramaic, in Latin, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> in Greek.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then the chief priests of the Jews said to Pilate, "Do not write 'The king of the Jews,' but, 'He said, I am king of the Jews.'"</verse>
    <verse num="22">Pilate replied, "What I have written, I have written." </verse>
    <verse num="23">Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his clothing and made four shares--for each soldier a share--and the tunic. (Now the tunic was seamless, woven from the top {in a single piece}.)<note>Literally "through the whole"</note></verse>
    <verse num="24">So they said to one another, "Let us not tear it apart, but cast lots for it, <transChange type="added">to see</transChange> whose it will be," so that the scripture would be fulfilled that says, </verse>
    <verse num="25">Now his mother and the sister of his mother, Mary the <transChange type="added">wife</transChange> of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene were standing near the cross of Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="26">So Jesus, seeing <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother and the disciple whom he loved standing there, said to <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> mother, "Woman, behold your son!"</verse>
    <verse num="27">Then he said to the disciple, "Behold your mother!" And from that hour the disciple took her into his own <transChange type="added">home</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="28">After this, Jesus, knowing that now at last everything was completed, in order that the scripture would be fulfilled, said, "I am thirsty."</verse>
    <verse num="29">A jar full of sour wine was standing there, so <transChange type="added">they</transChange> put a sponge full of the sour wine on a <transChange type="added">branch of</transChange> hyssop <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("put") has been translated as a finite verb</note> brought <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to his mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="30">Then when he had received the sour wine, Jesus said, "It is completed,"<note>Or (traditionally) "it is finished"</note> and bowing <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> head, he gave up <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> spirit. </verse>
    <verse num="31">Then the Jews, because it was the day of preparation, so that the bodies would not remain on the cross on the Sabbath (for that Sabbath was an important day), asked Pilate that their legs could be broken and they could be taken away.</verse>
    <verse num="32">So the soldiers came and broke the legs of the first and of the other who had been crucified with him.</verse>
    <verse num="33">But <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("came") which is understood as temporal</note> came to Jesus, after they saw he was already dead, they did not break his legs.</verse>
    <verse num="34">But one of the soldiers pierced his side with a spear, and blood and water came out immediately.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And the one who has seen <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> has testified, and his testimony is true, and that person knows that he is telling the truth, so that you also may believe.</verse>
    <verse num="36">For these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> happened in order that the scripture would be fulfilled: "Not a bone of his will be broken."<note>A quotation from Exod 12:46, Num 9:12, and Ps 34:20</note></verse>
    <verse num="37">And again another scripture says, "They will look on <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> whom they have pierced."<note>A quotation from Zech 12:10</note> </verse>
    <verse num="38">And after these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, Joseph <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> from Arimathea, who was a disciple of Jesus (but a secret one for fear of the Jews), asked Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus. And Pilate allowed <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> so he came and took away his body.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And Nicodemus--the one who had come to him formerly at night--also came, bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes <transChange type="added">weighing</transChange> about a hundred pounds.<note>The Greek term refers to a Roman pound, 327.45 grams (approximately 12 ounces)</note></verse>
    <verse num="40">So they took the body of Jesus and wrapped it in <transChange type="added">strips of</transChange> linen cloth with the fragrant spices, as is the Jews' custom to prepare for burial.</verse>
    <verse num="41">Now <transChange type="added">there</transChange> was a garden at the place where he was crucified, and in the garden a new tomb in which no one was yet buried.</verse>
    <verse num="42">So there, on account of the day of preparation of the Jews, because the tomb was close by, they buried Jesus. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">Now on the first <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the week, Mary Magdalene came to the tomb early, <transChange type="added">while it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was")</note> was still dark, and saw the stone had been taken away from the tomb.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So she ran and came to Simon Peter and to the other disciple whom Jesus loved and said to them, "They have taken away the Lord from the tomb and we do not know where they have put him!"</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then Peter and the other disciple went out and were going to the tomb.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And the two were running together, and the other disciple ran ahead, faster than Peter, and came to the tomb first.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And bending over to look, he saw the <transChange type="added">strips of</transChange> linen cloth lying there, though he did not go in.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then Simon Peter also came following him, and he went into the tomb and saw the <transChange type="added">strips of</transChange> linen cloth lying there,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and the facecloth that was on his head--not lying with the <transChange type="added">strips of</transChange> linen cloth, but folded up separately in one place.</verse>
    <verse num="8">So then the other disciple who had come to the tomb first also went in, and he saw and believed.</verse>
    <verse num="9">(For they did not yet know the scripture that it was necessary for him to rise from the dead.) </verse>
    <verse num="10">Then the disciples went away again to their <transChange type="added">own homes</transChange>.<note>*The phrase "<transChange type="added">own homes</transChange>" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">But Mary stood outside at the tomb, weeping. Then, while she was weeping, she bent over to look into the tomb,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and she saw two angels in white, seated one at the head and one at the feet where the body of Jesus had been lying.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And they said to her, "Woman, why are you weeping?" She said to them, "They have taken away my Lord, and I do not know where they have put him!"</verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">When she</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, she turned {around}<note>Literally "to the back"</note> and saw Jesus standing there, and she did not know that it was Jesus. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Jesus said to her, "Woman, why are you weeping? Who are you looking for?" She thought that it was the gardener, <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("thought") has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him, "Sir, if you have carried him away, tell me where you have put him, and I will take him."</verse>
    <verse num="16">Jesus said to her, "Mary." She turned around <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("turned around") has been translated as a finite verb</note> said to him in Aramaic, "Rabboni" (which means "Teacher").</verse>
    <verse num="17">Jesus said to her, "Do not touch me, for I have not yet ascended to the Father. But go to my brothers and tell them, 'I am ascending to my Father and your Father, and my God and your God.'"</verse>
    <verse num="18">Mary Magdalene came <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the participle ("announced") has been translated as a finite verb in keeping with English style</note> announced to the disciples, "I have seen the Lord," and he had said these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to her. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Now <transChange type="added">when it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was")</note> was evening on that day--the first <transChange type="added">day</transChange> of the week--and the doors had been shut where the disciples were because of fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in their midst and said to them, "Peace to you."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he showed <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> hands and <transChange type="added">his</transChange><note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> side to them. Then the disciples rejoiced <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as temporal</note> saw the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="21">So Jesus said to them again, "Peace to you. As the Father has sent me, I also send you."</verse>
    <verse num="22">And <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he breathed on <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and said to them, "Receive the Holy Spirit.</verse>
    <verse num="23">If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven them. If you retain <transChange type="added">the sins</transChange><note>*An understood repetition of the phrase from earlier in the verse</note> of any, they are retained." </verse>
    <verse num="24">Now Thomas, one of the twelve, who was called Didymus,<note>The Greek term means "the Twin"</note> was not with them when Jesus came.</verse>
    <verse num="25">So the other disciples said to him, "We have seen the Lord!" But he said to them, "Unless I see in his hands the mark of the nails, and put my finger into the mark of the nails, and put my hand into his side, I will never believe!" </verse>
    <verse num="26">And after eight days his disciples were again inside, and Thomas with them. <transChange type="added">Although</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had been shut") which is understood as concessive</note> the doors had been shut, Jesus came and stood in their midst and said, "Peace to you."</verse>
    <verse num="27">Then he said to Thomas, "Place your finger here and see my hands, and place your hand and put <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> into my side. And do not be unbelieving, but believing!"</verse>
    <verse num="28">Thomas answered and said to him, "My Lord and my God!"</verse>
    <verse num="29">Jesus said to him, "Because you have seen me, have you believed? Blessed <transChange type="added">are</transChange> those who have not seen and have believed." </verse>
    <verse num="30">Now Jesus also performed many other signs in the presence of the disciples<note>Some manuscripts have "his disciples"</note> which are not recorded in this book,</verse>
    <verse num="31">but these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are recorded in order that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("believing") which is understood as means</note> believing you may have life in his name. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">After these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> Jesus revealed himself again to the disciples by the Sea of Tiberias. Now he revealed <transChange type="added">himself</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> in this way:</verse>
    <verse num="2">Simon Peter and Thomas (who was called Didymus)<note>The Greek term means "the Twin"</note> and Nathanael from Cana in Galilee and the <transChange type="added">sons</transChange> of Zebedee and two others of his disciples were together.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Simon Peter said to them, "I am going fishing!" They said to him, "We also are coming with you." They went out and got into the boat, and during that night they caught nothing. </verse>
    <verse num="4">Now <transChange type="added">when it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was")</note> was already early morning, Jesus stood on the beach. However, the disciples did not know that it was Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="5">So Jesus said to them, "Children, you do not have any fish to eat, <transChange type="added">do you</transChange>?<note>*The negative construction in Greek anticipates a negative answer here, indicated in the translation by the phrase "<transChange type="added">do you</transChange>"</note> They answered him, "No."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And he said to them, "Throw the net on the right side of the boat, and you will find <transChange type="added">some</transChange>."<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> So they threw <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and were no longer able to haul it in from the large number of the fish. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Then that disciple whom Jesus loved said to Peter, "It is the Lord!" So Simon Peter, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard that it was the Lord, tied around himself his outer garment (for he was naked)<note>I.e., "he was naked underneath the outer garment," which he tucked into his belt; alternatively, this could mean "for he was stripped for work"</note> and threw himself into the sea.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But the other disciples came in the boat, dragging the net of fish, because they were not far from the land, but about two hundred cubits<note>Approximately 100 yards or 92 meters, based on a cubit of 18 inches.</note> away. </verse>
    <verse num="9">So when they got out on the land, they saw a charcoal fire laid <transChange type="added">there</transChange>, and a fish lying on <transChange type="added">it</transChange>,<note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and bread.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Jesus said to them, "Bring some of the fish that you have just now caught."</verse>
    <verse num="11">So Simon Peter got into <transChange type="added">the boat</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> and hauled the net to the land, full of large fish--one hundred fifty-three--and <transChange type="added">although there</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were") which is understood as concessive</note> were so many, the net was not torn.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Jesus said to them, "Come, eat breakfast!" But none of the disciples dared to ask him, "Who are you?" <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew that it was the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Jesus came and took the bread and gave <transChange type="added">it</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> to them, and the fish likewise.</verse>
    <verse num="14">This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> now <transChange type="added">the</transChange> third <transChange type="added">time</transChange> Jesus was revealed to the disciples <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had been raised") which is understood as temporal</note> had been raised from the dead. </verse>
    <verse num="15">Now when they had eaten breakfast, Jesus said to Simon Peter, "Simon <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of John, do you love me more than these?" He said to him, "Yes, Lord, you know that I love you." He said to him, "Feed my lambs!"</verse>
    <verse num="16">He said to him again a second time, "Simon <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of John, do you love me?" He said to him, "Yes, Lord, you know that I love you." He said to him, "Shepherd my sheep!"</verse>
    <verse num="17">He said to him a third <transChange type="added">time</transChange>, "Simon <transChange type="added">son</transChange> of John, do you love me?" Peter was distressed because he said to him a third <transChange type="added">time</transChange>, "Do you love me?" and he said to him, "Lord, you know everything! You know that I love you!" Jesus said to him, "Feed my sheep!</verse>
    <verse num="18">Truly, truly I say to you, when you were young, you tied <transChange type="added">your clothes</transChange><note>*The words "<transChange type="added">your clothes</transChange>" are not in the Greek text but are implied</note> around yourself and walked wherever you wanted. But when you grow old, you will stretch out your hands, and someone else will tie you up and carry <transChange type="added">you</transChange> where you do not want <transChange type="added">to go</transChange>.<note>*The words "<transChange type="added">to go</transChange>" are not in the Greek text but are implied</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">(Now he said this to indicate by what kind of death he would glorify God.) And <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had said") which is understood as temporal</note> had said this, he said to him, "Follow me!" </verse>
    <verse num="20">Peter turned <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("turned") has been translated as a finite verb</note> saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following <transChange type="added">them</transChange><note>*Here the direct object is supplied from context in the English translation</note> (who also leaned back on his chest at the dinner and said, "Lord, who is the one betraying you?")</verse>
    <verse num="21">So <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as temporal</note> saw this one, Peter said to Jesus, "Lord, but what about this one?"</verse>
    <verse num="22">Jesus said to him, "If I want him to remain until I come, what <transChange type="added">is that</transChange><note>*The words "<transChange type="added">is that</transChange>" are not in the Greek text but are supplied in keeping with English style</note> to you? You follow me!"</verse>
    <verse num="23">So this saying went out to the brothers that that disciple would not die. But Jesus did not say to him that he would not die, but "If I want him to remain until I come, what <transChange type="added">is that</transChange><note>*The words "<transChange type="added">is that</transChange>" are not in the Greek text but are supplied in keeping with English style</note> to you?" </verse>
    <verse num="24">This is the disciple who is testifying about these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and who has written down these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>. And we know that his testimony is true.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Now there are also many other <transChange type="added">things</transChange> that Jesus did, which--if they were written down one after the other--I suppose not even the world itself could contain the books that would be written. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>