<book num="2John">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The elder, to the elect lady and her children, whom I love in truth--and not I alone, but also all those who know the truth--</verse>
    <verse num="2">because of the truth that resides in us and will be with us {forever}<note>Or "in perpetuity"; literally "for the age"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Grace, mercy, peace will be with us from God the Father and from Jesus Christ the Son of the Father in truth and love. </verse>
    <verse num="4">{I was very glad}<note>Literally "I rejoiced exceedingly"</note> because I found <transChange type="added">some</transChange> of your children walking in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> truth, just as {the Father commanded us}<note>Literally "we received commandment from the Father"</note>. </verse>
    <verse num="5">And now I ask you, lady (not as <transChange type="added">if I were</transChange> writing a new commandment to you, but <transChange type="added">one</transChange> that we have had from the beginning), that we should love one another.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And this is love: that we walk according to his commandments. This is the commandment, just as you have heard from the beginning, so that you should walk in it.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For many deceivers have gone out into the world, those who do not confess Jesus Christ<note>Or "confess Jesus <transChange type="added">as</transChange> Christ coming in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> flesh" (see 1 John 4:2)</note> coming in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> flesh. This person is the deceiver and the antichrist!</verse>
    <verse num="8">Watch yourselves that you do not lose what we have worked for, but receive a full reward. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Everyone who goes too far and does not remain in the teaching of Christ does not have God. The one who remains in the teaching--this person has both the Father and the Son.</verse>
    <verse num="10">If anyone comes to you and does not bring this teaching, do not receive him into <transChange type="added">your</transChange> house and do not speak a greeting to him,</verse>
    <verse num="11">because the one who speaks a greeting to him shares in his evil deeds. </verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">Although</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have") which is understood as concessive</note> I have many <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to write to you, I do not want <transChange type="added">to do so</transChange> by means of paper and ink, but I hope to be with you and to speak {face to face}<note>Literally "mouth to mouth"</note>, so that your<note>Some manuscripts have "our"</note> joy may be complete.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The children of your elect sister greet you.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>