<book num="2Tim">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through the will of God, according to the promise of life which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in Christ Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="2">to Timothy, <transChange type="added">my</transChange> dear child. Grace, mercy, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. </verse>
    <verse num="3">{I am thankful}<note>Literally "I have thankfulness"</note> to God, whom I have served with a clear conscience {as my ancestors did}<note>Literally "from ancestors"</note>, when {I remember you constantly}<note>Literally "I have remembrance concerning you constantly"</note> in my prayers night and day,</verse>
    <verse num="4">longing to see you <transChange type="added">as I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("remember") which is understood as temporal</note> remember your tears, so that I may be filled with joy,</verse>
    <verse num="5">{remembering the}<note>Literally "receiving a remembrance of the"</note> sincere faith in you, which lived first in your grandmother Lois and your mother Eunice, and I am convinced that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in you also,</verse>
    <verse num="6">for which reason I remind you to rekindle the gift of God that is in you through the laying on of my hands.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For God has not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of power and love and self-discipline. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Therefore, do not be ashamed of the testimony about our Lord, nor me his prisoner, but suffer along with <transChange type="added">me</transChange> for the gospel, according to the power of God,</verse>
    <verse num="9">who saved us and called <transChange type="added">us</transChange> with a holy calling, not according to our works but according to his own purpose and grace that was given to us in Christ Jesus {before time began}<note>Literally "before times eternal"</note>,</verse>
    <verse num="10">but has now been disclosed by the appearing of our Savior Jesus Christ,<note>Some manuscripts have "our Savior Christ Jesus"</note> who has abolished death and brought to light life and immortality through the gospel,</verse>
    <verse num="11">for which I was appointed a proclaimer and an apostle and a teacher,</verse>
    <verse num="12">for which reason also I suffer these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>. But <transChange type="added">I am</transChange> not ashamed, because I know in whom I have believed, and I am convinced that he is able to guard <transChange type="added">what</transChange> I have entrusted until that day.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Hold fast to the pattern of sound words which you heard from me, in the faith and love <transChange type="added">that are</transChange> in Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Guard the good deposit through the Holy Spirit who lives in us. </verse>
    <verse num="15">You know this, that all those in Asia turned away from me, among whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes.</verse>
    <verse num="16">May the Lord grant mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he refreshed me many times, and was not ashamed of my imprisonment,</verse>
    <verse num="17">but <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was") which is understood as temporal</note> was in Rome, he diligently sought me and found <transChange type="added">me</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="18">May the Lord grant him to find mercy from the Lord in that day! And how much he served <transChange type="added">me</transChange> in Ephesus you know very well. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">You, therefore, my child, be strong in the grace <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> in Christ Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="2">and <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which you have heard from me in the presence of many witnesses, entrust these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to faithful people who will be competent to teach others also.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Suffer together with <transChange type="added">me</transChange> as a good soldier of Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="4">No one who serves as a soldier is entangled in the activities of <transChange type="added">everyday</transChange> life, so that he may please the one who enlisted <transChange type="added">him</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And also if anyone competes he is not crowned unless he competes according to the rules.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The farmer who works hard must <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the first to receive a share of the crops.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Consider what I am saying, for the Lord will grant you understanding in all <transChange type="added">these things</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Remember Jesus Christ, raised from the dead, a descendant of David according to my gospel,</verse>
    <verse num="9">in connection with which I suffer misfortune to the point of {imprisonment}<note>Literally "bonds"</note> as a criminal, but the word of God is not bound.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Because of this, I endure all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> for the sake of the chosen, in order that they also may obtain salvation <transChange type="added">which is</transChange> in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The saying <transChange type="added">is</transChange> trustworthy: </verse>
    <verse num="12">if we endure, we will also reign with <transChange type="added">him</transChange>; if we deny <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, he also will deny us;</verse>
    <verse num="13">if we are unfaithful, he remains faithful--{he cannot deny himself}<note>Literally "he is not able to deny himself"</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have "because he is not able to deny himself"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">Remind <transChange type="added">people</transChange> of these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, solemnly urging <transChange type="added">them</transChange> before the Lord<note>Some manuscripts have "before God"</note> not to dispute about words. <transChange type="added">This is</transChange> in no way beneficial <transChange type="added">and leads to</transChange> the ruin of the hearers.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Make every effort to present yourself approved to God, a worker having no need to be ashamed, guiding the word of truth along a straight path.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But avoid pointless chatter, for it will progress to greater ungodliness,</verse>
    <verse num="17">and their message {will spread}<note>Literally "will experience spreading"</note> like gangrene, among whom are Hymenaeus and Philetus,</verse>
    <verse num="18">who have deviated concerning the truth <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saying") which is understood as means</note> saying the resurrection has already taken place, and they are upsetting the faith of some.</verse>
    <verse num="19">However, the solid foundation of God stands firm, having this seal: "The Lord knows those who are his,"<note>A quotation from Num 16:5</note> and "Everyone who names the name of the Lord must abstain from unrighteousness." </verse>
    <verse num="20">Now in a great house <transChange type="added">there</transChange> are not only gold and silver vessels, but also wooden and earthenware <transChange type="added">ones</transChange>, some of which <transChange type="added">are</transChange> for honorable use, and some of which <transChange type="added">are</transChange> for ordinary use.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Therefore, if someone cleanses himself from these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, he will be a vessel for honorable use, set apart, useful to the Master, prepared for every good work. </verse>
    <verse num="22">But flee from youthful desires, and pursue righteousness, faith, love, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> peace, in company with those who call upon the Lord from a pure heart.</verse>
    <verse num="23">But avoid foolish and uninformed controversies, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know that they produce quarrels.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And the slave of the Lord must not quarrel, but be kind toward everyone, skillful in teaching, tolerant,</verse>
    <verse num="25">correcting those who are opposed with gentleness, <transChange type="added">seeing</transChange> whether perhaps God may grant them repentance to a knowledge of the truth,</verse>
    <verse num="26">and they will come to their senses again <transChange type="added">and escape</transChange> from the trap of the devil, being held captive by him to <transChange type="added">do</transChange> his will. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">But know this, that in the last days difficult times will come,</verse>
    <verse num="2">for people will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boasters, arrogant, slanderers, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, unholy,</verse>
    <verse num="3">hardhearted, irreconcilable, slanderous, without self-control, savage, with no interest for what is good,</verse>
    <verse num="4">traitors, reckless, conceited, loving pleasure rather than loving God,</verse>
    <verse num="5">maintaining a form of godliness, but denying its power. Avoid these <transChange type="added">people</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For from these are those who slip into houses and captivate foolish women loaded down with sins, led by various kinds of desires,</verse>
    <verse num="7">always learning and never able to come to a knowledge of the truth.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And {just as}<note>Literally "in the manner in which"</note> Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so also these oppose the truth, people corrupted in mind, disqualified concerning the faith.</verse>
    <verse num="9">But they will not progress to a greater extent, for their folly will be quite evident to everyone, as also the <transChange type="added">folly</transChange> of those <transChange type="added">two</transChange> was. </verse>
    <verse num="10">But you have faithfully followed my teaching, way of life, purpose, faith, patience, love, endurance,</verse>
    <verse num="11">persecutions, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> sufferings that happened to me in Antioch, in Iconium, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> in Lystra, what sort of persecutions I endured, and the Lord delivered me from all <transChange type="added">of them</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And indeed, all those who want to live in a godly manner in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But evil people and imposters will progress to the worse, deceiving and being deceived.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But you continue in <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> which you have learned and are convinced <transChange type="added">of</transChange>, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know from whom you learned <transChange type="added">them</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="15">and that from childhood you have known the holy writings that are able <transChange type="added">to make</transChange> you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</verse>
    <verse num="16">All scripture <transChange type="added">is</transChange> inspired by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, for training in righteousness,</verse>
    <verse num="17">in order that the person of God may be competent, equipped for every good work. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">I solemnly charge <transChange type="added">you</transChange> before God and Christ Jesus, who is going to judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom,</verse>
    <verse num="2">preach the word, be ready in season <transChange type="added">and</transChange> out of season, reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all patience and instruction.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For there will be a time when they will not put up with sound teaching, but in accordance with their own desires, they will accumulate for themselves teachers, {because they have an insatiable curiosity}<note>Literally "feeling an itching in the ear"; "because" is supplied as a component of the participle ("feeling an itching") which is understood as causal</note>,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and they will turn away from the hearing of the truth, but will turn to myths.</verse>
    <verse num="5">But you, be self-controlled in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, bear hardship patiently, do the work of an evangelist, fulfill your ministry. </verse>
    <verse num="6">For I am already being poured out as a drink offering, and the time of my departure is imminent.</verse>
    <verse num="7">I have fought the good fight, I have completed the race, I have kept the faith.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Finally, the crown of righteousness is reserved for me, that the Lord, the righteous Judge, will award to me on that day, and not only to me, but also to all who have loved his appearing. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Make haste to come to me quickly.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For Demas deserted me, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("loved") which is understood as causal</note> loved the present age, and went to Thessalonica. Crescens <transChange type="added">went</transChange> to Galatia; Titus <transChange type="added">went</transChange> to Dalmatia.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Luke alone is with me. Take along Mark <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied because the previous participle ("take along") has been translated as a finite verb</note> bring <transChange type="added">him</transChange> with you, because he is useful to me for ministry.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But I have sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</verse>
    <verse num="13"><transChange type="added">When you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("come") which is understood as temporal</note> come, bring the cloak that I left behind in Troas with Carpus, and the scrolls, especially the parchments.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Alexander the metalworker did me much harm; may the Lord pay back to him according to his deeds,</verse>
    <verse num="15">against whom you also be on guard, because he vehemently opposed our words.</verse>
    <verse num="16">At my first defense, no one came to my <transChange type="added">aid</transChange>, but <transChange type="added">they</transChange> all deserted me; may it not be counted against them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">But the Lord helped me and strengthened me, so that through me the proclamation might be fulfilled and all the Gentiles might hear, and he rescued <transChange type="added">me</transChange> from the lion's mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The Lord will rescue me from every evil deed, and will save <transChange type="added">me</transChange> for his heavenly kingdom, to whom <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the glory {forever and ever}<note>Literally "to the ages of the ages"</note>. Amen. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Greet Prisca and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Erastus remained in Corinth, but Trophimus I left behind in Miletus <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was sick") which is understood as causal</note> was sick.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Make haste to come before winter. Eubulus and Pudens and Linus and Claudia and all the brothers greet you.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The Lord <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with your spirit. Grace <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with you. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>