<book num="Nah">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The oracle concerning Nineveh-- the scroll of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite:</verse>
    <verse num="2">Yahweh is a jealous God and avenging; Yahweh is avenging and {full of wrath}.<note>Literally "a lord of wrath"</note> Yahweh takes vengeance against his enemies; he rages against his adversaries.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Yahweh is slow to anger but great <transChange type="added">in</transChange> power; he will certainly not allow <transChange type="added">the guilty</transChange> to go unpunished. {He marches}<note>Literally "His path"</note> in storm wind and in gale; storm clouds <transChange type="added">are the</transChange> dust of his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He rebukes the sea and he dries up the rivers; he makes all the rivers run dry. Bashan and Carmel wither;<note>MT reads "languishes," but the versions reflect "withers," which also restores the acrostic</note> the blossom of Lebanon languishes.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Mountains quake before him; the hills shake apart.<note>Or "melt"</note> The earth heaves before him-- the world and all her inhabitants.</verse>
    <verse num="6">His indignation--who can stand before it? Who can endure {his fierce anger}?<note>Literally "the heat of his anger"</note> His wrath is poured out like fire; rocks are shattered before<note>Or "by"</note> him.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Yahweh is good--a refuge in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> day of distress; <transChange type="added">he knows</transChange> those who take refuge in him.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But with a rushing torrent he will bring <transChange type="added">Nineveh</transChange> to an end; he will chase his enemies into darkness.</verse>
    <verse num="9">What<note>Or "Why ...?"</note> do you plot against Yahweh? {He will completely destroy it};<note>Literally "he will make a complete destruction"</note> trouble will not rise up a second time!</verse>
    <verse num="10">For like entangled thorns, and like their drink which is drunk, they will be consumed like fully dry chaff.</verse>
    <verse num="11">From you goes out one who plots evil against Yahweh, one who plans wickedness.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Yahweh says this: </verse>
    <verse num="13">And now, I will break his yoke from upon you; I will snap your bonds."</verse>
    <verse num="14">Yahweh has commanded concerning you: </verse>
    <verse num="15"><note>Nahum 1:15-2:13 in the English Bible is 2:1-14 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Look! On the mountains! The feet of the one who brings good tidings, the one who proclaims peace! "Celebrate <transChange type="added">a festival</transChange>, O Judah, Fulfill your vows! For he will not invade you again; the wicked one is cut off completely!"</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">{One who shatters}<note>Literally "a shatterer"</note> has come up against you! Guard <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fortification! Watch <transChange type="added">the</transChange> road!<note>Or "way"</note> Gird <transChange type="added">your</transChange> loins! {Muster}<note>Or "Collect"</note> all <transChange type="added">your</transChange> strength!</verse>
    <verse num="2">For Yahweh will restore the majesty of Jacob like the majesty of Israel; for ravagers have ravaged them and ruined <transChange type="added">their</transChange> branches.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The shields of his warriors <transChange type="added">are</transChange> dyed red; The powerful men <transChange type="added">are</transChange> dressed in scarlet. The metal of the chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> <transChange type="added">shines</transChange> like fire {on the day of battle},<note>Literally "on the day of his preparation"</note> and <transChange type="added">their</transChange> spears quiver.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The chariots<note>Hebrew "chariot"</note> race madly through the streets; they rush back and forth in the public squares. Their appearance like lightning bolts, they dart about like flashes of lightning.</verse>
    <verse num="5">He calls his officers; they stumble as they march; they rush to her wall; they set the covering<note>The Hebrew word describes a small portable roof to protect siege warriors from arrows and debris hurled at them from the fortified city wall</note> in place.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The gates of the river are opened; the palace trembles.</verse>
    <verse num="7">{Her goddess is taken out and taken into exile};<note>Literally "It is decreed <transChange type="added">that</transChange> she be exiled <transChange type="added">and</transChange> led away." MT reads the very enigmatic "And he is placed, she is sent into exile, she is taken up." The BHS editors suggest the conjectural emendation "And her goddess <transChange type="added">= the idol of the patron deity of Nineveh</transChange> is taken and taken into exile." This is adopted in the translation on the basis of internal evidence</note> her maidservants moan like doves; they beat on their breasts.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Nineveh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a pool of water without its water.<note>MT reads "from her days." Greek LXX and Syriac Peshitta reflect "from her waters"</note> {As they flee},<note>Literally "And they flee away"</note> <transChange type="added">she cries,</transChange> "Stop! Stop!" But there is no one who turns back.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Plunder the silver! Plunder the gold! There is no end to the spoils,<note>Literally "the supply"</note> an abundance of {everything one could want}!<note>Literally "every kind of desirable object"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Emptiness and plundering and devastation! Their hearts faint and their knees tremble,<note>Or "totter"</note> {All their loins shake}<note>Literally "And shaking of all loins"</note> and all their faces {turn}<note>Literally "gather"</note> pale.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Where <transChange type="added">now</transChange> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the den of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> lions and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> cave of the fierce lions? There the lioness, the cub, and the lion once {prowled},<note>Literally "went"</note> {and no one disturbed them}.<note>Literally "there <transChange type="added">is</transChange> no one making <transChange type="added">them</transChange> afraid"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">The lion tore apart enough <transChange type="added">prey</transChange> for his cubs, he strangled <transChange type="added">prey</transChange> for his lioness; he filled {his lair}<note>Literally "his holes"</note> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> prey and his den <transChange type="added">with</transChange> mangled carcass.</verse>
    <verse num="13">"Look! I am against you!" {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh of hosts. "I will burn her chariots {with fire};<note>Literally "with smoke"</note> the sword will devour fierce lions. I will cut off your prey from the earth; the voice of your messengers will no longer be heard."</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Woe to the city <transChange type="added">that has shed</transChange> {much blood}!<note>Literally "bloods"</note> {She is a deceiver},<note>Literally "All of her <transChange type="added">is</transChange> deception"</note> She is filled <transChange type="added">with</transChange> plunder, {She has hoarded her spoils of war}.<note>Literally "Prey does not depart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">The crack of the whip! The rumbling of the <transChange type="added">chariot</transChange> wheel! The galloping of the horse! The racing of the chariot!</verse>
    <verse num="3">Chariots charge! Swords flash! Spears glitter! {Many corpses are piled high}!<note>Literally "Many dead, piles of corpses"</note> There is no end to the slain! They stumble over their dead!</verse>
    <verse num="4">"Because of the many idolatries of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> prostitute, the beautiful charm <transChange type="added">of</transChange> a mistress of witchcraft, she who enslaves nations by her harlotries, and peoples by her sorceries,</verse>
    <verse num="5">"Look! I am against you!" {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note>Yahweh. "I will strip up your skirts over your face; I will let nations look <transChange type="added">at</transChange> your nakedness and your shame.</verse>
    <verse num="6">"I will throw filth upon you, I will treat you with contempt, I will make you a spectacle.</verse>
    <verse num="7">"And it will be that everyone who sees you will flee from you, And {they}<note>Hebrew "he"</note> will say, 'Nineveh is destroyed!' Who will mourn for her? From whence shall I seek comforters for you?"</verse>
    <verse num="8">Are you better than Thebes?<note>Hebrew "No-Amon"</note> She who sits at the Nile, surrounded by her waters, her rampart <transChange type="added">was the</transChange> sea and water <transChange type="added">was</transChange> her wall.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Cush <transChange type="added">was</transChange> her strength, Egypt without end; Put and Libya were among {your allies}.<note>Literally "your helpers"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">Yet she went into captivity as an exile; her children were dashed to pieces at the head of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> streets; they cast lots for all of her nobles; all of her dignitaries were bound with chains.</verse>
    <verse num="11">You also will behave like a drunkard; You also will hide yourself; You also will seek refuge from <transChange type="added">the</transChange> enemy.</verse>
    <verse num="12">All of your fortifications <transChange type="added">are like</transChange> fig trees with <transChange type="added">ripe</transChange> firstfruits-- if they are shaken, they will fall into the mouth of the eater.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Look! Your troops <transChange type="added">are like</transChange> women in your midst. The gates of your land are wide open to your enemies; fire will consume the bars <transChange type="added">of your gates</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Draw water for a siege! Strengthen your fortifications! Go to the mud <transChange type="added">pit</transChange>! Trample the clay! Grasp the brick mold!</verse>
    <verse num="15">There fire will consume you; the sword will cut you off. It will consume you like the locust.</verse>
    <verse num="16">You have increased your merchants more than the stars of heaven; <transChange type="added">like</transChange> the locust they will shed <transChange type="added">their skin</transChange> and fly away.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Your officials <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like locusts; your commanders <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like a swarm of locusts. They encamp on the walls on a cold day; when the sun rises, they fly away-- no one knows where they have gone.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Your shepherds are sleeping, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> king of Assyria! Your nobles slumber. Your people are scattered on the mountains; no one can gather them.</verse>
    <verse num="19">There is no healing for your wound; your injury is fatal. All who hear the report of you will clap <transChange type="added">their</transChange> hands <transChange type="added">for joy</transChange> concerning you, {For who has not suffered at the hands of your endless cruelty}?<note>Literally "For over whom has your endless cruelty not passed?"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
</book>