<book num="Heb">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1"><transChange type="added">Although</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("spoke") which is understood as concessive</note> God spoke long ago in many parts<note>Or "portions"</note> and in many ways to the fathers by the prophets,</verse>
    <verse num="2">in these last days he has spoken to us by a Son, whom he appointed heir of all <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, through whom also he made the world,<note>Or "the universe"; literally "the ages"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">who is the radiance of his glory and the representation of his essence, sustaining all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> by the word of power.<note>Some manuscripts have "by the word of his power. <transChange type="added">When he</transChange> had made purification for sins, he sat down"</note> <transChange type="added">When he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("had made") which is understood as temporal</note> had made purification for sins through him, he sat down at the right hand of the Majesty on high,</verse>
    <verse num="4">having become by so much better than the angels, by as much as he has inherited a more excellent name than theirs. </verse>
    <verse num="5">For to which of the angels did he ever say, </verse>
    <verse num="6">And again, when he brings the firstborn into the world, he says, </verse>
    <verse num="7">And concerning the angels he says, </verse>
    <verse num="8">but concerning the Son, </verse>
    <verse num="9">You have loved righteousness and hated lawlessness; because of this God, your God, has anointed you with the olive oil of joy more than your companions.<note>A quotation from Ps 45:6-7</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">And, </verse>
    <verse num="11">they will perish, but you continue, and they will all become old like a garment,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and like a robe you will roll them up, and like a garment they will be changed; but you are the same, and your years will not run out."<note>A quotation from Ps 102:25-27</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">But to which of the angels has he ever said, </verse>
    <verse num="14">Are they not all spirits engaged in special service, sent on assignment for the sake of those who are going to inherit salvation? </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Because of this, <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> all the more necessary <transChange type="added">that</transChange> we pay attention to the <transChange type="added">things</transChange> we have heard, lest we drift away.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For if the word spoken through angels was binding and every transgression and act of disobedience received a just penalty,</verse>
    <verse num="3">how will we escape <transChange type="added">if we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("neglect") which is understood as conditional</note> neglect so great a salvation which had <transChange type="added">its</transChange> beginning <transChange type="added">when it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal infinitive ("was spoken")</note> was spoken through the Lord <transChange type="added">and</transChange> was confirmed to us by those who heard,</verse>
    <verse num="4"><transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was testifying at the same time")</note> God was testifying at the same time by signs and wonders and various miracles and distributions of the Holy Spirit according to his will. </verse>
    <verse num="5">For he did not subject to angels the world to come, about which we are speaking.</verse>
    <verse num="6">But someone testified somewhere, saying, </verse>
    <verse num="7">You made him for a short <transChange type="added">time</transChange> lower than the angels; you crowned him with glory and honor;<note>Several important manuscripts add "and placed him over the works of your hands" to the end of v. 7</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">you subjected all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> under his feet.<note>A quotation from Ps 8:4-6</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">but we see Jesus, for a short <transChange type="added">time</transChange> made lower than the angels, because of the suffering of death crowned with glory and honor, so that apart from God<note>Some manuscripts have "so that by the grace of God"</note> he might taste death on behalf of everyone.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For it was fitting for him for whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> and through whom <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in bringing many sons to glory to perfect the originator of their salvation through sufferings.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For both the one who sanctifies and the ones who are sanctified <transChange type="added">are</transChange> all from one, for which reason he is not ashamed to call them brothers,</verse>
    <verse num="12">saying, </verse>
    <verse num="13">And again, </verse>
    <verse num="14">Therefore, since the children share in blood and flesh, he also in like manner shared in these <transChange type="added">same things</transChange>, in order that through death he could destroy the one who has the power of death, that is, the devil,</verse>
    <verse num="15">and could set free these who through fear of death were subject to slavery throughout all their lives.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For surely he is not concerned with angels, but he is concerned with the descendants of Abraham.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Therefore he was obligated to be made like his brothers in all <transChange type="added">respects</transChange>, in order that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in the things relating to God, in order to make atonement for the sins of the people.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For in that which he himself suffered <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was tempted") which is understood as temporal</note> was tempted, he is able to help those who are tempted. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, holy brothers, sharers in a heavenly calling, consider Jesus, the apostle and high priest of our confession,</verse>
    <verse num="2">who was faithful to the one who appointed him, as Moses also <transChange type="added">was</transChange> in his household.<note>Some manuscripts have "in all his household"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">For this one is considered worthy of greater glory than Moses, inasmuch as the one who builds it has greater honor than the house.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For every house is built by someone, but the one who built all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Moses <transChange type="added">was</transChange> faithful in all his house as a servant, for a testimony to the things that would be spoken,</verse>
    <verse num="6">but Christ <transChange type="added">was faithful</transChange><note>*The words "<transChange type="added">was faithful</transChange>" are not in the Greek text, but are an understood repetition from the previous verse and v. 2</note> as a son over his house, whose house we are, if<note>Some manuscripts have "if indeed"</note> we hold fast to our confidence and the hope we can be proud of. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Therefore, just as the Holy Spirit says, </verse>
    <verse num="8">do not harden your hearts as in the rebellion, in the day of testing in the wilderness,</verse>
    <verse num="9">where your fathers tested <transChange type="added">me</transChange> by trial and saw my works</verse>
    <verse num="10"><transChange type="added">for</transChange> forty years. Therefore I was angry with this generation, and I said, 'They always go astray in their heart, and they do not know my ways.'</verse>
    <verse num="11">As I swore in my anger, '{They will never enter}<note>Literally "if they will enter"</note> into my rest.'"<note>A quotation from Ps 95:7b-11</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">Watch out, brothers, lest there be in some of you an evil, unbelieving heart, <transChange type="added">with the result that you</transChange> fall away<note>*Here "<transChange type="added">with the result that</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the infinitive ("fall away") which is understood as result</note> from the living God.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But encourage one another {day by day}<note>Literally "by each day"</note>, as long as it is called "today," so that {none of you become hardened}<note>Literally "not anyone of you be hardened"</note> by the deception of sin.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For we have become partners of Christ, if indeed we hold fast the beginning of <transChange type="added">our</transChange> commitment steadfast until the end,</verse>
    <verse num="15">{while it is said}<note>Literally "in the saying"</note>, </verse>
    <verse num="16">For who, <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("heard") which is understood as temporal</note> heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, were disobedient? Surely <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> not all who went out from Egypt through Moses?</verse>
    <verse num="17">And with whom was he angry <transChange type="added">for</transChange> forty years? <transChange type="added">Was it</transChange> not with those who sinned, whose dead bodies fell in the wilderness?</verse>
    <verse num="18">And to whom did he swear <transChange type="added">they would</transChange> not enter into his rest, except those who were disobedient?</verse>
    <verse num="19">And <transChange type="added">so</transChange> we see that they were not able to enter because of unbelief. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Therefore let us fear, <transChange type="added">while there</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("remains") which is understood as temporal</note> remains a promise of entering into his rest, that none of you appear to fall short of <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="2">{For we also have had the good news proclaimed to us}<note>Literally "for we are also having had the good news proclaimed"</note>, just as those also <transChange type="added">did</transChange>, but the message {they heard}<note>Literally "of hearing"</note> did not benefit them, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("united") which is understood as causal</note> were not united with those who heard <transChange type="added">it</transChange> in faith.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For we who have believed enter into rest,<note>Some manuscripts have "that rest"</note> just as he has said, </verse>
    <verse num="4">For he has spoken somewhere about the seventh <transChange type="added">day</transChange> in this way: "And God rested on the seventh day from all his works,"<note>A quotation from Gen 2:2</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">and in this <transChange type="added">passage</transChange> again, '{They will never enter}<note>Literally "if they will enter"</note> into my rest.'"<note>A quotation from Ps 95:11</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">Since therefore it remains <transChange type="added">for</transChange> some to enter into it, and the ones to whom the good news was proclaimed previously did not enter because of disobedience,</verse>
    <verse num="7">again he ordains a certain day, today, speaking by David after so long a time, just as had been said before, </verse>
    <verse num="8">For if Joshua had caused them to rest, he would not have spoken about another day after these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Consequently a sabbath rest remains for the people of God.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For the one who has entered into his rest has also himself rested from his works, just as God <transChange type="added">did</transChange> from his own <transChange type="added">works</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="11">Therefore, let us make every effort to enter into that rest, in order that no one may fall in the same pattern of disobedience.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For the word of God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> living and active and sharper than any double-edged sword, and piercing as far as the division of soul and spirit, both joints and marrow, and able to judge the reflections and thoughts of the heart.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And no creature is hidden in the sight of him, but all <transChange type="added">things are</transChange> naked and laid bare to the eyes of him to whom {we must give our account}<note>Literally "our account"</note>. </verse>
    <verse num="14">Therefore, <transChange type="added">because we</transChange> have a great high priest who has gone through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast to our confession.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For we do not have a high priest who is not able to sympathize with our weaknesses, but who has been tempted in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in the same way, without sin.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Therefore let us approach with confidence to the throne of grace, in order that we may receive mercy and find grace to help in time of need. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">For every high priest taken from among men is appointed on behalf of people in the things relating to God, in order that he can offer both gifts and sacrifices on behalf of sins,</verse>
    <verse num="2">being able to deal gently with those who are ignorant and led astray, since he himself also is surrounded by weakness,</verse>
    <verse num="3">and because of it he is obligated to offer <transChange type="added">sacrifices</transChange> for sins {for himself also, as well as for the people}<note>Literally "as for the people so also for himself"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And someone does not take for himself the honor, but is called by God, just as Aaron also <transChange type="added">was</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Thus also Christ did not glorify himself to become high priest, but the one who said to him, </verse>
    <verse num="6">just as also in another <transChange type="added">place</transChange> he says, </verse>
    <verse num="7">who in the days of his flesh offered up both prayers and supplications, with loud crying and tears, to the one who was able to save him from death, and he was heard as a result of his reverence.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Although he was a son, he learned obedience from what he suffered,</verse>
    <verse num="9">and being perfected, he became the source of eternal salvation to all those who obey him,</verse>
    <verse num="10">being designated by God a high priest according to the order of Melchizedek. </verse>
    <verse num="11">Concerning this<note>Literally "which"</note> {we have much to say and it is difficult to explain}<note>Literally "great for us the message and hard to explain to say"</note>, since you have become sluggish in hearing.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For indeed, <transChange type="added">although you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("ought") which is understood as concessive</note> ought to be teachers {by this time}<note>Literally "because of the time"</note>, you have need of someone to teach you again the beginning elements of the oracles of God, and {you have need of}<note>Literally "you are having need of"</note> milk, not<note>Some manuscripts have "and not"</note> solid food.</verse>
    <verse num="13">For everyone who partakes of milk <transChange type="added">is</transChange> unacquainted with the message of righteousness, because he is an infant.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But solid food is for the mature, who because of practice have trained their faculties for the distinguishing of both good and evil. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, leaving behind the elementary message about Christ, let us move on to maturity, not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works and faith in God,</verse>
    <verse num="2">teaching about baptisms and laying on of hands, and resurrection of the dead and eternal judgment.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And this we will do, if God permits.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> impossible <transChange type="added">concerning</transChange> those who have once been enlightened, and have tasted the heavenly gift, and become sharers of the Holy Spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="5">and have tasted the good word of God and the powers of the coming age,</verse>
    <verse num="6">and having fallen away, to renew <transChange type="added">them</transChange> again to repentance, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have crucified again") which is understood as causal</note> have crucified again for themselves the Son of God and held him up to contempt.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For ground that drinks the rain that comes often upon it, and brings forth vegetation usable to those <transChange type="added">people</transChange> {for whose sake}<note>Literally "for the sake of whom"</note> <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> also cultivated, shares a blessing from God.</verse>
    <verse num="8">But <transChange type="added">if it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("produces") which is understood as conditional</note> produces thorns and thistles, <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> worthless and near to a curse, whose end <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for burning. </verse>
    <verse num="9">But even if we are speaking in this way, dear friends, we are convinced of better <transChange type="added">things</transChange> concerning you, and belonging to salvation.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not unjust, <transChange type="added">so as</transChange> to forget your work and the love which you demonstrated for his name <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("having served") which is understood as means</note> having served the saints, and continuing to serve <transChange type="added">them</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And we desire each one of you to demonstrate the same diligence for the full assurance of <transChange type="added">your</transChange> hope until the end,</verse>
    <verse num="12">in order that you may not be sluggish, but imitators of those who inherit the promises through faith and patience. </verse>
    <verse num="13">For <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("made a promise")</note> God made a promise to Abraham, since he had no one greater to swear by, he swore by himself,</verse>
    <verse num="14">saying, </verse>
    <verse num="15">And so, <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("persevering") which is understood as means</note> persevering, he obtained the promise.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For people swear by what is greater <transChange type="added">than themselves</transChange>, and the oath for confirmation <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> end of all dispute for them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">In the same way God, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("wanted") which is understood as causal</note> wanted to show even more to the heirs of the promise the unchangeableness of his resolve, guaranteed <transChange type="added">it</transChange> with an oath,</verse>
    <verse num="18">in order that through two unchangeable things, in which <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> impossible for God to lie, we who have taken refuge may have powerful encouragement to hold fast to the hope set before <transChange type="added">us</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="19">which we have like an anchor of the soul, both firm and steadfast, and entering into the inside of the curtain,</verse>
    <verse num="20">where Jesus, the forerunner for us, entered, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("became") which is understood as causal</note> became a high priest {forever}<note>Literally "to the age"</note> according to the order of Melchizedek. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">For this Melchizedek, king of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was returning") which is understood as temporal</note> was returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him,<note>This verse contains a number of quotations from Gen 14:17-19</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">to whom also Abraham apportioned a tenth of everything<note>A quotation from Gen 14:20</note>--in the first place, <transChange type="added">his name</transChange> is translated "king of righteousness," and then also "king of Salem," that is, "king of peace";</verse>
    <verse num="3">without father, without mother, without genealogy, having neither beginning of days nor end of life, but resembling the Son of God--he remains a priest for all time. </verse>
    <verse num="4">But see how great this man <transChange type="added">was</transChange>, to whom Abraham<note>Some manuscripts have "even Abraham"</note> the patriarch gave a tenth from the spoils!</verse>
    <verse num="5">And indeed those of the sons of Levi who receive the priesthood have a commandment to collect a tenth from the people according to the law, that is, from their brothers, although {they are descended from Abraham}<note>Literally "coming forth from the loins of Abraham"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="6">But the one who did not trace <transChange type="added">his</transChange> descent from them collected tithes from Abraham and blessed the one who had the promises.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Now without any dispute the inferior is blessed by the more prominent.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And in this case mortal men receive tithes, but in that case it is testified that he lives.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And, {so to speak}<note>Literally "as if to say a word"</note>, even Levi, the one who receives tithes, has paid tithes through Abraham.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For he was still in the loins of his father when Melchizedek met him. </verse>
    <verse num="11">Thus if perfection was through the Levitical priesthood, for on the basis of it the people received the law, what further need <transChange type="added">is there</transChange> for another priest to arise according to the order of Melchizedek and not said to be according to the order of Aaron?</verse>
    <verse num="12">For <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("changes")</note> the priesthood changes, of necessity there is a change of the law also.</verse>
    <verse num="13">For the one about whom these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are spoken belongs to another tribe from which no one has officiated at the altar.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> evident that our Lord is a descendant of Judah, a tribe <transChange type="added">with reference</transChange> to which Moses said nothing concerning priests.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And it is still more clear, if another priest according to the likeness of Melchizedek arises,</verse>
    <verse num="16">who has become <transChange type="added">a priest</transChange> not according to a law of physical requirement, but according to the power of an indestructible life.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For it is testified, </verse>
    <verse num="18">For on the one hand a preceding commandment is set aside because of its weakness and uselessness</verse>
    <verse num="19">(for the law <transChange type="added">made</transChange> nothing perfect), but on the other hand <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> the introduction of a better hope through which we draw near to God.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And by as much as <transChange type="added">this was</transChange> not without an oath (for these on the one hand {have become priests}<note>Literally "are having become priests"</note> without an oath,</verse>
    <verse num="21">but he with an oath by the one who said to him, </verse>
    <verse num="22">by so much more<note>Some manuscripts have "so much more also"</note> Jesus has become the guarantee of a better covenant. </verse>
    <verse num="23">And indeed many {have become}<note>Literally "are having become"</note> priests, because they were prevented by death from continuing <transChange type="added">in office</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="24">but he, because he continues {forever}<note>Literally "for the age"</note>, holds the priesthood permanently.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Therefore also he is able to save completely those who draw near to God through him, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("lives") which is understood as causal</note> always lives in order to intercede on their behalf. </verse>
    <verse num="26">For a high priest such as this indeed is fitting for us, holy, innocent, undefiled, separated from sinners, and having become exalted <transChange type="added">above</transChange> the heavens,</verse>
    <verse num="27">who does not {need every day}<note>Literally "have necessity every day"</note> like the former high priests to offer up sacrifices for his own sins <transChange type="added">and</transChange> then for the <transChange type="added">sins</transChange> of the people, because he did this once for all <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("offered up")</note> offered up himself.</verse>
    <verse num="28">For the law appoints men <transChange type="added">as</transChange> high priests who have weakness, but the statement of the oath, after the law, <transChange type="added">appoints</transChange> a Son, who is made perfect {forever}<note>Literally "for the age"</note>. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">Now <transChange type="added">this is</transChange> the main point in what has been said: we have a high priest such as this, who sat down at the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in heaven,</verse>
    <verse num="2">a minister of the sanctuary and of the true tabernacle which the Lord set up, not man.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For every high priest is appointed in order to offer both gifts and sacrifices; therefore <transChange type="added">it was</transChange><note>*Or "<transChange type="added">it is</transChange>"; either a present or a past tense verb may be supplied here</note> necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> this one also to have something that he offers.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Now if he were on earth, he would not even be a priest, <transChange type="added">because there</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as causal</note> are those who offer the gifts according to the law,</verse>
    <verse num="5">who serve a sketch and shadow of the heavenly <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, just as Moses was warned <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("about")</note> was about to complete the tabernacle, for he says, "See to it that you make everything according to the pattern which was shown to you on the mountain."<note>A quotation from Exod 25:40</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">But now he has attained a more excellent ministry, by as much as he is also mediator of a better covenant which has been enacted upon better promises.</verse>
    <verse num="7">For if that first <transChange type="added">covenant</transChange> had been faultless, occasion would not have been sought for a second.</verse>
    <verse num="8">For in finding fault with them he says, </verse>
    <verse num="9">not like the covenant which I made with their fathers on the day I took hold of them by my hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt, because they did not continue in my covenant and I disregarded them, says the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the covenant that I will decree with the house of Israel after those days, says the Lord: I am putting my laws in their minds and I will write them on their hearts, and I will be {their}<note>Literally "to them for"</note> God and they will be {my}<note>Literally "to me for"</note> people.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And they will not teach each one his fellow citizen and each one his brother, saying, 'Know the Lord,' because they will all know me, from the least of them to the greatest.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For I will be merciful toward their wrongdoings, and I will not remember their sins <transChange type="added">any</transChange> longer."</verse>
    <verse num="13">In calling <transChange type="added">it</transChange> new, he has declared the former <transChange type="added">to be old</transChange>. Now what is becoming obsolete and growing old <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near to disappearing. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">Now<note>Some manuscripts have "Now even"</note> the first <transChange type="added">covenant</transChange> had regulations for worship and the earthly sanctuary.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For a tent was prepared, the first <transChange type="added">one</transChange>, in which <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the lampstand and the table and the presentation of the loaves, which is called the holy place.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And after the second curtain <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a tent called the holy of holies,</verse>
    <verse num="4">containing the golden incense altar and the ark of the covenant covered on all sides with gold, in which <transChange type="added">were</transChange> a golden jar containing the manna and the rod of Aaron that budded and the tablets of the covenant.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And above it <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the cherubim of glory overshadowing the mercy seat, about which it is not now <transChange type="added">possible</transChange> to speak in detail. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Now these things having been prepared in this way, the priests enter into the first tent {continually}<note>Literally "throughout all"</note> <transChange type="added">as they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("accomplish")</note> accomplish their service,</verse>
    <verse num="7">but only the high priest <transChange type="added">enters</transChange> into the second <transChange type="added">tent</transChange> once a year, not without blood, which he offers on behalf of himself and the <transChange type="added">sins</transChange> of the people committed in ignorance.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The Holy Spirit <transChange type="added">was</transChange> making this clear, <transChange type="added">that</transChange> the way <transChange type="added">into</transChange> the holy place <transChange type="added">was</transChange> not yet revealed, <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was")</note> the first tent was still in existence,</verse>
    <verse num="9">which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a symbol for the present time, in which both the gifts and sacrifices which were offered were not able to perfect the worshiper with respect to the conscience,</verse>
    <verse num="10">concerning <transChange type="added">instead</transChange> only food and drink and different washings, regulations of outward things imposed until the time of setting <transChange type="added">things</transChange> right. </verse>
    <verse num="11">But Christ has arrived <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a high priest of the good <transChange type="added">things</transChange> to come. Through the greater and more perfect tent not made by hands, that is, not of this creation,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and not by the blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood, he entered once for all into the <transChange type="added">most</transChange> holy place, obtaining eternal redemption.</verse>
    <verse num="13">For if the blood of goats and bulls and the ashes of a young cow sprinkled on those who are defiled sanctify <transChange type="added">them</transChange> for the ritual purity of the flesh,</verse>
    <verse num="14">how much more will the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works to serve <transChange type="added">the</transChange> living God? </verse>
    <verse num="15">And because of this, he is the mediator of a new covenant, in order that, <transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("has taken place") which is understood as causal</note> a death has taken place for the redemption of transgressions <transChange type="added">committed</transChange> during the first covenant, those who are the called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For where <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> a will, <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> a necessity <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the death of the one who made the will to be established.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For a will <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in force concerning those who are dead, since <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> never in force when the one who made the will is alive.</verse>
    <verse num="18">Therefore not even the first <transChange type="added">covenant</transChange> was ratified without blood.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("had been spoken")</note> every commandment had been spoken by Moses to all the people according to the law, <transChange type="added">he</transChange> took the blood of calves<note>Some manuscripts have "calves and goats"</note> with water and scarlet wool and hyssop <transChange type="added">and</transChange> sprinkled both the scroll itself and all the people,</verse>
    <verse num="20">saying, </verse>
    <verse num="21">And likewise he sprinkled both the tabernacle and all the utensils of service with the blood.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Indeed, nearly everything is purified with blood according to the law, and apart from the shedding of blood there is no forgiveness. </verse>
    <verse num="23">Therefore <transChange type="added">it was</transChange> necessary <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the sketches of the <transChange type="added">things</transChange> in heaven to be purified with these <transChange type="added">sacrifices</transChange>, but the heavenly <transChange type="added">things</transChange> themselves <transChange type="added">to be purified</transChange> with better sacrifices than these.</verse>
    <verse num="24">For Christ did not enter into a sanctuary made by hands, a <transChange type="added">mere</transChange> copy of the true <transChange type="added">one</transChange>, but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God on our behalf,</verse>
    <verse num="25">and not in order that he can offer himself many times, as the high priest enters into the sanctuary {year by year}<note>Literally "according to year"</note> with blood not his own,</verse>
    <verse num="26">since it would have been necessary for him to suffer many times from the foundation of the world, but now he has appeared once at the end of the ages for the removal of sin by the sacrifice of himself.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And {just as}<note>Literally "in as much as"</note> it is destined for people to die once, and after this, judgment,</verse>
    <verse num="28">thus also Christ, having been offered once in order to bear the sins of many, will appear for the second time without reference to sin to those who eagerly await him for salvation. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">For the law, possessing a shadow of the good <transChange type="added">things</transChange> that are about to come, not the form of things itself, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> never able {year by year}<note>Literally "according to year"</note> by means of the same sacrifices which they offer without interruption to make perfect those who draw near.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For otherwise, would they not have ceased to be offered, because the ones who worship, having been purified once and for all, would no longer have any consciousness of sins?</verse>
    <verse num="3">But in them <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> a reminder of sins {year by year}<note>Literally "according to year"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="4">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> impossible <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the blood of bulls and goats to take away sins. </verse>
    <verse num="5">Therefore, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("came")</note> came into the world, he said, </verse>
    <verse num="6">you did not delight in whole burnt offerings and <transChange type="added">offerings</transChange> for sins.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then I said, 'Behold, I have come-- in the roll of the book it is written about me-- to do your will, O God.'</verse>
    <verse num="8"><transChange type="added">When he</transChange> says above, </verse>
    <verse num="9">then he has said, </verse>
    <verse num="10">by which will we are made holy through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all. </verse>
    <verse num="11">And every priest stands every day serving and offering the same sacrifices many times, which are never able to take away sins.</verse>
    <verse num="12">But this one, <transChange type="added">after he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("had offered")</note> had offered one sacrifice for sins for all time, sat down at the right hand of God,</verse>
    <verse num="13">from now on waiting until his enemies are made a footstool for his feet.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For by one offering he has perfected for all time those who are made holy.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the Holy Spirit also testifies to us, for after saying, </verse>
    <verse num="16">"This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the covenant that I will decree for them after those days, says the Lord: I am putting my laws on their hearts, and I will write them on their minds."<note>A quotation from Jer 31:33</note></verse>
    <verse num="17"><transChange type="added">He</transChange> also <transChange type="added">says</transChange>, </verse>
    <verse num="18">Now where <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> forgiveness of these, <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> no longer an offering for sin. </verse>
    <verse num="19">Therefore, brothers, <transChange type="added">since we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">since</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have") which is understood as causal</note> have confidence for the entrance into the sanctuary by the blood of Jesus,</verse>
    <verse num="20"><transChange type="added">by the</transChange> new and living way which he inaugurated for us through the curtain, that is, his flesh,</verse>
    <verse num="21">and <transChange type="added">since we have</transChange><note>These words are an implied repetition from v. 19 for clarity</note> a great priest over the house of God,</verse>
    <verse num="22">let us approach with a true heart in the full assurance of faith, our hearts sprinkled <transChange type="added">clean</transChange> from an evil conscience and our bodies washed with pure water.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Let us hold fast to the confession of <transChange type="added">our</transChange> hope without wavering, for the one who promised <transChange type="added">is</transChange> faithful.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And let us think about {how to stir one another up to love}<note>Literally "one another for the stirring up of love"</note> and good works,</verse>
    <verse num="25">not abandoning {our meeting together}<note>Literally "the meeting of ourselves"</note>, as <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the habit of some, but encouraging <transChange type="added">each other</transChange>, and by so much more as you see the day drawing near. </verse>
    <verse num="26">For <transChange type="added">if</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the conditional genitive absolute participle ("keep on sinning")</note> we keep on sinning deliberately after receiving the knowledge of the truth, there no longer remains a sacrifice for sins,</verse>
    <verse num="27">but a certain fearful expectation of judgment and a fury of fire that is about to consume the adversaries.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Anyone who rejected the law of Moses dies without mercy on <transChange type="added">the testimony of</transChange> two or three witnesses.</verse>
    <verse num="29">How much worse punishment do you think the person will be considered worthy of who treats with disdain the Son of God and who considers ordinary the blood of the covenant by which he was made holy and who insults the Spirit of grace?</verse>
    <verse num="30">For we know the one who said, </verse>
    <verse num="31"><transChange type="added">It is</transChange> a terrifying <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> to fall into the hands of the living God. </verse>
    <verse num="32">But remember the former days in which, <transChange type="added">after you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("were enlightened")</note> were enlightened, you endured a great struggle with sufferings,</verse>
    <verse num="33">sometimes being publicly exposed both to insults and to afflictions, and sometimes becoming sharers with those who were treated in this way.</verse>
    <verse num="34">For you both sympathized with the prisoners and put up with the seizure of your belongings with joy <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("knew") which is understood as causal</note> knew that you yourselves had a better and permanent possession.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Therefore do not throw away your confidence, which has great reward.</verse>
    <verse num="36">For you have need of endurance, in order that <transChange type="added">after you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("have done")</note> have done the will of God, you may receive what was promised.</verse>
    <verse num="37">For yet </verse>
    <verse num="38">But my righteous one will live by faith, and if he shrinks back, my soul is not well pleased with him."<note>A quotation from Hab 2:3-4</note></verse>
    <verse num="39">But we are not among those who shrink back to destruction, but among those who have faith to the preservation of <transChange type="added">our</transChange> souls. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Now faith is the realization of what is hoped for, the proof of things not seen.</verse>
    <verse num="2">For by this the people of old were approved.</verse>
    <verse num="3">By faith we understand the worlds were created by the word of God, in order that what is seen did not come into existence from what is visible. </verse>
    <verse num="4">By faith Abel offered to God a greater sacrifice than Cain, by which he was approved that he was righteous, <transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was")</note> God approved <transChange type="added">him</transChange> for his gifts, and through it<note>I.e., his faith</note> he still speaks, <transChange type="added">although he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("is dead") which is understood as concessive</note> is dead.</verse>
    <verse num="5">By faith Enoch was taken up, so that he did not experience death, and he was not found, because God took him up. For before his removal, he had been approved {as having been pleasing}<note>Literally "to be pleasing"</note> to God.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Now without faith <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> impossible to please <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, for the one who approaches God must believe that he exists and is a rewarder of those who seek him.</verse>
    <verse num="7">By faith Noah, having been warned about things not yet seen, out of reverence constructed an ark for the deliverance of his family, by which he pronounced sentence on the world and became an heir of the righteousness that comes by faith. </verse>
    <verse num="8">By faith Abraham, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was called")</note> was called, obeyed to go out to a place that he was going to receive for an inheritance, and he went out, not knowing where he was going.</verse>
    <verse num="9">By faith he lived in the land of promise as a stranger, living in tents with Isaac and Jacob, the fellow heirs of the same promise.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For he was expecting the city that has foundations, whose architect and builder <transChange type="added">is</transChange> God.</verse>
    <verse num="11">By faith also, {with Sarah}<note>Literally "with her, Sarah"</note>,<note>Some manuscripts have "even though Sarah herself was barren"</note> he received {the ability to procreate}<note>Literally "power to deposit seed"</note> even {past the normal age}<note>Literally "beyond the time of maturity"</note>, because he regarded the one who had promised <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> faithful.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And therefore these were fathered from one man, and <transChange type="added">he</transChange> being as good as dead, as the stars of heaven in number and like the innumerable sand by the shore of the sea. </verse>
    <verse num="13">These all died in faith without receiving the promises, but seeing them from a distance and welcoming <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, and admitting that they were strangers and temporary residents on the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For those who say such <transChange type="added">things</transChange> make clear that they are seeking a homeland.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And if they remember<note>Some manuscripts have "they had been remembering"</note> that <transChange type="added">land</transChange> from which they went out, they would have had opportunity to return.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But now they aspire to a better <transChange type="added">land</transChange>, that is, a heavenly <transChange type="added">one</transChange>. Therefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God, for he has prepared for them a city. </verse>
    <verse num="17">By faith Abraham, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange> was tested, offered Isaac, and the one who received the promises was ready to offer his one and only <transChange type="added">son</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="18">with reference to whom it was said, "In Isaac your descendants will be named,"<note>A quotation from Gen 21:12</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">having reasoned that God <transChange type="added">was</transChange> able even to raise <transChange type="added">him</transChange> from the dead, from which he received him back also as a symbol.</verse>
    <verse num="20">By faith also Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things that were going to happen.</verse>
    <verse num="21">By faith Jacob, <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was dying")</note> was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph and worshiped, <transChange type="added">leaning</transChange> on the top of his staff.</verse>
    <verse num="22">By faith Joseph, <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was dying")</note> was dying, mentioned about the exodus of the sons of Israel and gave instructions about his bones. </verse>
    <verse num="23">By faith Moses, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("afraid of")</note> was born, was hidden for three months by his parents, because they saw the child <transChange type="added">was</transChange> handsome, and they were not afraid of the edict of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="24">By faith Moses, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("was")</note> was grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter,</verse>
    <verse num="25">choosing instead to be mistreated with the people of God <transChange type="added">rather</transChange> than to experience the transitory enjoyment of sin,</verse>
    <verse num="26">considering {reproach endured for the sake of Christ}<note>Literally "the reproach of Christ"</note> greater wealth than the treasures of Egypt, for he was looking to the reward.</verse>
    <verse num="27">By faith he left Egypt, not fearing the anger of the king, for he persevered as <transChange type="added">if he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("saw") which is understood as conditional</note> saw the invisible one.</verse>
    <verse num="28">By faith he kept the Passover and the sprinkling of blood, in order that the one who destroyed the firstborn would not touch them.</verse>
    <verse num="29">By faith they crossed the Red Sea as if on dry land; the Egyptians, {when they made the attempt}<note>Literally "of which attempt making"</note>, were drowned.</verse>
    <verse num="30">By faith the walls of Jericho fell down <transChange type="added">after they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("had been marched around")</note> had been marched around for seven days.</verse>
    <verse num="31">By faith Rahab the prostitute did not perish with those who were disobedient, <transChange type="added">because she</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("welcomed") which is understood as causal</note> welcomed the spies in peace. </verse>
    <verse num="32">And what more shall I say? For time would fail me to tell about Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah, David, and Samuel and the prophets,</verse>
    <verse num="33">who through faith conquered kingdoms, accomplished justice, obtained what was promised, shut the mouths of lions,</verse>
    <verse num="34">extinguished the effectiveness of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, were made strong from weakness, became mighty in battle, put to flight enemy battle lines.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Women received back their dead by resurrection. But others were tortured, not accepting release, in order that they might gain a better resurrection.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And others {experienced mocking and flogging}<note>Literally "received experience of mocking and flogging"</note>, and in addition bonds and imprisonment.</verse>
    <verse num="37">They were stoned, they were sawed in two, they died by murder with a sword, they wandered about in sheepskins, in goatskins, impoverished, afflicted, mistreated,</verse>
    <verse num="38">of whom the world was not worthy, wandering about on deserts and mountains and in caves and in holes in the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And <transChange type="added">although they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were approved") which is understood as concessive</note> all were approved<note>Some manuscripts have "And all these, <transChange type="added">although they</transChange> were approved"</note> through their faith, they did not receive what was promised,</verse>
    <verse num="40"><transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the causal genitive absolute participle ("had provided")</note> God had provided something better for us, so that they would not be made perfect without us. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, <transChange type="added">since</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">since</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have") which is understood as causal</note> we also have such a great cloud of witnesses surrounding us, putting aside every weight and {the sin that so easily ensnares us}<note>Literally "the easily ensnaring sin"</note>, let us run with patient endurance the race that has been set before us,</verse>
    <verse num="2">fixing our eyes on Jesus, the originator and perfecter of faith, who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, disregarding the shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For consider the one who endured such hostility by sinners against himself,<note>*The plural reflexive pronoun can still be translated as singular; see Louw-Nida 92.25</note> so that you will not grow weary in your souls <transChange type="added">and</transChange> give up.</verse>
    <verse num="4">You have not yet resisted to the point of <transChange type="added">shedding your</transChange><note>*The words "shedding your" are not in the Greek text but are supplied for clarity</note> blood <transChange type="added">as you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("struggle")</note> struggle against sin.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And have you completely forgotten the exhortation which instructs you as sons? </verse>
    <verse num="6">For the Lord disciplines the one whom he loves, and punishes every son whom he accepts."<note>A quotation from Prov 3:11-12</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">Endure <transChange type="added">it</transChange> for discipline. God is dealing with you as sons. For what son <transChange type="added">is there</transChange> whom a father does not discipline?</verse>
    <verse num="8">But if you are without discipline, in which all <transChange type="added">legitimate sons</transChange><note>*The phrase "legitimate sons" is not in the Greek text but is implied</note> have become participants, then you are illegitimate and not sons.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Furthermore, we have had {our earthly fathers}<note>Literally "the flesh of our fathers"</note> who disciplined <transChange type="added">us</transChange>, and we respected <transChange type="added">them</transChange>. Will we not much rather subject ourselves to the Father of spirits and live?</verse>
    <verse num="10">For they disciplined <transChange type="added">us</transChange> for a few days according to what seemed <transChange type="added">appropriate</transChange> to them, but he <transChange type="added">does so</transChange> for our benefit, in order that <transChange type="added">we</transChange> can have a share in his holiness.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Now all discipline seems for the moment not to be joyful but painful, but later it yields the peaceful fruit of righteousness for those who are trained by it. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore strengthen your slackened hands and your weakened knees,</verse>
    <verse num="13">and make straight paths for your feet, so that what is lame will not be dislocated, but rather be healed.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Pursue peace with everyone, and holiness, without which no one will see the Lord.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Take care <transChange type="added">that</transChange> no one falls short of the grace of God; <transChange type="added">that</transChange> no one growing up <transChange type="added">like</transChange> a root of bitterness causes trouble, and by it many become defiled;</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">that</transChange> no one <transChange type="added">be</transChange> a sexually immoral or totally worldly <transChange type="added">person</transChange> like Esau, who for one meal traded his own birthright.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For you know that also afterwards, <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("wanted")</note> wanted to inherit the blessing, he was rejected, because he did not find an occasion for repentance, although he sought it with tears. </verse>
    <verse num="18">For you have not come to something that can be touched, and to a burning fire, and to darkness, and to gloom, and to a whirlwind,</verse>
    <verse num="19">and to the noise of a trumpet, and to the sound of words which those who heard begged <transChange type="added">that</transChange> not <transChange type="added">another</transChange> word be spoken to them.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For they could not endure what was commanded: "If even an animal touches the mountain, it must be stoned."<note>A quotation from Exod 19:12-13</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">And the spectacle was so terrifying <transChange type="added">that</transChange> Moses said, "I am terrified and trembling."<note>A quotation from Deut 9:19</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">But you have come to Mount Zion, and to the city of the living God, to the heavenly Jerusalem, and to tens of thousands of angels, to the festal gathering</verse>
    <verse num="23">and assembly of the firstborn who are enrolled in heaven, and to God the judge of all, and to the spirits of righteous <transChange type="added">people</transChange> made perfect,</verse>
    <verse num="24">and to Jesus, the mediator of a new covenant, and {to the sprinkled blood}<note>Literally "to the blood of sprinkling"</note> that speaks better than Abel's <transChange type="added">does</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="25">Watch out that you do not refuse the one who is speaking! For if those did not escape <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal participle ("refused")</note> refused the one who warned <transChange type="added">them</transChange> on earth, much less <transChange type="added">will</transChange> we <transChange type="added">escape</transChange>,<note>*Here the verb "will ... escape" is an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> <transChange type="added">if we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("reject") which is understood as conditional</note> reject the <transChange type="added">one who warns</transChange> from heaven,</verse>
    <verse num="26">whose voice shook the earth at that time, but now he has promised, saying, </verse>
    <verse num="27">Now the <transChange type="added">phrase</transChange> "yet once <transChange type="added">more</transChange>" indicates the removal of what is shaken, namely, things that have been created, in order that the things that are not shaken may remain.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Therefore, <transChange type="added">since we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">since</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are receiving") which is understood as causal</note> are receiving an unshakable kingdom, let us be thankful, through which let us serve God acceptably, with awe and reverence.</verse>
    <verse num="29">For indeed our God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a consuming fire. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">Brotherly love must continue.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Do not neglect hospitality, because through this some have received angels as guests without knowing <transChange type="added">it</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Remember the prisoners, as <transChange type="added">though you were</transChange> fellow-prisoners; <transChange type="added">remember</transChange><note>*This is an understood repetition of the verb from the previous clause</note> the mistreated, as <transChange type="added">though</transChange> <transChange type="added">you</transChange> yourselves also are being <transChange type="added">mistreated</transChange><note>*This is an understood repetition of the participle from the previous clause</note> in the body.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Marriage <transChange type="added">must be</transChange> held in honor by all, and the marriage bed <transChange type="added">be</transChange> undefiled, because God will judge sexually immoral people and adulterers.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Your lifestyle <transChange type="added">must be</transChange> free from the love of money, being content with what you have. For he himself has said, "I will never desert you, and I will never abandon you."<note>A quotation from Deut 31:6, 8</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">So then, we can say with confidence, </verse>
    <verse num="7">Remember your leaders, who spoke the word of God to you; {considering the outcome of their way of life}<note>Literally "of whom considering the outcome of the way of life"</note>, imitate their faith.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the same yesterday and today and {forever}<note>Literally "to the ages"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Do not be carried away by various and strange teachings, for <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> good <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the heart to be strengthened by grace, not by foods by which those who participate have not benefited.</verse>
    <verse num="10">We have an altar from which those who serve in the tabernacle do not have the right to eat.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For the bodies of those animals whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high priest for sins are burned up outside the camp.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore Jesus also suffered outside the gate, in order that he might sanctify the people by his own blood.</verse>
    <verse num="13">So we must go out to him outside the camp, bearing his reproach.</verse>
    <verse num="14">For here we do not have a permanent city, but we seek the <transChange type="added">city</transChange> that is to come.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Therefore through him let us offer up a sacrifice of praise {continually}<note>Literally "through all"</note> to God, that is, the fruit of lips that confess his name.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And do not neglect doing good and generosity, for God is pleased with such sacrifices. </verse>
    <verse num="17">Obey your leaders and submit <transChange type="added">to them</transChange>, for they keep watch over your souls as those who will give an account, so that they can do this with joy and not <transChange type="added">with</transChange> groaning, for this <transChange type="added">would be</transChange> unprofitable for you. </verse>
    <verse num="18">Pray for us, for we are convinced that we have a good conscience, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> want to conduct ourselves commendably in every <transChange type="added">way</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And I especially urge <transChange type="added">you</transChange> to do this, so that I may be restored to you more quickly. </verse>
    <verse num="20">Now may the God of peace, who brought up from the dead our Lord Jesus, the great shepherd of the sheep, by the blood of the eternal covenant,</verse>
    <verse num="21">equip you with every good <transChange type="added">thing</transChange> to do his will, carrying out in us <transChange type="added">what is</transChange> pleasing before him through Jesus Christ, to whom <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the glory {forever}<note>Literally "to the ages"</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have "forever and ever" (literally, "to the ages of the ages")</note> Amen. </verse>
    <verse num="22">Now I urge you, brothers, bear with my word of exhortation, for indeed I have written to you {briefly}<note>Literally "through few words"</note>.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Know <transChange type="added">that</transChange> our brother Timothy has been released, with whom I will see you, if he comes quickly <transChange type="added">enough</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Greet all your leaders and all the saints. Those from Italy greet you.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Grace <transChange type="added">be</transChange> with all of you. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>