<book num="Joel">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The word of Yahweh that came to Joel son of Pethuel. </verse>
    <verse num="2">Hear this, O elders, and give ear, all the inhabitants of the land. Has this happened in your days? Or the days of your ancestors?</verse>
    <verse num="3">Tell it to your children, and your children to their children, and their children to the following generation.</verse>
    <verse num="4">What the cutting locust left, the swarming locust has eaten. What the swarming locust left, the hopping locust has eaten. And what the hopping locust left, the destroying locust has eaten.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Wake up, drunkards, and weep! Wail, all drinkers of wine, over the new wine, for it is cut off from your mouth.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Because a nation has {invaded}<note>Literally "come up against"</note> my land, strong {and beyond counting}.<note>Literally "without number"</note> Its teeth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the teeth of a lion, and its fangs <transChange type="added">are those</transChange> of a lioness.</verse>
    <verse num="7">It has made my vine a desolation, and my fig tree a completely splintered stump. It has stripped them bare and thrown <transChange type="added">them</transChange> down; their branches have turned white.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Lament like a virgin girded in sackcloth for the husband of her youth.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The offering and libation are withheld from the house<note>Or "temple"</note> of Yahweh. The priests mourn, the ministers of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The field is destroyed; the earth mourns because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> grain is destroyed, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> new wine dries up, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> olive oil languishes.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Be ashamed, farmers; Wail, vinedressers, over <transChange type="added">the</transChange> wheat and over <transChange type="added">the</transChange> barley, because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> harvest of the field is ruined.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The vine withers and the fig tree droops. The pomegranate tree, and also the palm tree, the apple tree --all the trees of the field--are dried up. Indeed, joy is dried up among the sons of men.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Gird yourselves and lament, O priests! Wail, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> ministers of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> altar! Come spend the night in sackcloth, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> ministers of my God, because offering and libation are withheld from the house of your God.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Solemnize a fast! Call an assembly! Gather <transChange type="added">the</transChange> elders, all <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the inhabitants of the land <transChange type="added">in</transChange> the house of Yahweh your God, and cry out to Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Ah! For the day! For the day of Yahweh is near. It will come like destruction from Shaddai.<note>Often translated "the Almighty"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">Is</transChange> not food cut <transChange type="added">off</transChange> before our eyes, from the house of our God, joy and gladness?</verse>
    <verse num="17">The seeds shrivel under their clods; the storehouses are desolate. The grain storage places are destroyed because grain has dried out.</verse>
    <verse num="18">How <transChange type="added">the</transChange> beasts<note>Hebrew "beast"</note> groan; the herds of cattle wander around because there is no pasture for them; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> flocks of sheep are in distress.</verse>
    <verse num="19">To you, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Yahweh, I cry out, because fire has devoured the pastures of the desert, and flames<note>Hebrew "flame"</note> burned all the trees of the field.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Also, the beasts of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> field long for you, because the courses of water are dried up, and fire has devoured the pastures of the desert.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Blow <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trumpet<note>Hebrew "shofar"</note> in Zion, and sound the alarm on {my holy mountain}!<note>Literally "mountain of my holiness"</note> Let all the inhabitants of the land tremble, for the day of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> coming --<transChange type="added">it is</transChange> indeed near.</verse>
    <verse num="2">A day of darkness and gloom, a day of cloud and thick darkness, like the dawn spreads on the mountains, a great and strong army! There has been nothing like it from old, and after it nothing will be again {for generations to come}.<note>Literally "until years of generations"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">{Before them}<note>Literally "before the presence of it"</note> a fire devours, and behind them a flame burns. Like the garden of Eden is the land {before them},<note>Literally "before the presence of it"</note> and after them <transChange type="added">it is like</transChange> a desolate desert, and nothing can escape them.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> appearance of horses is their appearance, and like horsemen they run;</verse>
    <verse num="5">like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sound of chariots on the tops of the mountains, they leap about; like <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sound of a flame of fire devouring stubble; like a strong army arranged in rows <transChange type="added">for</transChange> battle.</verse>
    <verse num="6">{From before them}<note>Or "From in front of it," or "From the presence of it"</note> nations writhe, all faces {turn pale}.<note>Literally "gather paleness"</note></verse>
    <verse num="7">They run like mighty warriors,<note>That is, the "great and strong army" (see 2:2)</note> they scale the wall like men of war; each goes on its own way, and they do not swerve <transChange type="added">from</transChange> their paths.</verse>
    <verse num="8">They do not jostle {one another};<note>Literally "each man his brother"</note> each goes on its own trail; and through the falling weapons,<note>Hebrew "weapon"</note> they are not halted.</verse>
    <verse num="9">In the city they rush forth; on the walls<note>Hebrew "wall"</note> they run. Into the houses they climb up; through the windows they enter like <transChange type="added">a</transChange> thief.</verse>
    <verse num="10">{Before them}<note>Literally "Before the presence of it"</note> <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth quakes; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> heavens tremble; <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sun and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> moon grow dark, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> stars {have withheld}<note>Literally "gathered"</note> their splendor</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Yahweh {utters}<note>Literally "gives"</note> his voice before his army, because his encampment <transChange type="added">is</transChange> very large; strong <transChange type="added">is the</transChange> one who carries out his decree, for great <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the day of Yahweh and exceedingly fearful. Who can endure it?</verse>
    <verse num="12">"And even now," {declares}<note>Literally "a declaration of"</note> Yahweh, "return to me with all your heart, with fasting, and weeping, and wailing."</verse>
    <verse num="13">Rend your hearts<note>Hebrew "heart"</note> and not your garments, and return to Yahweh your God, because he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> gracious and compassionate, {slow to anger}<note>Or "patient"; literally "long of anger"</note> and great in loyal love, and relenting from harm.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Who knows <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> he will turn and relent, and leave a blessing behind him, an offering and a libation, for Yahweh your God?</verse>
    <verse num="15">Blow <transChange type="added">the</transChange> trumpet<note>Hebrew "Shofar"</note> in Zion, sanctify a fast, call an assembly;</verse>
    <verse num="16">gather <transChange type="added">the</transChange> people, consecrate <transChange type="added">the</transChange> assembly; assemble <transChange type="added">the</transChange> elders, gather <transChange type="added">the</transChange> children, even those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> breast-feeding; let <transChange type="added">the</transChange> bridegroom come out from his private room, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> bride from her canopy.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Between the colonnade and the altar, let the priests, the ministers of Yahweh, weep. And let them say, "Take pity, Yahweh, on your people. Do not make your inheritance a reproach, a byword among <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nations. Why should they say among the nations, 'Where <transChange type="added">is</transChange> their God?'"</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then Yahweh became jealous for his land and took pity on his people.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Yahweh answered and said to his people, "Look at me, <transChange type="added">I am</transChange> sending to you grain, new wine, and olive oil, and you will be satisfied by it. I will not give you <transChange type="added">over</transChange> any more as a disgrace among the nations.</verse>
    <verse num="20">{The northerners}<note>Or "The northern army"</note> I will remove from you; I will drive them to a desert and desolate land, its<note>That is, the northern army</note> front to the eastern sea, and its rear into the western sea; its stench and odor will rise up because he<note>That is, Yahweh (see v. 21)</note> has done great things.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Do not fear, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> land, rejoice and be glad, because Yahweh has done great things.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Do not fear, wild animals of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> field, because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> pastures of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> desert have put forth new green shoots, because <transChange type="added">the</transChange> tree has produced its fruit, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fig tree and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> vine have yielded their produce.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Be glad, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> children of Zion, be glad and rejoice in Yahweh your God, because he has given for you the autumn rains for <transChange type="added">your</transChange> righteousness,<note>Or "vindication"</note> and he has {poured down}<note>Literally "brought down"</note> for you rainwater, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> autumn and spring rains, as before.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The threshing floors will be full <transChange type="added">with</transChange> grain, and the vats will overflow <transChange type="added">with</transChange> new wine and olive oil.</verse>
    <verse num="25">I will repay you the years that the locust has eaten, the hopper, the destroyer, and the cutter, my mighty troops that I sent against you.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And you will eat abundantly and be satisfied, and praise the name of Yahweh your God, who has dealt with you {wondrously}.<note>Literally "to do a wonder"</note> My people {will never be ashamed}.<note>Literally "will forever not be ashamed"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">And you will know that I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> in the midst of Israel, and I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> Yahweh, your God, and there is no <transChange type="added">other</transChange>. My people {will never be ashamed again}.<note>Literally "will forever no longer be ashamed"</note></verse>
    <verse num="28"><note>Joel 2:28-32 in the English Bible is 3:1-5 in the Hebrew Bible</note> And it will happen afterward thus: I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh, and your sons and your daughters will prophesy, and your elders will dream dreams; your young men shall see visions.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And also on the male slaves and on the female slaves, I will pour out my Spirit in those days.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And I will {set}<note>Literally "give"</note> wonders in the heavens, and on earth, blood and fire and columns of smoke.</verse>
    <verse num="31">The sun will be changed to darkness, and the moon to blood, before the coming of the great and awesome day of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And it will happen--everyone who calls on the name of Yahweh will be rescued, because on Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be {those who escape},<note>Literally, "an escape"</note> as Yahweh said, and among the survivors whom Yahweh is calling. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1"><note>Joel 3:1-21 in the English Bible is 4:1-21 in the Hebrew Bible</note> For look! In those days, and in that time, when I will return<note>Or "restore"</note> the fortunes of Judah and Jerusalem,</verse>
    <verse num="2">I will gather all the nations, and I will bring them down to the valley of Jehoshaphat, and I will argue {a case against them}<note>Literally "a matter with them"</note> there concerning my people and my inheritance Israel whom they have scattered among the nations, and my land <transChange type="added">that</transChange> they have divided.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For my people they cast lots,<note>Hebrew "lot"</note> and {they traded}<note>Literally "gave"</note> the male child for the prostitute, and the female child they sold for wine and they drank <transChange type="added">it</transChange>. </verse>
    <verse num="4">What <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you to me, <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Tyre and <transChange type="added">O</transChange> Sidon, and all of the regions of Philistia? Are you repaying to me what is deserved? If you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> recompensing me, I will return swiftly <transChange type="added">and</transChange> quickly what you deserve on your head!</verse>
    <verse num="5">For you have taken my silver and my gold, and my beautiful treasures you have carried into your temples.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And the sons of Judah and Jerusalem you sold to the sons of the Greeks, in order to remove them from their border.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Look! I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> rousing them from the place where you have sold them, and I will return what you deserve on your head!</verse>
    <verse num="8">I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they will sell them to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> Sabeans and to a nation far <transChange type="added">away</transChange>, for Yahweh has spoken. </verse>
    <verse num="9">Proclaim this among the nations: {Prepare for war}!<note>Literally "Sanctify a battle"</note> Stir up the mighty warriors; let them approach and come up; <transChange type="added">let</transChange> all the men of war approach.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Beat your cutting tools of iron into swords and your pruning hooks into spears; let the weakling say, 'I am a mighty warrior!'</verse>
    <verse num="11">Hurry and come, all the nations, from all around, and gather <transChange type="added">yourselves</transChange> there. Bring down your mighty warriors, O Yahweh!</verse>
    <verse num="12">Let the nations be roused and let them come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat, for there I will sit to judge all the nations from all around.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Send forth <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sickle, for the harvest is ripe! Go tread, for <transChange type="added">the</transChange> winepress is full! The vats overflow, because their evil <transChange type="added">is</transChange> great!</verse>
    <verse num="14">Commotion, commotion in the valley of decision! For the day of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> near in the valley of decision!</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">The</transChange> sun and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> moon grow dark, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> stars {have withheld}<note>Literally "gathered"</note> their splendor.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Yahweh roars from Zion; from Jerusalem he utters his voice, and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> heavens and <transChange type="added">the</transChange> earth shake. But Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a refuge for his people, and a protection for the children of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And you will know that I, Yahweh your God, <transChange type="added">am</transChange> dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain. And Jerusalem will be <transChange type="added">a place of</transChange> holiness, and strangers will pass through <transChange type="added">it</transChange> no longer.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And it will happen on that day; the mountains will drip new wine, and the hills will flow with milk, and all the channels of Judah will flow with water. A spring from the house of Yahweh will come forth, and it will water the valley of Acacia Trees.<note>Or "the wadi Shittim"</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">Egypt will become a desolation, and Edom will become a {desolate desert},<note>Literally "desert of desolation"</note> because of the violence <transChange type="added">they did</transChange> against the children of Judah, in whose land they have shed innocent blood.</verse>
    <verse num="20">But Judah will be inhabited forever, and Jerusalem {for all generations}.<note>Or "for each generation"</note></verse>
    <verse num="21">{I will cleanse their bloodguilt}<note>Literally "I will not leave unpunished their blood"</note> <transChange type="added">that</transChange> {I did not cleanse},<note>Or "I did not consider innocent"</note> for Yahweh is dwelling in Zion.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>