<book num="2Pet">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Simeon Peter, a slave and apostle of Jesus Christ, to those who have obtained a faith equal in value to ours by the righteousness of our God and Savior Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="2">May grace and peace be multiplied to you in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord,</verse>
    <verse num="3">because his divine power has bestowed on us all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">that are</transChange> necessary for life and godliness, through the knowledge of the one who called us by his own glory and excellence of character,</verse>
    <verse num="4">through which things he has bestowed on us his precious and very great promises, so that through these you may become sharers of the divine nature <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("escaping from") which is understood as temporal</note> escaping from the corruption <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> in the world because of evil desire,</verse>
    <verse num="5">and <transChange type="added">for</transChange> this same <transChange type="added">reason</transChange>, and <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("applying") which is understood as means</note> applying all diligence, supply with your faith excellence of character, and with excellence of character, knowledge,</verse>
    <verse num="6">and with knowledge, self-control, and with self-control, patient endurance, and with patient endurance, godliness,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and with godliness, brotherly love, and with brotherly love, love. </verse>
    <verse num="8">For <transChange type="added">if</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as conditional</note> these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> are yours and are increasing, this does not make <transChange type="added">you</transChange> useless or unproductive in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="9">For <transChange type="added">the one</transChange> for whom these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not present is blind, being nearsighted, {having forgotten the cleansing}<note>Literally "receiving forgetfulness of the cleansing"</note> of his former sins.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Therefore, brothers, be zealous even more to make your calling and election secure, because <transChange type="added">if you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("do") which is understood as conditional</note> do these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, you will never ever stumble.</verse>
    <verse num="11">For in this way entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ will be richly supplied for you. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Therefore I intend to remind you continually concerning these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, although <transChange type="added">you</transChange> know <transChange type="added">them</transChange> and are established in the truth that you have.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But I consider <transChange type="added">it</transChange> right, for as long as I am in this habitation, to stir you up by a reminder,</verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">because I</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know that the removal of my habitation is imminent, as indeed our Lord Jesus Christ made clear to me.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And I will also make every effort <transChange type="added">that</transChange> you are able at any time, after my departure, {to recall these things to mind}<note>Literally "to make recollection of these"</note>. </verse>
    <verse num="16">For we did not make known to you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("following") which is understood as means</note> following ingeniously concocted myths, but <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being") which is understood as means</note> being eyewitnesses of that one's majesty.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For <transChange type="added">he</transChange> received honor and glory from God the Father <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was brought")</note> a voice such as this was brought to him by the Majestic Glory, "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased."</verse>
    <verse num="18">And <transChange type="added">we</transChange> ourselves heard this voice brought from heaven <transChange type="added">when we</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("were") which is understood as temporal</note> were with him on the holy mountain,</verse>
    <verse num="19">and we possess <transChange type="added">as</transChange> more reliable the prophetic word, to which you do well <transChange type="added">if you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">if</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("pay attention to") which is understood as conditional</note> pay attention to <transChange type="added">it</transChange> as to a lamp shining in a dark place, until the day dawns and the morning star rises in your hearts,</verse>
    <verse num="20">recognizing this above all, that every prophecy of scripture does not come about from one's own interpretation,</verse>
    <verse num="21">for no prophecy was ever produced by the will of man, but men carried along by the Holy Spirit spoke from God. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">But there were also false prophets among the people, as there will be false teachers among you also, who will bring in {destructive heresies}<note>Literally "heresies of destruction"</note>, even denying the Master who bought them, <transChange type="added">thus</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">thus</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("bringing on") which is understood as result</note> bringing on themselves swift destruction.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And many will follow their licentious ways, because of whom the way of truth will be reviled.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And in greediness they will exploit you with false words, whose condemnation <transChange type="added">from</transChange> long ago is not idle, and their destruction is not asleep. </verse>
    <verse num="4">For if God did not spare the angels who sinned, but held <transChange type="added">them</transChange> captive in Tartarus with chains of darkness <transChange type="added">and</transChange> handed <transChange type="added">them</transChange> over to be kept for judgment,</verse>
    <verse num="5">and did not spare the ancient world, but preserved Noah, a proclaimer of righteousness, {and seven others}<note>Literally "eighth"</note> <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("brought") which is understood as temporal</note> brought a flood on the world of the ungodly,</verse>
    <verse num="6">and condemned the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah to destruction, reducing them to ashes, having appointed <transChange type="added">them</transChange> <transChange type="added">as</transChange> an example for those who are going to be ungodly,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and rescued righteous Lot, worn down by the way of life of lawless persons in licentiousness</verse>
    <verse num="8">(for that righteous man, <transChange type="added">as he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("lived") which is understood as temporal</note> lived among them day after day, was tormenting <transChange type="added">his</transChange> righteous soul by the lawless deeds <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> seeing and hearing),</verse>
    <verse num="9"><transChange type="added">then</transChange> the Lord knows how to rescue the godly from trials and to reserve the unrighteous to be punished at<note>Or "until"</note> the day of judgment,</verse>
    <verse num="10">and especially those who go after the flesh in defiling lust<note>Literally "in lust of defilement," translated here as an attributive genitive</note> and who despise authority. </verse>
    <verse num="11">whereas angels, who are greater in strength and power, do not bring against them a demeaning judgment.<note>Some manuscripts have "a demeaning judgment from the Lord"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">But these persons, like irrational animals born <transChange type="added">only with</transChange> natural <transChange type="added">instincts</transChange> for capture and killing, blaspheming {about things}<note>Literally "with reference to which"</note> they do not understand, in their destruction will also be destroyed,</verse>
    <verse num="13">being harmed <transChange type="added">as the</transChange> wages of unrighteousness. Considering reveling in the daytime a pleasure, <transChange type="added">they are</transChange> stains and blemishes, carousing in their deceitful pleasures <transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("feast together") which is understood as temporal</note> feast together with you,</verse>
    <verse num="14">having eyes full of <transChange type="added">desire for</transChange> an adulteress and unceasing from sin, enticing unstable persons, <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied in keeping with English style</note> having hearts trained for greediness. Accursed children!</verse>
    <verse num="15"><transChange type="added">By</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("leaving") which is understood as means</note> leaving the straight path, they have gone astray, <transChange type="added">because they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("followed") which is understood as causal</note> followed the way of Balaam the <transChange type="added">son of</transChange> Bosor,<note>Although some English versions use "Beor" here, this is due to harmonization with the Old Testament; the vast majority of Greek manuscripts read "Bosor" here</note> who loved the wages of unrighteousness,</verse>
    <verse num="16">but received a rebuke for his own lawlessness: a speechless donkey, speaking with a human voice, restrained {the prophet's madness}<note>Literally "the of the prophet madness"</note>. </verse>
    <verse num="17">These <transChange type="added">people</transChange> are waterless springs and mists driven by a hurricane, for whom the gloom of darkness has been reserved.</verse>
    <verse num="18">{For by speaking high-sounding but empty words}<note>Literally "for speaking pompous <transChange type="added">words</transChange> of emptiness"</note>, they entice with desires of the flesh <transChange type="added">and</transChange> with licentiousness those who are scarcely escaping from those who live in error,</verse>
    <verse num="19">promising them freedom <transChange type="added">although they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are") which is understood as concessive</note> themselves are slaves of depravity. For to whatever someone succumbs, by this he is also<note>Some manuscripts omit "also"</note> enslaved.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For if, <transChange type="added">after they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have escaped from") which is understood as temporal</note> have escaped from the defilements of the world through the knowledge of the Lord<note>Some manuscripts have "of our Lord"</note> and Savior Jesus Christ, and they are again entangled in these <transChange type="added">things</transChange> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> succumb to <transChange type="added">them</transChange>, the last <transChange type="added">state</transChange> has become worse for them than the first.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For it would have been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness than having known <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, to turn back from the holy commandment that had been delivered to them.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The <transChange type="added">statement</transChange> of the true proverb has happened to them, "A dog returns to its own vomit,"<note>A paraphrased quotation from Prov 26:11</note> and "A sow, <transChange type="added">after</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("washing herself") which is understood as temporal</note> washing herself, <transChange type="added">returns</transChange><note>*The verb "<transChange type="added">returns</transChange>" is not in the Greek text, but is an understood repetition from the previous clause</note> to wallowing in the mud."<note>The source of this quotation is uncertain</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">Dear friends, this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> already the second letter I am writing to you, in <transChange type="added">both of</transChange> which I am attempting to stir up your sincere mind by a reminder,</verse>
    <verse num="2">to remember the words proclaimed beforehand by the holy prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior through your apostles,</verse>
    <verse num="3">above all knowing this, that in the last days scoffers will come with scoffing, following according to their own desires</verse>
    <verse num="4">and saying, "Where is the promise of his coming? For {ever since}<note>Literally "from which <transChange type="added">time</transChange>"</note> the fathers fell asleep, all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> have continued just as they have been from the beginning of creation."</verse>
    <verse num="5">For <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("maintain") which is understood as temporal</note> they maintain this, it escapes <transChange type="added">their</transChange> notice that the heavens existed long ago and the earth held together out of water and through water by the word of God,</verse>
    <verse num="6">by means of which things the world that existed at that time was destroyed <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being inundated") which is understood as means</note> being inundated with water.</verse>
    <verse num="7">But by the same word the present heavens and earth are reserved for fire, being kept for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly people. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Now, dear friends, do not let this one thing escape your <transChange type="added">notice</transChange>, that one day with the Lord <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a thousand years, and a thousand years <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like one day.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The Lord is not delaying the promise, as some consider slowness, but is being patient toward you, <transChange type="added">because he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("want") which is understood as causal</note> does not want any to perish, but all to come to repentance.</verse>
    <verse num="10">But the day of the Lord will come like a thief, in which the heavens will disappear with a rushing noise, and the celestial bodies will be destroyed <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being burned up") which is understood as means</note> being burned up, and the earth and the deeds <transChange type="added">done</transChange> on it will be disclosed.</verse>
    <verse num="11"><transChange type="added">Because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are being destroyed") which is understood as causal</note> all these things are being destroyed in this way, what sort of <transChange type="added">people</transChange> must you be in holy behavior and godliness,</verse>
    <verse num="12"><transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("waiting for") which is understood as temporal</note> waiting for and hastening the coming of the day of God, because of which the heavens will be destroyed <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being burned up") which is understood as means</note> being burned up and the celestial bodies will melt <transChange type="added">as they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">as</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are consumed by heat") which is understood as temporal</note> are consumed by heat!</verse>
    <verse num="13">But according to his promise, we are waiting for new heavens and a new earth in which righteousness resides. </verse>
    <verse num="14">Therefore, dear friends, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are waiting for") which is understood as causal</note> are waiting for these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, make every effort to be found at peace, spotless and unblemished in him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And regard the patience of our Lord as salvation, just as also our dear brother Paul wrote to you, according to the wisdom that was given to him,</verse>
    <verse num="16">as <transChange type="added">he does</transChange> also in all his<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note><note>Some manuscripts do not explicitly state "his"</note> letters, speaking in them about these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, in which there are some <transChange type="added">things</transChange> hard to understand, which the ignorant and unstable distort to their own destruction, as <transChange type="added">they</transChange> also <transChange type="added">do</transChange> the rest of the scriptures.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Therefore, dear friends, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know beforehand") which is understood as causal</note> know <transChange type="added">this</transChange> beforehand, guard yourselves so that you do not lose your own safe position <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have been led away") which is understood as causal</note> have been led away by the error of lawless persons.</verse>
    <verse num="18">But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. To him <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the glory, both now and to the day of eternity. Amen. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>