<book num="Song">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">The Song of Songs,<note>This construction conveys a superlative connotation, e.g., "The most exquisite song"</note> which <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for<note>Or "by Solomon" or "about/concerning Solomon"</note> Solomon. </verse>
    <verse num="2">{May<note>In the maiden's soliloquy, she thinks about her beloved in her thoughts ("May he kiss me!"), then poetically speaks to him as if he were in her presence ("for your love is better than wine"). To avoid confusion, the translation uses the second-person form throughout vv. 2-4</note> you kiss me}<note>Literally "May he kiss me"</note> {passionately with your lips},<note>Literally "with the kisses of his mouth"</note> for your love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> better than wine.<note>The shift from the third person "he ... his" to the second person "you ... your" in vv. 2-4 should not be interpreted as suggesting two different referents, that is, one male whom the maiden is addressing as "you," and another to whom she refers as "he." Rather, this shift is a poetic device (called "grammatical differentiation") that is not uncommon in Hebrew poetry (e.g., Gen 49:4; Deut 32:15; Psa 23:2-5; Isa 1:29; 42:20; 54:1; Jer 22:24; Amos 4:1; Mic 7:19; Lam 3:1; Song 4:2; 6:6). This shift is characteristic of a soliloquy, a dramatic or literary form in which a character reveals her thoughts without addressing a listener who is actually present (e.g., 2 Sam 19:4). In this case, the maiden's private thoughts about her beloved (v. 2a) shift to an imaginary address to her beloved (vv. 2b-4a)</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">As fragrance, {your perfumes}<note>Literally "your oil lotions"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {delightful};<note>Literally "good"</note> your name is poured out {perfume};<note>Literally "oil lotion"</note> therefore young women love you.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Draw me after you, let us run! May the king bring me into his chambers!<note>Or "The king has brought me into his chambers"</note> Let us be joyful and let us rejoice in you; let us extol your love more than wine. Rightly do they love you!</verse>
    <verse num="5">I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> black but beautiful,<note>Or "black and beautiful"</note> {O maidens of Jerusalem},<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note> like the tents of Kedar, like the curtains of Solomon.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Do not gaze at me because I am black, <note>This is figurative for the maiden's physical appearance; her skin was darkly tanned</note> because the sun has stared <transChange type="added">at</transChange> me. The sons of my mother were angry with me; they made me keeper of the vineyards, <transChange type="added">but</transChange> my own "vineyard"<note>Literally "my vineyard that for me"</note> I did not keep.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Tell me, <transChange type="added">you</transChange> whom my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> loves, where do you pasture your flock, where do your sheep lie down at the noon? {For why should I be like}<note>Literally "For to what will I be like"</note> one who is veiled<note>The reading of the MT ("like one who is veiled") is supported by the LXX. However, several ancient versions (Syriac Peshitta, Latin Vulgate, Symmachus) reflect an alternate Hebrew textual tradition in which two letters are transposed, resulting in the reading "like one who wanders about." This makes good sense contextually, since the maiden does not know where her beloved would be at noon</note> beside the flocks of your companions?</verse>
    <verse num="8">If you do not know, O fairest among women, follow {the tracks}<note>Literally "in the tracks"</note> of the flock, and pasture your little lambs<note>Or "your kids"</note> beside the tents of the shepherds.</verse>
    <verse num="9">To a mare<note>Or "my mare"</note> among the chariots<note>Or "chariot horses"</note> of Pharaoh, I compare you, my beloved.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Your cheeks are beautiful with ornaments, your neck with strings of jewels.</verse>
    <verse num="11">We will make ornaments of gold for you with studs<note>Or "droplets"</note> of silver.</verse>
    <verse num="12">While the king <transChange type="added">was</transChange> on his couch, my nard gave its fragrance.</verse>
    <verse num="13">My beloved <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to me {a pouch}<note>Literally "the bag"</note> of myrrh, he spends the night<note>Or "he lays"</note> between my breasts.</verse>
    <verse num="14">My beloved <transChange type="added">is</transChange> to me a cluster of blossoms of henna in the vineyards of En Gedi.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Look! You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful, my beloved. Look! You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful; your eyes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> doves.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Look! You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful, my beloved, truly pleasant. Truly our couch <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {verdant};<note>Literally "green"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">the beams of our house <transChange type="added">are</transChange> cedar; our rafter <transChange type="added">is</transChange> cypress.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> a rose<note>More likely "meadow saffron" or "crocus." Hebrew scholars and botanists suggest the term refers to Ashodelos (lily family), Narcissus tazetta (narcissus or daffodil), or Colchicum autumnale (meadow saffron or crocus) (e.g., Isa 35:1). The location of this flower in Sharon suggests a common wild flower rather than a rose. The maiden compares herself to a simple, common flower of the field</note> of Sharon, a lily of the valleys.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Like a lily among the thorns,<note>Or "brambles"</note> so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my love among the maidens.</verse>
    <verse num="3">As an apple tree among the trees of the forest, so <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my beloved among the young men. In his shade {I sat down with delight},<note>Literally "I sat down and I delighted"</note> and his fruit <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sweet to my palate.</verse>
    <verse num="4">He brought me to the house of the wine, and his intention <transChange type="added">was</transChange> love toward me.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Sustain me with the raisins, refresh me with the apples, {for I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> lovesick}.<note>Literally "for I myself <transChange type="added">am</transChange> sick with love"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">His left <transChange type="added">hand</transChange> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> under my head, and his right <transChange type="added">hand</transChange> embraces<note>Or "would embrace me"</note> me.</verse>
    <verse num="7">I adjure you, {O maidens of Jerusalem},<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note> by the gazelles or by the does of the field, do not arouse or awaken love until it pleases!<note>Or "Do not stir up or awaken the love until it is willing," or "Do not disturb or interrupt <transChange type="added">our</transChange> lovemaking until it is satisfied"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">The voice of my beloved! Look! Here {he}<note>Literally "this one"</note> comes leaping upon the mountains, bounding over the hills!</verse>
    <verse num="9">My beloved is like a gazelle or {a young stag}.<note>Literally "the fawn of the stag"</note> Look! {He is}<note>Literally "This <transChange type="added">is he</transChange>"</note> standing behind our wall, gazing {through}<note>Literally "from"</note> the window, looking {through}<note>Literally "from"</note> the lattice.</verse>
    <verse num="10">My beloved answered and said to me, "{Arise},<note>Literally "Arise, you"</note> my beloved! {Come, my beauty}!<note>Literally "And come, you"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">For look! The winter is over; {the rainy season}<note>Literally "the rain"</note> {has turned and gone away}.<note>Literally "is over; it is gone"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">The blossoms {appear}<note>Literally "is seen"</note> {in the land};<note>Literally "on the earth"</note> {the time of singing<note>Most likely, a subtle word play occurs here since there are two different words in Hebrew spelled the same way: "pruning" and "singing." The former plays upon the first line and the latter upon the third line</note> has arrived};<note>Literally "the time of the song arrived"</note> the voice of the turtledove is heard in our land.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The fig tree puts forth her figs, and the vines <transChange type="added">are in</transChange> blossom; they give fragrance. {Arise},<note>Literally "Arise, to you!"</note> my beloved! {Come, my beauty}!"<note>Literally "My beauty, come, you"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">My dove, in the clefts of the rock, {in the secluded place}<note>Literally "in the secret place"</note><note>Or "in the covering"</note> {in the mountain},<note>Literally "foothold in the rock"</note><note>Or "cliff"</note> Let me see your face, let me hear your voice; for your voice <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sweet and your face <transChange type="added">is</transChange> lovely.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Catch for us the foxes, the little foxes destroying vineyards, for<note>Or "while"</note> our vineyards <transChange type="added">are in</transChange> blossom!</verse>
    <verse num="16">{My beloved belongs to me and I belong to him};<note>Literally "My beloved for me and I for him"</note> he pastures his flock among the lilies.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Until the day breathes and the shadows flee, turn, my beloved! {Be like}<note>Literally "Be like for you"</note> a gazelle<note>Or "a buck gazelle"</note> or {young stag}<note>Literally "the fawn of the stag"</note> on the cleft mountains.<note>Or "the mountains of Bether"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">On my bed in the night, I sought<note>Or "I seek"</note> him whom my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> loves. I sought him, but I did not find him.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Now I will arise, and I will go about in the city, in the streets and in the squares; I will seek him whom my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> loves. I sought him, but I did not find him.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The sentinels who go about in the city found me. "Have you seen the one whom my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> loves?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">{Scarcely had I passed}<note>Literally "As little that I passed"</note> by them when I found him whom my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> loves. I held him and I would not let him go until I brought him to the house of my mother, into the bedroom chamber of she who conceived me.</verse>
    <verse num="5">I adjure you, {O maidens of Jerusalem},<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note> by the gazelles or by the does of the field, do not arouse or awaken love until it pleases!<note>Or "Do not stir up or awaken the love until it is willing," or "Do not disturb or interrupt <transChange type="added">our</transChange> love-making until it is satisfied"</note></verse>
    <verse num="6">What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this coming up from the desert like a column of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense from all the fragrant powders of the merchant?</verse>
    <verse num="7">Look! <transChange type="added">It is</transChange> Solomon's {portable couch}!<note>Literally "couch" or "portable sedan chair"</note> Sixty mighty men surround {it},<note>Literally "her"</note> the mighty men of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="8">All of them {wield swords};<note>Literally "holders of sword"</note> <transChange type="added">they are</transChange> {trained in warfare},<note>Literally "learnt of war"</note> each with his sword at his thigh <transChange type="added">to guard</transChange> {against terror}<note>Literally "because of the fear"</note> in the night.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{King Solomon}<note>Literally "The king, Solomon"</note> made for himself a sedan chair from the wood of Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="10">He made its column of silver, its back<note>Or "its support," "its base," "its headrest," "its litter," "its cover"</note> of gold, its seat of purple; its interior is inlaid <transChange type="added">with</transChange> leather<note>Or "love." The Hebrew term here translated "leather" is spelled the same as the term for "love." Most likely this is an example of a word play that puns on the intentional ambiguity: "Its interior was inlaid with leather//love by the maidens of Jerusalem"</note> by {the maidens of Jerusalem}.<note>Literally "by the daughters of Jerusalem"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Come out and look, {O maidens of Zion},<note>Literally "O daughters of Zion"</note> at {King Solomon},<note>Literally "the king, Solomon"</note> at the crown with which his mother crowned him on the day of his wedding, on the day of the joy of his heart!</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">{Oh my}!<note>Literally "Behold!" Or "Look!"</note> You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful, my beloved! {Oh my}!<note>Literally "Behold!" Or "Look!"</note> You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful! Your eyes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> doves from behind your veil. Your hair <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a flock of goats that move down from the mountains of Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Your teeth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like a flock of shorn ewes that came up from the washing, all of them bearing twins, and there is none bereaved among them.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Your lips <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like a thread of crimson, and your mouth <transChange type="added">is</transChange> lovely. Your temple <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like pomegranate from behind your veil.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Your neck <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the tower of David, built in courses; a thousand {ornaments}<note>Literally "shields"</note> are hung on it, all the shields of the warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Your two breasts <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like two fawns, twins of a gazelle that feed among the lilies.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Until the day breathes and the shadows flee, I will go to the mountain of the myrrh, to the hill of the frankincense.</verse>
    <verse num="7">You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> completely beautiful, my beloved! {You are flawless}!<note>Literally "There is no flaw in you!"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">Come<note>Or "You must come"</note> with me from Lebanon, my bride! Come with me<note>Or "With me"</note> from Lebanon! Look from the top of Amana, from the top of Senir and Hermon, from the dwelling places of the lions, from the mountains of leopard.</verse>
    <verse num="9">You have stolen (my) heart, my sister bride! You have stolen <transChange type="added">my</transChange> heart with one <transChange type="added">glance</transChange> from your eyes, with one ornament from your necklaces.</verse>
    <verse num="10">How beautiful is your love, my sister bride! How better is your love than wine, and the fragrance of your oils than any spice!</verse>
    <verse num="11">Your lips drip nectar, <transChange type="added">my</transChange> bride; honey and milk <transChange type="added">are</transChange> under your lips; the scent of your garments <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the scent of Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="12">A garden locked <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my sister bride, a spring enclosed,<note>Or "a source locked"</note> a fountain sealed.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Your shoots<note>Or "your channel"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> an orchard of pomegranates with {choice fruit},<note>Literally "fruit of choice things"</note> henna with nard;</verse>
    <verse num="14">nard and saffron, calamus and cinnamon spice with all trees of frankincense, myrrh and aloes with all chief spices.</verse>
    <verse num="15">A garden fountain, a well of living water, flowing (streams) from Lebanon.</verse>
    <verse num="16">Awake, O north wind! Come, O south wind! Blow upon my garden! Let its fragrances<note>Or "perfumes"</note> waft forth!<note>Or "His perfumes can waft down"</note> Let my beloved come to his garden, let him eat his choice fruit!</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">I have come to my garden, my sister bride, I have gathered my myrrh with my spice, I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey, I have drunk my wine with my milk! Eat, O friends! {Drink and become drunk <transChange type="added">with</transChange> love}!<note>Or "Drink and become drunk, O lovers!"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> asleep but<note>Or "and"</note> my heart was awake. A sound! My beloved knocking!<note>Or "The sound of my beloved knocking!"</note> "Open to me, my sister, my beloved, my dove, my perfect one! For my head is full of dew, {my hair drenched from the moist night air}."<note>Literally "my locks with drops of night"</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">I have taken off my tunic, {must I put it on}?<note>Literally "How will I put it on?"</note> I have bathed my feet, {must I soil them}?<note>Literally "How will I soil them?"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">My beloved thrust his hand into the opening, and my inmost yearned for him.</verse>
    <verse num="5">I myself arose to open to my beloved; my hands dripped with myrrh, my fingers with liquid myrrh upon the handles of the bolt.</verse>
    <verse num="6">I opened myself to my beloved, but my beloved had turned and gone;<note>Or "my beloved had left; he was gone"</note> my heart sank<note>Or "my soul left"</note> when he turned away.<note>Or "when he was speaking." Translations equivocate on how to translate this verb, since there are two terms in Hebrew spelled identically: "to speak" and "to turn aside" (HALOT 1:210). The context suggests the latter</note> I sought him, but I did not find him; I called him, but he did not answer me.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The sentinels making rounds in the city found me; they beat me, they wounded me; they took my cloak<note>Or "mantle"</note> away from me-- {those sentinels on the walls}!<note>Literally "the sentinels of the walls"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">I adjure you, {O maidens of Jerusalem},<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note> if you find my beloved, what will you tell him? <transChange type="added">Tell him</transChange> that I am {lovesick}!<note>Literally "sick <transChange type="added">with</transChange> love"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">{How is your beloved better than another lover},<note>Literally "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your beloved more than <transChange type="added">another</transChange> beloved ...?"</note> O most beautiful among women? {How is your beloved better than another lover}, <note>Literally "What <transChange type="added">is</transChange> your beloved more than <transChange type="added">another</transChange> beloved ...?"</note> that you adjure us thus?</verse>
    <verse num="10">My beloved <transChange type="added">is</transChange> radiant and {ruddy},<note>Literally "red"</note> distinguished {among}<note>Literally "more than"</note> ten thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="11">His head <transChange type="added">is</transChange> gold, refined gold; his locks <transChange type="added">are</transChange> wavy, black as a raven.</verse>
    <verse num="12">His eyes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like doves beside springs<note>Or "streams"</note> of water, bathed in milk, {set like mounted jewels}.<note>Literally "dwelling in a setting"</note><note>Or "seated at a <transChange type="added">suitable</transChange> mounting"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">His cheeks <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like beds of spice, a tower of fragrances; his lips <transChange type="added">are</transChange> lilies dripping liquid myrrh.</verse>
    <verse num="14">His arms <transChange type="added">are</transChange> {rods}<note>Literally "cylinders"</note><note>Or "rings"</note> of gold {engraved with}<note>Literally "filled with"</note> jewels; his belly<note>Or "body"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> polished ivory covered with sapphires.<note>Or "works of ivory set with sapphire"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">His legs <transChange type="added">are</transChange> columns of alabaster,<note>Or "marble"</note> set on bases of gold; his appearance <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like Lebanon, choice as {its cedars}.<note>Literally "the cedars"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">{His mouth}<note>Or "his palate"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> sweet, and he is altogether desirable. This <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my beloved; this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my friend, {O young women of Jerusalem}.<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">Where has your beloved gone, O most beautiful among women? Where has your beloved turned that we may seek him with you?</verse>
    <verse num="2">My beloved has gone down to his garden, to the garden bed of the spice, to pasture his flock and to gather lilies in the garden.</verse>
    <verse num="3">{I belong to my beloved and he belongs to me};<note>Literally "I for my beloved and he for me"</note> he pastures his flock among the lilies.</verse>
    <verse num="4">You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> beautiful, my beloved, as Tirzah, lovely as Jerusalem, {overwhelming as an army with banners}.<note>Literally "terrible as the bannered ones"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">Turn away your eyes from before me, for they overwhelm me. Your hair <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a flock of the goats that moves down from Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Your teeth <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like a flock of the ewes that have come up from the washing, all of them bearing twins, and there is none bereaved among them.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Your cheeks {behind}<note>Literally "from behind"</note> your veil <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like halves of a pomegranate.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Sixty queens there <transChange type="added">are</transChange>, eighty concubines, and maidens beyond number.</verse>
    <verse num="9">My dove, {she is the one};<note>Literally "she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one"</note><note>The term "one" functions here as an adjective of quality: "unique, singular, the only one"</note> my perfect, {she is the only one};<note>Literally "she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> one"</note><note>Or "the only daughter of her mother." Although the latter option is permissible, the term is used elsewhere of the heir as the favored child (e.g., Gen 22:2; Prov 4:3). This nuance is supported by the parallel term "favorite"</note> she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {the favorite of}<note>Or "she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the pure one." Since there are two Hebrew terms spelled the same way, some relate this to the adjective that means "pure." Others relate it to the verb that means "to choose, select." The parallelism favors the latter</note><note>Literally "the favorite for"</note> her mother who bore her. Maidens see her and consider her fortunate;<note>Or "call her happy" or "call her blessed" or "bless her"</note> queens and concubines praise her:</verse>
    <verse num="10">"Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this that looks down like the dawn, beautiful as the moon, {bright as the sun},<note>Literally "pure as the glow"</note><note>Or "bright as the heat of the sun." The Hebrew term "glow" poetically refers to the bright rays of the sun (Psa 19:7; Isa 24:23; 30:26)</note> {overwhelming as an army with banners}?"<note>Literally "terrible as the bannered ones"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">I went down to the orchard of the walnut trees to look at the blossoms of the valley, to see <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> the vine<transChange type="added">s</transChange> have sprouted, <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> the pomegranates have blossomed.</verse>
    <verse num="12">I did not know my {heart}<note>Literally "soul"</note> set me <transChange type="added">in</transChange> a chariot of my princely people.<note>Or "Before I was aware, my soul made me like the chariots of Amminadib" (KJV, ASV) or "Before I knew it, my desire set me mid the chariots of Ammi-nadib" (JPS) or "Before I was aware, my soul set me over the chariots of my noble people" (NASB) or "Before I realized it, my desire set me among the royal chariots of my people" (NIV) or "... among the chariots of Amminadab" (NIV margin) or "... among the chariots of the people of the prince" (NIV margin)</note></verse>
    <verse num="13"><note>Song of Songs 6:13-7:13 in the English Bible is 7:1-14 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Turn, turn,<note>Or "Return, return ...!"</note> O Shulammite!<note>Or "O perfect one," "O peaceful one," "O bride." Many interpreters take this moniker as suggesting the maiden was from the village of Shulem (alternately called Shunem)</note> Turn, turn<note>Or "Return, return ...!"</note> so that we may look upon you! Why do you look upon the Shulammite as <transChange type="added">at</transChange> a dance of the two armies?</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">How beautiful are your feet in sandals, O royal princess!<note>Or "O daughter of leader"</note> The curves of your {thighs}<note>Literally "thigh"</note> <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like {jewels},<note>Literally "ornaments"</note> the work of the hands of a craftsman.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Your navel <transChange type="added">is</transChange> {a round wine-mixing bowl}<note>Literally "a bowl of the roundness"</note> that does not lack mixed<note>Or "blended"</note> wine! Your belly <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a heap of wheat encircled with lilies.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Your two breasts <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like two fawns, twins of a gazelle.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Your neck <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like a tower of ivory; your eyes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> pools in Heshbon at the gate of Beth Rabbim. Your nose <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the tower of Lebanon {looking out over Damascus}.<note>Literally "looking out over the face of Damascus"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">{Your head crowns you like Carmel};<note>Literally "Your head <transChange type="added">is</transChange> on you like the Carmel"</note><note>Because of its height and fertility, Mount Carmel is often associated with royalty</note> the flowing locks of your head <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like {purple tapestry};<note>Literally "the purple"</note> a king is held captive in the tresses!</verse>
    <verse num="6">How beautiful you are and how pleasant, O loved one in the delights!</verse>
    <verse num="7">{Your stature}<note>Literally "this your height"</note> <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the palm tree, and your breasts <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like clusters.</verse>
    <verse num="8">I say, "I will climb up the palm tree; I will lay hold of its fruit clusters." Let your breasts <transChange type="added">be pleasing</transChange> like clusters of the vine and the scent of your breath like the apples.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Your palate <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like the best wine that goes down for my beloved, smoothly gliding over my lips and teeth.<note>Or "over lips of sleepers." One Hebrew textual tradition preserves the reading "lips of those who sleep" (MT). Another Hebrew tradition reads "my lips and my teeth," as reflected by the ancient versions (LXX, Latin Vulgate, Aramaic Targum, Syriac Peshitta). The latter is adopted here since it makes the most sense poetically</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">{I belong to my beloved},<note>Literally "I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> for my beloved"</note> {and he desires me}!<note>Literally "and his desire <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for me." Or "and his desire belongs to me"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">Come, my beloved, let us {go out to the countryside};<note>Literally "go forth into the field"</note> let us spend the night<note>Or "lodge"</note> in the villages.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Let us rise early <transChange type="added">to go</transChange><note>Or "let us go"</note> to the vineyards; let us see whether the vine has budded,<note>Or "sprouted"</note> <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> the grape blossom has opened, and <transChange type="added">whether</transChange> the pomegranates {are in bloom};<note>Literally "have bloomed"</note> there I will give my love to you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The mandrakes give <transChange type="added">off their</transChange> fragrance, and {over our doorway is every kind of delicious fruit};<note>Or "over our doorways all choice <transChange type="added">things</transChange>"</note> both {fresh and dried fruit I have stored up}<note>Literally "new also old I have laid up"</note> for you, O my beloved.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">{How I wish that you were my little brother},<note>Literally "O that he would give you like a brother to me"</note><note>The Hebrew construction (which is somewhat misleading if rendered in a woodenly literal sense) is an idiom expressing one's fanciful wish</note> <transChange type="added">who</transChange> nursed {upon my mother's breasts}!<note>Literally "at the breast of my mother"</note> <transChange type="added">If</transChange> {I met you outside},<note>Literally "I will find you in the street"</note> I would kiss you, {and no one would despise me}!<note>Literally "also they would not despise me"</note></verse>
    <verse num="2">{I would surely bring you}<note>Literally "I would lead you and I would bring you"</note><note>The combination of the two verbs creates a hendiadys which may be rendered more cogently as "I would surely bring you ..."</note> to the house of my mother, {who would surely teach me};<note>Literally "she will teach me"</note> {I would give you spiced wine to drink},<note>Literally "I would give you to drink from the wine of the spice"</note> the {sweet wine}<note>Or "juice"</note> of my pomegranates.<note>The traditional Hebrew reads the singular "my pomegranate." However, the plural reading "my pomegranates" is attested in numerous medieval Hebrew manuscripts and is reflected in the ancient versions (Greek Septuagint, Aramaic Targum, Syriac Peshitta). The latter makes the most sense in this context as a euphemistic description of the maiden's delights</note></verse>
    <verse num="3">His left <transChange type="added">hand is</transChange> under my head, and his right <transChange type="added">hand</transChange> embraces<note>Or "embraced"</note> me.</verse>
    <verse num="4">I adjure you, {O maidens of Jerusalem},<note>Literally "O daughters of Jerusalem"</note> do not<note>Or "Why must you ... before it pleases?"</note> arouse or awaken love until it pleases!<note>Or "Do not stir up or awaken the love until it is willing," or "Do not disturb or interrupt <transChange type="added">our</transChange> lovemaking until it is satisfied"</note></verse>
    <verse num="5">Who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> this coming up from the wilderness, leaning upon her beloved? Under the apple tree I awakened you; there your mother {conceived you};<note>Literally "was in labor with you"</note> there she who was in labor gave birth to you.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Set me as a seal upon your heart, as a seal upon your arm; for love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> strong as death; passion <transChange type="added">is</transChange> fierce as Sheol; its flashes <transChange type="added">are</transChange> flashes of fire; <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> a blazing flame.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Many waters cannot quench love; rivers cannot sweep it away.<note>Or "and rivers cannot engulf it"</note> If a man were to give all the wealth of his house {for love},<note>Literally "in the love"</note> he would be utterly scorned.<note>Literally "they will utterly scorn him"</note></verse>
    <verse num="8">{We have a little sister},<note>Literally "a little sister for us"</note> {and she does not yet have any breasts}.<note>Literally "and there is no breast for her"</note> What should we do for our sister {on the day when she is betrothed}?<note>Literally "on the day when it is spoken of her"</note><note>Or "on the day when she is spoken for"</note></verse>
    <verse num="9">If she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a wall, {we will adorn her with a turret of silver};<note>Literally "we will build upon her a camp of silver"</note><note>The term translated "turret" refers to the decorative parapet adorning the top of a building. This image is likely figurative for a silver tiara set upon the head</note> but if she <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a door, we will barricade her with boards of cedar.<note>Or "we will enclose her"</note></verse>
    <verse num="10">I <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a wall, and my breasts <transChange type="added">were</transChange> like the towers, {so <transChange type="added">my betrothed</transChange> viewed me with great delight}.<note>Literally "then I was in his eyes as <transChange type="added">one who</transChange> finds peace"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">{Solomon had a vineyard}<note>Literally "A vineyard was for Solomon"</note> at Baal-hamon; {he entrusted his vineyard to the keepers};<note>Literally "he gave the vineyard to the keepers"</note> {people paid a thousand silver <transChange type="added">pieces</transChange> for its fruit}.<note>Literally "each one brought a thousand silver <transChange type="added">pieces</transChange> for his fruit"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">{My own "vineyard" belongs to me};<note>Literally "My vineyard that for me before my face"</note> the "thousand" are for you, O Solomon, {and "two hundred" for those who tend its fruit}.<note>Literally "and two hundred for <transChange type="added">the</transChange> keepers <transChange type="added">of</transChange> his fruit"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">O you who dwell in the garden, <transChange type="added">my</transChange> companions are listening to your voice. Let me hear <transChange type="added">it</transChange>!</verse>
    <verse num="14">Flee, my beloved! {Be like a gazelle}<note>Literally "and be like for you to a gazelle"</note> or {a young stag}<note>Literally "to the fawn of the stag"</note> upon {the perfumed mountains}!<note>Literally "the mountains of spices"</note></verse>
  </chapter>
</book>