<book num="1Pet">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the chosen<note>Or "elect"</note> who are residing temporarily in the dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,</verse>
    <verse num="2">according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, by the sanctification of the Spirit, for obedience and <transChange type="added">for</transChange> sprinkling with the blood of Jesus Christ. May grace and peace be multiplied to you. </verse>
    <verse num="3">Blessed <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy has caused us to be born again to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,</verse>
    <verse num="4">into an inheritance imperishable and undefiled and unfading, reserved in heaven for you</verse>
    <verse num="5">who are being protected by the power of God through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last time,</verse>
    <verse num="6">in which you rejoice greatly, <transChange type="added">although</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("are distressed") which is understood as concessive</note> now for a short time, if necessary,<note>Some manuscripts have "if it is necessary"</note> you are distressed by various trials,</verse>
    <verse num="7">so that the genuineness of your faith, more valuable than gold that is passing away, but is tested by fire, may be found to <transChange type="added">result in</transChange> praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="8">whom, <transChange type="added">although you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("seen") which is understood as concessive</note> have not seen, you love; in whom now you believe, <transChange type="added">although you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">although</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("see") which is understood as concessive</note> do not see <transChange type="added">him</transChange>, and you rejoice greatly with joy inexpressible and full of glory,</verse>
    <verse num="9">obtaining the goal of your faith, the salvation of <transChange type="added">your</transChange><note>*This is an understood repetition of the previous "your"</note> souls. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Concerning this<note>Literally "which"</note> salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the grace meant for you sought and made careful inquiry,</verse>
    <verse num="11">investigating for what <transChange type="added">person</transChange> or which time the Spirit of Christ in them was indicating <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("testified beforehand") which is understood as temporal</note> testified beforehand to the sufferings with reference to Christ and the glories after these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="12">to whom it was revealed that they were serving not themselves but you with reference to the same <transChange type="added">things</transChange> which now have been announced to you through those who proclaimed the gospel to you by the Holy Spirit sent from heaven, {things into which}<note>Literally "into which <transChange type="added">things</transChange>"</note> angels desire to look. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Therefore, {when you have prepared your minds for action}<note>Literally "having girded up the loins of your mind"</note> <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being self-controlled") which is understood as means</note> being self-controlled, put your hope completely in the grace that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="14">As obedient children, do not be conformed to the former desires <transChange type="added">you used to conform to</transChange><note>*This is an understood repetition of the earlier verb "be conformed to"</note> in your ignorance,</verse>
    <verse num="15">but as the one who called you <transChange type="added">is</transChange> holy, <transChange type="added">you</transChange> yourselves be holy in all <transChange type="added">your</transChange> conduct,</verse>
    <verse num="16">for it is written, "You will be holy, because I <transChange type="added">am</transChange><note>*Here the verb is understood in Greek and is supplied in the translation</note> holy."<note>A quotation from Lev 19:2</note><note>Some manuscripts explicitly state "I am holy"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">And if you call on <transChange type="added">him</transChange> <transChange type="added">as</transChange> Father who judges impartially according to each one's work, conduct yourselves with fear during the time of your temporary residence,</verse>
    <verse num="18"><transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know that you were redeemed from your futile way of life inherited from your ancestors not with perishable things like silver or gold,</verse>
    <verse num="19">but with the precious blood of Christ, like <transChange type="added">that of</transChange> an unblemished and spotless lamb</verse>
    <verse num="20">who was foreknown before the foundation of the world, but has been revealed in these last times for you</verse>
    <verse num="21">who through him <transChange type="added">are</transChange> believing in God, who raised him from the dead and gave him glory, so that your faith and hope are in God. </verse>
    <verse num="22">Having purified your souls by your obedience to the truth for sincere brotherly love, love one another fervently from the heart,<note>Some manuscripts have "from a pure heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="23"><transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have been born again") which is understood as causal</note> have been born again, not from perishable seed but imperishable, through the living and enduring word of God.</verse>
    <verse num="24">For </verse>
    <verse num="25">but the word of the Lord endures {forever}<note>Literally "for the age"</note>."<note>A quotation from Isa 40:6, 8</note></verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, ridding yourselves of all malice and all deceit and hypocrisy and envy and all slander,</verse>
    <verse num="2">like newborn infants long for the unadulterated spiritual milk, so that by it you may grow up to salvation,</verse>
    <verse num="3">if you have tasted that the Lord <transChange type="added">is</transChange> kind,<note>A quotation from Ps 34:8</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">to whom you are drawing near, a living stone rejected by men but chosen <transChange type="added">and</transChange> precious in the sight of God.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And <transChange type="added">you</transChange> yourselves, as living stones, are being built up <transChange type="added">as</transChange> a spiritual house for a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <verse num="6">For it stands in scripture, </verse>
    <verse num="7">Therefore the honor <transChange type="added">is</transChange> for you who believe, but for those who refuse to believe, </verse>
    <verse num="8">and </verse>
    <verse num="9">But you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a chosen race,<note>Or "people," or "generation," or "nation"</note> a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for <transChange type="added">God's</transChange> possession, so that you may proclaim the virtues of the one who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light,</verse>
    <verse num="10">who once <transChange type="added">were</transChange> not a people, but now <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the people of God, the ones <transChange type="added">who were</transChange> not shown mercy, but now are shown mercy.<note>This verse contains quotations from Hos 1:6, 9; 2:23</note> </verse>
    <verse num="11">Dear friends, I urge <transChange type="added">you</transChange> as foreigners and temporary residents to abstain from fleshly desires which wage war against your<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> soul,</verse>
    <verse num="12">maintaining your good conduct among the Gentiles, so that in <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> in which they slander you as evildoers, by seeing your good deeds they may glorify God on the day of visitation. </verse>
    <verse num="13">Subject yourselves to every human authority for the sake of the Lord, whether to a king<note>Or "to the emperor"</note> as having supreme authority,</verse>
    <verse num="14">or to governors as those sent out by him for the punishment of those who do evil and the praise of those who do good.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For the will of God is as follows: <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("doing good") which is understood as means</note> doing good to silence the ignorance of foolish people.</verse>
    <verse num="16"><transChange type="added">Live</transChange> as free <transChange type="added">persons</transChange>, and not using your<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> freedom as a covering for evil, but as slaves of God.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Honor all <transChange type="added">people</transChange>, love the community of believers, fear God, honor the king.<note>Or "the emperor"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="18">Domestic slaves, be subject to your<note>*Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> masters with all respect, not only to those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> good and gentle, but also to those <transChange type="added">who are</transChange> unjust.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For this <transChange type="added">finds</transChange> favor, if because of consciousness of God someone endures sorrows <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("suffering") which is understood as temporal</note> suffering unjustly.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For what credit <transChange type="added">is it</transChange> if, <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("sin") which is understood as temporal</note> sin and are beaten <transChange type="added">for it</transChange>, you endure? But if you endure <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("do good") which is understood as temporal</note> do good and suffer <transChange type="added">for it</transChange>, this <transChange type="added">finds</transChange> favor with God.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For to this you were called, because Christ also suffered for you, leaving you an example, so that you should follow in his footsteps,</verse>
    <verse num="22">who did not commit sin, nor was deceit found in his mouth,<note>This verse contains quotations from Isa 53:9</note></verse>
    <verse num="23">who <transChange type="added">when he</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("was reviled") which is understood as temporal</note> was reviled, did not revile in return; <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("suffering") which is understood as temporal</note> suffering, he did not threaten, but entrusted <transChange type="added">himself</transChange> to the one who judges justly,</verse>
    <verse num="24">who himself bore our sins in his body on the tree, so that <transChange type="added">we</transChange> may die to sins <transChange type="added">and</transChange> live to righteousness, by whose wounds you were healed.</verse>
    <verse num="25">For you were going astray like sheep, but you have turned back now to the shepherd and guardian of your souls. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">In the same way, wives, be subject to your own husbands, so that even if some are disobedient to the word, they may be won over without a word by the conduct of their wives,</verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">when they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("see") which is understood as temporal</note> see your respectful, pure conduct.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Let your<note>Literally "of whom," referring to the wives</note> adornment not be the external <transChange type="added">kind</transChange>, braiding hair and putting on gold jewelry or putting on <transChange type="added">fine</transChange> clothing,</verse>
    <verse num="4">but the hidden person of the heart, with the imperishable <transChange type="added">quality</transChange> of a gentle and quiet spirit, which is highly valuable in the sight of God.</verse>
    <verse num="5">For in the <transChange type="added">same</transChange> way formerly the holy women also, who hoped in God, used to adorn themselves <transChange type="added">by</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">by</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("being subject") which is understood as means</note> being subject to their own husbands,</verse>
    <verse num="6">like Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord, whose children you have become <transChange type="added">when you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("do good") which is understood as temporal</note> do good and are not frightened with respect to any terror. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Husbands, in the same way live with <transChange type="added">your wives</transChange> {knowledgeably}<note>Literally "according to knowledge"</note>, as with the weaker female vessel, showing <transChange type="added">them</transChange> honor as fellow heirs also of the grace of life, so that your prayers will not be hindered. </verse>
    <verse num="8">And finally, all <transChange type="added">of you be</transChange> harmonious, sympathetic, showing mutual affection, compassionate, humble,</verse>
    <verse num="9">not repaying evil for evil or insult for insult, but on the other hand blessing <transChange type="added">others</transChange>, because for this <transChange type="added">reason</transChange> you were called, so that you could inherit a blessing.</verse>
    <verse num="10">For </verse>
    <verse num="11">And he must turn away from evil and do good; he must seek peace and pursue it.</verse>
    <verse num="12">For the eyes of the Lord <transChange type="added">are</transChange> on the righteous, and his ears <transChange type="added">are open to</transChange> their prayer. But the face of the Lord <transChange type="added">is</transChange> against those who do evil.<note>Verses 10-12 are a quotation from Ps 34:12-16</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">And who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the one who will harm you if you are a zealous adherent for what is good?</verse>
    <verse num="14">But even if you might suffer for the sake of righteousness, <transChange type="added">you are</transChange> blessed. And do not be afraid of their intimidation or be disturbed,<note>The second half of this verse contains a quotation from Isa 8:12</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">but set Christ apart <transChange type="added">as</transChange> Lord in your hearts, always ready to <transChange type="added">make</transChange> a defense to anyone who asks you <transChange type="added">for</transChange> an accounting concerning the hope <transChange type="added">that is</transChange> in you.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But <transChange type="added">do so</transChange> with courtesy and respect, having a good conscience, so that in <transChange type="added">the things</transChange> in which you are slandered, the ones who malign your good conduct in Christ may be put to shame.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> better to suffer for doing good, {if God wills it}<note>Literally "if the will of God wills"</note>, than for doing evil. </verse>
    <verse num="18">For Christ also suffered once for sins, the just for the unjust, in order that he could bring you to God, being put to death in the flesh, but made alive in the spirit,</verse>
    <verse num="19">in which also he went <transChange type="added">and</transChange> proclaimed to the spirits in prison,</verse>
    <verse num="20">who were formerly disobedient, when the patience of God waited in the days of Noah, <transChange type="added">while</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">while</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("was being constructed")</note> an ark was being constructed, in which a few--that is, eight souls--were rescued through water.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And<note>Literally "which"</note> also, corresponding to <transChange type="added">this</transChange>, baptism now saves you, not the removal of dirt from the flesh, but an appeal to God for a good conscience through the resurrection of Jesus Christ,</verse>
    <verse num="22">who is at the right hand of God, having gone into heaven, with angels and authorities and powers having been subjected to him. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">Therefore, <transChange type="added">because</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("suffered") which is understood as causal</note> Christ suffered in the flesh, you also equip yourselves with the same way of thinking, because the one who has suffered in the flesh has ceased from sin,</verse>
    <verse num="2">in order to live the remaining time in the flesh no longer for human desires, but for the will of God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">For the time that has passed <transChange type="added">was</transChange> sufficient {to do what the Gentiles desire to do}<note>Literally "to do the intention of the Gentiles"</note>, having lived in licentiousness, <transChange type="added">evil</transChange> desires, drunkenness, carousing, drinking parties, and wanton idolatries,</verse>
    <verse num="4">with respect to which they are surprised <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("run with") which is understood as temporal</note> you do not run with <transChange type="added">them</transChange> into the same flood of dissipation, <transChange type="added">and so they</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">and so</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("revile") which is understood as result</note> revile <transChange type="added">you</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="5">They<note>Literally "who"</note> will give an account to the one who is ready to judge the living and the dead.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Because for this reason also the gospel was preached to those who are dead, so that they were judged {by human standards}<note>Literally "according to men"</note> in the flesh, but they may live in the spirit {by God's standards}<note>Literally "according to God"</note>. </verse>
    <verse num="7">Now the end of all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> draws near. Therefore be self-controlled and sober-minded for <transChange type="added">your</transChange> prayers.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Above all, keep<note>Literally "having"</note> your love for one another constant, because love covers a large number of sins.</verse>
    <verse num="9"><transChange type="added">Be</transChange> hospitable to one another without complaining.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Just as each one has received a gift, <transChange type="added">use</transChange> it for serving one another, as good stewards of the varied grace of God.</verse>
    <verse num="11">If anyone speaks, <transChange type="added">let it be</transChange> as the oracles of God; if anyone serves, <transChange type="added">let it be</transChange> as by the strength that God provides, so that in all <transChange type="added">things</transChange> God will be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom is the glory and the power {forever and ever}<note>Literally "for the ages of the ages"</note>. Amen. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Dear friends, do not be surprised at the fiery ordeal among you, <transChange type="added">when it</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("takes place") which is understood as temporal</note> takes place to test you, as <transChange type="added">if</transChange> <transChange type="added">something</transChange> strange were happening to you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">But to the degree that you share in the sufferings of Christ, rejoice, so that also at the revelation of his glory you may rejoice <transChange type="added">and</transChange> be glad.</verse>
    <verse num="14">If you are reviled on account of the name of Christ, <transChange type="added">you are</transChange> blessed, because the Spirit of glory and of God rests on you.</verse>
    <verse num="15">By all means do not let anyone of you suffer as a murderer or a thief or an evildoer or as a meddler.</verse>
    <verse num="16">But if <transChange type="added">someone suffers</transChange> as a Christian, he must not be ashamed, but must glorify God with this name.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For <transChange type="added">it is</transChange> the time for the judgment to begin out from the household of God. But if <transChange type="added">it begins</transChange> out from us first, what will be the outcome for those who are disobedient to the gospel of God?</verse>
    <verse num="18">And if the righteous are saved with difficulty, {what will become of the ungodly and the sinner}<note>Literally "the ungodly and sinner where will he appear"</note>?<note>This verse contains a quotation from Prov 11:31</note></verse>
    <verse num="19">So then also those who suffer according to the will of God must entrust their souls to a faithful Creator in doing good. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">Therefore <transChange type="added">I, your</transChange> fellow elder and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, <transChange type="added">and</transChange><note>*The conjunction "<transChange type="added">and</transChange>" is supplied here to make it clear that the following phrase refers also to the author of the letter and not to Christ</note> also a sharer of the glory that is going to be revealed, exhort the elders among you:</verse>
    <verse num="2">shepherd the flock of God among you, exercising oversight not by compulsion but willingly, in accordance with God, and not greedily but eagerly,</verse>
    <verse num="3">and not as lording it over {those under your care}<note>Literally "the portion"</note>, but being examples for the flock.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And <transChange type="added">when</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">when</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the temporal genitive absolute participle ("appears")</note> the chief Shepherd appears, you will receive the unfading crown of glory. </verse>
    <verse num="5">In the same way, younger men, be subject to the elders, and all <transChange type="added">of you</transChange> clothe yourselves with humility toward one another, because God opposes the proud, but gives grace to the humble.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you at the <transChange type="added">right</transChange> time,</verse>
    <verse num="7">casting all your cares on him, because {he cares}<note>Literally "it is a care to him"</note> for you. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Be sober; be on the alert. Your adversary the devil walks around like a roaring lion, looking for someone to devour.</verse>
    <verse num="9">{Resist him}<note>Literally "to whom resist"</note>, steadfast in your<note>Literally "the"; the Greek article is used here as a possessive pronoun</note> faith, <transChange type="added">because you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">because</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("know") which is understood as causal</note> know the same <transChange type="added">kinds</transChange> of sufferings are being accomplished by your community of believers in the world.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the God of all grace, who called you to his eternal glory in Christ,<note>Some manuscripts have "in Christ Jesus"</note> <transChange type="added">after you</transChange><note>*Here "<transChange type="added">after</transChange>" is supplied as a component of the participle ("have suffered") which is understood as temporal</note> have suffered for a short time, will himself restore, confirm, strengthen, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> establish <transChange type="added">you</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="11">To him <transChange type="added">be</transChange> the power {forever and ever}<note>Literally "to the ages of the ages"</note>.<note>Some manuscripts have "forever" (literally "to the ages")</note> Amen. </verse>
    <verse num="12">Through Silvanus, the faithful brother (as I consider <transChange type="added">him</transChange>), I have written to you {briefly}<note>Literally "by a few"</note> to encourage <transChange type="added">you</transChange> and to attest that this is the true grace of God. Stand firm in it.</verse>
    <verse num="13">She <transChange type="added">who is</transChange> in Babylon, chosen the same as <transChange type="added">you</transChange>, greets you, and <transChange type="added">so does</transChange> my son Mark.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Greet one another with a loving kiss. Peace to all of you who are in Christ. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>