<book num="1Chr">
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">Adam, Seth, Enosh;</verse>
    <verse num="2">Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared;</verse>
    <verse num="3">Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech;</verse>
    <verse num="4">Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. </verse>
    <verse num="5">The sons of Japheth: Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, Diphath, and Togarmah.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The sons of Javan: Elishah, Tarshish, Kittim, and Rhodanim. </verse>
    <verse num="8">The sons of Ham: Cush, Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The sons of Cush: Seba, Havilah, Sabta, Raamah, and Sabteca. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Cush fathered Nimrod; he himself began to be mighty on earth.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Mizraim fathered the Ludim, the Anamim, the Lehabim, the Naphtuhim,</verse>
    <verse num="12">the Pathrusim, the Casluhim (from whence the Philistines descended), and the Caphtorim.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And Canaan fathered Zidon his firstborn, and Heth,</verse>
    <verse num="14">and the Jebusites, the Amorites, the Girgashites,</verse>
    <verse num="15">the Hivites, the Arkites, the Sinites,</verse>
    <verse num="16">the Arvadites, the Zemarites, and the Hamathites. </verse>
    <verse num="17">The sons of Shem: Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, Aram, Uz, Hul, Gether, and Meshech.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And Arphaxad fathered Shelah; and Shelah fathered Eber.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And two sons were born to Eber: the name of the one <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Peleg (for in his days the earth was divided), and the name of his brother <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Joktan.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Joktan fathered Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmaveth, Jerah,</verse>
    <verse num="21">Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah,</verse>
    <verse num="22">Ebal,<note>Spelled "Obal" in Genesis 10:28</note> Abimael, Sheba,</verse>
    <verse num="23">Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab; all these were the sons of Joktan.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah;</verse>
    <verse num="25">Eber, Peleg, Reu;</verse>
    <verse num="26">Serug, Nahor, Terah;</verse>
    <verse num="27">Abram, that is, Abraham. </verse>
    <verse num="28">The sons of Abraham: Isaac and Ishmael.</verse>
    <verse num="29">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth, and Kedar, Abdeel, Mibsam,</verse>
    <verse num="30">Mishma, Dumah, Massa, Hadad, Tema,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Jetur, Naphish, and Kedmah. These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the sons of Ishmael.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And the sons of Keturah, Abraham's concubine: she gave birth to Zimran, Jokshan, Medan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And the sons of Midian: Ephah, Epher, Enoch, Abida, and Eldaah. All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Keturah. </verse>
    <verse num="34">Abraham fathered Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau and Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="35">The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, Jeush, Jalam, and Korah.</verse>
    <verse num="36">The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, Omar, Zephi,<note>Spelled "Zepho" in Genesis 36:11</note> Gatam, Kenaz, Timna, and Amalek.</verse>
    <verse num="37">The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And the sons of Seir: Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, Dishon, Ezer, and Dishan.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And the sons of Lotan: Hori and Homam; and the sister of Lotan <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Timna.</verse>
    <verse num="40">The sons of Shobal: Alian, Manahath, Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah.</verse>
    <verse num="41">The sons of Anah: Dishon. And the sons of Dishon: Hamran, Eshban, Ithran, and Keran.</verse>
    <verse num="42">The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, Zaavan, and Jaakan. The sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran. </verse>
    <verse num="43">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the kings who reigned in the land of Edom before any king reigned over the {Israelites}:<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> Bela son of Beor, and the name of his city <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Dinhabah.</verse>
    <verse num="44">When Bela died, Jobab son of Zerah from Bozrah reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="45">When Jobab died, Husham from the land of the Temanites reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="46">When Husham died, Hadad son of Bedad, who defeated the Midianites in the country of Moab, reigned in his place. And the name of his city was Avith.<note>According to the reading tradition (Qere); Kethib has "Avuth"</note></verse>
    <verse num="47">When Hadad died, Samlah from Masrekah reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="48">When Samlah died, Shaul from Rehoboth-by-the-River reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="49">When Shaul died, Baal-Hanan son of Achbor reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="50">When Baal-Hanan died, Hadad reigned in his place, and the name of his city <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Pai.<note>Spelled "Pau" in Genesis 36:39</note> And the name of his wife <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Mehetabel, daughter of Matred, daughter of Me-Zahab.</verse>
    <verse num="51">And Hadad died. And the chiefs of Edom were: chiefs Timna, Aliah, Jetheth,</verse>
    <verse num="52">Oholibamah, Elah, Pinon,</verse>
    <verse num="53">Kenaz, Teman, Mibzar,</verse>
    <verse num="54">Magdiel, and Iram. These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the chiefs of Edom. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Zebulun,</verse>
    <verse num="2">Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The sons of Judah: Er, Onan and Shelah; <transChange type="added">these</transChange> three were born to him from Bathshua the Canaanite. Now Er, Judah's firstborn, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> evil in the sight of Yahweh, and he put him to death.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Tamar his daughter-in-law bore Perez and Zerah to him. The sons of Judah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> five in all. </verse>
    <verse num="5">The sons of Perez: Hezron and Hamul.</verse>
    <verse num="6">The sons of Zerah: Zimri, Ethan, Heman, Calcol, and Dara, five in all.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The son of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who acted unfaithfully in the matter of the devoted thing.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And the son of Ethan <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Azariah. </verse>
    <verse num="9">The sons of Hezron who were born to him: Jerahmeel, Ram, and Caleb.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Ram fathered Amminadab, and Amminadab fathered Nahshon, prince of the sons of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Nahshon fathered Salma, and Salma fathered Boaz.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Boaz fathered Obed, and Obed fathered Jesse.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And Jesse fathered Eliab his firstborn, Abinadab the second, Shimea the third,</verse>
    <verse num="14">Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,</verse>
    <verse num="15">Ozem the sixth, David the seventh.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And their sisters <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Zeruiah and Abigail. The sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, Joab, and Asahel, three.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Abigail bore Amasa, and the father of Amasa <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Jether the Ishmaelite. </verse>
    <verse num="18">And Caleb the son of Hezron fathered children by Azubah his wife and by Jerioth. And these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> her sons: Jesher, Shobab, and Ardon.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And when Azubah died, Caleb married<note>Or "took"</note> Ephrathah, and she bore Hur to him.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Hur fathered Uri, and Uri fathered Bezalel. </verse>
    <verse num="21">And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Makir the father of Gilead. And he married<note>Or "took"</note> her when he was sixty years old. And she bore Segub to him.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Segub fathered Jair, and he had twenty-three cities in the land of Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Geshur and Aram took Havvoth-Jair from them, Kenath and its villages, sixty cities. All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the {descendants}<note>Literally "sons"</note> of Makir, the father of Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And after the death of Hezron in Caleb-Ephrathah, Abijah the wife of Hezron bore to him Ashhur, the father of Tekoa. </verse>
    <verse num="25">And the sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were Ram his firstborn, Bunah, Oren, Ozem, and Ahijah.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And Jerahmeel had another wife, and her name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Atarah. She <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the mother of Onam.</verse>
    <verse num="27">The sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were Maaz, Jamin, and Eker.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And the sons of Onam were Shammai and Jada. And the sons of Shammai <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Nadab and Abishur.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And the name of the wife of Abishur <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Abihail, and she bore to him Ahban and Molid.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the sons of Nadab <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Seled and Appaim. And Seled died without children.</verse>
    <verse num="31">And the sons of Appaim: Ishi. The sons of Ishi: Sheshan. The sons of Sheshan: Ahlai.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether and Jonathan. And Jether died without children.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth and Zaza. These were the children of Jerahmeel.</verse>
    <verse num="34">And Sheshan had no sons, only daughters, but Sheshan had an Egyptian slave, and his name <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Jarha.</verse>
    <verse num="35">So Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his slave for a wife, and she bore to him Attai.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And Attai fathered Nathan, and Nathan fathered Zabad.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And Zabad fathered Ephlal, and Ephlal fathered Obed.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And Obed fathered Jehu, and Jehu fathered Azariah.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And Azariah fathered Helez, and Helez fathered Eleasah.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And Eleasah fathered Sismai, and Sismai fathered Shallum.</verse>
    <verse num="41">And Shallum fathered Jekamiah, and Jekamiah fathered Elishama. </verse>
    <verse num="42">And the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his firstborn; he <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Ziph. The sons of Mareshah: Hebron.</verse>
    <verse num="43">And the sons of Hebron <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Korah, Tappuah, Rekem, and Shema.</verse>
    <verse num="44">And Shema fathered Raham, the father of Jorkeam. And Rekem fathered Shammai.</verse>
    <verse num="45">And the son of Shammai <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Maon, and Maon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Beth-Zur.</verse>
    <verse num="46">And Ephah, the concubine of Caleb, gave birth to Haran, Moza, and Gazez. And Haran fathered Gazez.</verse>
    <verse num="47">And the sons of Jahdai <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Regem, Jotham, Geshan, Pelet, Ephah, and Shaaph.</verse>
    <verse num="48">Maacah, the concubine of Caleb, gave birth to Sheber and Tirhanah.</verse>
    <verse num="49">She also gave birth to Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbenah and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Acsah.</verse>
    <verse num="50">These were the {descendants}<note>Literally "sons"</note> of Caleb. </verse>
    <verse num="51">Salma the father of Bethlehem, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> Hareph the father of Beth-Gader.</verse>
    <verse num="52">And Shobal the father of Kiriath-Jearim had <transChange type="added">other</transChange> sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth.</verse>
    <verse num="53">And the families of Kiriath-Jearim: the Ithrites, the Puthites, the Shumathites, and the Mishraites. From these descended the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites.</verse>
    <verse num="54">The sons of Salma: Bethlehem, the Netophathites, Ataroth-Beth-Joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites.</verse>
    <verse num="55">And the families of the scribes who lived <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and the Sucathites. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the Kenites who came from Hammath, the father of the house of Recab. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">These were the sons of David who were born to him in Hebron: the firstborn, Amnon, by Ahinoam the Jezreelite; the second, Daniel, by Abigail the Carmelite;</verse>
    <verse num="2">the third, Absalom, the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai, king of Geshur; the fourth, Adonijah, the son of Haggith;</verse>
    <verse num="3">the fifth, Shephatiah, by Abital; the sixth, Ithream, by his wife Eglah.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Six were born to him in Hebron. And he reigned there seven years and six months. And he reigned thirty-three years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And these were born to him in Jerusalem: Shimea, Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, four by Bathshua the daughter of Ammiel;</verse>
    <verse num="6">then Ibhar, Elishama, Eliphelet,</verse>
    <verse num="7">Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia,</verse>
    <verse num="8">Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.</verse>
    <verse num="9">All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of David, besides the sons of the concubines. And Tamar was their sister. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Now the son of Solomon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Rehoboam; Abijah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Asa <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Jehoshaphat <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son,</verse>
    <verse num="11">Joram <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Ahaziah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Joash <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son,</verse>
    <verse num="12">Amaziah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Azariah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Jotham <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son,</verse>
    <verse num="13">Ahaz <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Hezekiah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Manasseh <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son,</verse>
    <verse num="14">Amon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Josiah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son. </verse>
    <verse num="15">And the sons of Josiah: Johanan the firstborn, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And the {descendants}<note>Literally "sons"</note> of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the sons of Jeconiah, the captive: Shealtiel his son,</verse>
    <verse num="18">Malchiram, Pedaiah, Shenazzar, Jekamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And the sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel and Shimei. And the sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister,</verse>
    <verse num="20">and Hashubah, Ohel, Berekiah, Hasadiah, and Jushab-Hesed, five.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And the sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah and Jeshaiah. The sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shecaniah.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And the sons of Shecaniah: Shemaiah. And the sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, Igal, Bariah, Neariah, and Shaphat, six.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And the sons of Neariah: Elioenai, Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And the sons of Elioenai: Hodaviah, Eliashib, Pelaiah, Akkub, Johanan, Delaiah, and Anani, seven. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, Carmi, Hur, and Shobal.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Reaiah the son of Shobal fathered Jahath, and Jahath fathered Ahumai and Lahad. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the clans of the Zorathites.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Etam: Jezreel, Ishma, and Idbash. And the name of their sister <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Hazzelelponi,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and Penuel <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Gedor, and Ezer <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Hushah. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah, the father of Bethlehem.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Ashhur, the father of Tekoa, had two wives: Helah and Naarah.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And Naarah bore him Ahuzzam, Hepher, Temeni, and Haahashtari. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Naarah.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The sons of Helah: Zereth, Izhar, and Ethnan.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And Koz fathered Anub, Zobebah, and the clans of Aharhel, the son of Harum.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Jabez was more honorable than his brothers. And his mother called his name Jabez, saying, "Because I bore him in pain."</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Jabez called upon the God of Israel, saying, "Oh that you would surely bless me and enlarge my border. And may your hand be with me, that you would keep me from evil so that it might not harm me!" And God granted what he asked.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Chelub, the brother of Shuhah, fathered Mehir. He <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Eshton.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And Eshton fathered Beth-Rapha, Paseah, and Tehinnah, the father of the city of Nahash. These <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the men of Recah.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The sons of Kenaz: Othniel and Seraiah. And the sons of Othniel: Hathath.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Meonothai fathered Ophrah; and Seraiah fathered Joab, the father of Ge-Harashim, because they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> craftsmen.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The sons of Caleb, the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam. And the sons of Elah: Kenaz.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The sons of Ezrah: Jether, Mered, Epher, and Jalon. And she became pregnant with Miriam, Shammai, and Ishbah, the father of Eshtemoa.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And his Judahite wife bore Jered the father of Gedor, Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Bithiah daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered married.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the fathers of Keilah the Garmite and Eshtemoa the Maacathite.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The sons of Shimon: Amnon, Rinnah, Ben-Hanan, and Tolon. The sons of Ishi: Zoheth and Ben-Zoheth.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The sons of Shelah, the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of linen workers at Beth Ashbea;</verse>
    <verse num="22">and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who ruled in Moab and returned to Lehem. (Now the records are ancient).</verse>
    <verse num="23">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the potters and inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah. They lived there with the king in his service. </verse>
    <verse num="24">The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul.</verse>
    <verse num="25">Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.</verse>
    <verse num="26">The sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters, but his brothers did not have many children. But all their families did not multiply like the men of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And they lived in Beersheba, Moladah, Hazar Shual,</verse>
    <verse num="29">Bilhah, Ezem, Tolad,</verse>
    <verse num="30">Bethuel, Hormah, Ziklag,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Beth-Marcaboth, Hazar-Susim, Beth-Biri, and Shaaraim. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> their cities until David reigned.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And their villages <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Etam, Ain, Rimmon, Token, and Ashan, five cities</verse>
    <verse num="33">and all their villages that surrounding these cities as far as Baal. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> their settlements, and they kept a genealogical record for them. </verse>
    <verse num="34">Meshobab, Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah,</verse>
    <verse num="35">Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, son of Seraiah, son of Asiel.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And Elioenai, Jaakobah, Jeshohaiah, Asaiah, Adiel, Jesimiel, Benaiah,</verse>
    <verse num="37">and Ziza the son of Shiphi, son of Allon, son of Jedaiah, son of Shimri, son of Shemaiah.</verse>
    <verse num="38">These {mentioned by name}<note>Literally "coming in the names"</note> <transChange type="added">were</transChange> leaders in their families, and their fathers' households increased greatly.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And they went to the entrance of Gedor, up to the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And they found fertile and good pasture, and the land <transChange type="added">was</transChange> very broad, quiet, and at ease, for the former inhabitants there <transChange type="added">were</transChange> from Ham.</verse>
    <verse num="41">These, mentioned by name, came in the days of Hezekiah, king of Judah, and attacked their tents and the Meunites who were found there. And they devoted them to destruction to this day, and they settled among them because <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> pasture there for their flocks.</verse>
    <verse num="42">And some of them from the Simeonites went to Mount Seir, five hundred men. And Pelatiah, Neariah, Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> under their leadership.</verse>
    <verse num="43">And they destroyed the remainder of the Amalekites who had escaped, and they have lived there to this day. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel (for he was the firstborn, but when he defiled the couch of his father, his birthright was given to the sons of Joseph, the son of Israel, so that he was not enrolled in the genealogy as the firstborn,</verse>
    <verse num="2">though Judah became strong among his brothers and a chief <transChange type="added">came</transChange> from him, but the birthright belonged to Joseph).</verse>
    <verse num="3">The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel: Enoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</verse>
    <verse num="4">The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son,</verse>
    <verse num="5">Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son,</verse>
    <verse num="6">Beerah his son, a leader of the Reubenites, whom Tiglath-Pilneser king of Assyria deported into exile.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And his kinsmen by their families, when their generations were recorded in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> genealogy: the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah,</verse>
    <verse num="8">and Bela son of Azaz, son of Shema, son of Joel, who lived in Aroer, as far as Nebo and Baal-Meon.</verse>
    <verse num="9">He also lived to the east up to the entrance of the desert {this side of}<note>Or "from"</note> the River Euphrates, for their livestock had multiplied in the land of Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And in the days of Saul they made war against the Hagrites, and they<note>That is, the Hagrites</note> fell into their hand. And they lived in their tents in all the region east of Gilead. </verse>
    <verse num="11">And the sons of Gad lived near to them in the land of Bashan as far as Salecah:</verse>
    <verse num="12">Joel the chief, Shapham the second, Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And their kinsmen according to their fathers' households: Michael, Meshullam, Sheba, Jorai, Jacan, Zia, and Eber, seven.</verse>
    <verse num="14">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Abihail the son of Huri, son of Jaroah, son of Gilead, son of Michael, son of Jeshishai, son of Jahdo, son of Buz.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Ahi son of Abdiel, son of Guni, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> chief in their fathers' households.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And they lived in Gilead, in Bashan, and in {its towns},<note>Literally "her daughters"</note> and in all the pasturelands of Sharon to their limits.</verse>
    <verse num="17">All of them were enrolled in <transChange type="added">the</transChange> genealogy in the days of Jotham, king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam, king of Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="18">The Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh <transChange type="added">had</transChange> {valiant}<note>Literally "sons of strength"</note> men <transChange type="added">who</transChange> carried a shield and a sword, and archers, and <transChange type="added">who were</transChange> expert in war, forty-four thousand seven hundred and sixty <transChange type="added">for</transChange> going out <transChange type="added">as</transChange> an army.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And they made war against the Hagrites, Jetur, Naphish, and Nodab.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And they were helped against them, and the Hagrites and all who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with them were given into their hand, for they cried out to God in the battle, and he responded to their prayer because they trusted in him.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And they captured their livestock: fifty thousand of their camels; two hundred and fifty thousand sheep; two thousand donkeys; and one hundred thousand men alive.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For many <transChange type="added">were</transChange> slain because the war was of God. And they lived under them until the exile. </verse>
    <verse num="23">And the sons of the half-tribe of Manasseh lived in the land from Bashan to Baal-Hermon, Senir, and Mount Hermon. They <transChange type="added">were</transChange> numerous.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Now these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of their fathers' households: Epher, Ishi, Eliel, Azriel, Jeremiah, Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of strength, {famous men},<note>Literally "men of the name"</note> heads of their fathers' households.</verse>
    <verse num="25">But they transgressed against the God of their ancestors<note>Or "fathers"</note> and prostituted themselves after the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God had destroyed before them.</verse>
    <verse num="26">So the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul, king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tiglath-Pilneser, king of Assyria, and he took them <transChange type="added">into exile</transChange>, namely, the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh. And he brought them to Halah, Habor, Hara, and the river Gozan, until this day. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1"><note>1 Chronicles 6:1-81 in the English Bible is 5:27-6:66 in the Hebrew Bible</note> The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The children of Amram: Aaron, Moses, and Miriam. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Eleazar fathered Phinehas; Phinehas fathered Abishua;</verse>
    <verse num="5">Abishua fathered Bukki; Bukki fathered Uzzi;</verse>
    <verse num="6">Uzzi fathered Zerahiah; Zerahiah fathered Meraioth;</verse>
    <verse num="7">Meraioth fathered Amariah; Amariah fathered Ahitub;</verse>
    <verse num="8">Ahitub fathered Zadok; Zadok fathered Ahimaaz;</verse>
    <verse num="9">Ahimaaz fathered Azariah; Azariah fathered Johanan;</verse>
    <verse num="10">and Johanan fathered Azariah. <transChange type="added">It was</transChange> he who served as priest in the temple that Solomon built in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Azariah fathered Amariah; Amariah fathered Ahitub;</verse>
    <verse num="12">Ahitub fathered Zadok; Zadok fathered Shallum;</verse>
    <verse num="13">Shallum fathered Hilkiah; Hilkiah fathered Azariah;</verse>
    <verse num="14">Azariah fathered Seraiah; Seraiah fathered Jehozadak.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Jehozadak went into exile <transChange type="added">when</transChange> Yahweh <transChange type="added">sent</transChange> Judah and Jerusalem into exile by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar. </verse>
    <verse num="16">The sons of Levi: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the names of the sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the families of the Levites according to their ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note></verse>
    <verse num="20">Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,</verse>
    <verse num="21">Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeatherai his son.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son,</verse>
    <verse num="23">Elkanah his son, Ebiasaph his son, Assir his son,</verse>
    <verse num="24">Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The sons of Elkanah: Amasai and Ahimoth,</verse>
    <verse num="26">Elkanah his son, Zophai his son, Nahath his son,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.</verse>
    <verse num="28">The sons of Samuel: <transChange type="added">Joel</transChange><note>"Joel" is from 1 Samuel 8:2, the parallel to this genealogy. The name has dropped out of the text here</note> his firstborn and Abijah the second.</verse>
    <verse num="29">The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son,</verse>
    <verse num="30">Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, and Asaiah his son. </verse>
    <verse num="31">Now these <transChange type="added">are the men</transChange> whom David appointed for {control of singing}<note>Literally "to the hands of song"</note> in the house of Yahweh where the ark rested.</verse>
    <verse num="32">They were ministering with song before the tabernacle of the tent of assembly<note>Or "meeting"</note> until Solomon built the temple of Yahweh in Jerusalem. And they stood according to their order with respect to their duty.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> those who served and their sons. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, son of Samuel,</verse>
    <verse num="34">son of Elkanah, son of Jeroham, son of Eliel, son of Toah,</verse>
    <verse num="35">son of Zuph, son of Elkanah, son of Mahath, son of Amasai,</verse>
    <verse num="36">son of Elkanah, son of Joel, son of Azariah, son of Zephaniah,</verse>
    <verse num="37">son of Tahath, son of Assir, son of Ebiasaph, son of Korah,</verse>
    <verse num="38">son of Izhar, son of Kohath, son of Levi, son of Israel;</verse>
    <verse num="39">and his brother Asaph, who stood on his right <transChange type="added">namely</transChange>, Asaph the son of Berechiah, son of Shimea,</verse>
    <verse num="40">son of Michael, son of Baaseiah, son of Malkijah,</verse>
    <verse num="41">son of Ethni, son of Zerah, son of Adaiah,</verse>
    <verse num="42">son of Ethan, son of Zimmah, son of Shimei,</verse>
    <verse num="43">son of Jahath, son of Gershom, son of Levi.</verse>
    <verse num="44">On the left <transChange type="added">were</transChange> their brothers, the sons of Merari: Ethan the son of Kishi, son of Abdi, son of Malluch,</verse>
    <verse num="45">son of Hashabiah, son of Amaziah, son of Hilkiah,</verse>
    <verse num="46">son of Amzi, son of Bani, son of Shemer,</verse>
    <verse num="47">son of Mahli, son of Mushi, son of Merari, son of Levi.</verse>
    <verse num="48">And their brothers the Levites were appointed for all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.</verse>
    <verse num="49">But Aaron and his sons made offerings on the altar of burnt offering and on the altar of incense for all the work of the most holy place, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded. </verse>
    <verse num="50">Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son,</verse>
    <verse num="51">Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son,</verse>
    <verse num="52">Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son,</verse>
    <verse num="53">Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.</verse>
    <verse num="54">And these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their dwellings according to their settlements within their borders: to the sons of Aaron of the clans of Kohathites, for the <transChange type="added">first</transChange> lot <transChange type="added">was</transChange> theirs,</verse>
    <verse num="55">and they gave to them Hebron in the land of Judah and its surrounding pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="56">but the fields of the city and its villages they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh.</verse>
    <verse num="57">To the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge: Hebron, Libnah with its pasturelands, Jattir, Eshtemoa with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="58">Hilen with its pasturelands, Debir with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="59">Ashan with its pasturelands, and Beth-Shemesh with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="60">And from the tribe of Benjamin, Geba with its pasturelands, Alemeth with its pasturelands, and Anathoth with its pasturelands. All their cities <transChange type="added">were</transChange> thirteen cities throughout their clans.</verse>
    <verse num="61">To the Kohathites who remained from the family of the half-tribe, the half of Manasseh, <transChange type="added">were given</transChange> by lot ten cities.</verse>
    <verse num="62">To the Gershomites according to their clans thirteen cities <transChange type="added">were allotted</transChange> out of the tribe of Issachar, out of the tribe of Asher, out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan.</verse>
    <verse num="63">To the Merarites twelve cities <transChange type="added">were</transChange> allotted according to their clans out of the tribe of Reuben, out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun.</verse>
    <verse num="64">So the {Israelites}<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> gave the Levites the cities with their pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="65">And they gave by lot out of the tribe of Judah, out of the tribe of Simeon, and out of the tribe of Benjamin these cities that are mentioned by name.</verse>
    <verse num="66">And of the clans of the sons of Kohath were cities of their territory out of the tribe of Ephraim.</verse>
    <verse num="67">And they gave them the cities of refuge: Shechem with its pasturelands in the hill country of Ephraim, Gezer with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="68">Jokmeam with its pasturelands, Beth-Horon with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="69">Aijalon with its pasturelands, and Gath-Rimmon with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="70">And out of the half-tribe of Manasseh: Aner with its pasturelands, and Bileam with its pasturelands for the remaining the clans of the Kohathites.</verse>
    <verse num="71">To the Gershomites <transChange type="added">were given</transChange> out of the clan of the half-tribe of Manasseh: Golan in Bashan with its pasturelands and Ashtaroth with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="72">And out of the tribe of Issachar: Kedesh with its pasturelands, Daberath with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="73">Ramoth with its pasturelands, and Anem with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="74">And out of the tribe of Asher: Mashal with its pasturelands, Abdon with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="75">Hukok with its pasturelands, and Rehob with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="76">And out of the tribe of Naphtali: Kedesh in Galilee with its pasturelands, Hammon with its pasturelands, and Kiriathaim with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="77">To the remainder of the Merarites <transChange type="added">were allotted</transChange> out of the tribe of Zebulun: Rimmono with its pasturelands, Tabor with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="78">And beyond the Jordan <transChange type="added">at</transChange> Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, out of the tribe of Reuben: Bezer in the wilderness with its pasturelands, Jahzah with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="79">Kedemoth with its pasturelands, and Mephaath with its pasturelands.</verse>
    <verse num="80">And out of the tribe of Gad: Ramoth in Gilead with its pasturelands, Mahanaim with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <verse num="81">Heshbon with its pasturelands, and Jazer with its pasturelands. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">The sons of Issachar: Tola, Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.</verse>
    <verse num="2">The sons of Tola: Uzzi, Rephaiah, Jeriel, Jahmai, Ibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers' houses; for Tola, mighty warriors of their generations, their number in the days of David <transChange type="added">were</transChange> twenty-two thousand six hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah. And the sons of Izrahiah: Michael, Obadiah, Joel, and Isshiah; all five of them <transChange type="added">were</transChange> chiefs.<note>Or "heads"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And in addition to them, according to their generations, according to the house of their fathers, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> troops of the army for war: thirty-six thousand. For {they had}<note>Literally "there were"</note> many wives and sons.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Now their kinsmen belonging to all the clans of Issachar <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in all eighty-seven thousand mighty warriors, enrolled according to their genealogy. </verse>
    <verse num="6"><transChange type="added">The sons of</transChange> Benjamin: Bela, Beker, and Jediael, three.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The sons of Bela: Ezbon, Uzzi, Uzziel, Jerimoth, and Iri, five, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> heads of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> house of <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fathers, mighty warriors. And their enrollment by genealogy <transChange type="added">was</transChange> twenty-two thousand thirty-four.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The sons of Beker: Zemirah, Joash, Eliezer, Elioenai, Omri, Jeremoth, Abijah, Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Beker.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And their enrollment by genealogy according to their generations, <transChange type="added">as</transChange> heads of the house of their fathers, mighty warriors, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> twenty thousand two hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The sons of Jediael: Bilhan. And the sons of Bilhan: Jeush, Benjamin, Ehud, Kenaanah, Zethan, Tarshish, and Ahishahar.</verse>
    <verse num="11">All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Jediael according to the heads of the {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> mighty warriors, seventeen thousand two hundred, {able to go to war}.<note>Literally "going out to the army to the war"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">And Shuppim and Huppim <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Ir; Hushim, the son of Aher. </verse>
    <verse num="13">The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, Guni, Jezer, and Shallum, the {descendants}<note>Literally "sons"</note> of Bilhah. </verse>
    <verse num="14">The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his Aramean concubine bore; she gave birth to Makir the father of Gilead.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Machir took a wife for Huppim and for Shuppim. And the name of his sister <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Maacah. And the name of the second, Zelophehad. And Zelophehad had daughters.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Maacah the wife of Machir gave birth to a son, and she called his name Peresh. And the name of his brother <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Sheresh, and his sons <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Ulam and Rekem.</verse>
    <verse num="17">The sons of Ulam: Bedan. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Gilead the son of Makir, son of Manasseh.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And his sister, Hammolecheth, gave birth to Ishhod, Abiezer, and Mahlah.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The sons of Shemida were Ahian, Shechem, Likhi, and Aniam. </verse>
    <verse num="20">The sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah and Bered his son, Tahath his son, Eleadah his son, Tahath his son,</verse>
    <verse num="21">Zabad his son, Shuthelah his son, and Ezer and Elead. And the men of Gath who were born in the land killed them because they came down to take their livestock.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brothers came to comfort him.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Ephraim went in to his wife, and she conceived and gave birth to a son. And he called his name Beriah because disaster <transChange type="added">had been</transChange> upon his house.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And his daughter <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Sheerah, and she built Lower and Upper Beth-Horon and Uzzen-Sheerah.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And Rephah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, Tahan his son,</verse>
    <verse num="26">Ladan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Nun his son, Joshua his son.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And their property and their dwellings <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Bethel and {its towns}.<note>Literally "her daughters," here and below</note> And to the east, Naaran. And to the west, Gezer and its towns, and Shechem and its towns, up to Aija and its towns.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And along the borders of the sons of Manasseh: Beth-Shean and its towns, Taanach and its towns, Megiddo and its towns, and Dor and its towns. In these lived the sons of Joseph the son of Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="30">The sons of Asher: Imnah, Ishvah, Ishvi, Beriah, and their sister Serah.</verse>
    <verse num="31">The sons of Beriah: Heber and Malkiel, who <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the father of Birzayith.<note>According to the reading tradition (Qere)</note></verse>
    <verse num="32">And Heber fathered Japhlet, Shomer, Hotham, and their sister Shua.</verse>
    <verse num="33">The sons of Japhlet: Pasach, Bimhal, and Ashvath. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Japhlet.</verse>
    <verse num="34">The sons of Shemer: Ahi, Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.</verse>
    <verse num="35">The sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, Imna, Shelesh, and Amal.</verse>
    <verse num="36">The sons of Zophah: Suah, Harnepher, Shual, Beri, Imrah,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Bezer, Hod, Shamma, Shilshah, Ithran, and Beera.</verse>
    <verse num="38">The sons of Jether: Jephunneh, Pispah, and Ara.</verse>
    <verse num="39">The sons of Ulla: Arah, Hanniel, and Rizia.</verse>
    <verse num="40">All of these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Asher, heads of the house of the fathers, chosen mighty warriors, heads of the princes. And their number enrolled by genealogy, in the army for the war, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> twenty-six thousand men. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">Now Benjamin fathered Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, Aharah the third,</verse>
    <verse num="2">Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And Bela had sons: Addar, Gera, Abihud,</verse>
    <verse num="4">Abishua, Naaman, Ahoah,</verse>
    <verse num="5">Gera, Shephuphan, and Huram.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the sons of Ehud (these were heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> for the inhabitants of Geba, and they took them away to Manahath):</verse>
    <verse num="7">Naaman, Ahijah, and Gera, who took them away. And he fathered Uzza and Ahihud.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And Shaharaim fathered <transChange type="added">children</transChange> in the fields of Moab after he had sent them away--Hushim and Baara, his wives.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And he fathered by Hodesh his wife Jobab, Zibia, Mesha, Malcam,</verse>
    <verse num="10">Jeuz, Sakia, and Mirmah. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> his sons, heads of the {families}.<note>Literally "fathers"</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And by Husham he fathered Abitub and Elpaal.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The sons of Elpaal: Eber, Misham, Shemed (he built Ono and Lod with {its towns}),<note>Literally "her daughters"</note></verse>
    <verse num="13">and Beriah and Shema who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of the inhabitants of Aijalon (they themselves chased away the inhabitants of Gath).</verse>
    <verse num="14">Now Ahio, Shashak, Jeremoth,</verse>
    <verse num="15">Zebadiah, Arad, Eder,</verse>
    <verse num="16">Michael, Ishpah, and Joha <transChange type="added">were</transChange> sons of Beriah.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Zebadiah, Meshullam, Hizki, Heber,</verse>
    <verse num="18">Ishmerai, Izliah, and Jobab <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Elpaal.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Jakim, Zikri, Zabdi,</verse>
    <verse num="20">Elienai, Zillethai, Eliel,</verse>
    <verse num="21">Adaiah, Beraiah, and Shimrath <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Shimei.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Ishpan, Eber, Eliel,</verse>
    <verse num="23">Abdon, Zikri, Hanan,</verse>
    <verse num="24">Hananiah, Elam, Antothijah,</verse>
    <verse num="25">Iphdeiah, and Peniel <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Shashak.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And Shamsherai, Shehariah, Athaliah,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Jaareshiah, Elijah, and Zikri <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Jeroham.</verse>
    <verse num="28">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> according to their generations, chiefs. These lived in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And <transChange type="added">Jeiel</transChange><note>The name Jeiel comes from 1 Chronicles 9:35; it has dropped out of the text here</note> the father of Gibeon lived in Gibeon. And the name of his wife <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Maacah.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And his firstborn son <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Abdon, then Zur, Kish, Baal, Nadab,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Gedor, Ahio, Zeker,</verse>
    <verse num="32">and Mikloth (he fathered Shimeah). Now these also lived nearby their brothers in Jerusalem with their kinsmen.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And Ner fathered Kish, and Kish fathered Saul, and Saul fathered Jonathan, Malchi-Shua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</verse>
    <verse num="34">And the son of Jonathan <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Merib-baal, and Merib-baal fathered Micah.</verse>
    <verse num="35">And the sons of Micah: Pithon, Melech, Tarea, and Ahaz.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And Ahaz fathered Jehoaddah, and Jehoaddah fathered Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And Moza fathered Binea; Raphah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Eleasah his son, and Azel his son.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And Azel had six sons, and these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Azel.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And the sons of Eshek his brother: Ulam his firstborn, Jeush the second, and Eliphelet the third.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And the sons of Ulam were men <transChange type="added">who were</transChange> mighty warriors, bowmen, and <transChange type="added">they had</transChange> many sons and grandsons, one hundred and fifty. All these were Benjaminites. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">So all Israel was enrolled in genealogy. And behold, they were written in the book of the kings of Israel. And Judah was taken away to Babylon on account of their sin.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Now the first inhabitants who <transChange type="added">were settled</transChange> on their property in their cities <transChange type="added">in</transChange> Israel <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And some of the people of Judah, Benjamin, Ephraim, and Manasseh lived in Jerusalem:</verse>
    <verse num="4">Uthai the son of Ammihud, son of Omri, son of Imri, son of Bani,<note>According to the reading tradition (Qere)</note> from the sons of Perez,<note>According to the reading tradition (Qere)</note> the son of Judah.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And from the Shilonites: Asaiah the firstborn and his sons.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And from the sons of Zerah: Jeuel and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And from the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah;</verse>
    <verse num="8">Ibneah the son of Jeroham; Elah the son of Uzzi, son of Michri; Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, son of Reuel, son of Ibnijah;</verse>
    <verse num="9">and their brethren according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty-six. All these men <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> in the house of their fathers. </verse>
    <verse num="10">And from the priests: Jedaiah; Jehoiarib; Jakin;</verse>
    <verse num="11">Azariah son of Hilkiah, son of Meshullam, son of Zadok, son of Meraioth, son of Ahitub, the commander of the house of God;</verse>
    <verse num="12">Adaiah son of Jeroham, son of Pashhur, son of Malkijah; Maasai the son of Adiel, son of Jahzerah, son of Meshullam, son of Meshillemith, son of Immer;</verse>
    <verse num="13">and their kinsmen, heads of the house of their fathers, one thousand seven hundred and sixty mighty men <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the work of the service of the house of God. </verse>
    <verse num="14">And from the Levites: Shemaiah son of Hasshub, son of Azrikam, son of Hashabiah, from the sons of Merari;</verse>
    <verse num="15">Bakbakkar; Heresh; Galal; Mattaniah the son of Mica, son of Zicri, son of Asaph;</verse>
    <verse num="16">Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, son of Galal, son of Jeduthun; and Berechiah the son of Asa, son of Elkanah, who lived in the villages of Netophathite. </verse>
    <verse num="17">And the gatekeepers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Shallum, Akkub, Talmon, Ahiman, and their brethren (Shallum <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the chief);</verse>
    <verse num="18">until then they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> gatekeepers at the gate of the king on the east <transChange type="added">side</transChange> toward the camps of the Levites.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And Shallum the son of Kore, son of Ebiasaph, son of Korah, and his kinsmen of the house of his fathers, the Korahites, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the work of the service, the guardians of the entrances to the tent, and their fathers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the camp of Yahweh, guardians of the entrance.</verse>
    <verse num="20">And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was the leader over them {in time past};<note>Or "before"</note> Yahweh <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> gatekeeper at the doorway to the tent of assembly.<note>Or "meeting"</note></verse>
    <verse num="22">All of them were chosen as gatekeepers at the entrances, two hundred and twelve. They were enrolled by genealogies in their villages. They <transChange type="added">were</transChange> established <transChange type="added">by</transChange> David and Samuel the seer on account of their faithfulness.</verse>
    <verse num="23">So they and their sons <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the gates of the house of Yahweh at the house of the tent as guards.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The gatekeepers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on four sides: east, west, north, and south.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And their brethren in their villages <transChange type="added">were</transChange> to come <transChange type="added">every</transChange> seven days {by turn}<note>Literally "from time to time"</note> <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> with these.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For the four mighty gatekeepers, they who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Levites, {were entrusted}<note>Literally "they in their faithfulness"</note> and <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the chambers and over the storerooms of the house of God.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And they lodged all around the house of God, for upon them <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a responsibility. And {they had charge of opening <transChange type="added">the house of God</transChange> every morning}.<note>Literally "they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the key and to morning to morning"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="28">And some of them <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the utensils of the service, for {they count them}<note>Literally "in number"</note> <transChange type="added">when</transChange> they are brought in and {they count them}<note>Literally "in number"</note> <transChange type="added">when</transChange> they are brought out.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And some of them were appointed over the objects, over the objects of the sanctuary, and over the wheat flour and the wine, the olive oil, the frankincense, and the spices.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And some of the sons of the priests mixed the fragrant ointment for the spices.</verse>
    <verse num="31">And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite and {was entrusted}<note>Literally "in faithfulness"</note> with the work of the pan breads.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And from the sons of the Kohathites, some of their kinsmen <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the {showbread}<note>Literally "bread of the rows"</note> to prepare <transChange type="added">it</transChange> {every Sabbath}.<note>Literally "Sabbath Sabbath"</note> </verse>
    <verse num="33">Now these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the singers; the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of the Levites <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the chambers free from other service, for day and night <transChange type="added">they were</transChange> over them on the service.</verse>
    <verse num="34">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of the Levites according to their genealogies, leaders. These lived in Jerusalem. </verse>
    <verse num="35">And <transChange type="added">these</transChange> lived in Gibeon: Jeiel the father of Gibeon. And the name of his wife <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Maacah.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, Kish, Baal, Ner, Nadab,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Gedor, Ahio, Zechariah, and Mikloth.</verse>
    <verse num="38">And Mikloth fathered Shimeam. And they also lived nearby their brothers in Jerusalem with their brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And Ner fathered Kish, and Kish fathered Saul, and Saul fathered Jonathan, Malchi-Shua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And the son of Jonathan <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Meribaal. And Meribaal fathered Micah.</verse>
    <verse num="41">And the sons of Micah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Pithon, Melech, Tahrea, <transChange type="added">and Ahaz.</transChange><note>The name is drawn from 1 Chronicles 8:35; it has dropped out of the text here</note></verse>
    <verse num="42">And Ahaz fathered Jarah, and Jarah fathered Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza,</verse>
    <verse num="43">and Moza fathered Binea; and Rephaiah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.</verse>
    <verse num="44">And Azel had six sons, and these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Azel. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">Now the Philistines fought against Israel, and every Israelite fled away from before the Philistines. And they fell slain upon Mount Gilboa.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And the Philistines {overtook}<note>Literally "caught up behind"</note> Saul and his sons. And the Philistines killed Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malki-Shua, the sons of Saul.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the battle was heavy against Saul, and the {archers}<note>Literally "shooters with the bow"</note> found him, and he was wounded by the {archers}.<note>Literally "shooters"</note></verse>
    <verse num="4">And Saul said to his armor-bearer, "Draw your sword and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and deal harshly with me." But he was very afraid. Then Saul took the sword and fell upon it.</verse>
    <verse num="5">When his armor-bearer saw that Saul <transChange type="added">was</transChange> dead, he also fell upon the sword, and he died.</verse>
    <verse num="6">So Saul died. And his three sons and all his house died together.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And when all the men of Israel who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the valley saw that they<note>That is, the army</note> had fled and that Saul and his sons were dead, they abandoned their cities and fled. Then the Philistines came and dwelled in them.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> on the next day when the Philistines came to strip the dead, they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gilboa.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And they stripped him and took his head and his weapons, and they sent <transChange type="added">them</transChange> throughout the land of the Philistines to bring news to their idols and the nation.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And they put his weapons in the temple of their gods, and they fastened his skull to the temple of Dagon.</verse>
    <verse num="11">When all Jabesh-Gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul,</verse>
    <verse num="12">every strong man arose and took the dead body of Saul and the dead bodies of his sons and brought them to Jabesh. And they buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh and fasted seven days.</verse>
    <verse num="13">So Saul died on account of his sin which he had sinned against Yahweh concerning the command of Yahweh that he did not keep. He also consulted a medium to seek <transChange type="added">guidance</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But he did not seek Yahweh. So Yahweh put him to death and turned over the kingship to David, the son of Jesse. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">Then all Israel gathered to David in Hebron, saying, "Look--we are your flesh and bones.</verse>
    <verse num="2">{For some time now},<note>Literally "also yesterday also in the past"</note> even when Saul was king, you were {the one who led the army of Israel in battle}.<note>Literally "the one who went out and brought in Israel"</note> And Yahweh your God said to you, 'You will shepherd my people Israel and will be leader over my people Israel.'"</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then all the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and David made a covenant with them at Hebron in the presence of Yahweh. And they anointed David as king over Israel according to the word of Yahweh by the hand of Samuel.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Jebus). And the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> there.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, "You will not enter here." But David captured the stronghold of Zion; that <transChange type="added">is,</transChange> the city of David.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then David said, "Whoever strikes the Jebusites first will be chief and commander." And Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first and became chief.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And David lived in the fortress. Therefore they called it the city of David.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And he built the city all around from the Millo and up to the circuit. And Joab restored the remainder of the city.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And David {became greater and greater}.<note>Literally "increased certainly and <transChange type="added">in</transChange> greatness"</note> And Yahweh of hosts <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with him. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the chiefs of the mighty men who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> for David, who gave him strong support in his kingdom, together with all Israel to make him king according to the word of Yahweh concerning Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And this <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the numbering of the mighty warriors who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> for David: Jashobeam son of Hachmoni <transChange type="added">was</transChange> chief of the three. He himself raised his spear against three hundred <transChange type="added">whom he</transChange> killed on one occasion. </verse>
    <verse num="12">And after him <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Eleazar son of Dodo the Ahohite. He <transChange type="added">was</transChange> among the three mighty warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="13">He himself <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with David at Pas-Dammim when the Philistines were gathered there for the battle. And there was a plot of the field filled with barley, and the people fled before the Philistines.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But they took their stand in the middle of the plot and defended it. And they killed the Philistines. And Yahweh saved <transChange type="added">them</transChange> <transChange type="added">with</transChange> a great victory. </verse>
    <verse num="15">And three of the thirty chiefs went down toward the rock to David at the cave of Adullam when the army of the Philistines was encamped in the valley of Rephaim.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And David <transChange type="added">was</transChange> then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines <transChange type="added">was</transChange> then in Bethlehem.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And David had a craving, and he said, "Who could give me a drink of water from the well of Bethlehem that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> by the gate!"</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then the three broke through into the camp of the Philistines and drew water from the well of Bethlehem that <transChange type="added">was</transChange> by the gate and brought <transChange type="added">it</transChange> and came to David. But David would not drink it and poured it out before Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And he said, "Far be it from me <transChange type="added">that</transChange> I would do this before my God. Shall I drink the lifeblood of these men? For {at the risk of their lives}<note>Literally "against their lives"</note> they brought it." And he was not willing to drink it. These things the three mighty men did. </verse>
    <verse num="20">Now Abishai the brother of Joab was himself the head of the three.<note>Other manuscripts have "thirty" which makes better sense in the context</note> And he roused himself with his spear against three hundred <transChange type="added">whom he</transChange> killed and <transChange type="added">made</transChange> a name for himself<note>According to the reading tradition (Qere)</note> among the three.</verse>
    <verse num="21">{He was twice as renowned}<note>Literally "he was glorified double"</note> among the three<note>Other manuscripts have "thirty," which makes better sense in the context</note> and was their commander. But he did not attain to the three.</verse>
    <verse num="22"><transChange type="added">And</transChange> Benaiah the son of Jehoiada <transChange type="added">was</transChange> {a strong man}<note>Literally "a son of a strong man"</note> from Kabzeel, <transChange type="added">one who did</transChange> great deeds. He himself struck down two <transChange type="added">sons of</transChange> Ariel of Moab. And he himself went down and struck down a lion within a pit on a snowy day.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And he himself struck down an Egyptian man, a large man five cubits <transChange type="added">tall</transChange>. And in the hand of the Egyptian <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a spear like a weaver's beam. But he went down to him with a club and seized the spear from the hand of the Egyptian and killed him with his own spear.</verse>
    <verse num="24">These things Benaiah son of Jehoiada did and had a name among the three mighty warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="25">He himself was certainly distinguished among the thirty, but he did not attain to the three. And David appointed him over his bodyguard. </verse>
    <verse num="26">Now the mighty warriors of the troops <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo from Bethlehem,</verse>
    <verse num="27">Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite,</verse>
    <verse num="28">Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite,</verse>
    <verse num="29">Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite,</verse>
    <verse num="30">Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite,</verse>
    <verse num="31">Ittai the son of Ribai from Gibeah of the people of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite,</verse>
    <verse num="32">Hurai of the valleys of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite,</verse>
    <verse num="33">Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite,</verse>
    <verse num="34">the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jehonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite,</verse>
    <verse num="35">Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur,</verse>
    <verse num="36">Hepher the Mekerathite, Ahijah the Pelonite,</verse>
    <verse num="37">Hezro the Carmelite, Naari the son of Ezbai,</verse>
    <verse num="38">Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri,</verse>
    <verse num="39">Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, the bearer of the weapons of Joab the son of Zeruiah,</verse>
    <verse num="40">Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,</verse>
    <verse num="41">Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai,</verse>
    <verse num="42">Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a leader of the Reubenites, and thirty with him,</verse>
    <verse num="43">Hanan the son of Maacah, Jehoshaphat the Mithnite,</verse>
    <verse num="44">Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite,</verse>
    <verse num="45">Jediael the son of Shimri and Joha his brother the Tizite,</verse>
    <verse num="46">Eliel the Mahavite, Jeribai and Joshaviah the sons of Elnaam, Ithmah the Moabite,</verse>
    <verse num="47">Eliel, Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">Now these are the ones who came to David at Ziklag while he was still shut up because {of Saul},<note>Literally "of the face of Saul"</note> the son of Kish. And they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the mighty warriors helping <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the war.</verse>
    <verse num="2"><transChange type="added">They were</transChange> armed with <transChange type="added">the</transChange> bow, <transChange type="added">able to shoot</transChange> right-handed or left-handed, <transChange type="added">slinging</transChange> stones or <transChange type="added">shooting</transChange> arrows with the bow; <transChange type="added">they were</transChange> kinsmen of Saul from Benjamin.</verse>
    <verse num="3">The leader <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ahiezer, then Jehoash, sons of Shemaah the Gibeonite; Jeiel and Pelet, sons of Azmaveth; Beracah; Jehu the Anathothite;</verse>
    <verse num="4">Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty warrior among the thirty <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> over the thirty;<note>1 Chronicles 12:5 begins here in the Hebrew Bible</note> Jeremiah; Jahaziel; Johanan; Jozabad the Gederathite;</verse>
    <verse num="5"><note>1 Chronicles 12:5-40 in the English Bible is 12:6-41 in the Hebrew Bible</note> Eluzai; Jerimoth; Bealiah; Shemariah; Shephatiah the Hariphite;</verse>
    <verse num="6">Elkanah, Isshiah, Azarel, Joezer, and Jashobeam the Korahites;</verse>
    <verse num="7">Joelah and Zebadiah, sons of Jeroham from the Gedor. </verse>
    <verse num="8">And from the Gadites, valiant mighty warriors, {soldiers fit for war},<note>Literally "men of battle for the war"</note> expert with shield and spear, defected to David at the fortress toward the wilderness. And {they had faces like lions}<note>Literally "faces of a lion <transChange type="added">were</transChange> their faces"</note> <transChange type="added">and were</transChange> swift as gazelles upon the mountains.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Ezer the chief, Obadiah second, Eliab third,</verse>
    <verse num="10">Mishmannah fourth, Jeremiah fifth,</verse>
    <verse num="11">Attai sixth, Eliel seventh,</verse>
    <verse num="12">Jehonan eighth, Elzabad ninth,</verse>
    <verse num="13">Jeremiah tenth, Macbannai eleventh.</verse>
    <verse num="14">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Gad, leaders of the army. The smallest one <transChange type="added">was</transChange> as a hundred, and the greatest as a thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="15">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> they who crossed the Jordan in the first month, when it was filled over its banks. And they put to flight all <transChange type="added">who were in</transChange> the valley to the east and to the west. </verse>
    <verse num="16">And some of the sons of Benjamin and <transChange type="added">from</transChange> Judah came to the fortress, to David.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And David went out {to meet them}<note>Literally "before them"</note> and answered and said to them, "If you come in peace to me, to help me, {my heart will be joined with you},<note>Literally "the heart will be to me to you together"</note> but if <transChange type="added">you come</transChange> to betray me to my adversaries, although <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> no wrong on my hands, may the God of our fathers see and pass judgment."</verse>
    <verse num="18">Then the Spirit came upon Amasai, chief of the thirty <transChange type="added">who said</transChange>: </verse>
    <verse num="19">And some Manassites deserted to David when he came with the Philistines to the battle against Saul, but he did not help them, for the rulers of the Philistines sent him away upon counsel, saying, "He will desert to his master Saul at <transChange type="added">the cost of</transChange> our heads."</verse>
    <verse num="20">When he went to Ziklag some Manassites deserted to him: Adnah, Jehozabad, Jediael, Michael, Jozabad, Elihu, and Zillethai, heads of the thousands that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> for Manasseh.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And they themselves helped David against the troops, for all of them <transChange type="added">were</transChange> mighty men of strength and were commanders in the army.</verse>
    <verse num="22">{Day in and day out}<note>Literally "for to the time of day to the day"</note> they came to David to help him until <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> a great army, like the army of God. </verse>
    <verse num="23">And these are the numbers of the chiefs of those prepared for the army who came to David at Hebron to turn the kingdom of Saul over to him according to the word of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The sons of Judah bearing shield and spear: six thousand eight hundred armed troops.</verse>
    <verse num="25">From the men of Simeon, mighty warriors of strength for war: seven thousand one hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="26">From the Levites: four thousand six hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Jehoiada the chief officer of <transChange type="added">the house of</transChange> Aaron, and with him, three thousand seven hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And Zadok, a young man, a mighty warrior of strength, and the house of his father: twenty-two commanders.</verse>
    <verse num="29">From the men of Benjamin, kinsmen of Saul, three thousand, and {even still}<note>Literally "and even they"</note> the majority of them {remained loyal}<note>Literally "keeping the responsibility"</note> to the house of Saul.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And from the men of Ephraim: twenty thousand eight hundred mighty warriors of strength, famous men in the house of their fathers.</verse>
    <verse num="31">And from the half-tribe of Manasseh: eighteen thousand who were designated by name to come to make David king.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And from the men of Issachar: {men who were skilled in understanding the times}<note>Literally "men who knew the understanding of the times"</note> to know what Israel should do. Their chiefs <transChange type="added">were</transChange> two hundred, and all their kinsmen <transChange type="added">were</transChange> under their command.</verse>
    <verse num="33">From Zebulun, those who went out armed, equipped for battle with all the weapons of war: fifty thousand to help David {with singleness of purpose}.<note>Literally "with not heart and heart"</note></verse>
    <verse num="34">From Naphtali: one thousand commanders; and <transChange type="added">those</transChange> with them with shield and spear: thirty-seven thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="35">From the Danites, <transChange type="added">those</transChange> equipped for battle: twenty-eight thousand six hundred.</verse>
    <verse num="36">And from Asher, those who went out armed <transChange type="added">and</transChange> prepared for battle: forty thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="37">And from beyond the Jordan, from the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh, with all <transChange type="added">their</transChange> weapons of war for battle: one hundred and twenty thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="38">All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> men of war arrayed in battle line {with a whole heart}.<note>Literally "with heart well"</note> They came to Hebron to make David king over all Israel. Likewise, all the rest of Israel <transChange type="added">had</transChange> one heart to make David king.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And they were there with David three days, eating and drinking, for their kinsmen were prepared for them.</verse>
    <verse num="40">And also their relatives, as far as Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought food on donkeys, on camels, on mules, and on oxen--provisions of flour, cakes of figs, raisin cakes, wine and oil, cattle and sheep in abundance, for <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> great joy in Israel. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">And David consulted with the commanders of thousands and hundreds, with every leader.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And David said to all the assembly of Israel, "{If it seems good to you}<note>Literally "If to you good"</note> and before Yahweh our God, {let us send word abroad}<note>Literally "let us spread out, let us send"</note> to our brothers who remain in all the land of Israel and <transChange type="added">to</transChange> the priests and Levites with them in the cities with their pasturelands that they might be gathered to us.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Then let us bring around the ark of our God to us, for we did not seek it in the days of Saul."</verse>
    <verse num="4">And all the assembly agreed to do so, for the word was pleasing in the eyes of all the people. </verse>
    <verse num="5">And David summoned all Israel from Shihor of Egypt up to Lebo-Hamath to bring the ark of God from Kiriath-Jearim.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And David and all Israel went up to Baalah, Kiriath-Jearim of Judah, to bring up from there the ark of Yahweh God <transChange type="added">who</transChange> is enthroned <transChange type="added">between</transChange> the cherubim, which is called the name.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And they carried the ark of God upon a new cart from the house of Abinadab, and Uzza and Ahio were driving the cart. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Now David and all Israel were celebrating before God with all <transChange type="added">their</transChange> strength, and with songs, lyres, harps, tambourines, cymbals, and trumpets.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And when they came to the threshing floor of Kidon, Uzza reached out his hand to hold the ark because the cattle had stumbled.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Yahweh {was angry}<note>Literally "nostrils became hot"</note> with Uzza, and he struck him down because he reached his hand upon the ark. And he died there before God.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And David {was angry}<note>Literally "it was hot"</note> because Yahweh had broken out in wrath against Uzza. And that place is called Perez Uzza unto this day.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And David feared God on that day, saying, "How can I bring the ark of God <transChange type="added">home</transChange> to me?"</verse>
    <verse num="13">So David did not move the ark to himself into the city of David but diverted it to the house of Obed-Edom the Gittite.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And the ark of God remained with the household of Obed-Edom in his house three months. And Yahweh blessed the household of Obed-Edom and all that he had. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">And Hiram, king of Tyre, sent messengers to David and cedar trees, {masons},<note>Literally "craftsmen of the wall"</note> and {carpenters}<note>Literally "craftsmen of wood"</note> to build a house for him.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And David knew that Yahweh had established him as king over Israel <transChange type="added">and</transChange> that his kingdom was highly exalted for the sake of his people Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And David took more wives in Jerusalem, and David fathered more sons and daughters.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Now these <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the names of the children who were <transChange type="added">born</transChange> to him in Jerusalem: Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon,</verse>
    <verse num="5">Ibhar, Elishua, Elpelet,</verse>
    <verse num="6">Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia,</verse>
    <verse num="7">Elishama, Beeliada, and Eliphelet. </verse>
    <verse num="8">When the Philistines heard that David had been anointed as king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to search for David. But David heard and went out from before them.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Now the Philistines came and carried out a raid in the Valley of Rephaim.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Then David inquired of God, saying, "Shall I go up against the Philistines? Will you put them into my hand?" And Yahweh said to him, "Go up. I will put them into your hand."</verse>
    <verse num="11">And he went up to Baal-Perazim, and David struck them there. And David said, "God has burst out against my enemies by my hand like waters burst out." Therefore they will call the name of this place Baal-Perazim.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And they abandoned their gods there. And David commanded, and they were burnt with fire.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then the Philistines {carried out another raid}<note>Literally "they added again and made a raid"</note> in the valley.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Then David inquired again of God. And God said to him, "You shall not go up after them. Go around from before them and come against them the opposite <transChange type="added">way</transChange> of the balsam trees.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And it shall be <transChange type="added">that</transChange> when you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the balsam trees, then go out into battle, for God goes out before you to strike the camp of the Philistines."</verse>
    <verse num="16">And David did as God commanded him, and they struck the camp of the Philistines from Gibeon to Gezer.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the fame of David went out through all the lands. And Yahweh put the fear of him upon all the nations. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">And David built houses for himself in the city of David, and he established a place for the ark of God. And he pitched a tent for it.</verse>
    <verse num="2">Then David ordered <transChange type="added">that</transChange> none except the Levites should carry the ark of God, for Yahweh had chosen them to carry the ark of Yahweh and to serve him forever.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And David gathered all Israel to Jerusalem to bring up the ark of Yahweh to its place that he had established for it.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And David gathered the sons of Aaron and the Levites.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Of the sons of Kohath: Uriel the chief and one hundred and twenty of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Of the sons of Merari: Asaiah the chief and two hundred and twenty of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Of the sons of Gershom: Joel the chief and one hundred and thirty of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Of the sons of Elizaphan: Shemaiah the chief and two hundred of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Of the sons of Hebron: Eliel the chief and eighty of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Of the sons of Uzziel: Amminadab the chief and one hundred and twelve of his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="11">Then David summoned Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and the Levites Uriel, Asaiah, Joel, Shemaiah, Eliel, and Amminadab.</verse>
    <verse num="12">And he said to them, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> for the Levites. Sanctify yourselves and your brothers and bring up the ark of Yahweh, the God of Israel, to <transChange type="added">the place</transChange> I have established for it.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Because the first time you did not, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> Yahweh our God burst out against us, for we did not care for it according to the law."</verse>
    <verse num="14">Then the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of Yahweh, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And the sons of the Levites carried the ark of God according to what Moses commanded, according to the word of Yahweh, on their shoulders with the carrying poles upon them. </verse>
    <verse num="16">Then David ordered the chiefs of the Levites to appoint their brothers <transChange type="added">as</transChange> singers with instruments of song, musical instruments, stringed instruments, and cymbals, {raising their voices for joy}.<note>Literally "causing to hear to the mountains with a sound of rejoicing"</note></verse>
    <verse num="17">So the Levites appointed Heman son of Joel, and from his brothers, Asaph the son of Berekiah, and from the sons of Merari, their brothers, Ethan the son of Kushaiah;</verse>
    <verse num="18">and with them their brothers <transChange type="added">of</transChange> the second <transChange type="added">rank</transChange>, Zechariah the son, Jaaziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattithiah, Eliphelehu, Mikneiah, and the gatekeepers Obed-Edom and Jeiel.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Now the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> to sound bronze cymbals;</verse>
    <verse num="20">Zechariah, Aziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Maaseiah, and Benaiah <transChange type="added">were to play</transChange> on harps according to Alamoth;</verse>
    <verse num="21">and Mattithiah, Eliphelehu, Mikneiah, Obed-Edom, Jeiel, and Azaziah <transChange type="added">were to play</transChange> lyres, directing according to the Sheminith.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Kenaniah, chief of the Levites in singing, <transChange type="added">was to be</transChange> an instructor in singing because he understood.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Berekiah and Elkanah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> gatekeepers for the ark.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And Shebaniah, Jehoshaphat, Nethanel, Amasai, Zechariah, Benaiah, and Elizezer the priests {sounded the trumpets}<note>Literally "trumpet blowers with trumpets"</note> before the ark of God. And Obed-Edom and Jehiah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> gatekeepers for the ark. </verse>
    <verse num="25">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> David and the elders of Israel and the commanders of thousands went to bring up the ark of the covenant of Yahweh from the house of Obed-Edom with joy.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> when God helped the Levites carrying the ark of the covenant of Yahweh, they sacrificed seven bulls and seven rams.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Now David was clothed with a robe of fine linen; so also all the Levites who were carrying the ark, the singers, and Kenaniah the chief of the singing. And David wore a linen ephod.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of Yahweh with shouting, with the sound of a shofar,<note>Or "horn, trumpet"</note> and with trumpets and cymbals, making loud music with musical instruments and stringed instruments. </verse>
    <verse num="29">And when the ark of the covenant of Yahweh came into the city of David, then Michal the daughter of Saul looked down from the window and saw the king, David, leaping and dancing. And she despised him in her heart. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">And they brought the ark of God and set it inside the tent that David had pitched for it. And they offered burnt offerings and fellowship offerings before God.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And when David had finished offering the burnt offerings and fellowship offerings, he blessed the people in the name of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And he distributed to every man of Israel, both men and women, to each <transChange type="added">person</transChange> a loaf of bread, a cake of dates, and a cake of raisins.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Then he appointed some of the Levites as ministers before the ark of Yahweh, to invoke, thank, and praise Yahweh the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Asaph <transChange type="added">was</transChange> chief, and his second <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Zechariah; Jeiel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Mattithiah, Eliab, Benaiah, Obed-Edom, and Jeiel <transChange type="added">were</transChange> on harps and lyres. And Asaph played on the cymbals.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests <transChange type="added">blew</transChange> on the trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God.</verse>
    <verse num="7">Then on that day David first appointed to give thanks to Yahweh by the hand of Asaph and his brothers. </verse>
    <verse num="8">Give thanks to Yahweh; call upon his name; make known his deeds among the nations!</verse>
    <verse num="9">Sing to him; sing praises to him; tell of his wondrous works!</verse>
    <verse num="10">Glory in his holy name; let the hearts of those seeking Yahweh rejoice!</verse>
    <verse num="11">Seek Yahweh and his strength; seek his face continually!</verse>
    <verse num="12">Remember his wonderful works that he has done, his wonders and the judgments of his mouth,</verse>
    <verse num="13">O offspring of Israel, his servant, O sons of Jacob, his chosen ones!</verse>
    <verse num="14">He <transChange type="added">is</transChange> Yahweh our God; his judgments <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in all the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="15">Remember his covenant forever, the word he commanded for a thousand generations,</verse>
    <verse num="16">that he {made}<note>Literally "cut"</note> with Abraham, his sworn oath to Isaac.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And he confirmed it to Jacob as a statute, an everlasting covenant to Israel,</verse>
    <verse num="18">saying, "To you I will give the land of Canaan, the portion of your inheritance."</verse>
    <verse num="19">When you were few in number, little, and sojourners <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it,</verse>
    <verse num="20">when they wandered from nation to nation, and from one kingdom to another people,</verse>
    <verse num="21">he did not allow anyone to oppress them, and he rebuked kings on their account,</verse>
    <verse num="22"><transChange type="added">saying,</transChange> "You must not touch my anointed nor do harm to my prophets!"</verse>
    <verse num="23">Sing to Yahweh, all the earth! Proclaim his salvation from day to day!</verse>
    <verse num="24">Proclaim his glory among the nations, his wondrous works among the peoples!</verse>
    <verse num="25">For Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> great and greatly praised, and he is feared among all gods.</verse>
    <verse num="26">For all the gods of the nations <transChange type="added">are</transChange> idols, but Yahweh made the heavens.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Splendor and majesty <transChange type="added">are</transChange> before him; strength and joy <transChange type="added">are</transChange> in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Ascribe to Yahweh, O clans of the nations, ascribe to Yahweh glory and strength!</verse>
    <verse num="29">Ascribe to Yahweh the glory of his name! Lift up an offering and come before him! Bow down to Yahweh in the splendor of holiness!</verse>
    <verse num="30">Tremble before him, all the earth; surely the world shall not be shaken.</verse>
    <verse num="31">Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be glad, and let them tell the peoples, "Yahweh reigns!"</verse>
    <verse num="32">Let the sea roar and its fullness; let the field rejoice and all that <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in it.</verse>
    <verse num="33">Then the trees of the forest shall sing for joy before Yahweh, for he comes to judge the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="34">Oh give thanks to Yahweh, for he <transChange type="added">is</transChange> good; his loyal love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> everlasting.</verse>
    <verse num="35">Then say, "Save us, O God of our salvation; gather us and rescue us from the nations that <transChange type="added">we may</transChange> give thanks to your holy name <transChange type="added">and</transChange> glory in your praise.</verse>
    <verse num="36">Blessed be Yahweh the God of Israel, from everlasting to everlasting!"</verse>
    <verse num="37">So he<note>That is, David</note> left Asaph and his brothers there before the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to minister before the ark regularly {as each day required},<note>Literally "according to the word of a day with respect to its day"</note></verse>
    <verse num="38">and <transChange type="added">he left</transChange> Obed-Edom with his sixty-eight brothers. And Obed-Edom, the son of Jeduthun, and Hosah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> gatekeepers.</verse>
    <verse num="39">And <transChange type="added">he left</transChange> Zadok the priest and his brothers the priests before the tabernacle of Yahweh at the high place which <transChange type="added">was</transChange> at Gibeon</verse>
    <verse num="40">to offer burnt offerings regularly to Yahweh on the altar of burnt offering, morning and evening, according to all that was written in the law of Yahweh that he commanded concerning Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="41">And with them <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Heman and Jeduthun and the remainder of those chosen, who were designated by name to give thanks to Yahweh, for his loyal love <transChange type="added">is</transChange> everlasting.</verse>
    <verse num="42">And Heman and Jeduthun with them <transChange type="added">had</transChange> trumpets and cymbals for making music, along with instruments for the song of God. And the sons of Jeduthun <transChange type="added">were</transChange> at the gate.</verse>
    <verse num="43">Then all the people went each to his house, and David turned to bless his household. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">And as David lived in his house, David said to Nathan the prophet, "Look, I live in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of Yahweh <transChange type="added">is</transChange> under tent curtains."</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Nathan said to David, "Whatever <transChange type="added">is</transChange> in your heart, do, for God <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with you." </verse>
    <verse num="3">And it happened that same night the word of God came to Nathan, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="4">"Go and say to David my servant, 'Thus says Yahweh, "You <transChange type="added">are</transChange> not to build a house for me to live <transChange type="added">in</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="5">for I have not lived in a house from the day that I brought out Israel unto this day. I have been from tent to tent and from tabernacle <transChange type="added">to tabernacle</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="6">In every <transChange type="added">place</transChange> I have moved about, did I say one word <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the judges of Israel I commanded to shepherd my people, saying, 'Why have you not built for me a house of cedar?'" '</verse>
    <verse num="7">So now, thus you shall say to my servant David, 'Thus says Yahweh of hosts, "I took you from the pasture, from following the sheep, to be leader over my people Israel,</verse>
    <verse num="8">and I have been with you wherever you went and have cut down your enemies from before you and will make a name for you, like the name of the great ones on the earth.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and I will plant them,<note>Or "him" (i.e., the nation)</note> and they<note>Or "he"</note> shall dwell in their<note>Or "his"</note> place and be in anguish no longer. And wicked men will no longer wear them down as before,</verse>
    <verse num="10">from the day that I commanded judges over my people Israel. And I will subdue your enemies, and I declare to you <transChange type="added">that</transChange> Yahweh will build for you a house.<note>Or "household" (that is, a dynasty)</note></verse>
    <verse num="11">And it shall be that when your days are fulfilled to go <transChange type="added">and sleep</transChange> with your ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> then I will raise up your seed after you, who will be one of your sons, and I will establish his kingdom.</verse>
    <verse num="12">He himself will build for me a house, and I will establish his throne forever.</verse>
    <verse num="13">I myself will be a father to him, and he himself will be a son to me. And I will not remove my steadfast love from him as I took it away from whoever was before you.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And I will establish him in my house and in my kingdom forever, and his throne will be established forever." '"</verse>
    <verse num="15">According to all these words and according to all this revelation, thus did Nathan speak to David. </verse>
    <verse num="16">Then King David went and sat before Yahweh and said, "Who <transChange type="added">am</transChange> I, O Yahweh God, and what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> my house that you have brought me thus far?</verse>
    <verse num="17">And this was a small <transChange type="added">matter</transChange> in your eyes, O God. And you have spoken concerning the house of your servant for a long <transChange type="added">time</transChange> and have shown me {future generations to come},<note>Literally "with a turn of humankind ascending"</note> O Yahweh God.</verse>
    <verse num="18">{What more}<note>Literally "What to add again"</note> can David <transChange type="added">do</transChange> to you for honoring your servant? Now you know your servant.</verse>
    <verse num="19">O Yahweh, for the sake of your servant and according to your heart you have done all this greatness, to make known all <transChange type="added">these</transChange> great things.</verse>
    <verse num="20">O Yahweh, there is none like you, and there is no God except you, according to all that we have heard with our ears.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And who <transChange type="added">is</transChange> like your people Israel, <transChange type="added">the</transChange> one nation upon earth whom God went to redeem for himself, to establish for you a reputation<note>Or "name"</note> for great and awesome things, to drive out nations from before your people whom you redeemed from Egypt?</verse>
    <verse num="22">And you made your people Israel an everlasting nation for yourself. And you, O Yahweh, became their God.</verse>
    <verse num="23">So now, O Yahweh, let the word that you spoke to your servant and to his house be established forever, that you might do what you have spoken.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And let your name be established and be magnified forever, saying, 'Yahweh of hosts, the God of Israel, is Israel's God, and may the house of David your servant be established before you.'</verse>
    <verse num="25">For you, my God, {have informed}<note>Literally "have opened the ear of"</note> your servant <transChange type="added">that</transChange> you will build a house for him. Therefore, your servant has found <transChange type="added">courage</transChange> to pray before you.</verse>
    <verse num="26">So now, O Yahweh, you yourself <transChange type="added">are</transChange> God, and you have spoken to your servant this good thing.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And now may you begin to bless the house of your servant {to continue forever}<note>Literally "to be forever"</note> before you, for you, O Yahweh, have blessed. And it will be blessed forever." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> after David struck the Philistines and subdued them, he captured Gath and its villages out of the hand of the Philistines.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he struck Moab, and the Moabites became servants to David, bearing tribute.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And David struck Hadadezer, king of Zobah-Hamath, as he set up his monument at the Euphrates River.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And David captured from him one thousand chariots, seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand foot soldiers. And David hamstrung all the chariot horses but left one hundred of them <transChange type="added">to</transChange> remain <transChange type="added">for</transChange> chariots.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And when the Arameans of Damascus came to help Hadadezer king of Zobah-Hamath, David struck down twenty-two thousand men of Aram.</verse>
    <verse num="6">Then David set up <transChange type="added">garrisons</transChange> in Aram of Damascus, and the Arameans became servants to David, bearing tribute. And Yahweh delivered David wherever he went.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And David took small round shields of gold that were upon the servants of Hadadezer and brought them <transChange type="added">to</transChange> Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And from Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadadezer, David captured very much bronze. Solomon made the bronze sea with it along with the columns and objects of bronze. </verse>
    <verse num="9">And when Tou the king of Hamath heard that David had defeated the whole army of Hadadezer the king of Zobah,</verse>
    <verse num="10">he sent Hadoram his son to King David to ask him for peace and to bless him because he had fought against Hadadezer and defeated him, for Tou {had been at war}<note>Literally "a man of battles"</note> with Hadadezer. And <transChange type="added">he brought with him</transChange> all the objects of gold, silver, and bronze.</verse>
    <verse num="11">King David dedicated these also to Yahweh, along with the silver and gold that he had taken from all the nations, from Edom, Moab, the sons of Ammon, the Philistines, and Amalek. </verse>
    <verse num="12">And Abishai son of Zeruiah defeated eighteen thousand of Edom in the Valley of Salt.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And he put garrisons in Edom, and all Edom became servants to David. And Yahweh delivered David wherever he went. </verse>
    <verse num="14">So David reigned over all Israel, and {he administered justice}<note>Literally "he was a doer of justice"</note> and righteousness to all his people.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And Joab son of Zeruiah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> over the army, and Jehoshaphat son of Ahilud <transChange type="added">was</transChange> recorder.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And Zadok son of Ahitub and Abimelech son of Abiathar <transChange type="added">were</transChange> priests, and Shavsha <transChange type="added">was</transChange> secretary.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And Benaiah son of Jehoiada <transChange type="added">was</transChange> over the Kerethites and the Pelethites. And the sons of David <transChange type="added">were</transChange> chief officials under the hand of the king. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> after this Nahash the king of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> died, and his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And David said, "I will deal kindly with Hanun the son of Nahash because his father showed kindness to me." So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And the servants of David came to the land of the {Ammonites},<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> to Hanun, to comfort him.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But the princes of the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> said to Hanun, "{Do you think}<note>Literally "In your eyes"</note> because David sent comforters to you <transChange type="added">that</transChange> David honors your father? Is it not for the purpose of exploring <transChange type="added">so as</transChange> to overthrow and spy out the land that his servants have come to you?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">So Hanun took the servants of David and shaved them and cut off their garments at the middle, up to the buttocks, and sent them away.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And they went and told David concerning the men, and he inquired of them, for the men were very disgraced. And the king said, "Dwell in Jericho until your beards grow out; then return." </verse>
    <verse num="6">And when the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> saw that they made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> sent one thousand talents of silver to hire for themselves horses and chariots from Aram-Naharaim, Aram-Maacah, and Zobah.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And they hired for themselves thirty-two thousand chariots and the king of Maacah and his people, and they came and encamped before Medeba. And the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> were gathered from their cities and came to the battle.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And when David heard, he sent Joab and the entire army of mighty warriors.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> went out and took up positions for battle at the entrance of the city. And the kings who had come <transChange type="added">were</transChange> alone in the field. </verse>
    <verse num="10">When Joab saw that <transChange type="added">there was</transChange> {a battle line}<note>Literally "the face of the battle"</note> against him at the front and the back, he chose from among the chosen <transChange type="added">men</transChange> in Israel and arranged <transChange type="added">them</transChange> to meet Aram.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And the remainder of the people he put in the hand of Abishai his brother, and they were arranged to meet the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note></verse>
    <verse num="12">And he said, "If Aram is too strong for me, then you must be a help to me, but if the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> are too strong for you, then I will help you.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Be strong! Let us strengthen ourselves on behalf of our people and on behalf of the cities of our God. And may Yahweh do <transChange type="added">what is</transChange> good in his eyes."</verse>
    <verse num="14">And Joab and the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> with him drew near before Aram for battle, and they fled before him.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And when the {Ammonites}<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> saw that Aram had fled, they also fled before Abishai his brother, and they came to the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem. </verse>
    <verse num="16">And when Aram saw that they were defeated before Israel, they sent messengers and brought out Aram, who <transChange type="added">was from</transChange> beyond the Euphrates,<note>Or "the river"</note> with Shophach the commander of the army of Hadadezer before them.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And when it was told to David, he gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan. And he came to them and was arrayed against them. Then David was arrayed to meet Aram in battle, and they fought with him.</verse>
    <verse num="18">And Aram fled before Israel. And David killed from Aram <transChange type="added">the men of</transChange> seven thousand chariots and forty thousand foot soldiers, and he put to death Shophach the commander of the army.</verse>
    <verse num="19">And when the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were defeated before Israel, they made peace with David and became servants to him. So Aram was no longer willing to help the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> {in the spring time of year},<note>Literally "at the time of the returning of the year"</note> the time <transChange type="added">when</transChange> kings go out <transChange type="added">to battle</transChange>, Joab led the troops of the army and destroyed the land of the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> And he came and besieged Rabbah, but David remained in Jerusalem. And Joab struck Rabbah and destroyed it.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And David took the crown of their king from his head and found it to weigh a talent of gold. And in it <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a precious stone. Then it was <transChange type="added">placed</transChange> upon the head of David. And he brought out the booty of the city, a large amount.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the people who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in it he brought out, and {he set them to work with saws and iron implements and axes}.<note>The translation comes from 2 Samuel 12:31 since the Hebrew text here is uncertain</note> Thus David did to all the cities of the {Ammonites}.<note>Literally "sons of Ammon"</note> Then David returned, and all the nation <transChange type="added">went</transChange> with him. </verse>
    <verse num="4">And after this there arose a war in Gezer with the Philistines. Then Sibbecai the Hushathite struck down Sippai, one of the descendants of the Rephaim. And they were subdued.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And again there was war with the Philistines. And Elhanan son of Jair struck down Lahmi, the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the shaft of whose spear <transChange type="added">was</transChange> like a weaver's beam.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And again there was war in Gath. And there was a {very tall}<note>Literally "measured"</note> man <transChange type="added">there</transChange>, and {he had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each foot, twenty-four in all}.<note>Literally "and his fingers, six and six, twenty-four"</note> He himself <transChange type="added">was</transChange> also a descendant of the Rephaim.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And he taunted Israel, but Jehonathan son of Shimea, brother of David, struck him down.</verse>
    <verse num="8">These were born to the giants in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">Then Satan<note>Or "<transChange type="added">an</transChange> accuser," or "<transChange type="added">an</transChange> adversary"</note> stood against Israel and urged David to count Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So David said to Joab and to the commanders of the nation, "Go, count Israel from Beersheba to Dan and bring a report to me that I might know their number."</verse>
    <verse num="3">But Joab said, "May Yahweh add to the people a hundred times what they are! Are they not, O my lord the king, all of them the king's servants? Why does my lord seek this? Why would he bring guilt to Israel?"</verse>
    <verse num="4">But the word of the king prevailed over Joab. Then he went about through all Israel and came to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And Joab gave the number of the enrollment of the people to David. And it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> all Israel <transChange type="added">was</transChange> one million one hundred thousand men drawing a sword, and in Judah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> four hundred and seventy thousand men drawing a sword.</verse>
    <verse num="6">But he did not count Levi and Benjamin among them, for the word of the king was repulsive to Joab. </verse>
    <verse num="7">But this word was displeasing in the eyes of God, and he struck Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="8">Then David said to God, "I have sinned severely <transChange type="added">in</transChange> that I have done this thing. But now, please forgive the sin of your servant, for I have been very foolish."</verse>
    <verse num="9">Then Yahweh spoke to Gad the seer of David, saying,</verse>
    <verse num="10">"Go, you must speak to David, saying, 'Thus says Yahweh: "Three <transChange type="added">choices</transChange> I offer to you. Choose one of them for yourself that I will do to you." '"</verse>
    <verse num="11">So Gad came to David and said to him, "Thus says Yahweh: 'Choose for yourself:</verse>
    <verse num="12">whether three years of famine or three months of devastation by your enemies while the sword of your enemies overtakes you, or three days of the sword of Yahweh, with disease in the land and the angel of Yahweh destroying throughout all the territory in Israel.' So now, see what word I should return to my sender."</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then David said to Gad, "{I am very troubled}.<note>Literally "Great trouble to me"</note> Let me into the hand of Yahweh, for his compassion is very great, but do not let me fall into the hand of a man." </verse>
    <verse num="14">So Yahweh sent a pestilence through Israel, and seventy thousand men from Israel fell.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy it, and as <transChange type="added">he was about</transChange> to destroy <transChange type="added">it</transChange>, Yahweh saw and was grieved on account of the calamity. Then he said to the angel, the destroyer, "<transChange type="added">It is</transChange> enough; slacken your hand." And the angel of Yahweh was standing by the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.</verse>
    <verse num="16">And David lifted his eyes and saw the angel of Yahweh standing between earth and heaven, with his sword drawn in his hand, stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders, clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces.</verse>
    <verse num="17">Then David said to God, "Was it not I <transChange type="added">who</transChange> gave a command to count the people? Now I <transChange type="added">am</transChange> he who has sinned, and I have certainly done wickedness, but these sheep, what have they done? O Yahweh, my God, please let your hand be against me and against the house of my father, but against your people, <transChange type="added">let there be</transChange> no plague." </verse>
    <verse num="18">Now the angel of Yahweh had spoken to Gad to say to David that David should go up <transChange type="added">and</transChange> erect an altar for Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="19">So David went up at the word of Gad that he had spoken in the name of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="20">Now Ornan was threshing wheat, and Ornan turned and saw the angel, and his four sons with him hid themselves.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Then David came to Ornan, and Ornan looked and saw David. And he went out from the threshing floor, and they bowed down to David, faces to the ground.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Then David said to Ornan, "Please give me the place, the threshing floor, that I might build an altar on it to Yahweh; at full price please give it to me, that the plague against the people might be stopped."</verse>
    <verse num="23">And Ornan said to David, "Take <transChange type="added">it</transChange> to yourself; let my lord the king do what <transChange type="added">is</transChange> good in his eyes. See, I give the cattle for the burnt offerings and threshing sledges for the wood and wheat for the grain offering--I give <transChange type="added">it</transChange> all."</verse>
    <verse num="24">But King David said to Ornan, "No, for I will certainly buy <transChange type="added">it</transChange> at full value; indeed, I will not take what is yours for Yahweh and offer burnt offerings for nothing."</verse>
    <verse num="25">So David gave to Ornan six hundred shekels of gold by weight for the place.</verse>
    <verse num="26">Then David built an altar there to Yahweh, and he offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and he called to Yahweh. And he answered him with fire from heaven upon the altar of burnt offering.</verse>
    <verse num="27">Then Yahweh commanded the angel, and he returned his sword to its sheath. </verse>
    <verse num="28">At that time, when David saw that Yahweh answered him at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite, he sacrificed there.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Now the tabernacle of Yahweh that Moses had made in the desert and the altar of burnt offering <transChange type="added">were</transChange> at that time at the high place of Gibeon.</verse>
    <verse num="30">But David was not able to go before it to seek God, for he was afraid on account of the sword of the angel of Yahweh. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">Then David said, "This will be the house of Yahweh God, and this altar of burnt offering for Israel." </verse>
    <verse num="2">And David commanded to assemble the resident aliens who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the land of Israel and appointed stone craftsmen to cut dressed stones to build the house of God.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And David provided much iron for nails for the doors of the gates and for the seams, and abundant copper <transChange type="added">that</transChange> could not be weighed,</verse>
    <verse num="4">and cedar timbers without number, for the Sidonians and Tyrians brought abundant cedars to David.</verse>
    <verse num="5">Then David said, "Solomon my son <transChange type="added">is</transChange> a boy and inexperienced, and the house built for Yahweh <transChange type="added">must be</transChange> exceedingly great in fame and splendor throughout every land. I will make preparations for him." So David provided abundant <transChange type="added">materials</transChange> before he died. </verse>
    <verse num="6">Then he called to Solomon his son and commanded him to build a house for Yahweh, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And David said to Solomon his son, "I myself had in my heart to build a house for the name of Yahweh my God,</verse>
    <verse num="8">but it happened <transChange type="added">that</transChange> the word of Yahweh <transChange type="added">came</transChange> over me, saying, 'You have shed much blood and have made much war; you shall not build a house for my name because you have shed much blood upon the ground before me.</verse>
    <verse num="9">Behold, a son shall be born to you; he himself will be a man of rest, and I will give rest to him from all his enemies all around, for his name will be Solomon, and peace and quietness I will give to Israel in his days.</verse>
    <verse num="10">He himself will build a house for my name, and he himself will be to me a son, and I <transChange type="added">will be</transChange> to him as a father, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel forever.'</verse>
    <verse num="11">Now, my son, Yahweh will be with you, that you may succeed and build the house of Yahweh your God as he has spoken concerning you.</verse>
    <verse num="12">Only may Yahweh give to you understanding and insight that he might give you charge over Israel and the keeping of the law of Yahweh your God.</verse>
    <verse num="13">Then you will prosper if you take care to do the statutes and judgments which Yahweh commanded Moses concerning Israel. Be strong and be courageous; fear not and do not be dismayed.</verse>
    <verse num="14">Now see, with great effort I have made provision for the house of Yahweh: 100,000 talents of gold, 1,000,000 talents of silver, and bronze and iron <transChange type="added">that</transChange> cannot be weighed, for there is an abundance. Also timber and stone I have provided, but to these you should add.</verse>
    <verse num="15">And with you <transChange type="added">there is</transChange> an abundance of craftsmen: stonecutters, masons, carpenters, and everyone skilled in every <transChange type="added">kind of</transChange> craftsmanship</verse>
    <verse num="16">with gold, silver, bronze, and iron without number. Arise and work! Yahweh will be with you!" </verse>
    <verse num="17">And David commanded all the commanders of Israel to help Solomon his son, <transChange type="added">saying</transChange>,</verse>
    <verse num="18">"Is not Yahweh your God with you? And has he <transChange type="added">not</transChange> given you rest all around? For he has put in my hand the inhabitants of the land, and the land is subdued before Yahweh and before his people.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Now set your heart and mind to seek Yahweh your Go, and arise and build the sanctuary of Yahweh God, that the ark of the covenant of Yahweh and the holy vessels of God might be brought into the house built for the name of Yahweh. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">Now David <transChange type="added">was</transChange> old and full of days. And he made Solomon his son king over Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And he assembled all the commanders of Israel and the priests and the Levites.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And the Levites thirty years old and above were counted, and their number according to their head count for the men <transChange type="added">was</transChange> thirty-eight thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Of these, <transChange type="added">David said,</transChange> "Twenty-four thousand <transChange type="added">are</transChange> to direct the work of the house of Yahweh, along with six thousand judges and officials,</verse>
    <verse num="5">four thousand gatekeepers, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> four thousand offering praise with the instruments that I have made for praise."</verse>
    <verse num="6">And David organized them <transChange type="added">in</transChange> divisions according to the sons of Levi: to Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. </verse>
    <verse num="7">For the Gershonites <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Ladan and Shimei.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief and Zetham and Joel, three.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, Haziel, and Haran, three. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of Ladan.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, Jeush, and Beriah; these four <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Shimei.</verse>
    <verse num="11">And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second, but Jeush and Beriah did not have many sons. They were enrolled as one for the house of a father. </verse>
    <verse num="12">The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses. And Aaron was set apart to consecrate the most holy things. He and his sons <transChange type="added">were</transChange> to burn offerings forever before Yahweh to serve him and to bless in his name forever.</verse>
    <verse num="14">But Moses the man of God <transChange type="added">and</transChange> his sons were reckoned among the tribe of Levi.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer.</verse>
    <verse num="16">The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the chief.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And the sons of Eliezer were Rehabiah, the head. And Eliezer had no other sons, but the sons of Rehabiah were very many.</verse>
    <verse num="18">The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the chief.</verse>
    <verse num="19">The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.</verse>
    <verse num="20">The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief and Isshiah the second. </verse>
    <verse num="21">The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And Eleazar died, and he did not have sons, but only daughters. And the sons of Kish, their relatives, married them.</verse>
    <verse num="23">The sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jeremoth, three. </verse>
    <verse num="24">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of Levi according to the house of their fathers, the heads of the {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> according to their enrollment, by the number of the names, according to their head count, <transChange type="added">who were to</transChange> do the work of the service of the house of Yahweh, from twenty years old and above.</verse>
    <verse num="25">For David said, "Yahweh, the God of Israel, has given rest to his people, and he dwells in Jerusalem forever.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And also, the Levites do not <transChange type="added">need</transChange> to carry the tabernacle and all its vessels for its service."</verse>
    <verse num="27">For by the last words of David, they <transChange type="added">are</transChange> the number of the sons of Levi, from twenty years old and above.</verse>
    <verse num="28">For their station <transChange type="added">was</transChange> {to assist}<note>Literally "for the hand of"</note> the sons of Aaron with the service of the house of Yahweh, over the courtyards, over the chambers, and over the cleansing of all the sanctified objects, and <transChange type="added">with</transChange> the work of the service of the house of God,</verse>
    <verse num="29">and with the rows of bread, the flour, the grain offering, the wafers of unleavened bread, the baked offering, the offering mixed with oil, and for all the amounts and measurements.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And <transChange type="added">they were</transChange> to stand {every morning},<note>Literally "in the morning, in the morning"</note> thanking and praising Yahweh, and likewise in the evening,</verse>
    <verse num="31">and for every burnt offering offered to Yahweh, on Sabbaths, on new moon festivals, and at the appointed feasts, according to the customary number {required of them},<note>Literally "over them"</note> regularly before Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="32">And they shall keep the responsibility of the tent of assembly,<note>Or "meeting"</note> the responsibility of the sanctified objects, and the responsibility of the sons of Aaron, their brothers, to serve the house of Yahweh. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">And as for the sons of Aaron, <transChange type="added">these were</transChange> their divisions. The sons of Aaron <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and {they had no sons},<note>Literally "sons were not to them"</note> so Eleazar and Ithamar served as priests.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And David, with Zadok of the sons of Eleazar and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, divided them according to their appointments for their service.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And more sons of Eleazar were found as heads of the men than the sons of Ithamar, so they divided them to the sons of Eleazar <transChange type="added">to be</transChange> sixteen heads over the house of the fathers, and to the sons of Ithamar over the house of the fathers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> eight <transChange type="added">heads</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="5">They divided them by lot {all alike},<note>Literally "these with those"</note> for they were commanders of the sanctuary and commanders of God from among the sons of Eleazar and the sons of Ithamar.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And Shemaiah the son of Nethanel, the scribe, from the Levites, recorded them before the king, the princes, Zadok the priest, Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> of the priests and Levites, one father's house drawn by Lot for Eleazar and one drawn by lot for Ithamar.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And the first lot went out to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah,</verse>
    <verse num="8">the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim,</verse>
    <verse num="9">the fifth to Malkijah, the sixth to Mijamin,</verse>
    <verse num="10">the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah,</verse>
    <verse num="11">the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shekaniah,</verse>
    <verse num="12">the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim,</verse>
    <verse num="13">the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab,</verse>
    <verse num="14">the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer,</verse>
    <verse num="15">the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Ha-Pizzez,</verse>
    <verse num="16">the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Ezekiel,</verse>
    <verse num="17">the twenty-first to Jakin, the twenty-second to Gamul,</verse>
    <verse num="18">the twenty-third to Delaiah, the twenty-fourth to Maaziah.</verse>
    <verse num="19">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> their appointments for their service to come into the house of Yahweh according to their custom by the hand of Aaron their father, as Yahweh the God of Israel had commanded him. </verse>
    <verse num="20">And as for the remainder of the sons of Levi: of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah.</verse>
    <verse num="21">Of Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, Isshiah the chief.</verse>
    <verse num="22">Of the Izharites, Shelomoth; of the sons Shelomoth, Jahath.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Of the sons of Jeriah, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.</verse>
    <verse num="24">The sons of Uzziel, Micah; the sons of Micah, Shamur.</verse>
    <verse num="25">The brother of Micah, Isshiah; of the sons of Isshiah, Zechariah.</verse>
    <verse num="26">The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the sons of Jaaziah, his son.<note>Or "Beno"</note></verse>
    <verse num="27">The sons of Merari: of Jaaziah, his son,<note>Or "Beno"</note> Shoham, Zakkur, and Ibri.</verse>
    <verse num="28">Of Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Of Kish: the sons of Kish, Jerahmeel.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And the sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jerimoth. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the sons of the Levites according to the house of their fathers.</verse>
    <verse num="31">And lots were also cast <transChange type="added">for</transChange> these, just as their brothers, the sons of Aaron, before David the king, Zadok, Ahimelech, and the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> for the priests and for the Levites the fathers, {on the principle of the chief and younger brother alike}.<note>Literally "the head like his brother the younger"</note> </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">And David and the commanders of the army set apart for the service the sons of Asaph, <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Heman, and <transChange type="added">of</transChange> Jeduthun, who prophesied with stringed instruments, with harps, and with cymbals. And their inventory of the men of the work <transChange type="added">and</transChange> for their duty was:</verse>
    <verse num="2">for the sons of Asaph: Zakkur, Joseph, Nethaniah, and Asarelah, sons of Asaph, under the hand<note>That is, under the direction</note> of Asaph, who prophesied under the hands<note>That is, under the direction</note> of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="3">Of Jeduthun, the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, Zeri, Jeshaiah,<note>One Hebrew manuscript and the LXX add "Shimei" between Jeshaiah and Heshabiah (see verse 17)</note> Heshabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands<note>That is, under the direction</note> of their father Jeduthun, who prophesied with the stringed instrument with thanksgiving and praise to Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="4">Of Heman, the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti and Romamti-ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, Mahazioth.</verse>
    <verse num="5">All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> sons to Heman, the seer of the king, according to the words of God to raise a horn.<note>That is, to exalt Heman</note> And God had given to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters.</verse>
    <verse num="6">All these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> under the {direction}<note>Literally "hands"</note> of their father in the music of the house of Yahweh, with cymbals, harps, and stringed instruments for the service of the house of God. Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman <transChange type="added">were</transChange> under the {direction}<note>Literally "hands"</note> of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And their number, along with their brothers, trained singers, all the skilled people for Yahweh, were two hundred and eighty-eight.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And they cast lots <transChange type="added">for</transChange> responsibilities {on the principle of small and great alike},<note>Literally "for like the small, like the great"</note> teacher with student. </verse>
    <verse num="9">And the first lot for Asaph went out to Joseph; the second to Gedaliahu; he and his brothers and his twelve sons.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The third, Zakkur, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="11">the fourth to Izri, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="12">the fifth, Nethaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="13">the sixth, Bukkiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="14">the seventh, Jesarelah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="15">the eighth, Jeshaiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="16">the ninth, Mattaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="17">the tenth, Shimei, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="18">eleventh, Azarel, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="19">the twelfth to Hashabiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="20">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> thirteenth, Shubael, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="21">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fourteenth, Mattithiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="22">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> fifteenth, to Jeremoth, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="23">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> sixteenth, to Hananiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="24">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> seventeenth, to Joshbekashah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="25">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> eighteenth, to Hanani, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="26">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> nineteenth, to Mallothi, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="27">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twentieth, to Eliathah, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="28">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-first, to Hothir, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="29">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-second, to Giddalti, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="30">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-third, to Mahazioth, his sons and his brothers, twelve;</verse>
    <verse num="31">to <transChange type="added">the</transChange> twenty-fourth, to Romamti-ezer, his sons and his brothers, twelve. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">As for the working groups of the gatekeepers: of the Korahites, Meshelemiah the son of Kore, from the sons of Asaph.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And Meshelemiah had sons: Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth,</verse>
    <verse num="3">Elam the fifth, Jehohana the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And Obed-Edom had sons: Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, Sachar the fourth, Nethanel the fifth,</verse>
    <verse num="5">Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth; for God blessed him.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And to Shemaiah his son were sons born who <transChange type="added">were</transChange> rulers in the house of their father, for they <transChange type="added">were</transChange> mighty warriors of ability.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, Rephael, Obed, and Elzabad, whose brothers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> sons of ability, Elihu and Semakiah.</verse>
    <verse num="8">All these from the sons of Obed-Edom, they and their sons, and their brothers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> men of ability with strength for service; sixty-two of Obed-Edom.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And Meshelemiah had sons and brothers, sons of ability, eighteen.</verse>
    <verse num="10">And Hosah, from the sons of Merari, had sons: Shimri the chief (though he was not firstborn, his father appointed him as chief),</verse>
    <verse num="11">Hilkiah the second, Tabaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brothers of Hosah <transChange type="added">were</transChange> thirteen. </verse>
    <verse num="12">These working groups of gatekeepers, corresponding to the chief men, had responsibilities like their brothers to serve in the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And they cast lots, small and great alike, by their fathers' houses, {for their gates}.<note>Literally "for gate and gate"</note></verse>
    <verse num="14">And the lot fell to the east to Shelemiah. As for Zechariah his son, {a wise counselor},<note>Literally "giving counsel with understanding"</note> they cast lots. And his lot came out for the north.</verse>
    <verse num="15">To Obed-Edom <transChange type="added">went out</transChange> the south, and to his sons, the storehouses.</verse>
    <verse num="16">For Shuppim and Hosah <transChange type="added">it went out</transChange> for the west, at the gate of Shalleketh, on the road that goes up, guard for guard.</verse>
    <verse num="17">To the east, six Levites; to the north, four daily; to the south, four daily; and at the storerooms, two <transChange type="added">by</transChange> two.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For the court to the west, four at the road, two at the court.</verse>
    <verse num="19">These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the working groups of the gatekeepers among the sons of the Korahites and among the sons of Merari. </verse>
    <verse num="20">And of the Levites: Ahijah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> over the treasuries of the house of God and over the treasuries of the sanctified objects.</verse>
    <verse num="21">The sons of Ladan: the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> belonging to Ladan the Gershonite: Jehieli.</verse>
    <verse num="22">The sons of Jehieli, Zetham and Joel his brother, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the treasuries of the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="23">Of the Amramites, the Izharites, the Hebronites, <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the Ozzielites:</verse>
    <verse num="24">Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> commander over the treasuries.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And his brothers: from Eliezer <transChange type="added">were</transChange> Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zikri his son, and Shelomoth his son.</verse>
    <verse num="26">That Shelomoth and his brothers <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over all the treasuries of the sanctified objects that King David and the heads of the {families}<note>Literally "fathers"</note> to the commanders of thousands and hundreds and the commanders of the army had dedicated.</verse>
    <verse num="27">From the battles and from the spoil they had dedicated <transChange type="added">these things</transChange> to strengthen the house of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah had dedicated--all the dedicated gifts <transChange type="added">were</transChange> under the hand of Shelomith and his brothers.</verse>
    <verse num="29">For the Izharites: Kenaniah and his sons <transChange type="added">were appointed</transChange> to the duties outside of Israel as officials and as judges.</verse>
    <verse num="30">For the Hebronites: Hashabiah and his brothers, one thousand seven hundred men of ability, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> over the administration of Israel beyond the Jordan westward, for all the work of Yahweh and for the service of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="31">For the Hebronites: Jeriah the chief of the Hebronites for the genealogy for the {families}.<note>Literally "fathers"</note> (In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were examined, and there was found among them mighty warriors of strength at Jazer in Gilead.)</verse>
    <verse num="32">And his brothers, sons of ability, <transChange type="added">were</transChange> two thousand seven hundred heads of the {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> and King David appointed them over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, for every matter of God and matter of the king. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">And as for the number of the {Israelites},<note>Literally "sons/children of Israel"</note> the heads of {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> the commanders of thousands and hundreds, and their officials who serve the king in all matters of the working groups that came and went, month by month, throughout all the months of the year, each working group: twenty-four thousand. </verse>
    <verse num="2">Over the first working group for the first month: Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="3">From the sons of Perez <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> the chief of the commanders of the armies for the first month.</verse>
    <verse num="4">And over the working groups of the second month: Dodai the Ahohite and his working group, and Mikloth the commander. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="5">The third commander of the army for the third month <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Benaiah son of Jehoiada the chief priest. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="6">This <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Benaiah <transChange type="added">who was</transChange> a mighty warrior of thirty, and over the thirty and his working group <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ammizabad his son.</verse>
    <verse num="7">The fourth, for the fourth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Asahel the brother of Joab and his son Zebadiah after him. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="8">The fifth, for the fifth month, the commander <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Shamhuth the Izrahite. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="9">The sixth, for the sixth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="10">The seventh, for the seventh month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Helez the Pelonite, from the sons of Ephraim. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="11">The eighth, for the eighth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Sibbecai the Hushathite of the Zerahites. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="12">The ninth, for the ninth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Abiezer the Anathothite of the Benjamites. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="13">The tenth, for the tenth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Maharai the Netophathite of the Zerahites. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="14">The eleventh, for the eleventh month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Benaiah the Pirathonite from the sons of Ephraim. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand.</verse>
    <verse num="15">The twelfth, for the twelfth month, <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel. And <transChange type="added">he was</transChange> over his working group <transChange type="added">of</transChange> twenty-four thousand. </verse>
    <verse num="16">And over the tribes of Israel, for the Reubenites: the commander <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Eliezer the son of Zikri. For the Simeonites: Shephatiah the son of Maacah.</verse>
    <verse num="17">For Levi: Hashabiah the son of Kemuel. For Aaron, Zadok.</verse>
    <verse num="18">For Judah: Elihu, from the brothers of David. For Issachar: Omri the son of Michael.</verse>
    <verse num="19">For Zebulun: Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah. For Naphtali: Jerimoth the son of Azriel.</verse>
    <verse num="20">For the Ephraimites: Hoshea the son of Azaziah. For the half-tribe of Manasseh: Joel the son of Pedaiah.</verse>
    <verse num="21">For the half-tribe of Manasseh in Gilead: Iddo the son of Zechariah. For Benjamin: Jaasiel son of Abner.</verse>
    <verse num="22">For Dan: Azarel the son of Jeroham. These <transChange type="added">were</transChange> the commanders of the tribes of Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="23">And David did not {take a census of those twenty years old or under}<note>Literally "take up their count from a son of twenty years and to less"</note> because Yahweh promised<note>Or "said"</note> to make Israel more numerous than the stars of heaven.</verse>
    <verse num="24">Joab the son of Zeruiah began to count, but he did not finish. But wrath came upon Israel concerning this, and the number was not included in {the chronicles}<note>Literally "in the numbering of the words of the days"</note> of King David. </verse>
    <verse num="25">And over the treasury rooms of the king <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Azmaveth the son of Adiel. And over the treasuries in the country, in the cities, in the unwalled villages, and in the towers <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Jonathan the son of Uzziah.</verse>
    <verse num="26">And over those who did the work in the field to till the soil <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Ezri the son of Kelub.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And over the vineyards <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Shemei the Ramathite. And over the produce in the vineyards for the storehouses of the wine <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Zabdi the Shiphmite.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And over the olive trees and the sycamore trees that <transChange type="added">were</transChange> in the Shephelah <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Baal-Hanan the Gederite. And over the treasury houses of olive oil <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Joash.</verse>
    <verse num="29">And over the cattle pastured in the Sharon <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Shitrai the Sharonite. And over the cattle in the valley <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Shaphat the son of Adlai.</verse>
    <verse num="30">And over the camels <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Obil the Ishmaelite. And over the female donkeys <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Jehdeiah the Meronothite.<note>1 Chronicles 27:31 begins here in the Hebrew Bible</note> And over the sheep <transChange type="added">was</transChange> Jaziz the Hagrite.</verse>
    <verse num="31">All of these <transChange type="added">were</transChange> officials of the property of King David. </verse>
    <verse num="32">And Jehonathan the uncle of David <transChange type="added">was</transChange> an adviser, a man of insight, and he was a scribe. And Jehiel the son of Hachmoni <transChange type="added">was</transChange> with the sons of the king.</verse>
    <verse num="33">And Ahithophel <transChange type="added">was</transChange> an adviser to the king, and Hushai the Arkite <transChange type="added">was</transChange> a friend of the king. </verse>
    <verse num="34">And after Ahithophel <transChange type="added">came</transChange> Jehoiada, the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar. And Joab <transChange type="added">was</transChange> the commander of the king's army. </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">Then David assembled all the commanders of Israel, the commanders of the tribes and the commanders of working groups who served the king, and the commanders of thousands, the commanders of hundreds, and the commanders over all the property of the king and his sons, with the court officials and mighty warriors, and all the mighty warriors of ability, at Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse num="2">And King David rose to his feet and said, "Listen to me, my brothers and my people. {I myself wanted}<note>Literally "I myself with my heart"</note> to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of Yahweh and the footstool of our God, and I prepared to build.</verse>
    <verse num="3">But God said to me, 'You may not build a house for my name because you <transChange type="added">are</transChange> a man of war, and you have shed blood.'</verse>
    <verse num="4">But Yahweh the God of Israel chose me from all of the house of my father to be king over Israel forever, for he chose Judah as leader, and in the house of Judah, the house of my father, and among the sons of my father he took pleasure in me to reign over all Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="5">And from all my sons--for Yahweh has given many sons to me--he has chosen Solomon my son to sit on the throne of the kingdom of Yahweh over Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="6">And he said to me, 'Solomon your son, he himself shall build my house and my courts, for I have chosen him as a son to myself, and I myself will be as a father to him,</verse>
    <verse num="7">and I will establish his kingdom forever if {he firmly performs}<note>Literally "if he is strong to do"</note> my commandments and my judgments as <transChange type="added">he has to</transChange> this day.'</verse>
    <verse num="8">So now in the sight of all Israel, the assembly of Yahweh, and in the hearing of our God, observe and seek all the commandments of Yahweh your God so that you may take possession of this good land and bestow <transChange type="added">it</transChange> as an inheritance to your children after you forever." </verse>
    <verse num="9">"And you, Solomon my son, know the God of your father and serve him with a whole heart and a willing mind, for Yahweh searches all hearts and understands every plan and <transChange type="added">all</transChange> thoughts. If you seek him, he will be found by you, but if you abandon him, he will reject you forever.</verse>
    <verse num="10">Look now, for Yahweh has chosen you to build a house for the sanctuary; be strong and do it!" </verse>
    <verse num="11">Then David gave to Solomon his son the plan of the vestibule and of its houses, its treasuries, its upper rooms, its inner chambers, and of the house of the lid of the ark,</verse>
    <verse num="12">and the plan of all {that he had in mind}<note>Literally "that was in the spirit with him"</note> for the courtyards of the house of Yahweh and for all the surrounding storage rooms, the treasuries of the house of God, and the treasuries for sanctified objects,</verse>
    <verse num="13">and for the working groups of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of Yahweh, and for all the vessels for the service of the house of Yahweh,</verse>
    <verse num="14"><transChange type="added">and</transChange> for the gold, according to the weight of the gold for all the vessels of the service, and the service of all the vessels of silver according to the weight of all the vessels {for every kind of service}.<note>Literally "service and service"</note></verse>
    <verse num="15">And the weight of the golden lampstands and the golden lamps, {the weight of each lampstand and each lamp},<note>Literally "by weight of lampstand and lampstand, with its lamp and to the lamps"</note> <transChange type="added">and</transChange> the silver according to the weight of a lampstand and its lamp, according to the use of {each lampstand},<note>Literally "lampstand and lampstand"</note></verse>
    <verse num="16">and the weight of gold for the tables of the arranged <transChange type="added">bread</transChange>, {each table},<note>Literally "to table and table"</note> and silver for the tables of silver,</verse>
    <verse num="17">and pure gold <transChange type="added">for</transChange> the three-pronged meat forks, and the bowls and the pitchers, and for the golden bowls, by weight for {each bowl},<note>Literally "for bowl and bowl"</note> and for the silver bowls, by weight for {each bowl},<note>Literally "for bowl and bowl"</note></verse>
    <verse num="18">and for the altar of incense <transChange type="added">made of</transChange> refined gold, by weight, and gold for the plan for the chariot--the cherubim with outspread and covering wings over the ark of the covenant of Yahweh.</verse>
    <verse num="19">"All this <transChange type="added">I give you</transChange> in writing; from the hand of Yahweh he instructed me <transChange type="added">about</transChange> all the workings of this plan." </verse>
    <verse num="20">Then David said to Solomon his son, "Be strong and courageous, and do <transChange type="added">this</transChange>! Do not be afraid and do not be dismayed, for Yahweh God, my God, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> with you. He will not fail you and will not forsake you until all the work of the service of the house of Yahweh is finished.</verse>
    <verse num="21">And behold, the working groups of the priests and the Levites for all the service of the house of God; and with you in all the work for all <transChange type="added">those</transChange> willing with the skill for every service, and the commanders and all the people for all your commands." </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">Then David the king said to all the assembly, "God has chosen Solomon my son alone, a young man and inexperienced, and the work <transChange type="added">is</transChange> great, for the citadel <transChange type="added">is</transChange> not for humankind, but for Yahweh God.</verse>
    <verse num="2">So I have provided for the house of my God according to all my strength, the gold for the things of gold, the silver for the things of silver, the bronze for the things of bronze, the iron for the things of iron, and the wood for the things of wood, <transChange type="added">along with</transChange> an abundance of onyx stones, stones for settings, stones of turquoise, and variegated stones, and all <transChange type="added">kinds of</transChange> precious stones and alabaster stones.</verse>
    <verse num="3">And moreover, with respect to my provisions for the house of my God I have a treasure of gold and silver that I have given to the house of my God above all that I have provided for the holy house:</verse>
    <verse num="4">three thousand talents of gold from the gold of Ophir and seven thousand talents of refined silver to overlay the walls of the houses,</verse>
    <verse num="5">gold for the golden things and silver for the silver things, for all the work by the hand of skilled craftsmen. Now who will offer willingly, {consecrating himself}<note>Literally "to consecrate his hand"</note> today to Yahweh?" </verse>
    <verse num="6">Then the commanders of the {families},<note>Literally "fathers"</note> the commanders of the tribes of Israel, and the commanders of thousands and hundreds, and the commanders of the work of the king offered themselves willingly.</verse>
    <verse num="7">And they gave for the service of the house of God five thousand talents and ten thousand darics of gold, ten thousand talents of silver, eighteen thousand talents of bronze, and one hundred thousand talents of iron.</verse>
    <verse num="8">And whoever had <transChange type="added">precious</transChange> stones gave <transChange type="added">them</transChange> to the treasury of the house of Yahweh under the authority<note>Or "hand"</note> of Jehiel the Gershonite.</verse>
    <verse num="9">And the people rejoiced over their freewill offering, for with a whole heart they had willingly offered to Yahweh, and King David also rejoiced with great joy. </verse>
    <verse num="10">Then David blessed Yahweh in the sight of all the assembly, and David said, "Blessed <transChange type="added">are</transChange> you, O Yahweh, God of Israel, our father forever and ever!</verse>
    <verse num="11">To you, O Yahweh, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the greatness and the power and the splendor and the glory and the strength, for everything in the heavens and in the earth. Yours, O Yahweh, <transChange type="added">is</transChange> the kingdom and exaltation over all as head!</verse>
    <verse num="12">And wealth and glory <transChange type="added">are</transChange> from you, and you rule over all. And in your hand <transChange type="added">is</transChange> power and might. And in your hand <transChange type="added">is power</transChange> to make great and to give strength to all.</verse>
    <verse num="13">And now, our God, we give thanks to you and offer praise to the name of your splendor.</verse>
    <verse num="14">And indeed, who <transChange type="added">am</transChange> I, and who <transChange type="added">are</transChange> my people that we retain power to offer according to these <transChange type="added">offerings</transChange> willingly? For everything <transChange type="added">is</transChange> from you, and from your hand we have given to you.</verse>
    <verse num="15">For we <transChange type="added">are</transChange> strangers before you and sojourners like all our ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note> Our days <transChange type="added">are</transChange> like the shadow upon earth, and there is no hope <transChange type="added">of abiding</transChange>.</verse>
    <verse num="16">O Yahweh our God, all this abundance that we have provided to build for you a house for your holy name is from your hand, and all <transChange type="added">of it</transChange> is yours.</verse>
    <verse num="17">And I know, my God, that you yourself test the heart and are pleased with uprightness. I, in the uprightness of my heart, have willingly offered all these <transChange type="added">things</transChange>, and now I have seen your people who are found here willingly offer to you.</verse>
    <verse num="18">O Yahweh, God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, our ancestors,<note>Or "fathers"</note> keep this forever as a plan <transChange type="added">and</transChange> thoughts of the heart of your people, and establish their heart toward you.</verse>
    <verse num="19">Grant to Solomon my son a heart of peace to keep your commands, your statutes, and your regulations to do everything, and to build the citadel for which I have provided."</verse>
    <verse num="20">And David said to all the assembly, "Bless Yahweh your God!" And all the assembly blessed Yahweh, the God of their ancestors.<note>Or "fathers"</note> And they bowed down and prostrated themselves before Yahweh and the king. </verse>
    <verse num="21">And they offered sacrifices to Yahweh, and on that next day they offered burnt offerings to Yahweh: one thousand bulls, one thousand rams, one thousand lambs, with their libations and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="22">And they ate and drank before Yahweh on that day with great joy. And they made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and they anointed <transChange type="added">him</transChange> commander for Yahweh, and Zadok the priest. </verse>
    <verse num="23">Then Solomon sat upon the throne of Yahweh as king in place of David his father. And he prospered, and all Israel obeyed him.</verse>
    <verse num="24">And all the officials and mighty warriors, and also all the sons of King David, {pledged allegiance to}<note>Literally "placed a hand under"</note> King Solomon.</verse>
    <verse num="25">And Yahweh made Solomon exceedingly great in the sight of all Israel, and he bestowed upon him royal splendor that was not <transChange type="added">bestowed</transChange> upon any king before him in Israel. </verse>
    <verse num="26">And David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel.</verse>
    <verse num="27">And the days that he reigned over Israel <transChange type="added">were</transChange> forty years. In Hebron he reigned seven years, and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years.</verse>
    <verse num="28">And he died in a good old age, full of days, wealth, and honor. And Solomon his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <verse num="29">Now the words of King David, <transChange type="added">from</transChange> the first to the last, see, they are written among the words of Samuel the seer, and among the words of Nathan the prophet, and among the words of Gad the seer,</verse>
    <verse num="30">with all <transChange type="added">the accounts of</transChange> his kingdom, his power, and the times that came upon him, and upon Israel, and upon all the kingdoms of the earth. </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>